<page><title>Bernhardt Line</title><ns>0</ns><id>200370</id><revision><id>943782853</id><parentid>940675462</parentid><timestamp>2020-03-03T22:05:41Z</timestamp><contributor><username>InternetArchiveBot</username><id>27015025</id></contributor><comment>Bluelinking 1 books for [[WP:V|verifiability]].) #IABot (v2.1alpha3</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="27407" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle for the Bernhardt Line
|partof=the [[Italian Campaign (World War II)|Italian Campaign]] of [[World War II]]
|campaign=
|image=Image:Sanpietvalley.jpg
|image_size= 300px
|caption=Mt. Sambucaro overlooking the modern town of San Pietro Infine (left) and ruins of the original town (center).
|date=1 December 1943 – 15 January 1944
|place=[[Mignano Gap]], [[Kingdom of Italy|Italy]]
|result=Allied victory
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}
* {{flag|British India}}
{{flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Dominion of New Zealand|name=New Zealand}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Canada|1921}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Free French}}&lt;br&gt;[[Allies of World War II|and others]]
|combatant2={{flag|Nazi Germany|name=Germany}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Harold Alexander, 1st Earl Alexander of Tunis|Harold Alexander]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Bernard Montgomery]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Oliver Leese]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Mark W. Clark|Mark Clark]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Albert Kesselring]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Heinrich von Vietinghoff]]{{#tag:ref|von Vietinghof went to Germany on sick leave in late November and Lemelsen commanded the Tenth Army during the major actions on the Bernhardt Line in December.&lt;ref&gt;Nicholson (1956), p. 269&lt;/ref&gt; Von Vietinghof returned in early January|group=nb}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Joachim Lemelsen]]
|strength1=
|strength2=
|casualties1=
|casualties2=
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Italy}}
{{Campaignbox Winter Line}}
}}
[[File:ItalyDefenseLinesSouthofRome1943 4.jpg|thumb|300px|German prepared defensive lines south of Rome]]
The '''Bernhardt Line''' (or Reinhard Line) was a [[Wehrmacht|German]] defensive line in [[Italy]] during the [[Italian Campaign (World War II)|Italian Campaign]] of [[World War II]]. Having reached the Bernhardt Line at the start of December 1943, it took until mid-January 1944 for the [[United States Army North|U.S. Fifth Army]] to fight their way to the next line of defences, the [[Winter Line|Gustav Line]]. The line was defended by [[XIV Panzer Corps]] (''XIV Panzerkorps''), part of the [[10th Army (Wehrmacht)|German Tenth Army]] (''10. Armee'').

Unlike most of the other defensive lines it did not run all the way across Italy but was merely a bulge in front of the main Gustav Line, running over the massif of Monte Cassino, enclosing the peaks of Monte Cassino (Monastery Hill), Monte la Difensa, Monte la Remetanea and Monte Maggiore, in the territory of [[Rocca d'Evandro]], and Monte Sambucaro (or Sammucro), which stands at the border of the three regions (Lazio, Molise and Campania). However, the defences of the Gustav Line on the [[Adriatic Sea|Adriatic]] are sometimes referred to as the Bernhardt Line and the battles for this part of the line are included in this entry.

The Bernhardt line was not as strong as the Gustav Line and was intended only to delay the [[Allies of World War II|Allies']] arrival at the Gustav Line. Together with the Gustav Line and the [[Hitler Line]], it made up the German [[Winter Line]] defences.

==Background==
Following the [[Allied invasion of Italy]] in September 1943, the Italian government had surrendered, but the German Army continued to fight. The [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[15th Army Group]], commanded by [[General (United Kingdom)|General]] [[Harold Alexander, 1st Earl Alexander of Tunis|Sir Harold Alexander]], in conquering the southern part of Italy but by early October had come up against the [[Volturno Line]], the first of two lines (the next being the [[Barbara Line]]) used to delay the Allied advance to buy time to prepare the most formidable defensive positions which formed the Winter Line. Alexander had three possible alternatives to reach the [[Italy|Italian]] capital of [[Rome]]. On the [[Adriatic Sea|Adriatic front]] he could advance to [[Pescara]] and then use Route 5 (the old Roman [[Via Valeria]]) which traversed the country to Rome on the other coast. Alternatively, on the other side of the Apennines, highway 7 (the old Roman [[Appian Way]]) followed along the west coast but south of Rome ran into the Pontine Marshes which the Germans had flooded. Finally, highway 6 ran in the same direction, but further inland, through the [[Liri|Liri valley]].

===Order of battle===
The German forces in Italy were commanded by Field Marshal (''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'') [[Albert Kesselring]]. The defence of the Winter Line was the task of the German 10th Army (''10. Armee'') under the temporary command of [[Lieutenant general|Lieutenant-General]] (''[[General der Panzertruppe]]'') [[Joachim Lemelsen]] (in the absence of General (''[[Generaloberst]]'') [[Heinrich von Vietinghoff]], who was in Germany on sick leave). The German 10th Army had [[Traugott Herr]]'s [[LXXVI Panzer Corps]] (''LXXVI Panzerkorps'') deployed on the eastern side of Italy, from the [[Apennine Mountains]] to the Adriatic, and [[Frido von Senger und Etterlin]]'s [[XIV Panzer Corps]] (''XIV Panzerkorps'') on the western side, from the mountains to the [[Tyrrhenian sea]].

The new [[Supreme Allied Commander]] of the [[Mediterranean Theater of Operations]] (MTO) was General [[Henry Maitland Wilson|Sir Henry Maitland Wilson]], replacing [[General (United States)|General]] [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] who had moved to command of the Allied forces preparing for [[Operation Overlord]], the Allied [[invasion of Normandy]]. The [[Allied Armies in Italy]] (AAI), formerly designated the 15th Army Group, were commanded by General Alexander. Under his command were two [[Field army|field armies]]: to the left, on the western side of Italy, was the [[United States Army North|U.S. Fifth Army]], commanded by [[Lieutenant general (United States)|Lieutenant General]] [[Mark W. Clark]], and to the right, on the eastern side, was the [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|British Eighth Army]], commanded by General [[Bernard Montgomery|Sir Bernard Montgomery]]. The Fifth Army consisted of American, British and French units. The Eighth Army, with British, [[British Raj|Indian]], [[New Zealand]], [[Canada|Canadian]] and [[Poland|Polish]] units, was from early January 1944 commanded by [[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Oliver Leese|Sir Oliver Leese]] after General Montgomery was, along with General Eisenhower, also recalled to [[England]] to prepare for Operation Overlord.

==Eighth Army on the Adriatic Winter Line defences==
===Prelude===
On 3 October, a battalion of the British Eighth Army's [[78th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|78th Infantry Division]] had crossed the Bifurno river to confront the German [[Volturno Line|Volturno-Viktor Line]] defences. Two [[British Commandos|Commando]] battalions landed from the sea north of the river at [[Termoli]], and a fiercely contested battle ensued which had hung in the balance when a ford became unusable after heavy rains and prevented Allied armour from moving forward. However, the British infantry — reinforced from the sea by two brigades — had held out long enough against the tanks of 16th Panzer Division (''16. Panzerdivision'') for a Bailey bridge to be laid across the river, and the crisis passed with the arrival of elements of [[1st Canadian Armoured Brigade]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Nicholson (1956), p. 253&lt;/ref&gt; By 6 October, the Germans were withdrawing to new defensive positions behind the Trigno river, the "[[Barbara Line]]".&lt;ref&gt;Carver (2002), p. 84&lt;/ref&gt;

At the Trigno, Eighth Army were obliged to pause because it had outrun its supply chain which stretched back over poor roads to the main ports of [[Bari]] and [[Taranto]], {{convert|120|mi|km|abbr=on}} and {{convert|170|mi|km|abbr=on}} to its rear. Port and transport capacity had also been affected by the logistic requirements of the Allied air force, which was establishing strategic bomber bases around [[Foggia]].&lt;ref name="Carver90"&gt;Carver (2002), p. 90&lt;/ref&gt;

The Eighth Army attacked across the Trigno on 2 November. By the next day, the German position had been turned and the Germans commenced a fighting withdrawal to the forward Winter-Line positions they were preparing on the ridges behind the Sangro River.&lt;ref name="Carver90"/&gt;

===Advance across the Sangro===
[[Image:Italy1943Sango+MoroCampaigns.svg|right|310px]]

The Eighth Army's forward units had reached the Sangro on 9 November. Alexander had planned for Montgomery to strike across the river on its coastal plain on 20 November with the [[V Corps (United Kingdom)|V Corps]] ([[8th Infantry Division (India)|Indian 8th Infantry]] and 78th Infantry Divisions). In secrecy, Montgomery shifted the Indian division to the right to narrow the V Corps front and concentrate its power, bringing the newly arrived [[2nd New Zealand Division]] into the gap.&lt;ref name="Nich276"&gt;Nicholson (1956), p. 276&lt;/ref&gt; Eighth Army also devised a deception scheme involving false troop movements and ammunition dumps to give the impression that the main attack would be through the [[XIII Corps (United Kingdom)|British XIII Corps]] front. The deception was to be maintained by an earlier diversionary attack some {{convert|40|mi|km|abbr=on}} inland by XIII Corps&lt;ref name="Nich276"/&gt;&lt;ref name="MC93"&gt;Carver, p. 93&lt;/ref&gt; and a secondary attack at the same time as V Corps some {{convert|15|mi|km|abbr=on}} inland by the New Zealanders.

However, Kesselring divined the Allies' intentions;&lt;ref&gt;Phillips (1957), [http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2-1Ita-c4-1.html#n67 p. 67]&lt;/ref&gt; on 18 November, Lemelsen had signaled Kesselring to the effect that the Allied concentrations on the coast led him to expect the main attack on his left wing.&lt;ref&gt;Nicholson (1956), p. 287&lt;/ref&gt; Then heavy rain raised the river levels forcing the postponement of the offensive to the night of 27 November and giving the Germans time to switch two divisions across the Apennines to the defending LXXVI ''Panzer'' Corps. This made three divisions on the coastal plain opposing V Corps: [[65th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|65th Infantry Division]] (''65. Infantriedivision''), [[90th Light Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|90th Panzergrenadier Division]] (''90. Panzergrenadierdivision'') and [[23rd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|26th Panzer Division]] (''26. Panzerdivision''). 16th ''Panzer'' Division opposed the New Zealanders and the [[1st Parachute Division (Germany)|German 1st Parachute Division]] (''1. Fallschirmjägerdivision'') faced XIII Corps ([[1st Canadian Division]] and [[5th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|British 5th Infantry Division]]).

In the early hours of 28 November, the Eighth Army attack went in supported by heavy artillery concentrations. The New Zealanders advanced steadily; although the German defences had been well prepared most of the New Zealanders' objectives were manned by 65th Division which was poorly equipped and untried in battle. The German Division was also hampered by the fact that their commander—Brigadier-General (''[[Generalmajor]]'') G.H. von Ziehlberg—was severely wounded on the afternoon of 28 November.&lt;ref&gt;Phillips (1957), p. [http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2-1Ita-c4-1.html#n73 pp. 73–74]&lt;/ref&gt; The 8th Indian Division, however, like the New Zealanders facing their first major combat action since arriving in Italy, experienced tougher opposition. Elements of 65th Infantry Division supported by an armoured battle group held tenaciously on to Mezzagrogna&lt;ref&gt;Ford (2003), p. 174&lt;/ref&gt; and the town was eventually taken on 29 November after tough, often hand to hand, fighting. On the morning of 29 November, 78th Infantry Division had joined the attack on the right of the Indian Division and had forced their way to Santa Maria by the evening, creating a base for their main attack the following day towards Fossacesia.&lt;ref&gt;Ford (2003), pp.175-176&lt;/ref&gt; By late on 30 November, 78th Division—supported by [[4th New Zealand Armoured Brigade|4th Armoured Brigade]]—had taken Fossacesia, and the whole ridge on the far bank of the Sangro—carrying the main Bernhardt defences—was under Eighth Army control.&lt;ref&gt;Nicholson (1956), p. 288&lt;/ref&gt;

As the Eighth Army pushed forward over the next few days, 65th Infantry Division crumbled (to the extent that German 10th Army were later to order a court-martial into its conduct&lt;ref&gt;Phillips (1957), [http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2-1Ita-c4-2.html#n80 p. 80]&lt;/ref&gt;). However, Herr was able to introduce 90th Panzergrenadier Division into the line from his reserve and transferred reinforcements from the quieter sector inland in the form of elements of 1st Parachute Division. The complications of these manoeuvres introduced considerable confusion within the German alignment but they were nevertheless able to manage a fighting withdrawal to the ridge on the far side of the Moro river. Unaware of the disorganisation in the German ranks, the New Zealanders failed on 2 December to exploit an opportunity to capture Orsogna, a key position near the headwaters of the Moro, which on that day was still only lightly held. It was only on the morning of 3 December that the New Zealand Division disputed possession of Orsogna, but 26th ''Panzer'' had had just enough breathing space to organise and were able to repel them. The 26th ''Panzer'' then proceeded to create a formidable defensive complex around the town and along the ridge towards Ortona on the coast&lt;ref&gt;Phillips (1957), [http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2-1Ita-c4-2.html#n89 pp. 89-92]&lt;/ref&gt; and Orsogna was not occupied by the Allies—despite a further two determined attempts during December—until the Germans withdrew after the Allied breakthrough at [[Battle of Monte Cassino|Cassino]] in May 1944.

===Moro offensive===
{{Main|Moro River Campaign}}

Montgomery now rested the tired 78th Division (which had been leading the V Corps advance since the [[Volturno Line]] offensive), swapping with the [[1st Canadian Division|1st Canadian Infantry Division]] from the relatively quiet XIII Corps sector. The Canadians, with the 8th Indian Infantry Division on their left, led the [[Moro River Campaign|main thrust across the Moro]] on 8 December aiming for [[Ortona]]. By 20 December, after a stubborn resistance, first from elements of the German 90th Panzergrenadier Division&lt;ref&gt;Carver, p. 94&lt;/ref&gt; and then elements of the 1st Parachute Division (which had relieved the ''panzergrenadier''s), they had patrols on the outerskirts of the town. But the [[Battle of Ortona|battle for Ortona]] took another week of fierce house to house fighting as the [[3rd Parachute Regiment (Germany)|German 3rd Parachute Regiment]] tenaciously held on before withdrawing to the other side of the Riccio river on 28 December.&lt;ref&gt;Hoyt (2007), p. 116&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, inland V Corps, [[Orsogna]] had suffered three successive assaults but XIII Corps spearheaded by the 2nd New Zealand Division could not get past the defending 26th ''Panzer'' Division. After advancing a total of only 18 miles (29&amp;nbsp;km) and sustaining 6,500 casualties,&lt;ref&gt;Lloyd Clark, p53&lt;/ref&gt; blizzards, drifting snow and zero visibility at the end of December in jagged terrain caused Eighth Army's offensive on the Adriatic front to grind to a halt. As the New Year approached, it became clear that with no prospect of better weather until the spring, the Eighth Army did not have the strength to force its way to [[Pescara]]. Alexander called a halt to the offensive, instructing Montgomery to maintain sufficient activity to pin LXXVI Panzer Corps and prevent troops from being sent across to reinforce XIV Corps facing the Fifth Army.&lt;ref&gt;Carver, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Phillips (1957), [http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2-1Ita-c7-1.html#n149 p. 149]&lt;/ref&gt;

The rest of the winter on the Adriatic front was spent in bitterly uncomfortable conditions with the opposing sides often in close proximity and engaged in night-time patrolling and vicious skirmishing.

==Fifth Army Bernhardt Line offensive==
It had taken Lieutenant General Mark Clark's Fifth Army, in deteriorating weather as the torrential autumn rains broke, from the middle of October to early November to fight their way across difficult terrain and through skillful and determined rearguard defences from the Volturno Line positions to the Bernhardt Line.

In the centre of the Fifth Army front lay the Mignano Gap, which, because of the marshy conditions on the coastal plain, represented the only realistic path to the mouth of the Liri valley, the route to Rome.

[[Image:MignanoGapNov1943.jpg|thumb|left|Area of the Fifth Army offensive in the autumn of 1943.]]

Flanking and overlooking Route 6 through the Mignano Gap and its villages ([[San Pietro Infine]], San Vittore Del Lazio and Cervaro) are, successively Monte Camino, Monte Lungo, Monte Porchia and Monte Trocchio on the left and Monte San Croce, Monte Corno, Monte Sambúcaro&lt;ref name=Sammucro group=nb&gt;This name usually appears as "Sammucro" on Allied military maps of the period.&lt;/ref&gt; and Monte Maio on the right. Monte Sambúcaro normally appears as Monte Sammucro on Allied maps of the time. On reaching the Bernhardt positions, an immediate attack was launched by the [[22nd Guards Brigade|201st Guards Brigade]], which was attached to the [[56th (London) Infantry Division]], part of Lieutenant-General [[Richard McCreery|Sir Richard McCreery]]'s [[X Corps (United Kingdom)|British X Corps]] on Monte Camino on 6 November, which was beaten back by the [[15th Panzergrenadier Division (Wehrmacht)|15th Panzergrenadier Division]] (''15. Panzergrenadierdivision''), with some 600 losses to the 201st Guards Brigade. By mid-November, it was clear that, after having sustained 10,000 combat casualties, since the Volturno Line offensive, the Fifth Army needed to pause, reorganise and re-gather its strength.&lt;ref&gt;Carver, p90&lt;/ref&gt;

The Fifth Army resumed its attack on 1 December. The first attack—[[Operation Raincoat]]—was delivered, after an intensive artillery and air bombardment, by the British X Corps on the left (comprising the [[46th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|46th]] and 56th Infantry Divisions) and elements of the [[II Corps (United States)|U.S. II Corps]], commanded by [[Major general (United States)|Major General]] [[Geoffrey Keyes]], including the [[First Special Service Force|1st Special Service Force]], under [[Lieutenant colonel (United States)|Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Robert T. Frederick]], on the right against the formidable Camino hill mass. The dominating peak on Monte Camino, Hill 963, is crowned by a monastery. Two slightly lower peaks, Monte la Defensa, [[Monte la Difensa]] (Hill 960) as it appeared on the military maps during the war, and Monte la Remetanea (Hill 907), lie less than {{convert|2|mi|km}} north of Camino. At the upper end of the Camino feature are the numerous peaks of Monte Maggiore. The entire hill mass is about {{convert|6|mi|km}} long and four miles (6.5&amp;nbsp;km) wide. On the east and northeast the slopes rise steeply to the heights, then fall away gradually to the west toward the [[Garigliano|Garigliano river]]. It took until 9 December before the Camino mass was secured from the 15th Panzergrenadier Division.

Meanwhile, on the Fifth Army's right flank, the [[VI Corps (United States)|U.S. VI Corps]], commanded by Major General [[John P. Lucas]] and composed of the [[34th Infantry Division (United States)|34th]] and [[45th Infantry Division (United States)|45th Infantry Division]]s, had attacked into the mountains but made little progress until reinforced by the mountain troops of the [[French Expeditionary Corps (1943–44)|French Expeditionary Corps]] (CEF), recently arrived in Italy;&lt;ref&gt;Carver, p104&lt;/ref&gt; they attacked again on 15 December.

On 8 December the U.S. [[3rd Infantry Division (United States)|3rd]] and [[36th Infantry Division (United States)|36th Infantry Division]]s and 1st Special Service Force of II Corps launched the attack on Monte Sambúcaro&lt;ref name=Sammucro group=nb/&gt; and into the Mignano Gap. By the night of 10 December, the peaks were taken, threatening the German positions in the gap. However, the German [[Battle of San Pietro Infine|positions at San Pietro]] in the valley held firm until 16 December, when an attack launched from the Camino mass took Monte Lungo. The Germans could no longer expect to hold San Pietro when the dominating ground on both flanks, Monte Lungo and the Sambúcaro&lt;ref name=Sammucro group=nb/&gt; peaks, was in II Corps' possession. Under the cover of a counterattack German forces withdrew to positions about {{convert|1|mi|km}} to their rear, in front of San Vittore. Several attacks were made in the next few days, and Morello Hill—overlooking the San Vittore positions from the north—was captured on 26 December.

On the U.S. VI Corps front, progress was made but proved very difficult over the mountainous terrain as the weather deteriorated further with the onset of winter. During the month of December, the Fifth Army suffered 5,020 wounded but total admissions to hospital totaled 22,816 with [[jaundice]], fevers and [[Immersion foot|trench foot]] prevalent.&lt;ref&gt;Fifth Army at the Winter Line, p87&lt;/ref&gt;

At the end of December, the Fifth Army had to pause once again to reorganise, replace its losses and gather itself for a final push to reach the Gustav Line defences. The U.S. VI Corps was taken into reserve to train and prepare for the [[Battle of Anzio|Anzio landings]] (codenamed [[Battle of Anzio|Operation Shingle]]) with the French troops, by this time at corps strength, taking over their front.&lt;ref&gt;Fifth Army at the Winter Line, p91&lt;/ref&gt;

The II Corps returned to the attack on 4 January 1944, with attacks parallel to Route 6 north and south of it. The northern attack took San Vittore, and by 7 January the overlooking height of La Chiaia. On the south side, the attack was made from Monte Lungo and captured Monte Porchia. Meanwhile, on their left, the British X Corps had attacked from positions on the Camino mass to take on 8 January the Cedro hill which with Monte Chiaia and Monte Porchia had formed a strong defensive line in front of Monte Trocchio.&lt;ref&gt;Fifth Army at the Winter Line, pp106-107&lt;/ref&gt;

The last offensive to clear the enemy in front of the Gustav defences started on 10 January. [[Cervaro]] was taken on 12 January and the overlooking hills to the north on 13 January. This opened up the northern flank of Monte Trocchio, and a heavy assault was planned for 15 January. However, the German XIV ''Panzer'' Corps considered the position to be untenable and withdrew across the Rapido. When the II Corps moved forward on 15 January, they encountered no resistance.&lt;ref&gt;Fifth Army at the Winter Line, p112&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
It had taken the U.S. Fifth Army six weeks of intense combat and 16,000 casualties to advance the 7 miles (11&amp;nbsp;km) through the Bernhardt Line defences, including the action at [[Battle of San Pietro Infine|San Pietro Infine]], to take Monte Trocchio and to reach the positions facing the main Gustav defences on 15 January.

==See also==
* [[Allied invasion of Italy]]
* [[Battle of San Pietro Infine]]
* [[Winter Line|Gustav Line]]
* [[United States Army North|U.S. Fifth Army]]
* [[Barbara Line]]
* [[36th Infantry Division (United States)|U.S. 36th Infantry Division]]

==Notes==
===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|group=nb}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book|authorlink=Michael Carver, Baron Carver|first=Field Marshal Lord|last=Carver|title= The Imperial War Museum Book of the War in Italy 1943-1945|publisher=Sidgwick &amp; Jackson|location= London|year=2002|origyear=2001|isbn=0-330-48230-0}}
* {{cite book|first=Lloyd|last=Clark|title=Anzio: The Friction of War. Italy and the Battle for Rome 1944|publisher=Headline Publishing Group, London|year=2006|isbn=978-0-7553-1420-1}}
* {{cite book|author=Fifth Army Historical Section|url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/winterline/winter-fm.htm|title=Fifth Army at the Winter Line (15 November 1943-15 January 1944)|series=American Forces in Action series|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]|location=Washington|year=1990|origyear=1945|id=CMH Pub 100-9}}
* {{cite book|author=Fifth Army Historical Section|url=https://archive.org/details/TheVolturnoToTheWinterLine|title=From the Volturno to the Winter Line 6 October-15 November 1943|series=CMH Online bookshelves: American Forces in Action series|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]|location=Washington|year=1990|origyear=1945|id=CMH Pub 100-8|isbn=0-16-001999-0|url-access=registration}}
* {{cite book|title=Battleaxe Division|first=Ken|last=Ford|year=2003|origyear=1999|location=Stroud, Gloucestershire|publisher=Sutton|isbn=0-7509-1893-4}}
* {{cite book|first=Edwin P.|last=Hoyt|title=Backwater War. The Allied Campaign in Italy, 1943-45| publisher=Stackpole|location=Mechanicsburg, PA|year=2007|isbn=0-8117-3382-3|origyear=2002}}
* {{cite web|first=Gerhard|last=Muhm|url=http://www.larchivio.org/xoom/gerhardmuhm2.htm|title=German Tactics in the Italian Campaign|accessdate=2007-10-12|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130922050607/http://www.larchivio.org/xoom/gerhardmuhm2.htm|archive-date=22 September 2013|url-status=dead}}
* {{cite book|first=Gerhard|last=Muhm|title=La Tattica tedesca nella Campagna d'Italia, in Linea Gotica avanposto dei Balcani|language=Italian|publisher=(Hrsg.) Amedeo Montemaggi - Edizioni Civitas|location=Roma|year=1993}}
* {{cite book|first=G.W.L.|last=Nicholson|authorlink = G. W. L. Nicholson |title=Official history of the Canadian Army in the Second World War, Vol II The Canadians in Italy, 1943-1945|url=http://www.dnd.ca/dhh/collections/books/engraph/details_e.asp?BfBookLang=1&amp;BfId=25&amp;cat=6|location=Ottawa|publisher=Queen's Printer|year=1956}}{{Dead link|date=June 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* {{cite book|url=http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2-1Ita.html|series=The Official History of New Zealand in the Second World War 1939–1945|title=Italy Volume I: The Sangro to Cassino| accessdate=2008-07-12|author=|last=Phillips|first=N.C.|authorlink=|date=|year=1957|month =|work=|publisher=Historical Publications Branch, republished by the [[NZETC]]|location=Wellington| pages=|language=|doi=|quote=}}
* {{cite book|first=Col. Kenneth V.|last=Smith|url=http://www.history.army.mil/brochures/naples/72-17.htm|title=Naples-Foggia 9 September 1943-21 January 1944|series=CMH Online bookshelves: World War II Campaigns|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]|location= Washington|year=c. 1990|id=CMH Pub 72-17}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Cimitero militare britannico di Torino di Sangro}}
{{Commons category|Ortona War Cemetery}}
* [http://www.military.com/Resources/ResourceFileView?file=worldwarii_europe_maps_map47.htm Map of the German defensive lines]

{{coord missing|Italy}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2017}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1943]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:1943 in Italy]]
[[Category:1944 in Italy]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Italian Campaign (World War II)]]
[[Category:German World War II defensive lines]]
[[Category:World War II sites in Italy]]
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Italian Campaign]]</text><sha1>sc9np8b8v6pmpmt8kapz112nwaa3uaz</sha1></revision></page>