<page><title>Battle of San Marino</title><ns>0</ns><id>24210681</id><revision><id>967578375</id><parentid>963737608</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-14T02:50:13Z</timestamp><contributor><username>2x2leax</username><id>16771471</id></contributor><minor /><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="16855" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|WWII battle}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of San Marino
| image       = Gothic Line - Concept of OperationOlive 1944.png
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = The initial plan for [[Operation Olive]], the attempt to break the Gothic Line (red); the planned offensive is shown in blue, along the eastern coast. The arrows converge north of San Marino.
| partof      = the [[Gothic Line]] Offensive during the [[Italian Campaign (World War II)]]
| coordinates =
| place       = [[San Marino]]
| date        = 17–20 September 1944
| result      = Allied victory
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}&lt;br&gt;[[Image:War flag of the Italian Social Republic.svg|border|23px]] [[Italian Social Republic]]
| combatant2  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
*{{flagicon|British India}} [[British India|India]]
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Harry Hoppe]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Arthur Holworthy]]
| casualties1 = 274 killed&lt;br&gt;54 captured
| casualties2 = 323 killed
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Gothic Line}}
{{Campaignbox Italy}}
}}
The '''Battle of San Marino''' was an engagement on 17–20 September [[1944]] during the [[Italian Campaign (World War II)|Italian Campaign]] of the [[World War II|Second World War]], in which [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German Army]] forces occupied the neutral [[Republic of San Marino]], and were then attacked by Allied forces. It is also sometimes known as the '''Battle of Monte Pulito'''.

San Marino had declared its neutrality earlier in the war, and had remained broadly unaffected by events in Europe until 1943, when Allied forces had advanced a sizable distance up the [[Italian Peninsula]]. A major German defensive position, the [[Gothic Line]], ran across the peninsula a short distance south of the Sammarinese border, and in late June, the country was bombed by the [[Royal Air Force]], killing 35 people, in the belief that the German Army had taken up positions on its territory. In [[Operation Olive]], launched in late August, a strong Allied force attacked at the very eastern end of the line, aiming to pass through [[Rimini]]—just east of San Marino—and break out onto the plains north of the city. Whilst San Marino was southwest of Rimini, the plan was for it to be bypassed entirely. In response to the Allied movements, the Germans sent a small force into San Marino to guard their [[lines of communication]] and act as [[artillery observer]]s.
[[File:San Marino in World War II.jpg|thumb|right|Neutrality placards at the borders of San Marino]]

After a few days, the main thrust of the offensive was halted south of Rimini by strong resistance and severe weather, and the British and Indian flanking forces began to push westwards, taking the frontline towards San Marino. On 17 September the [[4th Infantry Division (India)|4th Indian Infantry Division]] attacked forces of the [[278th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|278. ''Infanterie-Division'']] holding two hills just across the Sammarinese border; after heavy fighting to gain control of the hills, the situation stabilised on the 19th, and Allied forces began to push into the city of San Marino itself. The city was captured by the afternoon of 20 September, and the 4th Indian Division left the country on the 21st, leaving it under the control of the local defence forces.{{TOC limit|2}}

==Background==
The [[microstate]] of [[San Marino]], in the northern [[Italian Peninsula]] and fully surrounded by Italy, had played little role throughout the Second World War. It had a [[fascist]] government, closely aligned with [[Benito Mussolini]]'s regime, but remained neutral. It was reported to have declared war against the United Kingdom in September 1940,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,764742,00.html ''Southern Theatre: San Marino In''], in ''Time'', 30 September 1940.&lt;/ref&gt; though the Sammarinese government later transmitted a message to the British government stating that it had not.&lt;ref name=dp292&gt;[[#refDiplomatic|''Diplomatic papers, 1944'']], p. 292&lt;/ref&gt; In early 1942, the Sammarinese government reiterated it was not at war with the United States, a position that was confirmed by the US State Department.&lt;ref name=dp292/&gt; The British Foreign Office noted more equivocally in 1943 that Britain had never declared war, but also had never formally recognised San Marino's neutrality, and that it felt that military action on Sammarinese territory would be justified if it were being used by Axis forces.&lt;ref&gt;[[#refDiplomatic|''Diplomatic papers, 1944'']], p. 293&lt;/ref&gt;

The country was bombed by the Allies on 27 June 1943, killing at least 35.&lt;ref&gt;[[#refDiplomatic|''Diplomatic papers, 1944'']], p. 290&lt;/ref&gt; The Sammarinese government declared the same day that no military installations or equipment were located on its territory, and that no belligerent forces had been allowed to enter.&lt;ref&gt;[[#refDiplomatic|''Diplomatic papers, 1944'']], p. 291&lt;/ref&gt; In early July, it announced that prominent signs had been put up at the border crossings by the German command, to instruct German units not to enter the territory, and again reiterated its complete neutrality.&lt;ref&gt;[[#refDiplomatic|''Diplomatic papers, 1944'']], p. 295&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==
===Assault on the Gothic Line===
{{main|Gothic Line}}
By the late summer of 1944, German forces in [[Italian Social Republic|Italy]] had withdrawn toward the [[Gothic Line]], a chain of defended positions stretching across the [[Italian peninsula]]. The Allies formulated a plan to break through the defences, pushing north toward [[Rimini]] and the plains of Northern Italy. This would involve a strong thrust up the eastern seaboard by the [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|British Eighth Army]], codenamed [[Operation Olive]]; 11 divisions would attack along a narrow front, converging on the "Rimini Gap", an {{convert|8|mi|km|abbr=on}} stretch of plain along the coast around the city, and then moving northward. Once through the Gap, the force would deploy outward onto the Romagna Plain, and move westward toward [[Bologna]]. Meanwhile, the [[United States Army North|American Fifth Army]] would push north along the centre of the peninsula, hopefully converging on Bologna and trapping a large German force in a [[pincer movement]].&lt;ref name="Fisher p. 308"&gt;[[#refFisher1989|Fisher 1989]], p.308.&lt;/ref&gt;
{{OSM Location map
| lat= 43.95
| lon= 12.6
| zoom= 10

| mark = Volcano red 32x32.svg
| mark-size = 20
| mark-lat= 43.966667
| mark-lon= 12.6
| label = Coriano Ridge
| label-size =
| label-color =
| label-pos   = bottom
| label-offset-x=
| label-offset-y=
| mark-title=
| mark-image=
| mark-description=

&lt;!-- second and subsequent markers--&gt;

| mark1 = City icon (Noun Project).svg
| mark-size1 = 20
| mark-lat1= 43.924
| mark-lon1= 12.589
| label1= Croce
| label-pos1   = right
| label-offset-x1= 10

| mark2 = City icon (Noun Project).svg
| mark-lat2= 43.905
| mark-lon2= 12.585
| label2= Gemmano
| label-pos2   = right
| label-offset-x2= 10
}}
The main Allied assault began on 25 August,&lt;ref name="Fisher p. 314"&gt;[[#refFisher1989|Fisher 1989]], p. 314.&lt;/ref&gt; reaching the Foglia valley—the Gothic Line proper—on 29 August.&lt;ref name="Fisher p. 315"&gt;[[#refFisher1989|Fisher 1989]], p. 315.&lt;/ref&gt; It was quickly breached, and the German command attempted to assemble a second defensive line on the Coriano ridge, a hilly spur to the north of the [[Conca (river)|Conca river]], and the last major geographic obstacle south of Rimini. The Allied offensive reached the river on 3 September, but ground to a halt due to mechanical difficulties with its tanks, strengthening German resistance, and heavy rain.&lt;ref name="Fisher pp. 316-7"&gt;[[#refFisher1989|Fisher 1989]], pp. 316–7.&lt;/ref&gt; The Allied forces halted, and brought up reinforcements whilst waiting for a chance to resume the offensive along the coast.&lt;ref name="Fisher p. 318"&gt;[[#refFisher1989|Fisher 1989]], p. 318.&lt;/ref&gt; On the left flank of the assault, the attack had been halted in the [[Battle of Gemmano]], to the south of the Conca river.&lt;ref name="Linklater p. 363"&gt;[[#refLinklater1951|Linklater 1951]], p. 363.&lt;/ref&gt;

At this point, the forces on the Allied left wing were strung out in a line running due south from the Coriano ridge, facing westward toward San Marino, a few miles distant. The [[56th (London) Division|56th (London) Infantry Division]] was opposite Croce, with the [[46th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|46th Infantry Division]] opposite the heavily defended position at Gemmano. The [[4th Infantry Division (India)|4th Indian Infantry Division]] was to the south of the 46th, forming the very left wing of the offensive. When the assault on Coriano was resumed on the 12th, led by two armoured divisions with heavy artillery support, these forces pushed westwards; their goal was to pass through towards the town of [[Montescudo]], about two miles from the Sammarinese border.&lt;ref name="Linklater p. 363"/&gt; The main assault successfully pushed onto the ridge, and the 56th Division advanced about {{convert|1|mi|km|abbr=on}} past Croce, before digging in on the evening of the 13th; that night, the 4th Indian Division gained a foothold south of Gemmano. It was finally captured by the 46th and 4th Indian Divisions on the morning of the 15th, and the British forces prepared to move toward Montescudo and exploit the German confusion.&lt;ref name="Linklater p. 365"&gt;[[#refLinklater1951|Linklater 1951]], p. 365.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==
===Entry into San Marino===
The 46th Division took Montescudo on the 15th, and on the next day the 56th Division entered the town of Mulazzano, directly north of Montescudo and equally close to the border. The fighting pressed westward from here, with the 56th Division on the northern flank and the 46th on the south; both were held back by strong German resistance.&lt;ref name="Linklater p. 366"&gt;[[#refLinklater1951|Linklater 1951]], p. 366.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:British soldier at the Battle of Monte Pulito, 1944.jpg|thumb|left|British soldier observing German positions near San Marino]]

In early September, the German Army had sent a strong force into San Marino to defend it against the Allies; this would also give them control of one of the major roads in the area, and allow artillery observers to occupy the mountain peaks.&lt;ref&gt;[[#refBrooks1996|Brooks 1996]], pp. 210–11&lt;/ref&gt; The defending force was drawn from the [[278th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|278. ''Infanterie-Division'']],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://gurkhasfaetano.com/course.html |title=History |publisher=Gurkhas Faetano |year=2007 |accessdate=2010-02-08 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110711135155/http://gurkhasfaetano.com/course.html |archivedate=2011-07-11 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt; whilst the 4th Indian Division was assigned to attack it on the 17th.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;[[#refBrooks1996|Brooks 1996]], p. 211&lt;/ref&gt;

The leading elements of the division—the 3rd/[[10th Baluch Regiment]]—crossed the [[Marano River]] on the eastern border on the night of the 17th, with the 1st/[[9th Gurkha Rifles]] moving through them to attack Points 343 and 366 near [[Faetano]]. These small hills—just behind the river—were held by two battalions of the 993rd Grenadier Regiment. The first—Point 343—was taken at 05:00, but the force occupying Point 366 had to fall back after running low on ammunition.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; Rifleman [[Sher Bahadur Thapa]] was posthumously awarded the [[Victoria Cross]] for holding the crest of the hill single-handed for two hours, allowing two companies to withdraw in safety, before being killed whilst trying to rescue another wounded Gurkha.&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=36860|supp=y|page=5933|date=26 December 1944}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Point 343 was held through the 18th, however, though with the loss of 63 men; by the evening, a force of tanks had managed to come up and stabilise the position with the aid of artillery support. The 4th/[[11th Sikh Regiment]] moved around the Gurkhas to the north, covering the northern flank of the San Marino heights, and the division's [[11th Indian Infantry Brigade|11th Brigade]] passed through them to help encircle the city.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; On the evening of the 19th, the 2nd Battalion, [[Queen's Own Cameron Highlanders]] of 11th Indian Infantry Brigade began to push into the outskirts of the city from the north, but early on the morning of the 20th were held back by defensive positions in the north-west of the city, where the road to the upper part of the city, situated higher on the mountain, began.&lt;ref&gt;[[#refBrooks1996|Brooks 1996]], pp. 211–12&lt;/ref&gt; Tanks moved into the suburbs, whilst a company of the Camerons moved uphill toward the summit in heavy rain. The city was secured by the early afternoon, with only 24 casualties among the attackers, and 54 prisoners taken.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;[[#refBrooks1996|Brooks 1996]], p. 212&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:A soldier's grave in Monte Titano (September 1944).jpg|thumb|right|Allied troops passing through San Marino, September 1944]]

On the 21st, the local defence forces were enlisted to help mop up straggling German troops,&lt;ref name="Linklater pp. 367-8"&gt;[[#refLinklater1951|Linklater 1951]], pp. 367–8.&lt;/ref&gt; and the 4th Indian Division pressed onward through a heavy gale and passed out of the country.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt;

==Aftermath==
Allied forces remained in occupation of San Marino for a short period following the German surrender. In October 1945, after the end of the war, the Sammarinese government submitted a claim for 732 million ''[[lira]]'' to the British government for wartime compensation, of which 500 million ''lira'' were given as the related costs of the fighting in September and 20 million ''lira'' as the costs of the occupation. The British government rejected this claim, arguing that as Germany had breached the Sammarinese neutrality before Allied troops had entered the country, it was not liable; it did, however, offer an ''ex gratia'' payment of £26,000 in regard to the June bombing, later increased to £80,000 (equivalent of 32 million lira).&lt;ref name="Hansard1961"&gt;[http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_answers/1961/jul/07/san-marino-war-damage-claim Statement by Edward Heath], ''Hansard'', 7 July 1961. A statement giving the overall breakdown of the claim was given on [http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1952/jul/09/san-marino-war-damage-claim 9 July 1952].&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[battle honour]] "San Marino" was awarded to three British Army units — the [[Royal Lincolnshire Regiment]], the [[York and Lancaster Regiment]], and the [[Queen's Own Cameron Highlanders]] — and two [[British Indian Army|Indian Army]] units, the 1st/[[9th Gurkha Rifles]] and the 4th/[[11th Sikh Regiment]].&lt;ref name="Baker p. 336"&gt;[[#refBaker1986|Baker 1986]], p. 336.&lt;/ref&gt; The latter three of these had fought as part of 4th Indian Division in the main attack, whilst the first two had had battalions in the [[138th (Lincoln and Leicester) Brigade|138th Infantry Brigade]] of 46th Division.

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Baker|first=Anthony|title=Battle Honours of the British and Commonwealth Armies|publisher=Littlehampton Book Services Ltd|year=1986|isbn=0-7110-1600-3|ref=refBaker1986}}
* {{cite book|last=Brooks|first=Thomas R.|title=The War North of Rome: June 1944&amp;nbsp;– May 1945|publisher=Littlehampton Book Services Ltd|year=1996|isbn=1-885119-26-7}}
* &lt;cite id=refFisher1989&gt;{{cite book|last=Fisher|first=Ernest F.|title=Cassino to the Alps| publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]] |year=1989|url=http://ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/USA-MTO-Cassino/index.html|ref=refBrooks1996}}
* {{cite book|last=Linklater|first=Eric|title=The Campaign in Italy| publisher=[[Office of Public Sector Information|HMSO]]|year=1951|ref=refLinklater1951}}
* {{cite book|author=United States Department of State|title=Foreign Relations of the United States Diplomatic Papers, 1944. Europe (Volume IV)|publisher=United States Department of State|url=http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/cgi-bin/FRUS/FRUS-idx?type=header&amp;id=FRUS.FRUS1944v04&amp;isize=M|ref=refDiplomatic}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{commons|Battle of San Marino}}

{{San Marino topics}}
{{coord missing|San Marino}}
{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:San Marino, Battle of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:1944 in San Marino]]
[[Category:San Marino in World War II]]
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Italian Campaign]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving India]]
[[Category:History of San Marino]]
[[Category:September 1944 events]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|San Marino]]
[[Category:History of Emilia-Romagna]]</text><sha1>rcl7ijvekb7z0ixr2oinuqvdfz7o5vq</sha1></revision></page>