<page><title>Battle of the Argenta Gap</title><ns>0</ns><id>6964057</id><revision><id>875805177</id><parentid>861696811</parentid><timestamp>2018-12-29T03:41:34Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Bellerophon5685</username><id>1258165</id></contributor><comment>/* External links */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="18476" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{One source|date=July 2011}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of the Argenta Gap
|partof= the [[Spring 1945 offensive in Italy]]
| image= Churchill tanks being filmed by an AFPU cameraman during the advance of 56th Division north-east of Argenta, Italy, 17 April 1945. NA24288.jpg
| image_size = 300
|caption=[[Churchill tank]]s advance with the [[56th (London) Division|British 56th Infantry Division]] north-east of Argenta.
|date=12–19 April 1945
|place= Northern Italy
|casus= Allied advance north through Italy
|territory= Territory south of the River Po falls into Allied hands.
|result= Allied victory
|combatant1= {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[United Kingdom]]
|combatant2= {{flagicon|Germany|Nazi}} [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]
|commander1={{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Charles Keightley]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Germany|Nazi}} [[Gerhard von Schwerin]]
|strength1=
|strength2=
|casualties1= 625 dead
|casualties2= Over 3,000 prisoners taken
|casualties3=
|notes=
|campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Spring 1945 offensive in Italy}}
{{Campaignbox Italy}}
}}
The '''Battle of the Argenta Gap''' was an engagement which formed part of the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[Spring 1945 offensive in Italy|spring 1945 offensive]] during the [[Italian Campaign (World War II)|Italian Campaign]] in the final stages of the [[World War II|Second World War]]. It took place in northern Italy from 12–19 April 1945 between troops of [[V Corps (United Kingdom)|British V Corps]] commanded by [[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Charles Keightley]] and German units of [[LXXVI Panzer Corps]] commanded by [[Lieutenant general|Lieutenant General]] (''[[General der Panzertruppe]]'') [[Gerhard von Schwerin]].

==Background==
{{Main|Allied invasion of Italy}}

The Allied invasion of Italy occurred during September 1943, for a number of key reasons not least important of which was that support for the war in Italy had been declining and it was thought that an invasion would hasten the efforts of the new government that had deposed [[Benito Mussolini]], which was seeking peace. Furthermore, the weakening of Axis control of the Mediterranean supply routes eased the pressure on Allied forces operating in the [[Mediterranean and Middle East theatre of World War II|Middle]] and [[South-East Asian theatre of World War II|Far East]], as well as on the efforts to supply to [[Soviet Union]].

[[Allied invasion of Sicily|Operation Husky]] — the [[Allied invasion of Sicily|invasion of Sicily]] in July 1943 — was successful, serving as a springboard for the invasion of the mainland. In September, the first Allied troops to [[Allied invasion of Italy|land in Italy]] were of the [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|British Eighth Army]] under the then General [[Bernard Montgomery, 1st Viscount Montgomery of Alamein|Bernard Montgomery]], in [[Operation Baytown]]. Further landings on 9 September 1943 saw the [[Allied invasion of Italy#Salerno landings|main attack force landing]], despite the Italian surrender to the Allied forces on the previous day. After securing the beachheads, the [[United States Army North|U.S. Fifth Army]] began its advance northwards.

By the winter of 1944-5 the Allied armies had penetrated the main defences of the [[Gothic Line]] but had failed to break out into the Po river valley. A new major offensive was planned for the spring of 1945, when improving weather would allow the Allies to take advantage of their superior airpower and armoured and motorized ground forces.

==Order of battle==
Formations and units involved in the battle:
* [[15th Army Group]] - [[Lieutenant general (United States)|Lieutenant General]] [[Mark W. Clark|Mark Clark]]
** [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|British Eighth Army]] - [[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Richard McCreery]]
*** [[V Corps (United Kingdom)|British V Corps]] - Lieutenant-General [[Charles Keightley]]
**** [[56th (London) Infantry Division]] - [[Major-general (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[John Yeldham Whitfield|John Y. Whitfield]]
***** [[24th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|24th Guards Brigade]]
***** [[167th (1st London) Brigade|167th (London) Infantry Brigade]]
***** [[169th (3rd London) Brigade|169th (London) Infantry Brigade]]
***** [[2nd Special Service Brigade|2nd Commando Brigade]] (under command)
***** [[9th Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|9th Armoured Brigade]](under command)
**** [[78th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|78th Infantry Division]] - Major-General [[Keith Arbuthnott, 15th Viscount of Arbuthnott|Keith Arbuthnott]]
***** [[11th Infantry Brigade and Headquarters South East|11th Infantry Brigade]]
***** [[36th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|36th Infantry Brigade]]
***** [[38th (Irish) Infantry Brigade]]
***** [[2nd Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|2nd Armoured Brigade]] (under command)
* [[Army Group C|German Army Group C]] - General (''[[Generaloberst]]'') [[Heinrich von Vietinghoff]]
** [[10th Army (Wehrmacht)|German Tenth Army]] - Lieutenant-General (''[[General der Panzertruppe]]'') [[Traugott Herr]]
*** LXXVI Panzer Corps - Lieutenant-General (''General der Panzertruppe'') [[Gerhard von Schwerin]]
**** [[162nd Turkoman Division|162nd (Turkestan) Infantry Division]] - Major-General (''[[Generalleutnant]]'') [[Ralph von Heygendorff]]
**** [[42nd Jäger Division]] - Major-General (''Generalleutnant'') [[Walter Jost]]
**** [[362nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|362nd Infantry Division]] - Brigadier-General (''[[Generalmajor]]'') [[Alois Weber (general)|Alois Weber]]
*** In Army reserve
**** [[29th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|29th Panzergrenadier Division]] - Major-General (''Generalleutnant'') [[Fritz Polack]]
[[File:LocationPoRiver.PNG|right|thumb|The location of the Po River.]]

==Prelude==
As a preliminary to the main operation, a [[British Commandos|commando]] assault ([[Operation Roast]]) was launched across Lake Comacchio on 1 April to secure the right flank of the Eighth Army for the coming battle to seize "the Spit", the narrow isthmus between the eastern shore of Lake Comacchio and the [[Adriatic Sea]]. This would secure the eastern flank of the Eighth Army and also allow trials to be carried out in secret of the suitability of using newly arrived [[Landing Vehicle Tracked|LVT tracked landing craft]] for subsequent larger operations in the muddy and difficult conditions of Lake Comacchio.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p.200.&lt;/ref&gt; The operation was successful, although the LVTs failed dismally, becoming hopelessly bogged down.&lt;ref name="Jackson258"&gt;Jackson, p. 258.&lt;/ref&gt; It was in this raid that [[Corporal]] [[Thomas Peck Hunter]] of 43 Commando posthumously received the [[Victoria Cross]] for his actions. Two nights later further actions by the [[Special Boat Service]] (SBS) supported by Italian Partisans of the 28th Garibaldi Brigade captured islands in the middle of the lake. Danish national, Major [[Anders Lassen]] a patrol commander of the [[Special Boat Service]] (SBS) was killed in a subsequent fighting reconnaissance and was awarded a [[Victoria Cross]] posthumously.&lt;ref name="Jackson258"/&gt;

The 56th Infantry Division also made a preliminary attack on 5/6 April to secure its starting line for the Argenta gap operation. By 8 April, after meeting stiff resistance, it had completed its task in clearing "the Wedge", an area from the southern tip of Lake Comacchio where it meets the Reno river to the Fossa di Navigazione.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, pp.259-260.&lt;/ref&gt;

The main Eighth Army offensive across the Senio river commenced on 9 April and by 12 April the assault units had advanced to consolidate across the Santerno river and allow 78th Infantry Division to pass through towards the Reno river and the Argenta gap. The Argenta Gap was a well defended strip of land some {{convert|2|mi|km}} wide and {{convert|8|mi|km}} deep between [[Lake Comacchio]] and the Lombardy marshes, south of the town of [[Ferrara]].&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p. 199.&lt;/ref&gt;

==The battle==
On the night of 10/11 April, [[V Corps (United Kingdom)|British V Corps]] launched Operation ''Impact Plain'' to widen and deepen its bridgehead in the Wedge: [[40 Commando|40th (Royal Marine) Commando]] advanced along the raised causeway bordering the lake while, from [[56th (London) Division]], [[169th (3rd London) Brigade|169th (Queen's) Brigade]] advanced on the commando's left across the flooded margins of the lake with two battalions in LVTs. The 56th Division's [[167th (1st London) Brigade|167th Brigade]] advanced from the Wedge along the Reno flood banks.&lt;ref name="Jackson267"&gt;Jackson, p.267.&lt;/ref&gt; The commando column met stiff resistance at the bridge north east of Menate and took heavy casualties but were able to take the objective with the assistance of air support.&lt;ref name="Jackson267"/&gt; 42nd ''Jaeger'' Division seems to have been taken by surprise by their opponents' amphibious capacity and seemed somewhat unnerved by the LVTs emerging from the water so that by daylight on 12 April all three columns had made some {{convert|4|mi|km}} headway, linking up in the Menate-Longastrino area. 169th Brigade then pushed forward on the road towards Filo and 167th Brigade continued up the Reno, rolling up the German defences as far as the confluence with the Santerno river to link with the Italian Cremona Combat Group which had advanced from the south.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p. 268.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:ArgentaGap 1945 04 en.svg|left|thumb|Map of the Argenta Gap showing the Allied lines of advance.]]

Reacting to the Allied attack, von Vietinghof ordered [[29th Panzergrenadier Division (Wehrmacht)|29th ''Panzergrenadier'' Division]] south to reinforce the Argenta gap. Its [[15th Panzergrenadier Regiment|15th ''Panzergrenadier'' Regiment]] arrived to reinforce 42nd ''Jaeger'' Division on 12 April but the rest of the division had been north of the Po and, delayed by air damage and fuel shortages was not in position until 14 April.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p. 269.&lt;/ref&gt;

Early on 13 April the [[38th (Irish) Infantry Brigade|38th (Irish) Brigade]], of [[78th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|78th ''Battleaxe'' Division]], attacked northward from [[8th Infantry Division (India)|Indian 8th Division]]'s bridgehead across the Santerno river with the objective of seizing a bridgehead across the Reno at Bastia, in the mouth of the Argenta gap.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, to their right, 56th Infantry Division launched the second phase of its operation, ''Impact Royal''. This involved [[No. 9 Commando]] of [[2nd Special Service Brigade|2nd Commando Brigade]] and [[24th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|24th Guards Brigade]] advancing up the flooded margins of Lake Comacchio in LVTs to concentrate near Chiesa del Bando, {{convert|6|mi|km}} north west of Menate and develop a threat to Argenta which lay some {{convert|3|mi|km}} to the south west of this objective.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p. 271.&lt;/ref&gt; A foothold was established on the Fossa Marina, a canal running roughly east to west from Argenta to the lake and a {{convert|1|mi|km}} short of their objective but then the newly arrived 15th Panzer Grenadier Regiment blocked further progress and an attempt to take the bridge across the Fossa on 14 April was beaten back.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p.272.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the morning of 14 April forward elements of 38th Brigade had crossed the bridge over the Reno at Bastia but had been forced back by an armoured counterattack. It was decided to confine immediate activity to mopping up south of the Reno and await the approach of 167th Brigade which,&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p. 273.&lt;/ref&gt; advancing on both banks of the Reno, would shortly threaten the flank of the defenders north of the river in Bastia and oblige them to retire. Rather than wait for the bridge at Bastia to be cleared, V Corps commander, [[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Charles Keightley]] ordered 78th Division's [[11th Infantry Brigade and Headquarters South East|11th Infantry Brigade]] to use 56th Division's bridges over the Reno in order to get forward towards Argenta without delay.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p. 281.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:The British Army in Italy 1945 NA24311.jpg|thumb|Men of 56th Reconnaissance Regiment, of 78th Division, with a [[Humber Light Reconnaissance Car]] in Argenta, 18 April 1945.]]

On 15/16 April 56th Division renewed their attack on the Fossa Marina but failed again. However, the cumulative effect of heavy air attacks since 13 April took their toll and on the night of 16 April the 24th Guards Brigade were able to cross the canal with relatively little trouble although their advance was once again halted by resistance about {{convert|0.5|mi|m}} north of the canal. On the west side of the Argenta gap 11th Brigade was able to get across the Fossa Marina east of Argenta. The 2nd Battalion, [[Lancashire Fusiliers]] were able to hold on to a small bridgehead under heavy fire and counterattack while engineers positioned [[Hobart's Funnies|ARK armoured mobile bridges]] to allow supporting tanks to cross the canal.{{#tag:ref|29th Panzergrenadier Division's history states that the Argenta gap battle was effectively decided by the breaching of the Fossa Marina by 78th Division.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p. 284(footnote).&lt;/ref&gt;|group="note"}}&lt;ref name="Jackson282"&gt;Jackson, p. 282.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 17 April 38th (Irish) Brigade arrived from newly cleared Bastia and passed through 11th Brigade's bridgehead, tasked with widening the bridgehead to provide space to allow an armoured breakout. By dark the brigade had advanced {{Convert|1000|yd|m}} against determined resistance, working around the rear of Argenta. Meanwhile, 11th Brigade advanced into the town to clear it with the support of [[Hobart's Funnies|Crocodile]] armoured flame-throwers. An armoured counterattack early on 18 April was forced back towards 38th (Irish) Brigade. Meanwhile, on the west outskirts of the town the bridges over the Reno had been attacked and captured by 2nd Commando Brigade which had been advancing up the line of the river from Bastia. Attempted counterattacks on the bridges were broken up by supporting artillery.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, pp. 282-283&lt;/ref&gt; Also on 17 April 56th Division's 169th (Queen's) Brigade was passed through 11th Brigade's bridgehead across the Fossa Marina in order to drive eastwards to clear the north bank of the canal and link with the Guards Brigade.&lt;ref name="Jackson283"&gt;Jackson, p. 283.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 18 April 78th Division brought forward [[36th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|36th Infantry Brigade]] from reserve to pass through 38th (Irish) Brigade and conduct a series of right hooks north of Argenta. By dawn the brigade had reached Consandolo some {{Convert|4|mi|km}} northwest of Argenta, where German resistance stubbornly held until well into the afternoon. Meanwhile, a mobile force under the command of [[2nd Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|2nd Armoured Brigade]] Headquarters comprising one infantry battalion, a tank regiment, a regiment of armoured personnel carriers and supporting self-propelled guns and assault engineers (the "Kangaroo Army") was brought forward and, bypassing Consonaldo, secured a bridgehead over the Fossa Benvignante {{convert|1|mi|km}}north of the town. Advanced elements then pushed forward and before dark overran the artillery gun lines of 42nd ''Jaeger'' Division.&lt;ref name="Jackson283"/&gt;

The 78th Division's advance created flank pressure on the German units facing 56th Division so that at midday on 18 April 169th (Queen's) Brigade detected a lessening resistance in front of them. Pushing forward, the brigade advanced to the Fossa Benvignante and captured a bridge intact. To their right the 24th Guards Brigade were finally able to clear Chiesa del Bando and advance towards the Fossa Benvignante as well.&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p.284.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
With 56th and 78th Division now clear of the northern end of the Argenta gap, British 6th Armoured Division, from Eighth Army reserve, was released through the left wing of the advancing 78th Division to swing left to race north west along the line of the river Reno to Bondeno and link up with the U.S. Fifth Army units advancing north from west of Bologna and to complete the encirclement of the German armies defending Bologna. Effective Allied bombing of the crossings of the Po and shortage of fuel left much of the German Army Group's strength and almost all its heavy equipment and armament stranded south of the river, so sealing its fate. On 29 April an instrument of surrender was signed by German emissaries at Allied Army HQ and hostilities formally ceased on 2 May.

==War Cemetery==
An Allied war cemetery is now located  at Argenta.

===Notable burials===
* [[Arthur Banks]] [[George Cross|GC]]
* [[Tom Hunter (VC)]]
* [[Anders Lassen]] [[Victoria Cross|VC]], [[Military Cross|MC]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group="note"}}

==Citations==
{{Reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* {{cite book| last1=Jackson| first1=General Sir William| last2=Gleave| first2=Group Captain T.P.|editor-last=Butler| editor-first=Sir James| editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler | series=History of the Second World War, United Kingdom Military Series| title=The Mediterranean and Middle East, Volume VI: Victory in the Mediterranean, Part 3 - November 1944 to May 1945| publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |location=Uckfield, UK |year=2004| origyear=1st. pub. [[HMSO]]:1988| isbn=1-84574-072-6| lastauthoramp=y}}
* http://www.warlinks.com/pages/8thdeeds.html
* http://www.britishsoldier.com/argenta2.htm (Kindly providing the images)

==Bibliography==
* ''Dictionary of Battles''

==External links==
* [http://www.irishbrigade.co.uk The Irish Brigade] Contains accounts of the 38th (Irish) Brigade in the Battle Argenta Gap including The Official Histories of the 1st and 2nd Battalion of the London Irish Rifles and their role in the battle.

{{Coord missing|Italy}}
{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Argenta Gap}}
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Italy|Argenta]]
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Italian Campaign|Argenta]]
[[Category:1945 in Italy]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the United States|Argenta Gap]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany|Argenta Gap]]
[[Category:Battle honours of the Rifle Brigade]]
[[Category:Battle honours of the King's Royal Rifle Corps]]
[[Category:April 1945 events]]
[[Category:Battles in Emilia-Romagna|Argenta]]</text><sha1>9b9g7w66zgcjhjk9mhvxsj5iu7by763</sha1></revision></page>