<page><title>Battle of Collecchio</title><ns>0</ns><id>36404075</id><revision><id>954654699</id><parentid>948084945</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-03T15:59:15Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>163.182.220.151</ip></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="19096" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2014}}
{{infobox military conflict
|conflict = Battle of Collecchio
|partof = the [[Spring 1945 offensive in Italy]] during [[World War II]]
|image = General_German_Brazil.png
|image_size = 300px
|caption = Generals [[Otto Fretter-Pico]] and [[Mario Carloni]] surrender to Brazilian troops
|date = 26–29 April 1945
|place = [[Collecchio]] and [[Fornovo di Taro]], [[Italian Social Republic]]
|coordinates = {{coord|44.749659|10.215569|display=inline, title}}
|map_type = Italy
|map_relief = 1
|map_size = 
|map_marksize =
|map_caption = Location of Fornovo di Taro in Italy's [[Po Valley]]
|map_label = 
|territory = 
|result = Allied victory
|status = 
|combatant1 = {{flag|Italian Social Republic|war}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|Nazi Germany|name=Germany}} 
|combatant2 = {{flag|Brazil|1889}}&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Flag of Italian Committee of National Liberation.svg|border|22px]] [[Italian resistance movement|Italian partisans]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|United States|1912}}
|commander1 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Otto Fretter-Pico]]{{surrendered}}&lt;br/&gt;[[File:War flag of the Italian Social Republic.svg|22px]] [[Mario Carloni]]{{surrendered}} 
|commander2 = {{flagicon image|Flag of Brazil (1889-1960).svg}} [[Mascarenhas de Moraes]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of Brazil (1889-1960).svg}} Euclides Zenóbio da Costa&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of Brazil (1889-1960).svg}} Major Orlando Gomes Ramagem&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Flag of Italian Committee of National Liberation.svg|border|22px]] Federico Salvestri&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Edward Almond]]
|units1 =
|units2 = 
|strength1 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[90th Light Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|90th Panzergrenadier Division]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[148th Reserve Division (Wehrmacht)|148th Reserve Division]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:War flag of the Italian Social Republic.svg|22px]] [[1st Bersaglieri "Italia" Division|1st Bersaglieri Division]]&lt;br/&gt;[[File:War flag of the Italian Social Republic.svg|22px]] [[4th Italian "Monte Rosa" Alpine Division|4th Alpini Division]]
|strength2 = {{flagicon image|Flag of Brazil (1889-1960).svg}} 1st Expeditionary Division&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of Brazil (1889-1960).svg}} [[Brazilian Air Force|1st Connection and Observation Squadron]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} 751st Tank Battalion&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} 894th Tank Battalion&lt;br/&gt;[[File:Flag of Italian Committee of National Liberation.svg|border|22px]] One Partisan Company
|casualties1 = 500 German dead and wounded&lt;br/&gt; 14,779 soldiers surrendered (Germans and Italians)
|casualties2 = {{flagicon image|Flag of Brazil (1889-1960).svg}} 45 dead and wounded&lt;br&gt;[[File:Flag of Italian Committee of National Liberation.svg|border|22px]] Unknown&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} Unknown
|notes = 
|campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Spring 1945 offensive in Italy}}
{{Campaignbox Italy}}
}}

The '''Battle of Collecchio-Fornovo''' (26–29 April 1945) was a [[World War II]] battle between the [[Brazilian Expeditionary Force|1st Brazilian Expeditionary Division]] (''Força Expedicionária Brasileira'' – FEB), along with [[Italian partisans]] and units from the American [[1st Armored Division (United States)|1st Armored]] and [[92nd Infantry Division (United States)|92nd Infantry]] Divisions, against the ''[[Wehrmacht]]''{{'}}s [[148th Reserve Division (Wehrmacht)|148th Reserve]], [[90th Light Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|90th Panzergrenadier]]&lt;!-- Panzergrenadier is all one word. --&gt; Divisions and the fascist [[Esercito Nazionale Repubblicano|National Republican Army]]'s 1st [[Bersaglieri]] "''Italia''" and the 4th [[Alpini|Mountain]] "''Monte Rosa''" Divisions.{{sfn|Donato|1996|p=256 &amp; 291}}&lt;ref&gt;Chase 1995, p.90&lt;/ref&gt; The battle was fought around the town of [[Fornovo di Taro]], about {{convert|8|mi}} to the southwest of [[Parma]], Italy. The [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] defeated the [[Axis powers|Axis]] forces, which were attempting to break through to the north.{{sfn|Donato|1996|p=Ibidem}}&lt;ref&gt;Bohmler, 1964. Chapter IX (final)&lt;/ref&gt;

On 28 April, the Brazilian 6th [[Regimental combat team|RCT]] followed up with an attack on [[Fornovo di Taro|Fornovo]], with German General [[Otto Fretter-Pico]] surrendering the 148th Division, with almost 15,000 German and [[Fascist]] Italian troops at the morning of 29 April.{{sfn|Donato|1996|p=Ibidem}}

==History of Main Forces==

===1st Brazilian (Expeditionary) Infantry Division===
The Brazilian Expeditionary Division was commanded by General [[João Baptista Mascarenhas de Morais]].{{sfn|Fisher|1993|p=397}}
The FEB arrived in Italy in the latter part of 1944, at a time when Allied troops were being transferred from Italy to take part in operations in southern France.

On 16 July 1944, the 6th RCT reached Naples, the first of five contingents sent by Brazil. These troops were formed into a RCT under Brigadier General [[Euclides Zenóbio da Costa]]. With three U.S. tank companies as reinforcements, the 6th RCT moved to the front in September 1944, pursuing German units that were making a tactical retreat to the [[Gothic Line]].{{sfn|Scheina|2003|p=254}}

In October–November 1944, the 6th RCT fought several engagements, but were unable to break through the Gothic line positions before the winter snows.{{sfn|Scheina|2003|pp=255–256}} The 1st and 11th RCT arrived in November, bringing the FEB up to division strength.{{sfn|Fisher|1993|p=397}} At its peak, the Brazilian division had a total of 25,334 men in the 1st, 6th and 11th RCTs. Each RCT had three [[battalion]]s of four [[Company (military)|companies]].{{sfn|Camel|Forsey|Turner|2011}}

In February 1945, the Brazilians overcame the German defenders of the strong [[Monte Castello]] position. They then moved eastward, fighting at Roncovecchio, Seneveglio and Castelnuovo. The Brazilian division fought a tough four-day battle for [[Montese]], which was taken on 16 April.{{sfn|Scheina|2003|p=256}} Turning north, by 22 April the FEB had broken into the [[Po Valley]], pursuing the fleeing German forces. General Zenóbio da Costa took the vehicles from 10 of his 12 artillery batteries for use in infantry transport, creating a mobile force with 606 jeeps and 676 trucks of different types. On the morning of 26 April, Brazilian forces were consolidating the defenses of Parma, when they heard that German units were approaching from the south.{{sfn|Scheina|2003|p=257}}

===German 148th Infantry Division===
On 25 September 1943, General [[Otto Fretter-Pico]] took command of the 148th Infantry Division and led it for the rest of the war.{{sfn|Mitcham|2007|p=178}} In August 1944, the division was in action against the Allied [[Operation Dragoon]], the invasion of southern France. In late October 1944, the division was transferred to northern Italy.{{sfn|Neto|Maximiano|Bujeiro|2011|p=23}} In December 1944, the 148th Division struck decisively against the Americans in the [[Apennine Mountains]] in [[Battle of Garfagnana|Operation ''Wintergewitter'']] (Winter storm), causing serious disruption despite being out-numbered and inferior in weapons to the allies.{{citation needed|date=August 2014}}

However, by the end of March the German army was in an impossible situation. It suffered from an acute lack of supplies, total domination of the skies by the Americans, and large and rapidly growing partisan forces.{{citation needed|date=August 2014}} By 23 April, the situation for German forces in Italy was desperate. The partisans had taken Parma, [[Fiume]] had been occupied by Tito's Yugoslav forces and French units had entered Italy from the west.{{sfn|Moseley|2004|p=232}} The 148th Division, which had been based around the [[Gulf of Genoa]], was making a last effort to break out to the north across the Po Valley.{{sfn|Dulles|1978|p=154}}

==Battle==

===Collecchio===
On news of the German-Italian forces approach, retreating from [[Genoa]]-[[La Spezia]] region, which had been liberated by the US 92nd Division,{{sfn|Hargrove|1985|p=169}} a Brazilian armored [[reconnaissance]] squadron moved south from [[Parma]], meeting leading units of the Axis forces in Collecchio. They first met [[Armored car (military)|armored cars]] from the 90th Panzergrenadier Division's reconnaissance unit, and then tanks (of the same division) with infantry from the 281st regimental &lt;!-- regimental what? --&gt; of the 148th Infantry Division. The reconnaissance squadron called for reinforcements.{{sfn|Baber|2008|p=1}}  According to Captain Pitaluga of the reconnaissance troop, "I arrived in Collecchio at noon, and I was alone until 6 pm. I had already occupied almost half the town when the infantry arrived." Pitaluga's unit of [[M8 Greyhound|M8]] cars fought it out against more lightly armored German vehicles, which only had 20&amp;nbsp;mm cannons. However, the Brazilian armored cars were vulnerable to tanks and anti-tank weapons; Pitaluga said of his vehicles, "The M8 is for recon, not (for heavy) combat.".{{sfn|Maximiano|2011|p=50}} Like the [[M10 tank destroyer|M10]] (another vehicle used then by Brazilian supporting units of Cavalry), M8 had open-topped turrets, which made them more vulnerable (than fully enclosed tanks) to [[Anti-tank warfare#Infantry close assault|anti-tank infantry close attacks]], especially in [[urban combat]], as was the case at Collecchio. Also, in this first day of the battle, the Brazilians were outnumbered by a German battalion with two or three squadrons.

A force of Brazilian infantry was hastily ferried to the town in [[Jeep#World War II Jeeps|jeeps]], trucks (like [[M3 Half-track|M3s]]), and the transport sent back for more. By 18:30 on 26 April, the Brazilian infantry was in place and prepared for action. This included 5th Company, II Battalion, 11th Infantry; a machine gun platoon from 8th Company, 11th Infantry; and 9th Company, III Battalion, 6th RCT.{{sfn|Baber|2008|p=1}} Major Orlando Gomez Ramagem, commander of II Battalion, 11th Infantry was given command of the Brazilian forces.{{sfn|Baber|2008|p=2}} With the war clearly drawing to a close, the troops may have been reluctant to take unnecessary risks. At first, Major Ramagem was in favor of encamping for the night, but he was dissuaded by the Brazilian divisional commander, General [[Mascarenhas de Moraes]]. According to one source, "The old general acted with the enthusiasm of a lieutenant." {{sfn|Dulles|1978|p=152}}

Ramagem ordered some of his troops, supported by the machine guns, to dig in to block Highway 62, which led north to Parma. The 5th company of the 11th RCT was ordered to attack at 19:30.{{sfn|Baber|2008|p=2}} The first attacks were made from the southeast by this company, which quickly captured the church.{{sfn|Dulles|1978|p=153}} This was followed by attacks from the northeast by a company of the 6th RCT.{{sfn|Dulles|1978|p=153}} German infantry defending the outskirts of the town, supported by mortars, responded to the attacks with intense fire.{{sfn|Baber|2008|p=2}} Neither the Brazilians nor the Germans had any regular artillery. The Germans had only mortar and rifle fire.{{sfn|Dulles|1978|p=153}}

The church was used to hold German prisoners, and the church tower as an observation post. Lt. Jairo Junqueira da Silva of the 11th Infantry recounts an incident when General Zenóbio da Costa appeared unexpectedly at the church:

{{blockquote|That Zenóbio was crazy. We were close to the church door, and suddenly Zenóbio appeared, from heaven knows where.  It was rather crowded, and I had the mortars in position in front of the church. Suddenly, here comes a German patrol in front of the garden, under cover of the vegetation. They were only a short distance away, and the guys started shooting. The first thing you have to do is hit the dust, but Zenóbio stood there as if he was a squad leader, and began issuing orders&amp;nbsp;– 'Riflemen, here! Sergeant, go there!'... Like everyone else, I was lying down, with that machine gun firing close. But he didn't move, didn't lie down, did nothing of the sort.{{sfn|Neto|Maximiano|Bujeiro|2011|p=24}}}}

More Brazilian troops from 2nd Company, I Battalion, 6th RCT arrived at 21:00, some riding on American and Brazilian, M10 and [[M4 Sherman|M4]] tanks, to enter the fight. The Axis troops made several unsuccessful attempts to break through to the north, but by 02:00 on 27 April, Allied forces had penetrated into the town.{{sfn|Baber|2008|p=2}} The Axis forces, reinforced by artillery and some tanks made a final desperate assault just before dawn. When this failed, their resistance collapsed. By noon Allied forces, with Brazilians ahead, had full control of the town, forcing the Germans and Fascist Italians south toward Fornovo by late afternoon on 27 April.{{sfn|Baber|2008|p=2}}

===Fornovo di Taro===
[[File:General German Brazil.png|thumb|German General Otto Freter Pico, Commander of the 148 Infantry Division, and General Mario Carloni surrendering to Brazilian FEB after the battle of Fornovo di Taro.]]
Prisoners taken in the battle at Collecchio confirmed partisans and Rebels' reports that the 148th Division had come from the [[Gulf of Genoa]] and was in the area surrounding [[Fornovo di Taro]] about {{convert|9|mi}} to the southwest of Collecchio on Highway 62.{{sfn|Dulles|1978|p=154}} The German 148th Infantry Division made an attempt to halt the allies at Fornovo di Taro. The Allied forces attacked this position at 18:00 on 28 April.{{sfn|Scheina|2003|p=257}} The defeat at Collecchio and follow-up attacks in Fornovo, convinced the German commander that defeat was inevitable.{{sfn|Baber|2008|p=2}} At 22:00, General Otto Fretter-Pico sent emissaries seeking a cease fire while terms were discussed.{{sfn|Moraes|1966|p=175}} On 29 April, he surrendered the 148th Division intact.{{sfn|Scheina|2003|p=257}}

==Aftermath==
The Brazilian commander, General Mascarenhas de Moraes, received the surrender of the ''Wehrmacht'' and ENR Divisions on 29 April 1945. In one week the Brazilians had taken 14,700 troops, 800 officers and two generals.{{sfn|Edwards|2010|p=90}} The Brazilians also took 1,500 vehicles and 80 guns. All Axis forces in Italy capitulated on 2 May 1945.{{sfn|Scheina|2003|p=257}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite web|ref=harv |url=http://sotcw.co.uk/downloads/Collecchio_-_Italy_1945.pdf |title=The Battle at Collecchio |publisher=The Society of Twentieth Century Wargamers |work=The Journal |last=Baber |first=Richard |year=2008 |accessdate=2012-07-12 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140303041640/http://sotcw.co.uk/downloads/Collecchio_-_Italy_1945.pdf |archivedate=3 March 2014 |df=dmy }}
*{{cite book|first=Rudolf| last=Bohmler| title=''Monte Cassino: a German View'' |publisher=Cassell |year=1964| id=ASIN B000MMKAYM}}
*{{cite web |ref=harv |url=http://www.flamesofwar.com/hobby.aspx?art_id=209 |work=Flames of War |title=The Cobra is Smokin'|last1= Camel |first1=Ken |first2=Jonathan |last2=Forsey |first3=Wayne |last3=Turner |date=19 October 2011 |accessdate=2012-07-12}}
*Chase, Patrick J. ''Seek, Strike, Destroy: the History of the 894th Tank Destroyer Battalion in World War II'' Gateway Press, 1995.
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Donato|first= Hernâni|title=Dicionário das Batalhas Brasileiras ('Dictionary of Brazilian Battles') |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xeyuqtq3ImUC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=Dicion%C3%A1rio+das+Batalhas+Brasileiras&amp;hl=pt-BR&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=hjVpUqy0OYL88QSmiYHIAg&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;q=Dicion%C3%A1rio%20das%20Batalhas%20Brasileiras&amp;f=false |language= pt| year=1996|edition=2nd|publisher=Ibrasa|isbn=8534800340}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Dulles|first=John W. F.|title=Castello Branco: the making of a Brazilian president |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=dwMkAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=2012-07-12 |year=1978|publisher=Texas A&amp;M University Press|isbn= 978-0-89096-043-1}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Edwards|first=Paul M.|title=Between the Lines of World War II: Twenty-One Remarkable People and Events
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zaXnzYGuo_4C&amp;pg=PA90|accessdate=2012-07-12|date=2010-08-24|publisher=McFarland|isbn= 978-0-7864-4667-4}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Fisher|first=Ernest F. Jr.|title=Mediterranean Theater of Operations: Cassino to the Alps (Paperback)
|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=eTC1EXVwu-0C&amp;pg=PA397|accessdate=2012-07-13 |date=1993-11-16|publisher=Government Printing Office|isbn=978-0-16-061310-4}}
*Gibran, Daniel K. (2001) ''The 92nd Infantry Division and the Italian Campaign in World War II'' McFarland &amp; Co. Inc. Publishers {{ISBN|0786410094}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Hargrove|first=Hondon B. |title=Buffalo Soldiers in Italy: Black Americans in World War II |url= https://books.google.com/books/about/Buffalo_Soldiers_in_Italy.html?id=tmu8GJI_E4UC&amp;redir_esc=y |date=1985|edition=1st| publisher=McFarland &amp; Co. Inc., Publishers|isbn=0786417080}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Maximiano|first=Cesar Campiani|title=Brazilian Expeditionary Force in World War II |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=L6HVtOSmWAEC&amp;pg=PT50|accessdate=2012-07-12 |date=2011-12-20|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn= 978-1-78096-285-6}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Mitcham|first=Samuel W.|title=Retreat to the Reich: The German Defeat in France, 1944 |url= https://books.google.com/books?id=qBrjZ8-VtEMC&amp;pg=PA178|accessdate=2012-07-12 |date=2007-01-30|publisher=Stackpole Books|isbn= 978-0-8117-3384-7}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Moraes|first=João Baptista Mascarenhas de|title=The Brazilian Expeditionary Force by its commander |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=CaAGAQAAIAAJ|accessdate=2012-07-12 |year=1966|publisher=U.S. Govt. Print. Off.}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Moseley|first=Ray|title=Mussolini: The Last 600 Days of Il Duce |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=UmxaWvOL_IgC&amp;pg=PA232|accessdate=2012-07-12 |year=2004|publisher=Taylor Trade Publications|isbn=978-1-58979-095-7}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last1=Neto|first1=Ricardo|last2=Maximiano|first2=Cesar Campiani|last3=Bujeiro|first3=Ramiro|title=Brazilian Expeditionary Force in World War II |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=602usxQTOF8C&amp;pg=PA23|accessdate=2012-07-12 |date= 2011-03-22|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=978-1-84908-483-3}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Scheina|first=Robert L|title=Latin America's Wars |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=FojnWy7_RN4C&amp;pg=PT254|accessdate=2012-07-12 |date=2003-07-31|publisher=Potomac Books, Inc.|isbn=978-1-59797-478-3|pages=254–}}
{{refend}}

==Citations==
{{reflist |colwidth=30em}}

{{World War II}}
{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Collecchio}}
[[Category:1945 in Italy]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1945|Collecchio]]
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Italian Campaign|Collecchio]]
[[Category:Battles in Emilia-Romagna]]
[[Category:Province of Parma]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Brazil|Collecchio]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany|Collecchio]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Italy|Collecchio]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States|Collecchio]]
[[Category:April 1945 events]]</text><sha1>g5h337zr8s4mtev3qtkcofjjjzabd7g</sha1></revision></page>