<page><title>Battle of Drøbak Sound</title><ns>0</ns><id>2716238</id><revision><id>964533286</id><parentid>964457194</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-26T02:21:43Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Jonesey95</username><id>9755426</id></contributor><comment>Fix [[Special:LintErrors|Linter]] errors</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="32941" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict          = Battle of Drøbak Sound
|image             = German cruiser Blücher sinking.jpg
|image_size        = 300px
|caption           = ''Blücher'' sinking in the Oslofjord
|partof            = the [[Norwegian Campaign]] of [[World War II]]
|date              = 9 April 1940
|place             = [[Drøbak Sound]], [[Oslofjord]], [[Norway]]
|result            = Norwegian victory 
* [[Operation Weserübung|German invasion force]] delayed
* Evacuation of the [[Storting|Norwegian Parliament]], [[Norwegian royal family|Royal Family]], and [[Flight of the Norwegian National Treasury|gold reserve]]
|combatant1        = {{flagcountry|Norway}}
|combatant2        = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1        = {{flagdeco|Norway}} [[Birger Eriksen]]
|commander2        = {{flagdeco|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[Oskar Kummetz]] &lt;br&gt; {{flagdeco|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[August Thiele]]
|strength1         = 407 &lt;br&gt; 1 fortress &lt;br&gt; 18 coastal guns &lt;br&gt; 11 anti-aircraft guns &lt;br&gt; 2 protection guns &lt;br&gt; 1 torpedo battery&lt;ref name="Fjeld190"&gt;Fjeld 1999: 190&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="S&amp;L2 260"&gt;Stangeland&amp;Valebrokk 2001: 260&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Fjeld99 160"&gt;Fjeld 1999: 160&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Fjeld 231"&gt;Fjeld: 231&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Fjeld 266"&gt;Fjeld: 266&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Fjeld 335"&gt;Fjeld: 335&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Fjeld99 160"&gt;Fjeld 1999: 160&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Hauge 42"&gt;Hauge 1995: 42&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength2         = 2 heavy cruisers &lt;br&gt; 1 light cruiser &lt;br&gt; 1 torpedo boat &lt;br&gt; 2 minesweepers
|casualties1       = None&lt;ref&gt;Ribsskog 1998: 55&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2       = 700-850 killed and wounded &lt;br&gt; 1,000 captured &lt;br&gt; 1 heavy cruiser sunk &lt;br&gt; 1 heavy cruiser damaged&lt;ref name= "Ribsskog 53"&gt;Ribsskog 1998: 53&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Hauge 42"/&gt;
|casualties3       = 4 civilians killed &lt;br&gt; 1 cutter sunk &lt;br&gt; 1 cargo ship damaged&lt;ref&gt;Fjeld 1999: 189&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Fjeld190"/&gt;&lt;ref name="WarsSør"&gt;{{Cite web|last=Lawson |first =Siri Holm |url=http://warsailors.com/homefleet/shipss2.html#sorland |title=M/K Sørland |accessdate=16 January 2017 |work=Warsailors.com |publisher= |date= }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="SkovSør"&gt;Skovheim Shipwreck website: [http://www.skovheim.org/located/akershus/sorland/sorland.htm ''Sørland''] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080820061725/http://www.skovheim.org/located/akershus/sorland/sorland.htm |date=20 August 2008 }} {{in lang|no|en}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|last=Lawson |first =Siri Holm |url=http://www.warsailors.com/homefleet/shipsh1.html#haldenI |title=D/S Halden 1 |accessdate=16 January 2017 |work=Warsailors.com |publisher= |date= }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
{{Campaignbox Norwegian Campaign}}

The '''Battle of Drøbak Sound''' took place in [[Drøbak Sound]], the northernmost part of the outer [[Oslofjord]] in southern [[Norway]], on 9 April 1940. It marked the end of the "[[Phoney War]]" and the beginning of [[World War II]] in [[Western Front of World War II|Western Europe]].

A [[Nazi Germany|German]] fleet led by the cruiser ''[[German cruiser Blücher|Blücher]]'' was dispatched up the Oslofjord to begin the [[Operation Weserübung|German invasion of Norway]], with the objective of seizing the Norwegian capital of [[Oslo]] and capturing [[List of Norwegian monarchs|King]] [[Haakon VII of Norway|Haakon VII]] and his government. The fleet was engaged in the fjord by [[Oscarsborg Fortress]], an ageing coastal installation near [[Drøbak]], that had been relegated to training coastal artillery servicemen, leading the Germans to disregard its defensive value. However, unbeknownst to German military intelligence, the fortress' most powerful weapon was a torpedo battery, which would be used to great effect against the German invaders.&lt;ref name="Kongsberg"&gt;{{cite web |last=Hansvoll |first=Jan W. |date=15 September 2006 |title=Besøket på Oscarsborg festning lørdag 2 september. |url=http://www.kongsberg.net/forsvarsforeningen/frame.asp?Id=48592 |url-status=dead |website=Kongsberg Defence Association |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071016213227/http://www.kongsberg.net/forsvarsforeningen/frame.asp?Id=48592 |archive-date=16 October 2007 |access-date=17 January 2017 |language=Norwegian }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The fortress' armaments worked flawlessly despite their age, sinking the ''Blücher'' in the sound and forcing the German fleet to fall back. The loss of the German flagship, which carried most of the troops and Gestapo agents intended to occupy Oslo, delayed the [[German occupation of Norway|German occupation]] long enough for King Haakon VII and his government to escape from the capital.

==Before the battle==
As the political situation was chaotic, the 64-year-old commander, ''[[Norwegian military ranks|Oberst]]'' (Colonel) [[Birger Eriksen]], had not received any clear orders and had received no notice as to whether the approaching warships were [[Kriegsmarine|German]] or [[Allies of World War II|Allied]]. He was well aware that Norway was officially [[policy of neutrality|neutral]], but that the government was inclined to side with the British in case of direct Norwegian involvement in the war.

Apart from the officers and [[Non-commissioned officer|NCOs]], almost all the soldiers manning the fortress were fresh recruits, having only been conscripted seven days before, on 2 April. Because of the influx of 450 fresh recruits, the fortress' [[naval mine]]s were not deployed on 9 April. Part of the recruits' training was to lay the mine barrier, a process planned for a few days later.

===Torpedo battery===
The commander of the torpedo battery at Oscarsborg had at the time of the battle been on sick leave since March 1940. Due to this, the retired ''[[Norwegian military ranks|Kommandørkaptein]]'' (Commander Senior Grade) Andreas Anderssen, who lived in nearby [[Drøbak]], had been assigned as temporary commander for the battery. As an unidentified flotilla started [[Action in the Oslofjord|forcing its way]] past the outer fortifications in the south of the Oslofjord, late at night on 8 April, ''Oberst'' Eriksen called Anderssen in and had him come down to the fortress. ''Kommandørkaptein'' Anderssen donned his old uniform and was transported by boat over the fjord to the torpedo battery.&lt;ref&gt;Hansen 2005: 49&lt;/ref&gt; Anderssen would show himself worthy of the important task of leading the fortress' most lethal weapon system; having first served at the torpedo battery in 1909, he knew the ageing weapons intimately.&lt;ref name=aftenpostentime&gt;{{cite news |last=Bjørnsen |first=Bjørn |authorlink=Bjørn Bjørnsen |date=30 March 2004 |title=Fra time til time |url=http://www.aftenposten.no/fakta/verdenskrig/article449062.ece?service=print |url-status=dead |newspaper=[[Aftenposten]] |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071221024222/http://www.aftenposten.no/fakta/verdenskrig/article449062.ece?service=print |archive-date=21 December 2007 |access-date=16 January 2017 |language=Norwegian }}&lt;/ref&gt; When Anderssen had been called back into duty a month previously, he had been a pensioner for 13 years, having originally retired from his post as commander of the torpedo battery in 1927.&lt;ref&gt;Hansen 2005: 48&lt;/ref&gt; The battery had three torpedo tunnels which could fire six torpedoes without reloading and a total of nine torpedoes were stored and ready for use.&lt;ref name="S&amp;L2 260"/&gt;

==Battle==

===Main Battery rounds===
[[File:28 cm gun at Oscarsborg Fortress.jpg|thumb|200px|left|One of the three {{convert|28|cm|in|0|abbr=on}} main battery guns at Oscarsborg]]
While the main combat station for the Main Battery and the commander of Oscarsborg fortress was on the island [[Håøya, Akershus|Håøya]] north-west of South Kaholmen, due to the special circumstances in 1940, ''Oberst'' Eriksen took position in the backup station on the eastern flank of the main battery at South Kaholmen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.verneplaner.no/?f=oscarsborg&amp;id=67497&amp;a=6 |title=1001 Hovedbatteriet |accessdate=7 November 2008 |work= |publisher=Nasjonale Festningsverk |date= |language=Norwegian }}&lt;/ref&gt;

At 04:21 on 9 April, Eriksen gave the Main Battery guns the order to fire at the lead ship of the unknown flotilla forcing its way towards [[Oslo]].&lt;ref name="Ribsskog 50"/&gt; Upon giving the command, Eriksen was questioned. He responded with his now famous response; "Either I will be decorated or I will be court martialled, Fire!"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lofotenkrigmus.no/april2.htm |title=9 april 3 |accessdate=31 January 2009 |work=Lofoten Krigsminnemuseum |language=Norwegian |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081016061047/http://www.lofotenkrigmus.no/april2.htm |archive-date=16 October 2008 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; Two rounds from the [[28 cm MRK L/35|{{convert|28|cm|in|1|abbr=on}}]] [[Krupp]] guns ''Moses'' and ''Aron'' engaged the German cruiser {{Ship|German cruiser|Blücher||2}} at {{convert|1800|m|yd|abbr=on}} range. The two Norwegian guns had been loaded with live, {{convert|255|kg|lb|abbr=on}} high-explosive shells;&lt;ref name="Hauge 35"&gt;Hauge 1995: 35&lt;/ref&gt; firing them "in anger" was a violation of the pre-war Norwegian [[rules of engagement]] which dictated [[warning shot]]s be fired first, as had been the case at [[Oslofjord Fortress]] further down the fjord.&lt;ref name=aftenpostentime/&gt; Colonel Eriksen later explained his decision by alluding to the fact that the German naval force already had forced their way past the Oslofjord Fortress' forts and had received both warning shots and live rounds from these more outlying coastal fortifications. As the vessels had continued up the fjord toward the capital, Eriksen was of the opinion that he had the right to consider them enemy warships and to engage them as such.
[[File:Birger Kristian Eriksen.jpg|thumb|200px|''Oberst'' (Colonel) [[Birger Eriksen]], the commander of Oscarsborg, 9 April 1940]]
[[File:Karte Oscarsborg.png|thumb|200px|Map of [[Oslofjord]] and the fortress of Oscarsborg]]

The first 28&amp;nbsp;cm shell hit ''Blücher'' right in front of the aft mast,&lt;ref name="Ribsskog 50"&gt;Ribsskog 1998: 50&lt;/ref&gt; and set the midship area up to the fore mast on fire.&lt;ref&gt;Ribsskog 1998: 50–51&lt;/ref&gt; The second 28&amp;nbsp;cm round hit the base of the forward {{convert|20.3|cm|in|1|abbr=on}} gun turret shortly thereafter, throwing large parts of it into the fjord and igniting further fires on board.&lt;ref name="Ribsskog 51"&gt;Ribsskog 1998: 51&lt;/ref&gt; There was only time for the Main Battery to fire these two rounds, due to their slow reload time with only 30 untrained recruits manning them at the time.&lt;ref name="Ribsskog 50"/&gt; Only one gun crew of actual artillerymen was available, and two guns could only be made operational by splitting the real gunners between the two guns and using non-combatant privates to assist the gunners.&lt;ref name= "Hauge 35"/&gt; The personnel pressed into service on the main guns included cooks woken up to man the Main Battery.&lt;ref name="Ribsskog 50"/&gt; There was no time to reload; there was not even time to fire the third gun, ''Josva'', which was loaded but unmanned.

The reason for the significant effect of the two 28&amp;nbsp;cm rounds on ''Blücher'' was that the first round penetrated the side of the ship and exploded inside a magazine containing cans of oil, smoke dispensers, incendiary bombs, aircraft bombs for the cruiser's [[Arado Ar 196]] reconnaissance [[floatplane]]s and depth charges. The [[Bulkhead (partition)|bulkhead]]s on that deck were blown out and the burning oil developed into an intense fire. The second 28&amp;nbsp;cm shell also knocked out the electricity central for the ship's main guns, rendering them unable to return fire.&lt;ref name="Ribsskog 51"/&gt;

===Kopås and Husvik batteries===
While fire raged aboard ''Blücher'', the secondary Norwegian coastal batteries fired at her with guns ranging in calibre from the two small {{convert|57|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} pieces at Husvik, intended to protect the fortress' missing mine barrier, to the three {{convert|15|cm|in|1|abbr=on}} guns of the Kopås Battery on the eastern side of the fjord. The larger guns wrought havoc on board ''Blücher'', while the 57&amp;nbsp;mm guns concentrated on the cruiser's superstructure and the anti-aircraft weapons,&lt;ref name="Fjeld2 36"&gt;Fjeld2 1999:36&lt;/ref&gt; and were partially successful in suppressing the fire from her light artillery as ''Blücher'' slowly sailed past the fortress. The Husvik battery had to be abandoned when ''Blücher'' passed in front of it and fired her light AA guns directly down into the positions.&lt;ref name="Fjeld2 36"/&gt; Although the main building at the battery caught fire, the Norwegians suffered no casualties.&lt;ref name="Fjeld2 36"/&gt; In all, thirteen 15&amp;nbsp;cm rounds and around thirty 57&amp;nbsp;mm shells hit the German cruiser as it passed the guns of the fortress' secondary batteries. One of the 15&amp;nbsp;cm rounds from Kopås disabled ''Blücher''{{'}}s steering gear and forced the cruiser's crew to steer her using the engines to avoid running aground. ''Blücher''{{'}}s [[fire-fighting]] system was also knocked out by shell fragments from the two Norwegian batteries, making attempts to control the fires aboard the ship and rescue the many wounded much more difficult.&lt;ref name="Fjeld2 36"/&gt;

===Identity of the intruders becomes known===
As the now crippled ''Blücher'' passed the fortress guns, a sudden outburst of voices from the burning cruiser could be heard above the battle noises; Norwegian sources state that the crew broke into singing ''[[Deutschlandlied|Deutschland, Deutschland über alles]]''.&lt;ref name="Hauge 36"&gt;Hauge 1995: 36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="T&amp;N 87"&gt;Tamelander&amp;Zetterling 2001: 87&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Berg 13"&gt;Berg 1997: 13&lt;/ref&gt; Only at this point did it become clear to the men of the fortress whom they were fighting.&lt;ref name="Hauge 36"/&gt;&lt;ref name="T&amp;N 87"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Berg 12-13"&gt;Berg 1997: 12–13&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ribsskog 1998:45–50&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Grimnes 1990: 7–8&lt;/ref&gt; Later, at 04:35, ''Oberst'' Eriksen received a message from the Norwegian [[Minesweeper (ship)|minesweeper]] [[HNoMS Otra (1939)|HNoMS ''Otra'']] confirming that the intruding ships were German.&lt;ref name="Berg 13"/&gt; The message had been sent to the naval base in [[Horten]] at 04:10, but the massive communications problems that severely hampered the efforts of the Norwegian military throughout the Norwegian Campaign had prevented it from reaching Oscarsborg in time.&lt;ref&gt;Berg 1997: 10&lt;/ref&gt;

The return fire from ''Blücher'' was ineffective, with the light artillery mostly pointing too high and the main batteries, 20.3&amp;nbsp;cm guns, unable to fire due to the damage caused by the second 28&amp;nbsp;cm round from Oscarsborg's Main Battery. The shelling lasted only for five to seven minutes. When the guns on both sides silenced, with all the "passengers" still under deck—"there was a dead silence on board the whole ship, no movement whatsoever was identified".&lt;ref name= "Binder 77"&gt;Binder 2001: 77&lt;/ref&gt;

===''Kommandørkaptein'' Anderssen launches the torpedoes===
After passing the line of fire of the fortress' gun batteries, the cruiser was burning and severely damaged, but her captain still hoped he would be able to save his ship. At this point, however, ''Blücher'' entered the sights of ''Kommandørkaptein'' Anderssen as she slid past the torpedo battery at a range of only {{convert|500|m|yd|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;Hauge 1995: 37&lt;/ref&gt; The retired torpedoes the officer was aiming at the cruiser were 40-year-old [[Robert Whitehead#Use of the torpedo|Whitehead]] weapons of [[Austria-Hungary|Austro-Hungarian]] manufacture. These torpedoes had been practice-launched well over 200 times before, but no one was certain if they would function or not.&lt;ref name="Hauge 36"/&gt; As ''Kommandørkaptein'' Anderssen pushed the firing mechanism button for the torpedoes, at approximately 04:30, the weapons turned out to work perfectly; first one and then another torpedo raced out of their underwater exit tunnels at {{convert|3|m|ft|abbr=on}} below the surface toward the burning warship. As Anderssen had overestimated the speed of his target slightly, the first torpedo hit near ''Blücher''{{'}}s forward turret (nicknamed "''Anton''"), creating only inconsequential damage.&lt;ref name="Ribsskog 51"/&gt; The aim was corrected for the second torpedo launch and the torpedo struck ''Blücher'' amidships, hitting the same general area as the first 28&amp;nbsp;cm shell.&lt;ref name="Ribsskog 51"/&gt; This caused catastrophic damage to the cruiser and blew open many of her bulkheads, allowing water to flood her decks while she was burning furiously.&lt;ref name= "Ribsskog 53"/&gt; The third torpedo launcher was left loaded in case more ships were to follow close behind ''Blücher''. After firing, the two other tubes were reloaded and readied for the next target.

===End of ''Blücher''===
[[File:Senkingen av Blücher (5654566265).jpg|thumb|''Blücher'' on fire and sinking in [[Drøbak Sound]]]]
With all engines knocked out by the second torpedo hit, the cruiser anchored near the [[Askholmene, Frogn|Askholmene]] islets just north and out of the arc of fire of the fort's guns to try to fight the ferocious fires raging throughout the vessel. ''Blücher''{{'}}s torpedoes were fired against land to avoid them exploding in the uncontrolled fires aboard.&lt;ref name="Hauge 38"&gt;Hauge 1995: 38&lt;/ref&gt; The crew's struggle ended when, at 05:30,&lt;ref name="Hauge 38"/&gt; fires reached a midship ammunition hold for the [[10.5 cm FlaK 38|{{convert|10.5|cm|in|2|abbr=on}} ''Flak'' gun]]s, blowing a large gap in the ship's side.&lt;ref name="Hauge 38"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Will 33-34"&gt;Williamson 2003: 33–34&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Tamelander&amp;Zetterling 2001: 88&lt;/ref&gt; The magazine blast ruptured the bulkheads between the boiler rooms and tore open the cruiser's fuel bunkers, igniting further fires. By this point, ''Blücher'' was doomed.&lt;ref name="Will 33-34"/&gt;

At 06:22, ''Blücher'' sank bow first into the depths of the Oslofjord, first laying over on her port side, then turning upside-down and finally succumbing with her screws the last to disappear below the surface.&lt;ref name="Ribsskog 53"/&gt; After the ship had disappeared from the surface, large quantities of oil floated up and covered the close to two thousand sailors and soldiers fighting for their lives in the freezing water. The oil rapidly caught fire, killing hundreds more Germans.&lt;ref name="Hauge 42"/&gt;

''[[Obergefreiter]]'' Günther Morgalla—who survived the sinking—later said that, swimming toward his shivering crew mates onshore, he heard someone defiantly singing the ''[[Deutschlandlied]]'' followed by "''Das kann doch einen Seemann nicht erschüttern.''" ("''That cannot shake a sailor''").&lt;ref name="Binder 89"&gt;Binder 2001: 89&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:German soldiers and Blücher sinking.jpg|thumb|right|German survivors, with the sinking ''Blücher'' in the background]]
In all, 650–800 Germans died,&lt;ref name="Ribsskog 53"/&gt; and 550 of the approximately 1,400 wet and cold survivors of ''Blücher'' were [[Prisoner of war|captured]] by soldiers from Company no. 4 of the [[Hans Majestet Kongens Garde|Norwegian Royal Guards]] under the command of ''[[Norwegian military ranks|Kaptein]]'' (Captain) A. J. T. Petersson.&lt;ref name="Hauge 42"/&gt; In total, some 1,200 of the survivors had made it ashore at [[Frogn]] near Drøbak. The guardsmen were supposed to take all the Germans prisoner, but mainly focused on caring for the many wounded and dying.&lt;ref&gt;Hansen 2005: 71&lt;/ref&gt; Around 1,000 of the Germans, including ''[[Generalmajor]]'' [[Erwin Engelbrecht]] and Admiral [[Oskar Kummetz]], were eventually moved to a nearby farm and placed under light guard. None of the prisoners were interrogated. By 18:30, the Norwegian soldiers withdrew from the area, abandoning the Germans. Engelbrecht and  Kummetz then made their way to Oslo.&lt;ref&gt;Arneberg 1989: 62, 65&lt;/ref&gt; The leading German officers reached Oslo at 22:00, moving into the [[Hotel Continental, Oslo|Hotel Continental]], though without most of the troops intended to occupy the capital.&lt;ref&gt;Arneberg 1989: 65&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hansen 2005: 72&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the German wounded were initially taken to Åsgården summer hotel in [[Åsgårdstrand]] for medical care, where Norwegian wounded had already been brought. The hotel was the temporary improvised location for the Royal Norwegian Navy Hospital, which had been evacuated from Horten at midnight on 8 April.&lt;ref&gt;Sivertsen 2001: 78&lt;/ref&gt;

==Remaining ships retreat==
By the time ''Blücher'' sank, the remaining naval force destined for [[Oslo]] had long since turned around and retreated back down the fjord. Seeing the geysers of water from underwater explosions on ''Blücher'', and unaware of the torpedo battery, the commander of the [[heavy cruiser]] [[German cruiser Deutschland|''Lützow'']] (the recently renamed [[Deutschland-class cruiser|'pocket battleship' ''Deutschland'']]) assumed the flagship had hit mines and at 04:40 the decision was made for the flotilla to turn back and land the invasion forces out of range of the Oscarsborg batteries. The planned coup against Oslo to force the surrender of the Norwegian government was replaced by a land advance up the Oslofjord.&lt;ref&gt;Grimnes 1990: 14&lt;/ref&gt;

As the force made good its escape, the fortress managed to damage ''Lützow'', the 15&amp;nbsp;cm guns of the Kopås battery scoring three hits and knocking out the ship's forward 28&amp;nbsp;cm turret ("Anton").&lt;ref name="Fjeld2 36"/&gt; Kopås kept firing at the retreating ships until they disappeared in the mist at a range of around {{convert|3000|m|yd|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref name="Berg 13"/&gt; After pulling out of range of the fortress guns, ''Lützow'' employed her remaining turret "Bruno" to bombard the defenders from a range of {{convert|9|-|10|km|nmi mi|lk=on|abbr=on}} down the fjord.

During the battle, another burning ship was spotted in the distance from Oscarsborg, leading the Norwegian defenders to believe they had sunk another German warship in addition to ''Blücher''. For some time after the battle, the belief was that Oscarsborg had sunk the artillery training ship {{Ship|German training ship|Brummer||2}}. The reality, however, was that the burning ship was the {{convert|107|LT|t|abbr=on}} Norwegian cargo [[Cutter (boat)|cutter]] {{MS|Sørland||2}} that had stumbled into the battle while on her way from [[Moss, Norway|Moss]] to Oslo with a cargo of paper. As the small ship had mistaken the events as a military exercise, she kept going until fired upon and set ablaze by the German minesweepers ''R-18'' and ''R-19''. ''Sørland'' sank with two of her six-man crew near the village of Skiphelle in Drøbak, as the first civilian Norwegian ship lost during the invasion.&lt;ref name="Fjeld190"/&gt;&lt;ref name="WarsSør"/&gt;&lt;ref name="SkovSør"/&gt; ''Brummer'' was indeed lost in connection with the invasion, but only when she was on her way back to Germany on 14 April, when she was torpedoed by the Royal Navy submarine {{HMS|Sterlet|2S|6}} and sank the next day.&lt;ref&gt;German-navy.de: [http://german-navy.de/kriegsmarine/ships/training/brummer/history.html ''Brummer''] {{in lang|en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Luftwaffe'' bombing==
[[File:Oscarsborg Fortress under air attack, 9 April, 1940.jpg|thumb|Oscarsborg's Hovedøya under ''Luftwaffe'' attack]]

The fortress was subjected to heavy ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' bombing later on the same day, to which the fortress could only reply with two [[Bofors 40 mm gun|Bofors 40 mm L/60]] [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft (AA) gun]]s and three [[M1917 Browning machine gun|Colt M/29]] {{convert|7.92|mm|in|3|abbr=on}} AA [[machine gun]]s at Seiersten Battery, as well as another four Colt M/29 7.92&amp;nbsp;mm AA machine guns at Håøya Battery,&lt;ref&gt;Grimnes 1990: 15&lt;/ref&gt; but again there were no Norwegian casualties. Initially, four machine guns on the roof of the Main Battery also returned fire, but these had to be abandoned early on.&lt;ref name="Fjeld190"/&gt;

One of the two 40&amp;nbsp;mm guns became unserviceable after only 22 rounds; the other gun kept firing until 12:00, but to little effect. After a break in the attacks from 12:00 to 13:30, during which time ''Lützow'' bombarded Hovedøya,&lt;ref name="Fjeld190"/&gt; the ''Luftwaffe'' bombers returned at 13:30 and soon [[Strafing|strafed]] the remaining Norwegian anti-aircraft guns, forcing the crew to seek shelter in the nearby forest at around 14:00. In all, the fortress was subjected to nearly nine hours of air attack, during which time around five hundred bombs—ranging from {{convert|50|-|200|kg|lb|abbr=on}} in size—were dropped on Oscarsborg.&lt;ref name="Fjeld191"&gt;Fjeld 1999: 191&lt;/ref&gt; Amongst the bombers that attacked Oscarsborg were twenty-two long-range [[Junkers Ju 87|Junkers Ju 87R "Stuka"]] dive bombers of ''[[Sturzkampfgeschwader 1]]'' under the command of ''[[Hauptmann]]'' [[Paul-Werner Hozzel]], operating from [[Kiel-Holtenau airport]] in northern Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Weal 1997: 34–35&lt;/ref&gt;

==Surrender==
Although the German naval attack on Oslo had been thwarted by the actions of Oscarsborg, the city was seized later that day by forces that were airlifted into [[Oslo Airport, Fornebu|Fornebu Airport]]. In light of the fall of the capital, and with news of German landings at the village of [[Son, Norway|Son]] south of Drøbak,&lt;ref name="Fjeld191"/&gt; Colonel Eriksen decided that further fighting without adequate infantry support was in vain, and agreed to a ceasefire in the evening of 9 April. The fortress was surrendered intact on the morning of 10 April.&lt;ref name=fjeld192&gt;Fjeld 1999: 192&lt;/ref&gt;

The garrison at the main battery and at Håøya were treated separately by the Germans from those captured from the mainland batteries, and were released a week after the battle. The soldiers and non-commissioned officers captured at the mainland batteries were released three days after the fortress' surrender, while the officers were held as prisoners of war at [[Fredriksten Fortress]]. The [[Military reserve force|reserve officers]] were released on 15 May, while the full-time officers were transferred to [[Grini detention camp|Grini prison camp]] and released in late May 1940.&lt;ref name=fjeld192/&gt;

==Aftermath==
In one of the more peculiar battles of the war, a hundred year old fortification, manned by raw recruits and pensioners and armed with 40- to 50-year-old weaponry of German and Austro-Hungarian manufacture, had destroyed a ship so new, its crew was still finishing training. Oscarsborg had fulfilled its mission and denied an invader access to the capital. Even though it and the country were ultimately captured and occupied, the effects of delaying the German advance were immediate and considerable. On board ''Blücher'' were troops specially designated to capture the King, [[Cabinet Nygaardsvold|the Norwegian cabinet]], the [[Storting]] (Norwegian Parliament) and the national [[Flight of the Norwegian National Treasury|gold reserve]]; the delay made it possible for all these to escape.&lt;ref name=blucher&gt;{{cite encyclopedia |first=Ole Kristian |last=Grimnes |authorlink=Ole Kristian Grimnes | encyclopedia=[[Norsk krigsleksikon 1940-45]] |title=Blücher |editor=[[Hans Fredrik Dahl|Dahl]] |editor2= [[Guri Hjeltnes|Hjeltnes]] |editor3= [[Berit Nøkleby|Nøkleby]] |editor4= [[Nils Johan Ringdal|Ringdal]] |editor5= [[Øystein Sørensen|Sørensen]] |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2010113005006 |accessdate= | year=1995 |publisher=Cappelen |location=Oslo |isbn=82-02-14138-9 |pages=46–47 |language=Norwegian }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 April, the Storting was able to convene at [[Elverum]] and give the cabinet [[Elverum Authorization|a wide authorization]] to govern until a Storting could again assemble. Thus, the Norwegian government was able to continue the defence of Norway until it had evacuated to exile in the [[United Kingdom]] on [[7 June in Norway|7 June]], with the [[Norwegian Army]] laying down their arms on 10 June.

==Media adaption==
The battle is depicted in the 2016 feature film ''[[The King's Choice]]''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.forsvarsbygg.no/festningene/Nyhetsarkiv/2016/kongens-nei/ |title=Kongens nei |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |date=24 August 2016 |website=[[Norwegian Defence Estates Agency]] |publisher= |access-date=16 January 2017 |language=Norwegian }}{{Dead link|date=June 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book |last=Arneberg |first=Sven T. |authorlink= |author2=Kristian Hosar |title=Vi dro mot nord : felttoget i Norge i april 1940, skildret av tyske soldater og offiserer: (Oslo, Østfold, Akershus, Hedmark, Oppland, Møre og Romsdal) |publisher=Aventura |location=Oslo |year=1989 |isbn= |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2009063001017 |language=Norwegian}}
*{{cite book |title=I skjærgården og på havet – Marinens krig 8. april 1940 &amp;ndash; 8. mai 1945 |last=Berg |first=Ole F. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1997 |publisher=Marinens krigsveteranforening |location=Oslo |isbn=82-993545-2-8 |page= |pages= |url= |language= Norwegian}}
*Binder, Frank &amp; Schlünz Hans Hermann: ''Schwerer Kreuzer Blücher'', Koehlers Verlagsgesellschaft mbH, Hamburg 2001 {{ISBN|3-7822-0784-X}} {{in lang|de}}
*{{lang|no|Engdahl, Odd G. (ed.): ''Norsk Marinehistorisk Atlas 900–2005'', Vigmostad &amp; Bjørke, Bergen 2006|italic=unset}} {{in lang|no}}
*{{cite book |title=Klar til strid – Kystartilleriet gjennom århundrene |last=Fjeld |first=Odd T. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1999 |publisher=Kystartilleriets Offisersforening |location=Oslo |isbn=82-995208-0-0 |page= |pages= |url= |language=Norwegian}}
*{{lang|no|Fjeld, Odd T. (ed.): ''Kystartilleriet 100 år'', Sjømilitære Samfund ved Norsk Tidsskrift for Sjøvesen, Hundvåg 1999 {{ISBN|82-994738-6-1}}|italic=unset}} {{in lang|no}}&lt;br&gt;(to be quoted as Fjeld2 1999)
*{{lang|no|[[Ole Kristian Grimnes|Grimnes, Ole Kristian]]: ''Oscarsborg festning – 9. april 1940'', Forsvarets Krigshistoriske Avdeling, 1990|italic=unset}} {{in lang|no}}
*{{lang|no|Hansen, Ola Bøe (ed.): ''Sjøkrigens skjebner – deres egne beretninger'', Sjømilitære Samfund ved Forlaget Norsk Tidsskrift for Sjøvesen, Gjøvik 2005 {{ISBN|82-92217-22-3}}|italic=unset}} {{in lang|no}}
*{{cite book|last=Hauge|first=Andreas|title=Kampene i Norge 1940|volume=1|publisher=Krigshistorisk Forlag|location=Sandefjord|year=1995|isbn=82-993369-0-2|language=Norwegian}}
*{{lang|no|Ribsskog, Asbjørn: ''Kystartilleriet under den annen verdenskrig 1939–1945'', Atheneum Forlag as, Vinterbro 1998|italic=unset}} {{in lang|no}}
*{{lang|no|Sivertsen, Svein Carl (ed.): ''Sjøforsvaret dag for dag 1814–2000'', Sjømilitære Samfund ved Norsk Tidsskrift for Sjøvesen, Hundvåg 2001 {{ISBN|82-92217-03-7}}|italic=unset}} {{in lang|no}}
*{{lang|no|Stangeland, Gro &amp; Valebrokk, Eva: ''Norges bedste Værn og Fæste – Nasjonale festningsverk'', Wigestrand Forlag AS, Stavanger 2001 {{ISBN|82-91370-35-4}}|italic=unset}} {{in lang|no}}
*{{lang|no|Tamelander, Michael &amp; Zetterling, Niklas: ''9. april Nazitysklands invasjon av Norge'', Spartacus Forlag AS, Oslo 2001|italic=unset}} {{in lang|no}}
*{{cite book |last=Weal |first=John |title=Junkers Ju 87 Stukageschwader 1937–41 |series=Osprey Combat Aircraft |volume=1 |year=1997 |edition=First |location=Oxford |publisher=Osprey Publishing |isbn=978-1-84176-439-9}}
*[[Gordon Williamson (writer)|Williamson, Gordon]]: ''German Heavy Cruisers 1939–45'', Osprey Publishing Ltd., Oxford 2003 {{ISBN|1-84176-502-3}}

==External links==
{{commons category|The Sinking of Blücher 1940}}
*[http://www.forsvaretsmuseer.no/Oscarsborg Oscarsborg Fortress Museum official website] {{in lang|no}}
*[http://www.akershus.com/en/Follo/product/?TLp=180567&amp;Oscarsborg-Fortress= Oscarsborg Fortress website]{{in lang|en}}
*[http://www.oscarsborg.no Website on the fortress] {{in lang|no}}
*[https://www.forsvarsbygg.no/contentassets/f5fe5db8478843a9bb89cdfabe6d6156/oscarsborg-festningsloype-engelsk_2013.pdf Oscarsborg Fortress, map] [[Norwegian Defence Estates Agency]] {{in lang|en}} 
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20120119055430/http://www.festningsverk.no/oscarsborg3.htm Oscarsborg Museum – history of the fortress] {{in lang|no|en}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20130323063435/http://mil.no/culture-attractions/museums/oscarsborgfortress/Pages/default.aspx Norwegian Armed Forces website page about the fortress] {{in lang|en}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070321163034/http://www.aftenposten.no/fakta/verdenskrig/article449062.ece 50 year anniversary Aftenposten newspaper article on the invasion of Norway] {{in lang|no}}

{{coord|59.7009|N|10.5927|E|source:wikidata|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Drobak Sound, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Norway]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Norwegian Campaign]]
[[Category:1940 in Norway]]
[[Category:History of Viken (county)]]
[[Category:Frogn]]
[[Category:April 1940 events]]</text><sha1>2gdbbzqjpishsr6po2jbi1jaxg8krzx</sha1></revision></page>