<page><title>Battle of Dombås</title><ns>0</ns><id>15073165</id><revision><id>964864140</id><parentid>948220850</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-28T01:16:21Z</timestamp><contributor><username>InternetArchiveBot</username><id>27015025</id></contributor><comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0.1</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="35957" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2019}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Battle of Dombås
|image = Dombås 1940 4.PNG
|image_size = 300px
|caption = German [[Junkers Ju 52]] downed at Dombås
|partof = the [[Norwegian Campaign]] of the Second World War
|date = 14–19 April 1940
|place = [[Dombås]] area in [[Dovre]], [[Gudbrandsdal]], Norway
|result = Norwegian tactical victory
* German [[Fallschirmjäger (Nazi Germany)|''Fallschirmjäger'']] company blocks the north-south and west-east rail and road systems for five days before surrendering
|combatant1 = {{flagcountry|Norway}}
|combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1 = '''14–17 April:'''&lt;br /&gt;[[Ivar Navelsaker]]&lt;ref name="Høgevold84 121"&gt;Høgevold 1984: 121&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'''17–19 April:'''&lt;br /&gt;[[Arne Sunde]]&lt;ref name="Hauge95 261"&gt;Hauge-1 1995: 261&lt;/ref&gt;
|commander2 = [[Herbert Schmidt (Fallschirmjäger)|Herbert Schmidt]]{{POW}}&lt;ref name="Hauge95 251"&gt;Hauge-1 1995: 251&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength1 = '''14–17 April:'''&lt;br /&gt;•2nd Battalion,&lt;br /&gt;Infantry Regiment 11&lt;ref name= "Hauge95 251"/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;•No. 1 Company of&lt;br /&gt;Infantry Regiment 5&lt;ref name="Hauge95 258"&gt;Hauge-1 1995: 258&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'''17–19 April:'''&lt;br /&gt;•1st Battalion,&lt;br /&gt;Infantry Regiment 11&lt;br /&gt;•No. 1 Company of&lt;br /&gt;Infantry Regiment 5&lt;br /&gt;•Machine gun platoon from [[Norwegian Army Air Service|NoAAS]] Jagevingen&lt;br /&gt;•40 mm anti-aircraft gun&lt;ref name="Hauge95 259"&gt;Hauge-1 1995: 259&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'''19 April:'''&lt;br /&gt;•[[Railway gun|Rail mounted]] [[howitzer]] manned by [[Royal Marines]]&lt;ref name="Hauge95 261"/&gt;
|strength2 = •4 officers and 181 men of the 1st Company,&lt;br /&gt;1st Regiment of the&lt;br /&gt;[[1st Parachute Division (Germany)|7th ''Flieger'' Division]]&lt;ref name="Jervaas"&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.nuav.net/fallschirm.html |title=The Fallschirmjäger Battle at Dombaas |accessdate=22 January 2009 |author=Bjørn Jervaas |work=Norway during world war 2 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090201081816/http://nuav.net/fallschirm.html |archivedate=1 February 2009 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties1 = 20 dead&lt;br /&gt;20 wounded&lt;ref name=Molmen42&gt;Mølmen 1998: 42&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2 = '''During the drop:'''&lt;br /&gt;15 dead,&lt;br /&gt;20 wounded&lt;br /&gt;and 14 injured.&lt;br /&gt;7 [[Junkers Ju 52]]s shot down,&lt;br /&gt;an eighth Ju 52 landed in Sweden and sank through a frozen lake.&lt;br /&gt;'''During the fighting:'''&lt;br /&gt;6 [[Killed in action|killed]]&lt;br /&gt;6 [[Wounded in action|wounded]]&lt;br /&gt;ca. 150 captured
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Norwegian Campaign}}
}}

The '''Battle of Dombås''' was fought between [[Norwegian Army]] infantry forces and [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[Fallschirmjäger (Nazi Germany)|''Fallschirmjäger'']] paratroops in mid-April 1940. As part of their conquest of Norway south of [[Trondheim]], and as a countermeasure against reported [[Åndalsnes landings|Allied landings]] in the [[Romsdal]] area of [[Vestlandet|south western Norway]], the Germans dropped a company of [[paratrooper]]s near the vital railroad junction of [[Dombås]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.jernbaneverket.no/english/forTravellers/index.jhtml;jsessionid=BWTKPWOSKDU5VQ5BAIJSBHQ?intSecId=1151413&amp;expanded=Domb%E5s#Domb%E5s|title=Dombås|accessdate=22 January 2009|work=[[Norwegian National Rail Administration]]|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090125082339/http://www.jernbaneverket.no/english/forTravellers/index.jhtml#Domb%E5s|archive-date=25 January 2009|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; on 14 April 1940. For the next five days, the German force blocked the [[Dovre Line]] railroad line between [[Oslo]] and Trondheim, as well as the main road between the two cities.

==Background==
Shortly after the [[Operation Weserübung|German invasion of Norway]] on 9 April 1940, the Allies launched [[Allied campaign in Norway|their own campaign in Norway]] to support the [[Norwegian Defence Force]] and prevent the Germans in seizing control of the strategically important country.

On 13 April, [[Colonel General|''Generaloberst'']] [[Nikolaus von Falkenhorst]]—the commander of the German invasion forces in Norway—received orders from the ''[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]'' (Armed Forces High Command; OKW) in Berlin to seize control of the village of Dombås, some {{convert|336|km|mi|abbr=on}} north of Oslo, by paratroop attack. The reason for the OKW's decision was a false report of [[Åndalsnes landings|Allied landings at Åndalsnes]], an event that only occurred several days later. The main task at hand for the German troops was the destruction of the railroad, as well as blocking any Allied advance inland, particularly south through the [[Gudbrandsdal]] valley.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 249"&gt;Hauge-1 1995: 249&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Quarrie8&gt;Quarrie 2007: 8&lt;/ref&gt;

==Opposing forces==

===German===
The German force air dropped on Dombås was the 1st Company of the 1st Battalion of the 1st Regiment of the [[1st Parachute Division (Germany)|7th ''Flieger'' Division]]. Based at [[Stendal|Heimatstandort Stendal]] near [[Magdeburg]] the unit was ordered to Norway on 12 April, landing at [[Oslo Airport, Fornebu|Fornebu Airport]] near Oslo on 13 April. 1st Company was commanded by ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' [[Herbert Schmidt (Fallschirmjäger)|Herbert Schmidt]] and was 185 strong, armed with light weaponry and 22 [[MG34]] machine guns; four of which were mounted on tripods for the [[medium machine gun]] role.&lt;ref name="Jervaas"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Quarrie7&gt;Quarrie 2007: 7&lt;/ref&gt; While the other four companies of the battalion had been sent into action on the first day of the German invasion of Denmark and Norway, the 1st Company had initially been held in reserve.&lt;ref name=Quarrie7/&gt;

===Norwegian===
The Norwegian force initially based at Dombås was the 2nd Battalion of Infantry Regiment 11.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 251"/&gt; Two days after the attack No. 1 Company of Infantry Regiment 5 arrived as reinforcements&lt;ref name="Hauge95 258"/&gt; and on 17 April 2 Battalion was replaced by its sister unit, 1st Battalion of Infantry Regiment 11. Reinforcements in the form of a machine gun platoon and an [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft gun]] also arrived on 17 April.&lt;ref name= "Hauge95 259"/&gt; On the last day of the battle, the Norwegians were joined by some of the first British forces [[Allied campaign in Norway|to see action]] on land in Norway when a [[howitzer]] manned by [[Royal Marines]] joined the fighting.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 261"/&gt;

==Battle==

===Day one===
At around 17:00 Norwegian time on 14 April, 15 [[Junkers Ju 52]] transport aircraft took off from Fornebu Airport near Oslo in hail and sleet with low cloud cover. An hour earlier, one Ju 52 had flown a reconnaissance flight over the drop area at Dombås without being able to see anything through the cloud cover.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 251"/&gt;

Even though the officers on the site wished to postpone the mission due to the weather conditions the fact that the mission was based on a direct command from [[Adolf Hitler]] meant that it had to be carried out despite the risks involved.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 251"/&gt;

The mission the German ''Fallschirmjäger'' embarked on was the second opposed paratroop attack in history, the first had occurred five days previously when the Norwegian airbase of [[Sola Air Station|Sola]] near [[Stavanger]] was captured during the 9 April invasion of Norway.&lt;ref name= "Hauge95 251"/&gt;

====The drop====
[[File:NorwegianGroundCampaign.jpg|thumb|left|180px|Map of the ground campaign in southern Norway in April and May, 1940. [[Dombås]] is in the centre of the top half of the map.]]

When the German aircraft arrived over their target area, after a {{convert|275|km|mi|abbr=on}} flight, small breaks in the cloud cover enabled most of the Ju 52s to drop their sticks (loads) of paratroopers. The poor weather conditions led to the Germans being spread over a large area, stretching from [[Lesja]] {{convert|20|km|mi|abbr=on}} west of the target, [[Vålåsjø]] {{convert|18|km|mi|abbr=on}} north east of the target and locations {{convert|8|km|mi|abbr=on}} to the south in the Gudbrandsdal valley.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 251"/&gt;

====Fighting the II/IR11====
To the misfortune of the German paratroopers, their target area was coincidentally also the temporary base and encampment of the 2nd Battalion of the Norwegian Army's Infantry Regiment 11 (II/IR 11). The battalion had been mobilised in [[Molde]] a few days previously and had arrived by train in Dombås in the evening of 13 April.&lt;ref name="Høgevold84 121"/&gt; The deployment had been made in preparation for what the Norwegian Army High Command expected would be a major attempt at reconquering Trondheim in cooperation with Allied forces. Although there were no anti-aircraft guns in the area, II/IR11 had positioned their {{convert|7.92|mm|in|3|abbr=on}} [[M1917 Browning machine gun|Colt M/29]] [[heavy machine gun]]s on anti-aircraft mounts in order to provide some basic low-level air defence.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 251"/&gt;

The arrival of the German aircraft over Dombås came as a surprise to the Norwegian forces who nonetheless soon opened fire on the Ju 52s with all available arms. Gunners aboard the Ju 52s returned fire while flying at treetop level. Soon after, the first paratroopers were dropped over the area and took heavy fire while descending to the ground. The ground fire took a heavy toll on the German transport aircraft, with only five out of the original 15 Ju 52s making it back to Fornebu, with another two landing at [[Trondheim Airport, Værnes|Værnes Airbase]] near Trondheim, all seven surviving aircraft riddled with bullet holes.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 262"/&gt; The remaining eight transports were shot down or made forced landings.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 253"&gt;Hauge-1 1995: 253&lt;/ref&gt; One Ju 52 made an emergency landing on [[Vänern]] Lake near [[Mariestad]], Sweden, where it later broke through the ice and sank. The aircraft was salvaged and returned to the [[Luftwaffe]] by the Swedish authorities in January 1941.&lt;ref&gt;Hafsten 1991: 31–32&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the paratroopers that had been on the shot-down aircraft died in the crashes, or were killed or captured by Norwegian patrols soon after.

Of his originally 185 strong force&lt;ref name="Jervaas"/&gt; ''Oberleutnant'' Schmidt only managed to gather around him 63 men, the rest having died or been scattered over a vast area. With this straitened force, Schmidt began carrying out the assigned task of blocking the Norwegian rail and road network. The German force blocked the main road in the area and cut the telephone wire running next to it. After capturing a Norwegian [[taxicab]] and putting as many of his men as he could in and onto the vehicle, Schmidt drove north toward Dombås, stopping at regular intervals to make forward observations.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 253"/&gt;

====Schmidt is wounded====
[[File:Ulekleiv south of Dombås.jpg|thumb|The road near Ulekleiv]]

When the taxi-borne German force reached the farmstead of Li on the road to Dombås, they ran into two truck-loads of soldiers from No. 5 Company, IR 11. After some initial confusion the Norwegian opened fire and the Germans charged with [[submachine gun]]s and [[hand grenade]]s. Following a short fire fight during which Schmidt was severely wounded and the Norwegians pushed back, the paratroopers abandoned their advance on Dombås. They instead pulled back and took up positions in a hedgehog [[defensive fighting position]] at the farms of Ulekleiv and Hagevolden, covering all directions and dominating the surrounding landscape. Schmidt—although seriously wounded in the hip and stomach—never relinquished command and ordered his men to use sand to write messages in the snow to the ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' asking for supplies of provisions and ammunition. The force was not spotted by ''Luftwaffe'' reconnaissance aircraft and received no supply drops while at Ulekleiv/Hagevolden.&lt;ref name=Quarrie8/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hauge-1 1995: 254&lt;/ref&gt;

====Side-effects of the attack====
The attack at Dombås made the [[Norges Bank|Norwegian Central Bank]] speed up [[Flight of the Norwegian National Treasury|the evacuation]] of the Norwegian [[Official gold reserves|gold reserves]]. The {{convert|50|t|ST|lk=on|abbr=on}} of gold had been evacuated from Oslo on 9 April and was being kept in a [[Bank vault|vault]] in [[Lillehammer]]&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://home.online.no/~aaroenes/krigen/Bakgrunn_gulltransporten.htm |title=Dette er Gulltransporten |accessdate=22 January 2009 |date=19 April 2000 |work=Glimt fra Molde |language=Norwegian |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070930065418/http://home.online.no/~aaroenes/krigen/Bakgrunn_gulltransporten.htm |archivedate=30 September 2007 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; when the German attack on Dombås began. As soon as news of German paratroopers landing spread, the gold was put on a train and brought to [[Åndalsnes]] from where it was evacuated by way of [[Royal Navy|British]] [[cruiser]]s and Norwegian [[fishing boat]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url= http://www.dokpro.uio.no/umk/blanding/gullbehold.html|title=Verdens største mynthandel|accessdate= 22 January 2009|work=[[University of Oslo]]|language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Haakon VII of Norway|King Haakon VII of Norway]] and his son, [[Olav V of Norway|Crown Prince Olav]] were both at [[Dovre]], near the drop zone and only 30 minutes from the nearest groups of paratroopers when the attack began on 14 April. The King and Crown Prince both had to be escorted out of the area by members of the Dovreskogen Rifle Club.&lt;ref&gt;Hauge-1 1995: 257&lt;/ref&gt;

===Day two===
[[File:Dombås Station.jpg|thumb|[[Dombås Station]], the primary objective of the German attack]]

15 April saw the last remaining stragglers rejoining the ''Fallschirmjäger'' force at Dombås, from then on no reinforcements reached the 1st Company. During the morning the paratroopers fulfilled part of their mission when they blew up the rail road line in three places.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 256"&gt;Hauge-1 1995: 256&lt;/ref&gt; The damage to the line was however quickly repaired by Norwegian work crews, and trains passed through the next day.&lt;ref&gt;Årflot 1985: 49&lt;/ref&gt;

In the meanwhile Norwegian forces had been assembled and ordered to stop the German advance in the Dombås area. As intelligence on the ''Fallschirmjägers'' was very scarce the Norwegian commanders had little idea of the size and location of the German force. During the day a force of two heavy machine gun platoons with 41 men under the command of [[Norwegian military ranks|''Kaptein'']] [[Eiliv Austlid]]—&lt;ref name="VGDovre"&gt;{{Cite news|first=Guri|last=Hjeltnes|authorlink=Guri Hjeltnes |title=Dramaet på Dovre|url=http://www.vg.no/pub/vgart.hbs?artid=225040|work=[[Verdens Gang]]| date=27 April 2004|accessdate=11 February 2009|language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; under orders from government minister [[Trygve Lie]]—launched an assault without the benefit of a vanguard on Schmidt's position to secure a route of escape for the Norwegian royal family and the Norwegian cabinet.&lt;ref name="VGDovre"/&gt; The assault team—composed of Austlid and six or seven volunteers—stormed across a {{convert|200|m|yd|abbr=on}}-long [[Field (agriculture)|field]] toward the German positions while receiving cover fire from his own heavy machine guns. With only {{convert|75|m|yd|abbr=on}} between them and the Germans, the eight Norwegians had to make their way up the hillside through deep snow. Austlid was only {{convert|8|-|10|m|yd|abbr=on}} below the first German machine gun nest when he was struck down by a bullet to the chest and the counterattack faltered without its leader. Of the 41 Norwegians caught in the ambush, 28 were captured and five escaped.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 256"/&gt;&lt;ref name="VGDovre"/&gt;

===Day three===
On 16 April, No. 1 Company, IR 5 under the command of ''Kaptein'' Botheim arrived on the scene of battle. No. 1 Company attacked the German strongholds from the south while II/IR 11 attacked with one company from the north. The northern onslaught was supported by two {{convert|81|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} [[Mortar (weapon)|mortars]] and numerous Colt M/29s.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 258"/&gt;

After a short fire fight, a white flag appeared at the German positions, and one of the Norwegian soldiers captured in the previous day's ambush was sent over to the Norwegian forces. The released [[prisoner of war]] brought with him a demand that the Norwegians surrender and told the Norwegian officer in charge that Schmidt threatened to shoot his prisoners unless the fire ceased.&lt;ref name= "Hauge95 258"/&gt; This was probably based on a misunderstanding between the Norwegian POW and ''Oberleutnant'' Schmidt, the real meaning most likely being that the prisoners held were endangered by the mortar fire that the German positions were subjected to.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 258"/&gt; In response to the surrender demands a German ''[[Feldwebel]]'' that the Norwegians had captured was despatched back to Schmidt calling for ''his'' surrender. The Germans likewise refused to give in.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 258"/&gt;

====Breakout from Ulekleiv and Hagevolden====
While the fruitless negotiations were taking place the ''Fallschirmjägers'' were preparing to move away from their stronghold and find a new place to fight from. The arrival of the two Norwegian mortars had completely changed the tactical situation and the German force's supply of ammunition was also running dangerously low. Schmidt decided that he had to move his troops into a new and more defensible position. Negotiations were kept up to buy time so the paratroopers could slip away into cover of darkness. Schmidt believed that strong German forces were advancing up the Gudbrandsdal valley and that if he could hold out for a little while longer the situation might still be salvaged. The reality of the situation was however that the German advanced units were stuck just north of [[Minnesund]] far to the south of both Gudbrandsdal and Dombås.&lt;ref name= "Hauge95 258"/&gt;

As negotiations collapsed, the Norwegians opened fire again, but a sudden [[ground blizzard]] blinded the gunners and allowed the Germans to make a counterattack and break out of their encirclement. The attack threw back the Norwegian forces in the north, whose commander ordered a general retreat to Dombås. On the night of 16/17 April, the ''Fallschirmjäger'' under Schmidt—having thrown back the nearest Norwegian forces—disengaged and began to make their way south in the direction of Dovre.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 258"/&gt;

16 April also saw the continuation of mopping up operations by Norwegian units. Twenty-two Germans were captured at Kolstad near Lesja and another 23 at [[Bottheim Station|Bottheim train station]].&lt;ref name= "Hauge95 258"/&gt; The prisoners were initially held in the basement sitting room of Ulekleiv Hotel in Dombås.&lt;ref&gt;Årflot 1985: 67&lt;/ref&gt;

===Day four===
Early in the morning on 17 April, the Germans withdrew from their positions, covered by three heavy machine guns captured from the Norwegians in the ambush on 15 April. The paratroopers formed a fighting column with hand grenade armed soldiers at the front followed by the wounded and the POWs on trucks with a rearguard at the end.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 258"/&gt;

At Landheim road bridge, a 25-strong Norwegian force blocked the way, but was quickly thrown back to [[Dovre Church]] by a night attack with hand grenades. The German force took up temporary positions at Einbugga road bridge, midway between the village of [[Toftemo]] to the north and Dovre to the south.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 258"/&gt;

====Lindse Farms====
With daybreak, Schmidt's men began to search out a new position which could provide good cover without the risk of being attacked from the rear. This they found at the North and South Lindse Farm,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://visitnorway.com/templates/NTRproduct.aspx?id=173645#|title=The Lindse Farms – Dovre|accessdate=22 January 2009|date=13 March 2007|work=[[Innovation Norway]]|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071114171637/http://www.visitnorway.com/templates/NTRproduct.aspx?id=173645|archivedate=14 November 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; a farmstead high on a hillside and dominating both the railway line ({{convert|250|m|yd|abbr=on}} away) and the main road ({{convert|700|m|yd|abbr=on}} away). North Lindse—with its stone barn—became the strong point of the defence, with South Lindse being used to keep Norwegian prisoners; 15 military personnel and 40 civilians. The farm buildings were quickly fortified with sandbags and planking. ''Oberleutnant'' Schmidt was carried to Lindse on a door by Norwegian POWs.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 258"/&gt;

====Renewed fighting====
On the morning of 17 April, fighting was renewed when first the Norwegian [[Norwegian military ranks|Major]] [[Alv Kjøs]] and then No. 1 Company ran into German ambushes by Lindse. Kjøs was captured, as was the vanguard of No. 1 Company. The main force of No. 1 Company fought its way out, pulling back to Dovre Church at 10:00.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 259"/&gt;

After the first encounter of the day, the main Norwegian forces failed to realise that the whole ''Fallschirmjäger'' force had moved to Lindse and spent the day reorganizing and receiving reinforcements. II/IR 11 was replaced by its sister battalion, I/IR 11, and a machine gun platoon from the [[Norwegian Army Air Service]]′ ''Jagevingen'' fighter unit (the unit having lost all its aircraft around Oslo on 9 April) arrived to reinforce the attacks on Schmidt's paratroopers. For most of the day the abandoned German positions at Ulekleiv was bombarded by Norwegian mortars. Only in evening did the Norwegian commanders discover where the Germans had relocated.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 259"/&gt; On the night of 17/18 April, [[Norwegian military ranks|''fenrik'']] (''Second Lieutenant'') L. K. Løkken of the [[Raufoss]] Anti-aircraft Command arrived with a 40&amp;nbsp;mm anti-aircraft gun.&lt;ref name="ZG222"&gt;Zeiner-Gundersen: 222&lt;/ref&gt;

===Day five===
18 April turned out to be a decisive day in the battle. The Germans at Lindse were surrounded to the north by the battalion I/IR 11 and to the south by No. 1 Company, IR 5, reinforced by various smaller forces that had arrived the previous day. The company in the south also had the 40&amp;nbsp;mm AA gun, positioned at Dovre Train Station,&lt;ref name="Hauge95 262"/&gt; as [[artillery]] support. Early in the morning Norwegian soldiers made their way into the hills south of Lindse Farm and opened fire. According to Schmidt, this was when the situation became truly dire:

&lt;blockquote&gt;One step out of the nest or the house brought death. We now clung on only to the thought of immediate assistance.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 259"/&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Although the German positions were well fortified their ammunition was running very low and it was soon only a question of time before surrender became the only option left. Help, however, arrived that very morning when a Junkers Ju 52 air dropped ammunition, warm clothing, provisions, medical supplies and the radio frequency for communicating with headquarters.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 259"/&gt;

Later in the day a Norwegian officer approached Schmidt asking for his surrender, but was rejected. The Norwegian 40&amp;nbsp;mm AA gun kept up a bombardment of Lindse Farms throughout the day, firing 40–50 rounds at positions around the farm buildings and in two nearby [[ravine]]s.&lt;ref name= "Hauge95 259"/&gt;&lt;ref name="ZG222"/&gt; By evening the Germans had all sought shelter in the farm houses as these could not be bombarded directly due to the Norwegian prisoners being held there.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 259"/&gt;

===The last day===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-L04881, Herbert Schmidt.jpg|thumb|''Oberleutnant'' [[Herbert Schmidt (Fallschirmjäger)|Herbert Schmidt]] after receiving his [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] in May 1940]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-L06889, General Karl Kitzinger verleiht Eiserne Kreuze.jpg|thumb|''Fallschirmjägers'' being awarded with the [[Iron Cross]] in May 1940 by General [[Karl Kitzinger]]]]
[[File:Herbert Schmidt Die Fallschirmspringer von Dombas.jpg|thumb|The book by Herbert Schmidt: ''Die Fallschirmjäger von Dombas'', Berlin 1941]]

By dawn on 19 April, the Germans were completely surrounded by better-armed Norwegian troops. During the night, a final reinforcement had reached the Norwegians; a [[Railway gun|rail-mounted]] howitzer manned by a gun crew of Royal Marines that had arrived from Åndalsnes. The howitzer had 300 rounds available and opened fire at 06:00, firing ten rounds with good accuracy. Soon after another Ju 52 transport arrived carrying supplies to the beleaguered Germans but turned around without making its drop after receiving a radio message from Schmidt informing that the paratroopers were going to surrender.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 261"/&gt;

Later on. Schmidt sent out his second-in-command—''[[Leutnant]]'' Ernst Mössinger—to negotiate a surrender, hoping to reach favourable terms. ''Major'' [[Arne Sunde]], the Norwegian commander, however refused to accept anything but an unconditional surrender. Sunde told Mössinger that unless the Germans announced their surrender within 10 minutes by launching three flares the British and Norwegian artillery would recommence bombarding Lindse Farm. Nine and a half minutes later, at 11:30, the ''Fallschirmjäger'' force at Lindse fired three signal flares.&lt;ref name="Hauge95 261"/&gt;

Forty-five ''Fallschirmjäger'' surrendered at Lindse Farms, six of whom were wounded.&lt;ref name= "Hauge95 262"/&gt; After having been fed at the municipal building in Dovre, the captured Germans were sent by train to Dombås.&lt;ref&gt;Årflot 1985: 119&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
The Germans lost a total of 21 dead during the battle, as well as 40 wounded or injured. Of these, 15 of the fatalities occurred during the initial phase of the attack, as well as 20 wounded and 14 personnel suffering injuries. Six more were killed and another six wounded during the fighting that led to the final German surrender on 19 April. Around 150 Germans were taken as prisoners of war. Seven Junkers Ju 52 transports were shot by ground-fire and an eighth Ju 52 landed in [[Sweden during World War II|neutral Sweden]].&lt;ref name="Hauge95 262"&gt;Hauge-1 1995: 262&lt;/ref&gt; Norwegian casualties in the battle totaled 20 dead and 20 wounded.&lt;ref name=Molmen42/&gt; The Norwegian and German wounded who were treated by the Norwegian medical service were first treated at a [[field hospital]] in Dombås, before being moved to a regular hospital. The first train loads of wounded, leaving Dombås on 16 April, were destined for [[Molde Hospital]] in Molde, with later transports sent with the hospital ship {{MS|Brand IV||2}} from Åndalsnes to [[Ålesund Hospital]] in [[Ålesund]].&lt;ref&gt;Årflot 1985: 45–46&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Flatmark 1988: 54, 62&lt;/ref&gt; German dead were buried by the Norwegian military in [[mass grave]]s, eventually being moved post-war to a [[German War Graves Commission]] cemetery in [[Alfaset]], Oslo.&lt;ref&gt;Årflot 1985: 51&lt;/ref&gt;

Following their surrender, the captured German soldiers were sent to rear areas in the [[Romsdal]] region, the severely wounded to the hospital in Ålesund and the remainder (135 soldiers)&lt;ref&gt;Hauge-2 1995: 178&lt;/ref&gt; to a school in [[Kristiansund]].&lt;ref name=aarflot125&gt;Årflot 1985: 125&lt;/ref&gt; During German bombing raids on Kristiansund on 28–29 April, the prisoners of war suffered several wounded.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite encyclopedia|first=Nils Johan|last=Ringdal|authorlink=Nils Johan Ringdal|encyclopedia=[[Norsk krigsleksikon 1940-45]]|title=Kristiansund|editor=[[Hans Fredrik Dahl|Dahl]] |editor2= [[Guri Hjeltnes|Hjeltnes]] |editor3= [[Berit Nøkleby|Nøkleby]] |editor4= [[Nils Johan Ringdal|Ringdal]] |editor5= [[Øystein Sørensen|Sørensen]]|url=http://www.nb.no/utlevering/nb/d2e8afecb1aba47bf48bb3cd246dd070#&amp;struct=DIV234|year=1995|publisher=Cappelen|location=Oslo|isbn=82-02-14138-9|pages=233–234| language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the bombing of Kristiansund, the prisoners were moved by [[Lighter (barge)|lighters]] to [[Averøy]] near Kristiansund, where they were initially kept in a school until a proper a [[prisoner-of-war camp]] had been built at [[Bruhagen]].&lt;ref name="Jervaas"/&gt;&lt;ref name=aarflot125/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Årflot 1985: 71&lt;/ref&gt; Initially the prisoners had been sent to a transit prisoner-of-war-camp at [[Isfjorden (village)|Isfjorden]] near Åndalsnes, but this camp did not have the capacity to house the numbers captured at Dombås.&lt;ref name=aarflot125/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Årflot 1985: 70–71&lt;/ref&gt;

The intention of Norwegian authorities was to first keep the prisoners for interrogation and then ship them to the United Kingdom, but in the chaos of the collapse of resistance in the southern parts of Norway and the Allies' evacuation from Åndalsnes in late April/early May the German POWs were left behind to be freed by elements of the Luftwaffe's [[Fallschirm-Panzer Division 1 Hermann Göring#Luftwaffe control - early campaigns|''General Göring'' Regiment]].&lt;ref name="Jervaas"/&gt; Of the captured ''Fallschirmjägers'' only three fell into British hands and were brought to the United Kingdom when the British evacuated from the southern parts of Norway. One of the three had been able to evade capture after the jump over Dombås until he was caught by retreating British and Norwegian forces in Dombås proper on 29 April.&lt;ref&gt;Mølmen 1996: 224&lt;/ref&gt;

Thirteen paratroopers had been taken prisoner near [[Lillehammer]] on 14 April after their Ju 52 had been shot down en route to the target. Three of the Germans on board were wounded and were sent to [[Lillehammer Hospital]]. The unwounded prisoners were eventually transferred to [[Lom prisoner of war camp]] in [[Lom, Norway|Lom]] in [[Oppland]].&lt;ref name= "Jervaas"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mølmen 1996: 196–197&lt;/ref&gt; The pilot of the downed Ju 52 had committed suicide when Norwegian troops approached.&lt;ref&gt;Årflot 1985: 48&lt;/ref&gt;

In the aftermath of the German attack on Dombås, efforts were made by Norwegian military authorities to prevent further ''Fallschirmjäger'' landings by organizing volunteers into anti-paratroop ski patrols. By 23 April 415 volunteers from 13 local rifle clubs were carrying out regular patrols of the mountains of [[Østerdalen]]. Of the volunteers, 100 had military uniforms, the rest only armbands. Second-line regular troops were also employed to guard against new German paratroop attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Den krigshistorisk avdeling 1953, pp. 170–171&lt;/ref&gt; The weapons captured from the Germans at Dombås were not distributed to Norwegian troops, but rather stored at the village of [[Tretten]], where they were recaptured by the Germans on 23 April.&lt;ref&gt;Mølmen 1996: 225&lt;/ref&gt;

Most of the freed paratroopers soon after volunteered to jump into the isolated [[Battles of Narvik#Land battle|Narvik front]] in [[North Norway]] to help the hard pressed [[Gebirgsjäger]]s of the German [[3rd Mountain Division (Wehrmacht)|3rd Mountain Division]] fighting under the command of [[General (Germany)|''Generalleutnant'']] [[Eduard Dietl]] from 16 May. Many of the survivors from Dombås died fighting under the leadership of ''Leutnant'' Mössinger at Narvik.&lt;ref name="Jervaas"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.bjerkvik.gs.nl.no/dietl2.htm|title=General Dietls dagbok – 1. mai – 31. mai 1940|accessdate=22 January 2009|author=Magnor Fjellheim|work=Bjerkvik skole|language=Norwegian|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090707013954/http://www.bjerkvik.gs.nl.no/dietl2.htm|archivedate=7 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Herbert Schmidt—the leader of the ''Fallschirmjäger'' force at Dombås—received the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] on 24 May 1940,&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.lexikon-der-wehrmacht.de/Orden/Ritterkreuz/RKS-R.htm|title=Die Träger des Ritterkreuzes – S|accessdate=22 January 2009|work=Lexikon der Wehrmacht|publisher=Volksbund Deutscher Kriegsgräberfürsorge e.V.|language=German| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20081230123219/http://www.lexikon-der-wehrmacht.de/Orden/Ritterkreuz/RKS-R.htm| archivedate= 30 December 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; for his efforts during the battle.&lt;ref name=Quarrie8/&gt; He later recovered from the wounds he had suffered, and in 1941 wrote a book detailing his experiences during the battle called ''Die Fallschirmjäger von Dombaas''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title =Die fallschirmjäger von Dombas. by Herbert Schmidt|work=[[WorldCat]]|oclc = 1280242}}&lt;/ref&gt; Schmidt was killed by the [[French Resistance]] in 1944.&lt;ref name= "Jervaas"/&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==Literature==
* {{cite book |last=Årflot |first=Odd |year=1985 |title=Soldat, april 1940 |url=http://www.nb.no/nbsok/nb/94acc379f7103b224124c9ca392a733c?index=0 |location=Oslo |publisher=Samlaget |isbn=8252126472 |language=Norwegian}}
* {{cite book |last=Arneberg |first=Sven T. |year=1989 |title=Vi dro mot nord: felttoget i Norge i april 1940, skildret av tyske soldater og offiserer: (Oslo, Østfold, Akershus, Hedmark, Oppland, Møre og Romsdal) |url=http://www.nb.no/nbsok/nb/5ca8e103474aaf434f95a905bbc30b2f?index=2#0 |publisher=Aventura |isbn=8258806149 |language=Norwegian}}
* {{Cite book|title=Krigen i Norge 1940. [3] : Operasjonene i Glåmadalføret, Trysil og Rendalen |last=Den krighistoriske avdeling |year=1953 | publisher=Gyldendal |location=Oslo |url=http://www.nb.no/nbsok/nb/c58bff5fab81ee5f5b41a8bad93f985b?index=8 |language=Norwegian}}
* {{cite book |last=Flatmark |first=Jan Olav |year=1988 |title=Ålesund i hverdag og krig: små og store hendelser fra de underlige åra 1940–1945. 1: Ålesund under okkupasjonen 1940–1945 |url=http://urn.nb.no/URN:NBN:no-nb_digibok_2013091838139 |location=Ålesund |publisher=Nordvest forlag |isbn=8290330448 |language=Norwegian}}
* {{Cite book|last=Hafsten|first=Bjørn|author2=Larsstuvold, Ulf|author3= Olsen, Bjørn and Stenersen, Sten| title=Flyalarm – luftkrigen over Norge 1939–1945|edition=1st|publisher=Sem og Stenersen| location=Oslo|year=1991|isbn=82-7046-058-3|language=Norwegian}}
* {{Cite book|last=Hauge|first=Andreas|title=Kampene i Norge 1940|volume=1|publisher=Krigshistorisk Forlag|location=Sandefjord|year=1995|isbn=82-993369-0-2|language=Norwegian}}
* {{Cite book|last=Hauge|first=Andreas|title=Kampene i Norge 1940|volume=2|publisher=Krigshistorisk Forlag|location=Sandefjord|year=1995|isbn=82-993369-0-2|language=Norwegian}}
* {{Cite book|last=Høgevold|first=John|title=Vår militære innsats hjemme og ute 1940–45| publisher=Norwegian High Command|location=Oslo|year=1984|isbn=82-991210-0-0|language=Norwegian}}
* {{Cite book|title=Krigen 1940–45|last=Mølmen|first=Øystein|year=1996| publisher=Ø. Mølmen|location=Lesjaskog|isbn=82-993958-0-1|url=http://www.nb.no/utlevering/nb/25a6be20152a0a7751b141332d56e72f#&amp;struct=DIV320|language=Norwegian}}
* {{Cite book|title=Raumabanen/Romsdalen, Lesja og Dovre: kamphandlingene i april 1940|last=Mølmen| first=Øystein|year=1998|publisher=Raumabanens kulturlag|isbn=82-994722-0-2|url= http://www.nb.no/utlevering/nb/149ae66b9b7b85358b2c8866e403d95e#&amp;struct=DIV42|language=Norwegian}}
* {{Cite book|last=Quarrie|first=Bruce|authorlink=Bruce Quarrie|title=German Airborne Troops 1939–45 |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]]|location=Oxford|origyear=1983|year=2007|isbn=978-0-85045-480-2}}
* {{Cite book|last=Voksø|first=Per|authorlink=Per Voksø|author2=John Berg|title=Krigens dagbok – Norge 1940–1945|publisher=Forlaget Det Beste|location=Oslo|year=1994|isbn=82-7010-166-4|language= Norwegian}}
* {{Cite book|last=Zeiner-Gundersen|first=Herman Fredrik|authorlink=Herman Fredrik Zeiner-Gundersen| title=Norsk artilleri gjennom 300 år|publisher=Agdin Forlag|location=Arendal|year=1986|isbn= 82-7360-003-3|language=Norwegian}}

{{coord missing|Norway}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dombas, Battle Of}}
[[Category:1940 in Norway]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Norway]]
[[Category:Norwegian Campaign]]
[[Category:History of Oppland]]
[[Category:Dovre]]
[[Category:April 1940 events]]</text><sha1>mzv8pf2fgufpfl2lusuyk2mtmo9kpkd</sha1></revision></page>