<page><title>Battle of Hegra Fortress</title><ns>0</ns><id>2708072</id><revision><id>917043126</id><parentid>904822689</parentid><timestamp>2019-09-22T00:32:12Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Monkbot</username><id>20483999</id></contributor><minor /><comment>[[User:Monkbot/task 16: remove replace deprecated dead-url params|Task 16]]: replaced (6×) / removed (0×) deprecated |dead-url= and |deadurl= with |url-status=;</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="34804" xml:space="preserve">{{pp-move-vandalism|small=yes}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Hegra Fortress
| image       = Hegra Fortress gun position.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = Norwegian 7.5 cm gun position
| partof      = the [[Norwegian Campaign]]
| date        = 15 April – 5 May 1940
| place       = [[Hegra]], [[Norway]]
| result      = German victory&lt;br/&gt;[[Hegra Fortress]] capitulated 5 May after all other Norwegian forces in southern Norway had laid down their arms.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ny.kildenett.no/artikler/2007/Hegra%20festning |archive-url=https://archive.today/20070814142134/http://ny.kildenett.no/artikler/2007/Hegra%20festning |url-status=dead |archive-date=14 August 2007 |title=Hegra Festning |author=Nissen, Hans |author2=Kirkhusmo Anders |year=2007 |work=Historisk kilde- og kunnskapsbase for Trøndelag |publisher=[[Sør-Trøndelag County Municipality]], [[Trondheim]] municipality and the [[Norwegian Archive, Library and Museum Authority]] |accessdate=5 April 2010 |language=Norwegian }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| combatant1  = {{flag|Norway}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Norway}} [[Hans Reidar Holtermann]]{{surrendered}}&lt;ref&gt;Brox 1988: 45&lt;/ref&gt;
| commander2  = '''15–20 April:'''&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} Weiss&lt;ref name="Brox88: 102"&gt;Brox 1988: 102&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''20 April-5 May:'''&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} Kurt Woytasch&lt;ref name="Brox88: 102"/&gt;
|units1       ={{flagicon|Norway}} Unknown
|units2       ={{flagicon|Nazi Germany|army}} 138. Gebirgsjägerregiment&lt;ref name="Brox88: 102"/&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(15-27 April)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany|army}} [[181st Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|181. Infantry Division]]&lt;ref name="Brox88: 102"/&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(27 April-5 May)&lt;/small&gt;
| strength1   = '''Positional artillery:'''&lt;ref name="Brox88: 81"&gt;Brox 1988: 81&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;4×10.5 cm guns&lt;br&gt;2×7.5 cm guns&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(under Captain Evjen, with 25 men)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''Field artillery:'''&lt;ref name ="Brox88: 81"/&gt;&lt;br&gt;4×8.4 cm guns&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(under 2nd Lieutenant Reitan, with 10 men)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''Total force:'''&lt;ref name="hegrafestning.no"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.hegrafestning.no/ |title=Hegra Festning |year=2009 |work=Foreningen Hegra Festnings Venner |accessdate=5 April 2010 |language=Norwegian| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20100326065000/http://www.hegrafestning.no/| archivedate= 26 March 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;250 volunteer soldiers&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(most of whom had had a short [[national service]] with Artillery Regiment no. 3 (AR 3) before the war)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;1 female volunteer nurse
| strength2   = 1  battalion&lt;br&gt;1 reinforced infantry company&lt;br&gt;1 [[artillery]] unit&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(with numerous [[mortar (weapon)|mortar]]s, [[cannon]]s and [[howitzer]]s)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name="Brox88: 191"/&gt;
| casualties1 = 6 killed&lt;br&gt;14 wounded&lt;ref name="Mil.no"/&gt;&lt;br&gt;200+ captured
| casualties2 = 150–200 killed or wounded&lt;ref name="Brox88: 125"&gt;Brox 1988: 125&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Mil.no"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.mil.no/haren/ks/start/article.jhtml?articleID=163063 |title=Holtermann 08, Evne og Vilje til Handling |author=Møller, Anders |date=24 November 2005 |work=[[Norwegian Military Academy]] |publisher= |accessdate=5 April 2010 |language=Norwegian }}{{dead link|date=July 2017 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;1 captured&lt;ref name="Brox8894"&gt;Brox 1988: 94&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;1 aircraft destroyed&lt;br&gt;1 aircraft damaged&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 14, 20&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties3 = '''Civilian casualties:'''&lt;br/&gt;One Norwegian civilian killed&lt;br&gt;2 Finnish civilian refugees wounded
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Norwegian Campaign}}
}}

The '''Battle of Hegra Fortress''' was a 25-day engagement in the 1940 [[Norwegian Campaign]] which saw a small force of Norwegian volunteers fighting numerically superior [[Wehrmacht|German forces]] from a fortified position. After initial fighting around the [[Meråker Line]] railway line, the [[Norwegians]] pulled back into [[Hegra Fortress]] and held off further German attacks before surrendering on 5 May as one of the last Norwegian units active in southern Norway.

==Opposing forces==
[[File:Hegra Fortress - group of soldiers 1940.jpg|thumb|A group of Norwegian soldiers early on during the battle]]

===Norwegian force===
The [[Norwegian Army|Norwegian]] defenders were 250 [[Military volunteer|volunteer]] [[soldier]]s and the volunteer nurse [[Anne Margrethe Strømsheim|Anne Margrethe Bang]].&lt;ref name="hegrafestning.no"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Brox88: 87"&gt;Brox 1988: 87&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the volunteers that served at Hegra were from the area [[Hegra]]/[[Stjørdal]]/[[Trondheim]], but they also included three Swedes.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 45&lt;/ref&gt;

The garrison at Hegra was equipped with small arms ([[Krag-Jørgensen]] rifles and carbines), as well as [[Madsen machine gun|Madsen]] and [[Colt M/29]] [[machine gun]]s.

The fortress also had [[artillery]], four {{convert|10.5|cm|in|2|abbr=on}} and two {{convert|7.5|cm|in|2|abbr=on}} positional pieces of reasonably modern make in [[Gun turret|half-turrets]]; as well as four [[Krupp 8.4 cm Model 1887|Krupp m/1887 {{convert|8.4|cm|in|2|abbr=on}}]] [[field gun]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Brox 1988: 48&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://hem.fyristorg.com/robertm/norge/Norw_weapons.html |title=Norwegian weapons: Field artillery |author=Mårtensson, Robert |year=2002 |accessdate=6 January 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110716031412/http://hem.fyristorg.com/robertm/norge/Norw_weapons.html |archive-date=16 July 2011 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The artillery had a maximum range of between six and nine kilometres.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.forn.no/heg/7001.htm |title=Ingstadkleven Fort, 1907–1910 |author=Fornes, Greta |year=2007 |accessdate=5 April 2010 |language=Norwegian |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110724175414/http://www.forn.no/heg/7001.htm |archivedate=24 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of these men had been mobilized to Artillery Regiment no. 3 at Øyanmoen army camp at [[Trondheim Airport, Værnes|Værnes Air Station]] and were brought to Hegra to continue the mobilization after the Germans had reached their camp. The fortress at Hegra was originally only intended as a temporary refuge for the artillery regiment, but ended up as the centre of the volunteers' war in 1940.

===German force===
The attacking force initially consisted of ''[[Gebirgsjäger]]'' of the German 138. ''Gebirgsjägerregiment'' (part of the [[3rd Mountain Division (Wehrmacht)|3. ''Gebirgsdivision'']]), which landed in [[Trondheim]] on 9 April. Later, from 20 April to 27 April, the Germans substituted the 138. ''Gebirgsjägerregiment'' with units from the [[181st Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|181. Infantry Division]] and the 138. ''Gebirgsjäger'' were sent north to try to relieve their comrades at the [[Battles of Narvik#Land battle|Narvik Front]].&lt;ref name="Brox88: 102"/&gt;

By the end of the battle the German forces employed against Hegra Fortress consisted chiefly of one infantry battalion at Hegra and one company of ''Gebirgsjäger'' in the nearby village of [[Sona, Norway|Sona]]. In addition further units were deployed to the village of [[Elvran]] and to the [[Selbu]] region.&lt;ref name=ostbye165&gt;Østby 1963: 165&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
[[File:Værnes 1936.jpg|thumb|Værnes in 1936]]
The old mothballed fort at Ingstadkleiva that was to become known as Hegra Fortress was not intended by any of the parties as a battlefield. It only became of importance when the Norwegian artillery major [[Hans Reidar Holtermann]] started organising troops to resist the German invasion forces which had been landed at Trondheim. Holtermann first travelled to the army camp at Værnes to mobilize his Artillery Regiment no. 3. This mobilization began at 14:00 on 9 April 1940, but the Germans landed at [[Stjørdal Station]] the very next day, and by 10:30 approached the camp. As his forces were not combat ready, Holtermann had to evacuate and move to what was at that point known as Ingstadkleiva Fort to complete his mobilization.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 7–8&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, at 15:00 on 10 April 1940, most of the personnel and equipment under Holtermann's command arrived at the small mountain fortification of Ingstadkleiva Fort. At this point, Holtermann was given orders to proceed with the mobilization and otherwise do what he himself thought best.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 8&lt;/ref&gt; Holtermann thus began to gather and equip a fighting force of local volunteers. After arriving at the fort Holtermann first took residence in the buildings outside the mountain fortifications, not intending to defend the facility, only use it as a temporary base.&lt;ref&gt;Grimnes 1994: 3&lt;/ref&gt;

===Mobilization===
By 10 April, Holtermann already had fifty volunteers under his command and a steady stream of mostly local men kept being drawn to the fort.&lt;ref&gt;Grimnes 1994: 6&lt;/ref&gt; On 11 April, men of Holtermann's unit returned to Værnes to remove more of the materiel and provisions stored there. Due to poor security amongst the German forces stationed at the camp, the Norwegians were able to carry out their mission undetected. The reclaimed supplies were taken partly to the fortress and partly to a number of nearby farms.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 11"&gt;Soldat 1985: 11&lt;/ref&gt; When a force of 250 soldiers had been assembled, Holtermann had to turn away further volunteers due to the fact he could not arm or equip any more soldiers than those he already had under his command at that point. From 12 April work was carried out to reactivate the fortress' artillery, which was found to have plentiful ammunition, but no direction systems or charts for indirect fire.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 11"/&gt; Only a few 1:100,000 scale maps were available at the fortress.&lt;ref&gt;Arnstad 1965: 27&lt;/ref&gt; The actual artillery charts for the fortress were stored in Trondheim and fell into the hands of the Germans on 9 April and were used by the Wehrmacht during the siege to deploy artillery in places that the fortress could not hit. The same day troops of Holtermann's unit were positioned around [[Hegra Station|Hegra railway station]] and Mælen bridge, and the first German attempt at making the fortress surrender was carried out. A German [[Major (Germany)|''Major'']] approached the fortress together with two Norwegian officers who had given up the same day. Despite the best efforts by both the German officer and the two surrendered Norwegians, Holtermann refused to capitulate.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 11–12&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, 13 April, Major Holtermann achieved contact with his superiors at the [[5th Division (Norway)|5th Division]] for the last time during the Norwegian Campaign. Through a telephone conversation, the commander of the force at Hegra was told to act as he saw best and, if possible, to hinder the Germans in gaining control of the [[Meråkerbanen]] [[Rail transport|railway line]] to Sweden. In response to these orders, 20 soldiers were sent to the village of [[Flornes]] to set up [[Defensive fighting position|field fortification]]s and block the road and railway to [[Meråker]].&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 13"&gt;Soldat 1985: 13&lt;/ref&gt;

===Friendly fire incident===
On 14 April, reports came in to the troops stationed at Hegra village stating that a train loaded with German soldiers had left [[Hell Station|Hell]] [[Train station|railway station]] and was on its way to Hegra. Not long after a train approached Hegra Station and ignored signals to stop. In response to what was interpreted as a German troop train trying to force its way through, the soldiers guarding the station opened fire on the approaching train. However, the train was in fact carrying Finnish refugees home after the [[Winter War]]. The fire killed one Norwegian man and wounded two Finnish women.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 13"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Brox 1988: 85&lt;/ref&gt; Later that afternoon, the garrison's sole female member joined when nurse Anne Margrethe Bang from Trondheim arrived at the fortress bearing a load of medical supplies. The daughter of a doctor and trained in [[first aid]], Bang stayed in the fortress for the duration of the siege, helping two [[Military medicine|military doctors]] care for the sick and wounded.&lt;ref name="Brox88: 87"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Brox 1988: 87–88&lt;/ref&gt;

===German aircraft driven off by ground fire===
The first shots fired by the fortress' defenders occurred on 14 April, the same day as the friendly-fire train incident, when a Norwegian [[heavy machine gun]] fired at and damaged a German aircraft, driving it away. More equipment and ammunition from Værnes arrived at the fortress the same day.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 14&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===German capture of the surrounding area===
[[File:Hegra Bridge in 1940.jpg|thumb|Hegra Bridge after the initial fighting]]

====Attack on Hegra village====
At 05:30 on 15 April, the Germans attacked the Norwegian positions defending the Hegra railway station, Hegra road bridge and Mælen bridge, supported by artillery fire. Having been partly caught by surprise, the Norwegian forces at the Hegra road bridge and the railway station made a fighting retreat to the fortress over a two- to three-hour period. Early on in the fighting, the Norwegians demolished the Hegra road bridge,&lt;ref&gt;Arnstad 1965: 33&lt;/ref&gt; forcing the German infantry to cross the precarious ice of the frozen [[Stjørdalselva|Stjørdal River]] under fire.&lt;ref&gt;Arnstad 1965: 34&lt;/ref&gt; At Mælen bridge, the guards withdrew to the south.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 20"&gt;Soldat 1985: 20&lt;/ref&gt; Four Norwegian soldiers fell in and around Hegra, while one was killed at Mælen bridge.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 21"&gt;Soldat 1985: 21&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to those killed, eight Norwegian soldiers were taken prisoner during the initial German attack.&lt;ref name="Brox 2005: 97"&gt;Brox 2005: 97&lt;/ref&gt;

====Fortress artillery intervenes====
As the German attack developed, the artillery pieces at Hegra Fortress opened up to support the Norwegian troops under attack in the valley below, and later covered their retreat. The Norwegian artillery fire was directed at German artillery positions, machine gun nests and convoys of trucks pushing east towards the [[Norway–Sweden border|Swedish border]]. The [[Switchboard operator|telephone operator]] at Hegra [[Electrical telegraph|telegraph]] station acted as an [[Artillery observer|observer]] for the artillery at the fortress. Artillery fire from the fortress knocked out three German artillery pieces and inflicted casualties on the attacking force.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 20"/&gt;

====Skirmish on the fortress road====
As the Norwegian infantry force pulled out of Hegra and up the road towards the fortress, the Germans pursued them until they reached a number of field fortifications blocking the road. At this position, the Norwegians held their ground and inflicted fatalities on the attacking force. Amongst the German fatalities was the attacking platoon's leader, ''[[Oberleutnant]]'' Hans-Joachim Herrmann. After the fighting, as the Norwegians were going through the area to seize German arms and equipment, they found the German ''[[Gefreiter]]'' Hugo Bayerle. Bayerle had been hit in both thighs, sustaining a broken femur, and was bleeding profusely. The Norwegian troops brought him on a ski [[sled]] to the fortress for medical care.&lt;ref name="Brox8894"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 20"/&gt;

====End of the first day of the battle====
At the end of the first day of serious fighting, the Germans pushed on along the Meråkerbanen railway line and broke through the blocking position at Flornes. The troops holding Flornes withdrew first to Meråker, then further north to join other Norwegian forces. As night fell, German troops had occupied the areas around the villages of Hegra, Avelsgaard, Flornes, Ingstad and Sona. During the day, ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' aircraft had repeatedly overflown Hegra Fortress. The Norwegian troops had fired on the aircraft with both rifles and machine guns, damaging one aircraft, which crashed while attempting an [[emergency landing]] at Værnes.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 20"/&gt;

===Attempts to storm the fortress===
The day after the German capture of the area surrounding the fortress, ''Luftwaffe'' aircraft repeatedly attacked with bombs and machine gun fire. German infantry probed the approaches to the fortifications but were driven off by artillery and heavy machine gun fire. A German [[Mountain gun|mountain howitzer]] brought up to Avelsgaard bombarded the fortress, destroying most of the houses outside the walls. One Norwegian soldier was killed by a shell hitting the fortress [[parapet]]. He was the last Norwegian fatality of the battle.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 21"/&gt;

====First German charge====
17 April began with a bombardment at 07:00 from the air and by the [[howitzer]] position at Avelsgaard.
At 09:00, a large force of German infantry attacked from the north-east, supported by machine gun positions situated a mere {{convert|150|m|yd|abbr=on}} north of the fortress. The progress of the attack was only halted when it reached the [[Wire obstacle|barbed wire entanglements]] directly in front of the Norwegian [[Trench warfare|trenches]]. At this point, the attacking force was subjected to heavy fire at close range from artillery, machine guns and riflemen, and thrown back. German bombers kept on hitting the fortress throughout the day, knocking out both the telephone line and the electricity supply. Neither came back into operation during the siege.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 21–22&lt;/ref&gt; From then until the end of the battle, all light inside the Norwegian tunnels and halls was provided by candles and nine [[kerosene lamp]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Grimnes 1994: 10&lt;/ref&gt;

====Second attack is aborted====
The day after their first unsuccessful attack, the German forces made another attempt at storming the mountain fortress. In preparation, the fortifications were subjected to heavy machine gun and [[mortar (weapon)|mortar]] fire during the early daylight hours. A battalion of infantry was brought forward towards the fortress, but was hit by a [[blizzard]] while marching through [[no man's land]]. As the attacking units lost their bearing in the storm, fire fights erupted between groups of Germans mistaking each other for Norwegian patrols and the whole enterprise collapsed before reaching the Norwegian positions. Bombers and heavy calibre artillery pieces kept up steady fire against the fortress throughout the day.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 23"&gt;Soldat 1985: 23&lt;/ref&gt;

===Siege===
[[File:Hegra Fortress - soldiers 1940.jpg|thumb|Some of the Norwegian defenders gathered in one of the fortress' subterranean halls during the siege]]

====Evacuation of wounded====
In the evening of 18 April, two Norwegian doctors—Sigurd Aarrestad and Peter Berdal—approached the German commander of the Hegra-Son area and requested permission to pass through the German lines to evacuate wounded soldiers from the fortress. During the previous days' fighting many German wounded had been brought to Hegra village and the doctors feared that there had been numerous casualties on the Norwegian side as well. Permission for the mission was granted, and the shelling of Hegra Fortress was temporarily suspended while local volunteers made their way up to the fortress, pulling ski sleds for the wounded. While Aarrestad led the expedition, Berdal was held hostage by the Germans to ensure that the Norwegians returned from the fortress after finishing their mission. When Aarrestad returned from Hegra Fortress a few hours later, he brought along nine wounded Norwegian soldiers and ''Gefreiter'' Bayerle, who had been released by his captors and sent along with the wounded Norwegians.&lt;ref&gt;Brox 1988: 127–128&lt;/ref&gt; As part of the agreement, the Norwegian wounded did not become [[Prisoner of war|prisoners of war]].&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 23"/&gt;

====Attempts to storm the fortress are abandoned====
From around 25 April, the Germans gave up on storming Hegra Fortress. The pressing need to remove the Norwegian force ended in large part when the important town of [[Steinkjer]] fell to the Germans on 21 April and the Allied advance [[Namsos Campaign|from the north]] was checked. The [[Åndalsnes landings|southern arm]] of the Allied counter-attack had never swung north from [[Åndalsnes]] and had instead been directed to the [[Gudbrandsdal]] in order to support the Norwegian forces fighting there. As the immediate crisis had passed for the German force in Trondheim, they preferred to push south to link up with forces coming up from [[Oslo]]. The focus of the ''Wehrmacht'' became to bombard Hegra Fortress with artillery and air power to try to pummel it into submission.&lt;ref&gt;Grimnes 1994: 18&lt;/ref&gt;

====Artillery duels, aerial bombing and patrol engagements====
For the remainder of the battle, the Germans did not try to storm the fortress again. Fighting consisted of aerial bombing of the fortress, duels between the fortress' guns and German field artillery and skirmishes between German and Norwegian ski units doing reconnaissance and bringing in supplies of food, ammunition and fuel. Several Norwegian soldiers were captured as a result of the patrol actions. To counter German guns placed in the positional guns' blind zones, the Norwegian artillerymen positioned their two 8.4&amp;nbsp;cm field guns to cover areas the fixed guns could not reach. During the siege, the Norwegian guns targeted machine gun nests, gun positions, command posts and ammunition depots in the surrounding area. On 23 April, one of the 7.5&amp;nbsp;cm positional guns was knocked out, one of the fortress' command towers was destroyed and the [[Pipeline transport|water line]] was broken. The second 7.5&amp;nbsp;cm gun was destroyed on 24 April. The fortress was under constant artillery fire and held out chiefly in order to be in a position to support the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] offensive expected from the north.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 27&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Brox 2005: 101–102, 105–106&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 April, the Germans employed a new weapon against the fortress when a [[seaplane]] dropped a {{convert|1800|kg|lb|abbr=on}} bomb, destroying the houses outside the walls, with shrapnel ending up in Hegra village several kilometres away.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 30&lt;/ref&gt; From 29 April, the artillery bombardment steadily increased in strength, with German guns reinforced by captured Norwegian [[Rheinmetall 12 cm leFH 08|{{convert|12|cm|in|1|abbr=on}} howitzer]]s from the [[Armory (military)|armoury]] in Trondheim, and the next day one of the three 10.5&amp;nbsp;cm guns at the fortress was knocked out.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 34&lt;/ref&gt; During the siege, a total of over 2,300 shells struck Hegra Fortress.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Sterke inntrykk i Hegra |newspaper=[[Trønder-Avisa]] |date=28 September 2007 |url=http://www.t-a.no/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070928/NYHETER/709280015 |archive-url=https://archive.today/20070504204357/http://www.t-a.no/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20070928/NYHETER/709280015 |url-status=dead |archive-date=4 May 2007 |language=Norwegian }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Værnes Air Station====
One way that Holtermann wanted to directly support the main war effort in Norway was to bombard Værnes Air Base, the northernmost airfield in German hands and vital for the support of German forces north of Trondheim. This was particularly so for the [[Battles of Narvik|Narvik front]], which could not be reached by aircraft flying from further south than Værnes. Recognising this, the Germans had hired some 2,000 Norwegian [[Collaborationism|collaborationist]] labourers to work full-time at expanding and improving the air strip. Bombarding Værnes would both have disrupted this work and impaired the bombing raids being flown against Norwegian forces fighting further to the north. However, since Værnes is {{convert|11.5|km|mi|abbr=on}} from Hegra, and the fortress' guns only had a maximum range of some {{convert|9|km|mi|abbr=on}}, this was impossible. For accurate firing, the effective range was a mere {{convert|6.9|km|mi|abbr=on}}, as that was the range of the artillery's height angle meter.&lt;ref name="Arnstad26"&gt;Arnstad 1965: 26&lt;/ref&gt; Efforts were made at the fortress to increase the elevation of the guns from 19° to 26° by removing part of the gun shields,&lt;ref name="Background"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.verneplaner.no/?f=hegra&amp;id=137184&amp;a=4 |title=Hegra Festning - 4.1 Festningens utvikling |author= |date= |work=Nasjonale Festningsverk |publisher= |accessdate=5 April 2010 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; and part of the gun mounting,&lt;ref name="Arnstad26"/&gt; but these failed as no [[welding]] equipment could be acquired to carry out the modifications.&lt;ref name="Background"/&gt; Even though no modifications could be carried out, one of the 10.5&amp;nbsp;cm guns at Hegra opened fire in the direction of Værnes on 22 April. With the gun firing at maximum elevation, the rounds still fell hundreds of metres short of their intended target.&lt;ref&gt;Arnstad 1965: 85&lt;/ref&gt;

The earliest attempt by the Hegra garrison to attack the airfield at Værnes had occurred on 14 April, when a Norwegian [[dog sled]] patrol spotted massive German air activity at the air base. Plans were made to manhandle one of the fortress' 8.4&amp;nbsp;cm field guns to a nearby hill called Blankhammeren, and from there bombard German targets out of range from the fortress itself, including the strategically important airfield. The plan, however, could not be carried out before the German attack of 15 April brought large German infantry forces into the area and rendered the plans infeasible.&lt;ref&gt;Arnstad 1965: 63–64&lt;/ref&gt;

====International media attention====
During the siege, the struggle of Hegra Fortress captured the attention of the international media, with articles such as those in ''[[The Daily Telegraph]]'' on 22 April&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.verneplaner.no/?f=hegra&amp;id=136891&amp;a=2 |title=Hegra Festning - Forord |author= |date= |work=Nasjonale Festningsverk |publisher= |accessdate=5 April 2010 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; and 2 May,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.verneplaner.no/?f=hegra&amp;id=137933&amp;a=4 |title=Hegra Festning - 4.8 Tegninger av historiske bygninger |author= |date= |work=Nasjonale Festningsverk |publisher= |accessdate=5 April 2010 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; and that in ''[[The Guardian|The Manchester Guardian]]'' on 16 April.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.verneplaner.no/?f=hegra&amp;k=9.1&amp;id=139438&amp;a=6 |title=Hegra Festning - Katalogbidrag |author= |date= |work=Nasjonale Festningsverk |publisher= |accessdate=5 April 2010 |language=Norwegian}}&lt;/ref&gt; The fortress was also mentioned in articles in ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine on 6 May&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Northern Theatre: Struggle for Trondheim |author= |newspaper=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |date=6 May 1940 |url= http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,763924,00.html }}&lt;/ref&gt; and 13 May.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |title=Northern Theatre: 23 Days |author= |newspaper=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |date=13 May 1940 |url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,884024-2,00.html }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Surrender==

===Preparations and influencing factors===
[[File:Hegra Fortress - Hauptman Giebel accepts the fortress' surrender.jpg|thumb|''[[Hauptmann]]'' Giebel entering the fortress gates to accept the Norwegian surrender]]
News came in over the radio on 2 May of the Allied retreat from the Åndalsnes area, that the Germans had seized control of the [[Dovre Line]] from [[Dombås]] to [[Støren]], and of the surrender of the Norwegian [[4th Brigade (Norway)|4th Brigade]] in [[Western Norway]]. This came on top of increasing supply problems, with the bread supply already having run out on 30 April. The next day, 3 May, the garrison started destroying its artillery ammunition in preparation for surrender.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 36&lt;/ref&gt; The three Swedish volunteers that had endured the siege with the Norwegians were released from their duties and guided across the mountains to the Swedish border by a ski patrol. During the day, a radio message from Colonel [[Ole Berg Getz]]—the Norwegian commander in the Trøndelag area—was broadcast. Getz had surrendered his forces in [[Nord-Trøndelag]] and advised all Norwegian forces in Trøndelag to lay down their arms as the situation had become hopeless after the British retreat from the southern parts of Norway. The decision to surrender Trøndelag had been influenced by [[Neville Chamberlain]]'s radio message that day announcing the end of the Allied campaign in Southern Norway.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 37&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 May, destruction of radios, machine guns, carbines and other small arms was initiated and ski patrols were sent out carrying loads of important documents. By 13:50 that day confirmation of Colonel Getz's capitulation was received and the destruction of the fortress' artillery began.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 38"&gt;Soldat 1985: 38&lt;/ref&gt;

===Capitulation===
In the early hours of 5 May, the situation was such that there was very little food left and water for only a few days, all other Norwegian and Allied forces in all of southern Norway had been withdrawn or had surrendered and Hegra Fortress was the last remaining pocket of resistance south of [[Nordland]].&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 38"/&gt; At 05:00, Major Holtermann had his men assemble in the tunnels and relayed to them his decision to surrender the fortress. In a short speech, he thanked them for their efforts and then led them in singing the [[Ja, vi elsker dette landet|Norwegian National Anthem]]. By 05:25, a [[white flag]] was raised over the fortress, and at 06:30 a force of 60 German soldiers and three officers&lt;ref&gt;Brox 1988: 190&lt;/ref&gt;—led by one ''[[Hauptmann]]'' Giebel&lt;ref name="Brox88: 191"&gt;Brox 1988: 191&lt;/ref&gt;—arrived to accept the surrender of the garrison. Later that day, 190 men and one woman marched out of the fortress and into captivity. At the surrender, the garrison at Hegra Fortress consisted of 14 officers, one technical officer, seven sergeants, one officer cadet, six corporals, 161 privates and nurse Anne Margrethe Bang.&lt;ref name=ostbye165/&gt;

===Garrison as prisoners of war===
[[File:Hegra Fortress - surrender 5 May 1940.jpg|thumb|The surrendered garrison assembled in the ruined fortress camp]]
After the surrender, the Norwegians were marched down to Hegra railway station from where they were transported by train. In Trondheim, the officers and Anne Margrethe Bang were taken off the train and interned at [[Trondheim katedralskole]] secondary school while the [[Non-commissioned officer|NCO]]s and soldiers continued their journey to [[Lundamo]] in [[Gauldalen]] valley.&lt;ref name ="Soldat85: 40"&gt;Soldat 1985: 40&lt;/ref&gt; At Lundamo, the prisoners were interned in a barn for the night. The next day, 6 May, the prisoners from Hegra were force-marched for {{convert|50|km|mi|abbr=on}} to [[Berkåk]] where a [[prisoner-of-war camp]] was established.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 40"/&gt; At Berkåk, the prisoners were set at work at building an improvised road from the river [[Orklaelva|Orkla]] near Berkåk across the woods to Brattset. The road was intended to help the German logistic system that had been severely hampered by the numerous bridges that had been blown by the Norwegian Army during the preceding month. Due in part to the poor physical condition of the prisoners after the harsh siege they had just experienced, the road was never completed despite threats of punishment made by the German camp commander.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 41"&gt;Soldat 1985: 41&lt;/ref&gt; At the end of May the German High Command in [[Berlin]] announced that [[Adolf Hitler]] had personally ordered the release of Norwegian prisoners of war as an act of recognition of the defence they had put up under difficult conditions.&lt;ref name="Soldat85: 41"/&gt; The release of the prisoners from Hegra happened in groups and by mid-June the last PoWs had been let go.
[[File:Battle of Hegra Fortress fallen memorial (2014).jpg|thumb|Memorial at Hegra Fortress, commemorating the six Norwegian soldiers killed in the battle]]

==Casualties==
Six Norwegian soldiers were killed in action during the battle, with 14 wounded.&lt;ref name= "Mil.no"/&gt; All the Norwegian fatalities occurred during the first two days of the fighting.&lt;ref&gt;Soldat 1985: 20–21&lt;/ref&gt; In the first years after [[World War II]], Norwegian estimates of the number of German casualties were exaggerated, some spoke of up to 1,100 dead or wounded. Later research has however led to a substantially lower number, at about 150&lt;ref name="Brox88: 125"/&gt; to 200&lt;ref name="Mil.no"/&gt; Wehrmacht soldiers killed or wounded at Hegra.&lt;ref name="Brox 2005: 97"/&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|3}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book |title=Beleiringen av Hegra Festning 10. april &amp;ndash; 5. mai 1940 |last=Arnstad |first=Johan |year=1965 |publisher=F. Bruns bokforhandels forlag |location=Trondheim |isbn= |page= |pages= |url= |accessdate= |language=Norwegian}}
*{{cite book |title=Hegra festning 1905&amp;ndash;2005 |last=Brox |first=Karl H. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2005 |publisher=Foreningen Hegra Festnings Venner |location=Oslo |isbn=82-303-0476-9 |page= |pages= |url= |accessdate= |language=Norwegian}}
*{{cite book |title=Kampen om Hegra &amp;ndash; festningen tyskerne ikke greide å ta |last=Brox |first=Karl H. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1988 |publisher=[[Gyldendal Norsk Forlag]] |location=Oslo |isbn=82-05-17716-3 |page= |pages= |url= |accessdate= |language=Norwegian}}
*{{cite book |title=Kampen om Hegra 1940 |last=Grimnes |first=Ole Kristian |authorlink=Ole Kristian Grimnes |coauthors= |year=1994 |publisher=Forsvarets Pressetjeneste |location=Oslo |isbn= |page= |pages= |url= |accessdate= |language=Norwegian}}
*{{cite book|title=Krigen i Norge 1940. Operasjonene i Nord-Trøndelag |first=Gudbrand |last=Østbye  |authorlink=Gudbrand Østbye |year=1963 |publisher=Forsvarets Krigshistoriske Avdeling / Gyldendal |location=Oslo |language=Norwegian}}
*{{cite book |title=Rapport fra Hegra Fort |last=Soldat 31358-38 |first= |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1985 |publisher=Foreningen Hegra 1940 |location=Trondheim  |isbn= |page= |pages= |url= |accessdate= |language=Norwegian}}

==External links==
*{{cite web |url=http://www.mil.no/felles/rkt/start/Hegra_festning/ |title=Hegra festning |work=[[Norwegian Armed Forces]] |accessdate=5 April 2010 |language=Norwegian |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070930202115/http://www.mil.no/felles/rkt/start/Hegra_festning/ |archivedate=30 September 2007 }}

{{coord missing|Norway}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hegra, Battle of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1940]]
[[Category:1940 in Norway]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Norway]]
[[Category:Meråker]]
[[Category:Norwegian Campaign]]
[[Category:Stjørdal]]
[[Category:History of Trøndelag]]
[[Category:April 1940 events]]
[[Category:May 1940 events]]</text><sha1>p2a3ouxbadkdxpxosdr7lpz4f1ghgzo</sha1></revision></page>