<page><title>Battle for Kvam</title><ns>0</ns><id>57420317</id><revision><id>964850762</id><parentid>959697156</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-27T23:24:47Z</timestamp><contributor><username>InternetArchiveBot</username><id>27015025</id></contributor><comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0.1</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="23032" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2018}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle for Kvam
|image= [[File:KvamApril1940.png|300px]]
|caption= Battle of Kvam, 25–26 April 1940
|partof=the [[Norwegian Campaign]] of [[World War II]]
|date= 25–26 April 1940
|place=Kvam, Norway
|result=German victory
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Norway}}
|combatant2={{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1={{flagicon|UK}} Gen. [[Bernard Paget]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|UK}} Brig. H. E. F. Smyth&lt;br&gt;(22 April–12:00pm 25 April)&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|UK}} Lt-Col. A. L. Kent-Lemon&lt;br&gt;(12:00pm 25–26 April)&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|UK}} Lt-Col. E.E.E. Cass&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Norway}} Maj-Gen. [[Otto Ruge]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Norway}} Gen. [[Jacob Hvinden Haug]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} Gen. [[Richard Pellengahr]]
|strength1= {{flagicon|UK|army}} [[15th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|15th Infantry Brigade]]
* [[King's Own Yorkshire Light Infantry]]
** 1st Battalion
* [[York and Lancaster Regiment]]
** 1st Battalion
|strength2= 8,500
* 1 mountain infantry battalion
* 6 infantry battalions
* 1 motorised infantry battalion
* 2 artillery batteries
|casualties1={{flagicon|UK}}:&lt;br&gt;54 killed&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Norway}}:&lt;br&gt;3 killed
|casualties2=light
|casualties3=3 civilians killed
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Norwegian Campaign}}
}}

The '''Battle for Kvam''' took place 25 and 26 April 1940, in the [[Gudbrandsdalslågen|Gudbrandsdal]] Valley in the village of [[Kvam, Oppland|Kvam]], [[Oppland]], [[Norway]], between British, Norwegian, and German troops. The Germans were moving rapidly north up the river valley to conquer central Norway. In the battle, soldiers from 1st Battalion, [[York and Lancaster Regiment]] and the 1st Battalion, [[King's Own Yorkshire Light Infantry]] (KOYLI), together with their Norwegian counterparts, held a rapidly advancing German army at bay for two days.  It was one of the hardest fought battles of the [[Norwegian Campaign]].

== Background ==
{{Main|Norwegian Campaign|Haakon VII of Norway}}
The German invasion of Norway began on 9 April 1940. It was the first instance of a modern combined operation of land, sea and air forces.&lt;ref name=Hubatch1985p173&gt;{{harvnb|Hubatsch|1985|p=173}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans started by taking the major ports of Norway, but once they had accomplished those goals, they began to move through the interior of the country.&lt;ref name="Berglund 2015 p"&gt;{{harvnb|Berglund|2015|p=}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  At the outset of the invasion, [[Haakon VII of Norway|King Haakon]]  moved to escape capture by the Germans.  He and his wife, [[Princess Märtha of Sweden|Crown Princess Martha]], together with their children, including [[Olav V of Norway|Crown Prince Olav]] made their way east toward [[Hamar]] in the [[Gudbrandsdalen|Gudbrandsdal]] Valley.&lt;ref name="Hambro 1940 144"&gt;{{harvnb|Hambro|1940|p=144}}.&lt;/ref&gt;  When news of their escape reached the German high command. they ordered 100 highly trained German paratroopers to start chasing the royals and officials of the Norwegian government. As a result, the royal family had to stay constantly on the move through the Gudbandsdal Valley and the Swedish border.&lt;ref name="Berglund 2015 p"/&gt; While the King and his family eventually made it to neutral Sweden, a larger mechanized German force followed the paratroopers and began to make its way up the Gudbrandsdal Valley, moving north toward Otta.&lt;ref name="Hambro 1940 144"/&gt;

== The Battle ==

=== 24 April ===
The British force was part of the 1st Battalion, [[York and Lancaster Regiment]] and the 1st Battalion, [[King's Own Yorkshire Light Infantry]] (KOYLI).  They had landed at [[Åndalsnes landings|Åndalsnes]] on the night of 23/24 April. On the night that they landed, the battle had already been lost and the British were retreating in the face of the German advance up the Gudbrandsdal Valley.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Dix|2014|p=117}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The commander of the Norwegian forces [[Otto Ruge|Major General Otto Ruge]] had already informed the British commanders that his troops were completely exhausted and any lines of defense in the Gudbrandsdal Valley were near collapse.&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p189&gt;{{harvnb|Plevy|2017|p=189}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Lt. Col. E.E.E. Cass was in command to the 1st Battalion of the KOYLI, which made its way quickly by rail towards Kvam.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Adams|1989|p=181}}.&lt;/ref&gt; They arrived at Kvam in the early morning hours of the 25th. When they reached Kvam, they encountered Norwegian and British soldiers in full retreat from the German advance at [[Ringebu]] to the south.&lt;ref name="Adams 1989 126"&gt;{{harvnb|Adams|1989|p=126}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:FV361 Nordbygdsvegen ved Kvam.jpg|thumb|left|Highway near Kvam facing south.  Note the steep slope on the east side of the highway.]]

==== Topography of Kvam ====
The topography of Kvam made a perfect location to set up a defense against the advancing German army.&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p189/&gt;
Downriver from Kvam is a sharp bend in the Lågen River, known as the "Kvam's knee." Above the bend in the river, the Gudbrandsdal Valley widens to flat and open farmland, giving good fields of fire. At the bend in the river,  the road is narrow with very steep hills to the east.  There is a large island on the Lågen where the river splits. Due to ice jams on the river, much of the island was flooded.&lt;ref name="Adams 1989 126"/&gt;  Battlefield accounts refer to the island as Viksøya (on most maps, it is called Storøya).  There are hills on the island near the road directly opposite steep slopes to the east.&lt;ref name=Mårtensson2002&gt;{{harvnb|Mårtensson|2002}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The hillsides were still covered in knee deep snow and the local lakes were still solidly frozen over to the point that the British were able to establish a brief airfield on one frozen lake a few days before the battle.&lt;ref name="Dix 2014 115"&gt;{{harvnb|Dix|2014|p=115}}&lt;/ref&gt; In April at Kvam's latitude, [[Twilight|civil twilight]] begins around 4:30&amp;nbsp;a.m. and ends around 10:00&amp;nbsp;p.m.&lt;ref name=Timeanddate.com2018&gt;{{harvnb|Timeanddate.com|2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was at the small village of Kvam that the British set up their defenses to stop the German advance.
[[File:Battle of Kvam 25 April 1940 troop positions.jpg|thumb|left|Battle of Kvam troop positions on 25 April 1940]]

=== 25 April ===
In order to slow the German movement up the Gudbrandsdal valley, the retreating British and Norwegians first tried to blow up a very narrow portion of the road south of Kvam called the ''Kvamsporten'' [the gates of Kvam]. This narrow portion of the road was lined with steep rock cliffs.  The demolition did little to slow the advancing Germans.&lt;ref name=Øvrelid2014&gt;{{harvnb|Øvrelid|2014}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

A few British planes from the airfield on the nearby lake appeared in the sky, offering encouragement of air support in the early hours of the 25 April; however, the Germans quickly destroyed the airfield, any surviving planes retreated north to safety, and British airpower was non-existent during the battle.&lt;ref name="Dix 2014 115"/&gt;

Upon his arrival, Brig. Gen. Smyth set up his headquarters in front of the Kvam Church.&lt;ref name="Adams 1989 126"/&gt;
The British soldiers of the KOYLI arrived around 4:15&amp;nbsp;a.m. They quickly shed their heavy arctic clothing and, carrying only their weapons, ammunition and [[1937 Pattern Web Equipment|'37 web gear]], began to set up defensive positions. Lt. Col. Cass  put "A" and "C" companies on the island in the Lågen river west of the road and "B" company east of the road up on the steep slopes.&lt;ref name="Adams 1989 127"&gt;{{harvnb|Adams|1989|p=127}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The British soldiers were armed with rifles and bayonets, [[Bren light machine gun]]s, and two [[Ordnance ML 3 inch mortar]]s.&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p190&gt;{{harvnb|Plevy|2017|p=190}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to their light weapons, the British soldiers had five [[25 mm Hotchkiss anti-tank gun]]s set up at the forefront, and three in support further behind.&lt;ref name=Grøndahl2014&gt;{{harvnb|Grøndahl|2014}}.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Hotchkiss 25mm anti tank gun at Gudbrandsdal Krigsminnesamling.jpg|thumb|left|Hotchkiss 25mm anti tank gun at Gudbrandsdal Krigsminnesamling]]

General [[Jacob Hvinden Haug]] had informed the British that Norwegian soldiers under his command, who had dug in south of Kvam, could hold until the evening of the 25th.&lt;ref name="Adams 1989 127"/&gt; Unfortunately at 7:30&amp;nbsp;a.m. on the 25th, the Norwegian soldiers moved into Kvam, carrying their wounded through the British lines. There was now nothing between the British and the advancing German army.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Dix|2014|p=117}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The advanced elements of the German forces came up the road  at 11:50&amp;nbsp;a.m. As the Germans approached, the first up the road was a [[Panzer II]] tank, followed by a light tank and an armored car.&lt;ref name="Grøndahl2014"/&gt;  The KOYLI held their fire until the Germans were within 150 yards, when they opened fire disabling the tanks and causing immediate casualties on the German infantry, who were accompanying the tanks.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Dix|2014|p=118}}&lt;/ref&gt;  The Germans immediately responded with their artillery and mortars.  The heavy artillery and mortar barrage caused heavy casualties for the British soldiers near the front line positions.
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-761-221N-06, Norwegen, Panzer "Neubaufahrzeug".jpg|thumb|German [[Neubaufahrzeug]] advancing through the streets of Lillehammer in April 1940.]]
At noon, Brigadier General Smyth was badly wounded by shrapnel from the artillery and was forced to relinquish command to Lt. Col A.L. Kent-Lemon, battalion commander of the [[York and Lancaster Regiment]].&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p190/&gt;

After a brief pause, the Germans infantry moved up the slope on the east side of the road to attack "B" company, but they were repulsed.  The Germans then moved across the frozen river to attack the "A" company position on the island.  "A" company had already suffered heavy losses from the artillery barrage, and was unable to stop the German offensive.  By mid-afternoon, "A" company ceased to exist as an independent company, having lost 4 officers and 85 other ranks. "C" company moved forward to reinforce the line.&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p191&gt;{{harvnb|Plevy|2017|p=191}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

At 5:30&amp;nbsp;p.m., the first reinforcements arrived from the 1st Battalion, [[York and Lancaster Regiment]], which reinforced the left flank.&lt;ref name="Grøndahl2014"/&gt;

By nightfall, company "B" on the east slope had held its position against the Germans, but its position was precarious.  It decided to withdraw toward the village center of Kvam. Company "B" was reportedly in high spirits, having fought off several German attacks. In their withdrawal, the company had to abandon two of its Hotchkiss anti-tank guns.&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p191/&gt;

At the end of the first day of fighting, the British had 89 casualties killed or wounded, while the Germans had 4 soldiers killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Adams|1989|p=128}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

=== 26 April ===
[[File:Nett Tyske soldate 3581766a.jpg|left|thumb|German soldiers moving past Hillingen seter on 26 April 1940]]
At 5:30&amp;nbsp;a.m. the next day, the Germans commenced an intense artillery and machine gun barrage on the KOYLI. The Germans then commenced a series of infantry attacks against the left flank held by "C" company of the [[York and Lancaster Regiment]].  These attacks were all beaten off.&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p191/&gt;

At 9:00&amp;nbsp;a.m., the Germans continued to attack the left flank of the British.  This time they moved further up the steep hillside to the farmstead called Hillingen seter.  Here they were met by three brave Norwegian soldiers, who though outnumbered, fought them off, losing their lives in the process.&lt;ref name="Grøndahl2014"/&gt;

At 11:00&amp;nbsp;a.m., the Germans renewed their attack, and now had air support, as well as increased artillery, to bomb the village of Kvam.  They began to have some success infiltrating the British lines.&lt;ref name="Grøndahl2014"/&gt;

Around 1:00&amp;nbsp;p.m., the Germans brought tanks down the road toward "B" and "C" companies of the KOYLI in front of the village. The British had three of their [[25 mm Hotchkiss anti-tank gun]]s positioned to defend the road; however, a light road block had been created across the road using tree branches.  These tree branches prevented any of the anti-tanks guns from finding their targets.&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p191/&gt;

According to Plevy, Captain A.F. McRiggs crossed the road twice, fully exposed to machine gun fire from the German positions, to remove the debris from the road. Just as he finished, a bullet hit him in the shoulder, but one anti-tank gun could now see the tank.&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p192&gt;{{harvnb|Plevy|2017|p=192}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Corporal Stokes of the [[York and Lancaster Regiment]] was in command of the third Hotchkiss gun beside the road at the back of the village.  He could now see the tank and with his first shot he stopped the tank.  His second shot set it on fire and left it at the side of the road.  Moments later a second tank came up the road.  Stokes waited until it was immediately beside the first tank, and he destroyed it with two shots in exactly the same way he stopped the first. Then the Germans sent an armored car rapidly down the road, and when it came between the two tanks, Corporal Stokes knocked it out with one shot.  The three disabled vehicles now blocked the road. Corporal Stokes realized that his Hotchkiss gun was about to become a prime target, so he pulled his crew away from the position just before the Germans destroyed it.  Stokes and his crew now became infantrymen.&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p192/&gt;

Around 4:00&amp;nbsp;p.m., the British were in danger of being flanked on the left, but a company from the York and Lancaster battalion managed to hold them off.  Then a company of 40 Norwegian skiers came down from high on the slopes above the battle.  These Norwegian ski  troops under the command of Paul Jørgenvåg opened fire on the Germans from a long distance up on the valley side. Although the fire had little effect from that distance, the Germans were forced to retreat because of their exposed position.&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p192/&gt;
[[File:Ødeleggelser - U2 016.jpg|thumb|Residents of Kvam rebuilding shortly after the battle in 1940.]]
Unfortunately the situation was deteriorating and at 5:00&amp;nbsp;p.m., [[Bernard Paget|General Paget]] issued orders for Kvam to be abandoned at 11:00&amp;nbsp;p.m. and the companies were to retreat behind new positions at Kjørem approximately 4–5&amp;nbsp;km further north, where companies from [[York and Lancaster Regiment|York and Lancaster]] and from [[Green Howards]] had set up a new defensive position.&lt;ref name=Plevy2017p192/&gt;

At 6:00&amp;nbsp;p.m., the Germans gained full control of the island in the Lågen. German artillery began to fire phosphorus shells into the forests where several British companies were in position, and the resulting forest fires forced the British to escape.  Still the British held until ordered to retreat by General Paget.&lt;ref name="Grøndahl2014"/&gt;
[[File:BritishwarmemorialKvam.jpg|thumb|left|Memorial to 54 British soldiers killed in the Battle for Kvam, Norway, 25–26 April 1940]]
The battle in Kvam on 25 and 26 April 1940 was the hardest in southern and central Norway. 1st Battalion KOYLI and 1st Battalion York and Lancaster had 54 soldiers killed. In addition, three Norwegian soldiers and three Norwegian civilians were killed in Kvam.&lt;ref name="Grøndahl2014"/&gt;

The three civilians killed included a Dane, Søren Sørensen, who was staying on the Svarthaugen farm.  When he saw that the farm was burning, he went down to save the farm animals. After the battle, he was found near the railway line with three bullets through the head.&lt;ref name=Øvrelid2015&gt;{{harvnb|Øvrelid|2015}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The other civilian was Petter Klomstad at Kjestad farm.&lt;ref name=VG.no2018&gt;{{harvnb|VG.no|2018}}.&lt;/ref&gt; He had seen the farm on fire and he ran to help a 92 year old bed-ridden woman on the farm. When some grenades began exploding, he ran into the barn for shelter. When he ran out of the barn, he was killed by shrapnel from a grenade.&lt;ref name=Øvrelid2015/&gt;

Later in the day, 70-year-old Mari Bakken returned to her house to pick up more clothes. Her son found her in the courtyard the following morning with a bullet through her heart.&lt;ref name=Øvrelid2015/&gt;

== Aftermath ==
Over 70 buildings in Kvam were burned to the ground as a result of the fighting.  The village and church were essentially leveled.  Families were left homeless and lost everything.  One survivor recalled how residents lost their bank passbooks in the fire.  It became necessary for each family to meet with the local bank boards to settle accounts with the bank.&lt;ref name=Ringen2013&gt;{{harvnb|Ringen|2013}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 54 British soldiers killed in the battle were buried in the Kvam churchyard.&lt;ref name=cwgc.org2018&gt;{{harvnb|cwgc.org|2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Today, a monument to the British soldiers stands in the Kvam churchyard. In addition, a war museum provides artifacts and information on the battle.&lt;ref name=www..krigsminne.no2018&gt;{{harvnb|www..krigsminne.no|2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The three Norwegian soldiers who lost their lives in the fighting at Hillingen seter (farm) have been memorialized by a monument on the farmstead.&lt;ref name=Grøndahl2015&gt;{{harvnb|Grøndahl|2015}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Today, there is a very popular hiking trail to the Hillingen seter and the war memorial to the three brave Norwegians who died there defending their country.&lt;ref name=Bertelsen2017&gt;{{harvnb|Bertelsen|2017}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2014, the main  north-south highway up the Gudbrandsdal through Kvam was rebuilt and widened.  During construction, the work crews came across unexploded ordnance from the battle near Kvam.  Construction had to be halted while Norwegian military units moved in to dispose of the ordnance.&lt;ref name=Øvrelid2015/&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* {{cite book |ref=harv|last=Adams |first=Jack |date=1989 |title= The Doomed Expedition: The Campaign in Norway, 1940|url= |location=United Kingdom |publisher=Pen and Sword |page=286 |isbn=  978-0850520361 |author-link= }}
* {{cite news |ref=harv|last=Berglund |first=Nina|date=8 April 2015 |title=The king’s defiance, and chaotic escape |url=http://www.newsinenglish.no/2015/04/08/the-kings-defiance-and-chaotic-escape/ |work=NewsinEnglish.no from newspaper Dagsavisen |location= |access-date=17 June 2018 }}
* {{Cite journal |ref=harv|last=Bertelsen |first=Gitte|date= 14 June 2017|title=Kveldstur til Hillingen|trans-title=Evening hike to Hillingen|url=https://gudbrandsdalen.dnt.no/artikler/turreferater/9555-kveldstur-til-hillingen/|journal=DNT Gudbrandsdalen|language=Norwegian|volume=|pages=|via= |access-date=19 July 2018}}
* {{cite web |ref=harv |url=https://www.cwgc.org/find/find-war-dead/results/?cemetery=KVAM%20CHURCHYARD |title=Commonwealth War Graves Commission: Kvam Churchyard |last= |first= |date=2018 |website= cwgc.org|publisher= |access-date= 18 July 2018 |quote=}}
* {{cite book |ref=harv|last=Dix |first=Anthony |date=2014 |title= The Norway campaign and the rise of Churchill 1940|url= |location=United Kingdom |publisher=Pen and Sword |page=244 |isbn= 978-1783400607|author-link= }}
* {{Cite journal |ref=harv|last=Grøndahl|first=Carl Henrik|date=11 April 2014|title=I strid for første gang i sitt liv|trans-title=I fight for the first time in my life|url=https://fronhistorielag.com/2014/04/11/i-strid-for-forste-gang-i-sitt-liv/|journal=Fron Historielag|language=Norwegian|volume=|pages=|via= |access-date=7 July 2018}}
* {{Cite journal |ref=harv|last=Grøndahl|first=Carl Henrik|date= 13 March 2015|title=Minnesmerke i Fron: Hillingen 26.4.1940|trans-title=Memorial in Fron: Hillingen 26 April 1940|url=https://fronhistorielag.com/2015/03/13/minnesmerke-i-fron-hillingen-26-4-1940/|journal=Fron Historielag|language=Norwegian|volume=|pages=|via= |access-date=19 July 2018}}
* {{cite web|ref=harv|url=http://www.krigsminne.no|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20021030103513/http://www.krigsminne.no/|url-status=dead|archive-date=2002-10-30|title=Gudbrandsdal Krigsminnesamling|trans-title=Gudbrandsdal War Memorial Collection|date=2018|website=www..krigsminne.no|access-date=19 July 2018}}
* {{cite book |ref=harv|last=Hambro |first=C.J. |date=1940 |title= I saw it happen in Norway|url= |location=New York, London |publisher=D. Appleton-Century Company, Inc. |page= |isbn= |author-link= }}
* {{Cite book|ref=harv|last=Hubatsch|first=Walter|date=1985|title=The Norwegian Campaign, 1940: Strategy in Critical Retrospect. In: Studies in Medieval and Modern German History|location=London|publisher=Palgrave Macmillan|isbn= 978-1-349-17822-3|pages=173–187|doi=10.1007/978-1-349-17822-3_10|chapter=The Norwegian Campaign, 1940: Strategy in Critical Retrospect}}
* {{cite web |ref=harv |url=http://hem.fyristorg.com/robertm/norge/battle_for_kvam.html |title=The Battle for Kvam |last=Mårtensson |first=Robert |date=2002 |website=Norway 1940 |publisher= |access-date=26 June 2018 |quote= |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20081006115750/http://hem.fyristorg.com/robertm/norge/battle_for_kvam.html |archive-date=6 October 2008 |url-status=dead }}
* {{cite book|ref=harv|last=Plevy |first=Harry |date=2017 |title=Norway 1940: Chronicle of a Chaotic Campaign|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=A2MpDwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT256|publisher=Fonthill Media|pages=416–|isbn= 978-1781555811|id=GGKEY:0PEP9KHTAZ4}}
* {{Cite journal|ref=harv|last=Ringen|first=Asbjørn|date=15 October 2013|title=Brent bankbok|trans-title=Burned bank book|url=https://fronhistorielag.com/2013/10/15/brent-bankbok/|journal=Fron Historielag|language=Norwegian|volume=|pages=|access-date=4 June 2018|via=}}
* {{cite web |ref=harv |url=https://www.timeanddate.com/sun/norway/oslo?month=4&amp;year=2018 |title=Timeanddate.com |last=|first= |date=2018 |website= Timeanddate.com|publisher= |access-date= 12 July 2018 |quote=}}
* {{cite web |ref=harv |url=https://www.vg.no/spesial/2015/vaare_falne/index.php?personId=15559=2018 |title=Dette er de 11 902 norske ofrene for annen verdenskrig|trans-title="These are the 11 902 Norwegian victims of World War II"|last=|first= |date=2018 |website=VG.no|language=Norwegian|publisher= |access-date= 12 July 2018 |quote=}}
* {{Cite journal |ref=harv|last=Øvrelid|first=Ragnar|date=17 April 2014|title=Sprenginga av Kvamsporten var mislukka|trans-title=The demolition of the 'gates of Kvam' was unsuccessful|url=https://fronhistorielag.com/2014/04/17/sprenginga-av-kvamsporten-var-mislukka/|journal=Fron Historielag|language=Norwegian|volume=|pages=|via= |access-date=4 June 2018}}
* {{Cite journal |ref=harv|last=Øvrelid|first=Ragnar|date= 17 April 2015|title=Vart skoten da ho skulle hente meir klede|trans-title=When the shooting was going on, and you needed more clothes|url=https://fronhistorielag.com/2014/04/17/vart-skoten-da-ho-skulle-hente-meir-klede/|journal=Fron Historielag|language=Norwegian|volume=|pages=|via= |access-date=21 July 2018}}

[[Category:Norwegian Campaign]]
[[Category:Kvam]]</text><sha1>t2tefhp3d6l1v3lm3baks3kaw4tsi98</sha1></revision></page>