<page><title>Battle of Vinjesvingen</title><ns>0</ns><id>4150165</id><revision><id>956811884</id><parentid>955525702</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-15T13:12:42Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Bjerrebæk</username><id>12289497</id></contributor><comment>it has nothing to do with Vestfold</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="3486" xml:space="preserve">{{no footnotes|date=September 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Vinjesvingen
|image=
|caption=
|partof=the [[Norwegian Campaign]]
|date=3–5 May 1940
|place=[[Vinjesvingen]] in [[Telemark]], [[Norway]]
|result=The forces at Vinjesvingen capitulated May 5 after all other Norwegian forces in southern Norway had laid down their arms.
|combatant1={{flag|Norway}}
|combatant2={{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1={{flagdeco|Norway}}[[Thor O. Hannevig]]{{POW}}
|commander2=?
|strength1= ~300 soldiers
|strength2=?
|casualties2=
|casualties1=
}}
{{Campaignbox Norwegian Campaign}}

The '''Battle of Vinjesvingen''' was a battle of the [[Norwegian Campaign]] and took place in May 1940 in the [[Telemark]] county, [[Norway]]. It became one of the two last strongholds of Norwegian resistance in southern Norway during [[World War II]], the other being [[Battle of Hegra Fortress|Hegra Fortress]].

==Background==
Under the command of Second Lieutenant [[Thor O. Hannevig]], the Norwegians held their position against superior German forces until 5 May 1940. Hannevig managed to sneak great loads of arms, equipment and fuel from depots right in front of the German forces. The equipment was brought to [[Vinje]] and [[Vågsli]] in [[Telemark]], where Hannevig established a unit which came to be known as [[Telemark Infantry Regiment]]. This included [[Krag-Jørgensen]] [[bolt action rifle]]s, [[Madsen machine gun|Madsen]] [[light machine gun]]s, [[Colt M/29]] [[heavy machine gun]]s, {{convert|81|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} [[Mortar (weapon)|mortar]]s as well as [[Land mine|mine]]s and [[explosives]] to destroy bridges and roads. The plan was to prevent German advance westward through [[Telemark]] and [[Setesdal]], and to support [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] reinforcements from the west.

==Battle==
A full mobilization was carried out in the area, and at most the force totaled around 300 men, but the number changed constantly. Several small battles were fought, mostly involving Norwegian [[ambush]]es on advancing German formations, using [[small arms]] and [[Improvised explosive device|IED]]s. The Norwegian defenders often destroyed and/or damaged bridges and roads in the area to delay the German advance.

The main battle took place from 3–5 May. Large German forces were eventually deployed to the area, and the German losses were considerable. When it was realized that the entire south of Norway was lost, and that the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[Battle of Åndalsnes|Åndalsnes task force]] would not break through from the west, Hannevig initiated negotiations for surrender. The battles of Vinjesvingen had a great symbolic effect during the occupation, and provided a moral boost to a rather depressing occupation. It was however not known to the rest of the country while the battles were fought.

==References==
* {{cite book |last=Lødrup |first=Hans P. |authorlink=Hans P. Lødrup |date=1945 |title=Vinjesvingen. Et lite blad av krigens historie i Norge |url= |location=Oslo |publisher=H. Aschehoug &amp; Co. (W. Nygaard) |page= |isbn= |accessdate= |language=Norwegian }}

{{coord|59|37|13|N|7|48|23|E|source:nnwiki_region:NO_type:city|display=title}}

[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Norway|Vinjesvingen]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany|Vinjesvingen]]
[[Category:Norwegian Campaign]]
[[Category:1940 in Norway]]
[[Category:History of Telemark]]
[[Category:Vinje]]
[[Category:May 1940 events]]</text><sha1>78tf1x6qlafk74csoch8jb2a79rfcy0</sha1></revision></page>