<page><title>Battle of Belgium</title><ns>0</ns><id>23180963</id><revision><id>966880504</id><parentid>964285714</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-09T19:15:12Z</timestamp><contributor><username>JHunterJ</username><id>842922</id></contributor><minor /><comment>Fixing [[Wikipedia:Disambiguation pages with links|links to disambiguation pages]], [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: km² → km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, replaced: 3 million → 3&amp;nbsp;million</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="112067" xml:space="preserve">{{For|the invasion in World War I|German invasion of Belgium}}
{{Good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Battle of Belgium
| partof   = the [[Manstein Plan|German invasion of France and the Low Countries]] in [[World War II]]
| image    = [[File:Infanterie-Regiment 489 Westfeldzug Gefangene Fort Eben-Emael 1940-2 by-RaBoe.jpg|300px|alt=Belgian soldiers taken prisoner by the Germans marching down a road|link=File:Infanterie-Regiment 489 Westfeldzug Gefangene Fort Eben-Emael 1940-2 by-RaBoe.jpg]]
| caption  = Belgian soldiers under German guard following the [[Battle of Fort Eben-Emael|fall of Fort Eben-Emael]] on 11 May 1940.
| date     = 10–28 May 1940
| place    = Belgium and Luxembourg
| result   = Decisive German victory
* Belgian surrender
* Establishment of [[Belgian government in exile|Belgian government]] and [[Free Belgian Forces|army]] in exile
| territory   = [[German occupation of Belgium during World War II|German occupation of Belgium]]
| combatant1  = '''{{flag|Belgium}}'''&lt;br&gt;{{flagcountry|French Third Republic}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Netherlands}}{{efn|name=Netherlands}}
| combatant2  = '''{{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}'''
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Belgium}} [[Leopold III of Belgium|Leopold III]]{{POW}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Belgium}} [[Hubert Pierlot]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|France|1830}} [[Maurice Gamelin]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|France|1830}} [[Maxime Weygand]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[John Vereker, 6th Viscount Gort|Lord Gort]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Gerd von Rundstedt]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Fedor von Bock]]
| strength1   = 144 divisions{{efn|name=Divisions}}&lt;br/&gt;13,974 guns{{efn|name=Guns}}&lt;br/&gt;3,384 tanks{{efn|name=tanks}}&lt;br/&gt;2,249 aircraft{{efn|name=Aircraft}}
| strength2   = 141 divisions{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=324}}&lt;br/&gt;7,378 guns {{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=324}}&lt;br/&gt;2,445 tanks{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=324}}&lt;br/&gt;5,446 aircraft (4,020 operational){{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=324}}
| casualties1 = 222,443+ casualties (200,000 [[Belgian prisoners of war in World War II|captured]]){{efn|name=Men lost}}&lt;br/&gt;~900 aircraft{{efn|name=Aircraft lost}}
| casualties2 = Uncertain (see [[#German|German casualties]]){{efn|name=German casualties}}
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Western Front (World War II)}}{{The Belgian Campaign}}
}}
The '''Battle of Belgium''' or '''Belgian Campaign''',{{sfn|Belgian American Educational Foundation|1941}} often referred to within [[Belgium]] as the '''18 Days' Campaign''' ({{lang-fr|Campagne des 18 jours}}, {{lang-nl|Achttiendaagse Veldtocht}}), formed part of the greater [[Battle of France]], an [[Military offensive|offensive]] campaign by [[Nazi Germany|Germany]] during the [[World War II|Second World War]]. It took place over 18 days in May 1940 and ended with the [[German occupation of Belgium during World War II|German occupation of Belgium]] following the surrender of the [[Belgian Land Component|Belgian Army]].

On 10 May 1940, Germany [[Invasion of Luxembourg|invaded Luxembourg]], [[Battle of the Netherlands|the Netherlands]], and Belgium under the operational plan ''[[Manstein Plan|Fall Gelb]]'' (Case Yellow). The Allied armies [[French war planning 1920–1940|attempted to halt]] the [[German Army (1935–1945)|German Army]] in Belgium, believing it to be the main German thrust. After the French had fully committed the best of the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] armies to Belgium between 10 and 12 May, the Germans enacted the second phase of their operation, a [[Manstein Plan|break-through]], or sickle cut, through the [[Ardennes]], and advanced toward the [[English Channel]]. The German Army (''[[German Army (Wehrmacht)|Heer]]'') reached the Channel after five days, encircling the Allied armies. The Germans gradually reduced the pocket of Allied forces, forcing them back to the sea. The Belgian Army surrendered on 28 May 1940, ending the battle.{{sfn|Shirer|1990|p=729}}

The Battle of Belgium included the first tank battle of the war, the [[Battle of Hannut]].{{sfn|Healy|2008|p=36}} It was the largest tank battle in history at the time but was later surpassed by the battles of the [[North African Campaign]] and the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]. The battle also included the [[Battle of Fort Eben-Emael]], the first strategic [[Airborne forces|airborne]] [[Military operation|operation]] using [[paratrooper]]s ever attempted.

The German official history stated that in the 18 days of bitter fighting, the Belgian Army were tough opponents, and spoke of the "extraordinary bravery" of its soldiers.{{sfn|Keegan|2005|pp=95–96}} The Belgian collapse forced the Allied withdrawal from continental Europe. The British [[Royal Navy]] subsequently evacuated Belgian ports during [[Dunkirk evacuation|Operation Dynamo]], allowing the [[British Expeditionary Force (World War II)|British Expeditionary Force]] (BEF), along with many Belgian and French soldiers, to escape capture and continue military operations. France reached its own [[Armistice of 22 June 1940|armistice with Germany]] in June 1940. [[German occupation of Belgium during World War II|Belgium was occupied by the Germans]] until the autumn of 1944, when it was liberated by the Western Allies.

==Pre-battle plans==

===Belgium's strained alliances===
[[File:Congrès universel pour la paix 1936.jpg|thumb|A pacifist rally in [[Heysel Park|Heysel]], near [[Brussels]], in 1936]]
The Belgian strategy for a defence against German aggression faced political as well as military problems. In terms of [[military strategy]], the Belgians were unwilling to stake everything on a linear defence of the Belgian–German border, in an extension of the [[Maginot Line]]. Such a move would leave the Belgians vulnerable to a German assault in their rear, through an attack on [[the Netherlands]]. Such a strategy would also rely on the French to move quickly into Belgium and support the garrison there.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=8}}

Politically, the Belgians did not trust the French. Marshal [[Philippe Pétain]] had suggested a French strike at Germany's [[Ruhr]] area using Belgium as a spring-board in October 1930 and again in January 1933. Belgium feared it would be drawn into a war regardless, and sought to avoid that eventuality. The Belgians also feared being drawn into a war as a result of the [[Franco-Soviet Treaty of Mutual Assistance|French–Soviet pact of May 1935]]. The Franco-Belgian agreement stipulated Belgium was to mobilise if the Germans did, but what was not clear was whether Belgium would have to mobilise in the event of a German invasion of Poland.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=8}}

The Belgians much preferred an alliance with the [[United Kingdom]]. The British had entered the [[First World War]] in response to the German violation of Belgian neutrality. The Belgian Channel [[port]]s had offered the [[German Imperial Navy]] valuable bases, and such an attack would offer the German ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' and the ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' bases to engage in strategic offensive operations against the United Kingdom in the coming conflict. But the British government paid little attention to the concerns of the Belgians. The lack of this commitment ensured the Belgian withdrawal from the [[Western Allies|Western Alliance]], the day before the [[remilitarisation of the Rhineland]].{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=8}}{{sfn|Ellis|2004|p=8}} The lack of opposition to the remilitarisation served to convince the Belgians that France and Britain were unwilling to fight for their own strategic interests, let alone Belgium's. The Belgian [[General Staff]] was determined to fight for its own interests, alone if necessary.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=8}}

===Belgian place in Allied strategy===
[[File:Leopold III van België (1934).jpg|thumb|left|[[Leopold III of Belgium|King Leopold III]], Belgian head of state, who was partisan of the policy of neutrality]]
The French were infuriated at [[Leopold III of Belgium|King Leopold III]]'s open declaration of neutrality in October 1936. The [[French Army]] saw its strategic assumptions undermined; it could no longer expect closer cooperation with the Belgians in defending the latter's eastern borders, enabling a German attack to be checked well forward of the French border.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=9}} The French were dependent on how much cooperation they could extract from the Belgians. Such a situation deprived the French any prepared defences in Belgium to forestall an attack, a situation which the French had wanted to avoid as it meant engaging the German [[Panzer Division]]s in a mobile battle.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=21}} The French considered invading Belgium immediately in response to a German attack on the country.{{sfn|Bond|Taylor|2001|p=14}} The Belgians, recognising the danger posed by the Germans, secretly made their own defence policies, troop movement information, communications, fixed defence dispositions, intelligence and air reconnaissance arrangements available to the French military attaché in [[Brussels]].{{sfn|Bond|1990|pp=9–10}}

The Allied plan to aid Belgium was the [[Dyle Plan]]; the cream of the Allied forces, which included the French [[armoured division]]s, would advance to the [[Dijle|Dyle]] river in response to a German invasion. The choice of an established Allied line lay in either reinforcing the Belgians in the east of the country, at the [[Meuse]]–[[Albert Canal]] line, and holding the [[Scheldt Estuary]], thus linking the French defences in the south with the Belgian forces protecting [[Ghent]] and [[Antwerp]], seemed to be the soundest defensive strategy.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=22}}
The weakness of the plan was that, politically at least, it abandoned most of eastern Belgium to the Germans. Militarily it would put the Allied rear at right angles to the French frontier defences; while for the British, their communications located at the [[Bay of Biscay]] ports, would be parallel to their front. Despite the risk of committing forces to central Belgium and an advance to the Schedlt or Dyle lines, which would be vulnerable to an outflanking move, [[Maurice Gamelin]], the French commander, approved the plan and it remained the Allied strategy upon the outbreak of war.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=22}}

The British, with no army in the field and behind in rearmament, was in no position to challenge French strategy, which had assumed the prominent role of the Western Alliance. Having little ability to oppose the French, the British strategy for military action came in the form of [[strategic bombing]] of the Ruhr industry.{{sfn|Bond|1990|pp=22–23}}

===Belgian military strategy===
[[File:Léopold III-1940-revue-01.jpg|thumb|[[Leopold III of Belgium|Leopold III]], Belgium's monarch from 1934, reviewing Belgian troops in early 1940]]

Upon the official Belgian withdrawal from the Western Alliance, the Belgians refused to engage in any official staff meetings with the French or British military staff for fear of compromising its neutrality. The Belgians did not regard a German invasion as inevitable and were determined that if an invasion did take place it would be effectively resisted by new [[Fortified Position of Liège|fortifications]] such as [[Eben Emael]].{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=24}}
The Belgians had taken measures to reconstruct their defences along the border with the German state upon [[Adolf Hitler]]'s rise to power in January 1933. The Belgian government had watched with increasing alarm the German withdrawal from the [[League of Nations]], its repudiation of the [[Treaty of Versailles]] and its violation of the [[Locarno Treaties]].{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=2}} The government increased expenditure on modernising the [[fortification]]s at [[Namur (city)|Namur]] and [[Liège]]. New lines of defence were established along the [[Maastricht]]–Bois-le-Duc canal, joining the Meuse, Scheldt and the Albert Canal.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=2}} The protection of the eastern frontier, based mainly on the destruction of a number of roads, was entrusted to new formations (frontier cyclist units and the newly formed ''[[Chasseurs Ardennais]]'').{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=3}} By 1935, the Belgian defences had been completed.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=3}} Even so, it was felt that the defences were no longer adequate. A significant mobile reserve was needed to guard the rear areas, and as a result it was considered that the protection against a sudden assault by German forces was not sufficient.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=3}} Significant manpower reserves were also needed, but a bill made for the provision of longer military service and training for the army was rejected by the public on the basis that it would increase Belgium's military commitments as well as the request of the Allies to engage in conflicts far from home.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=4}}

King Leopold III made a speech on 14 October 1936 in front of the Council of Ministers, in an attempt to persuade the people (and its Government) that the defences needed strengthening.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=4}} He outlined three main military points for Belgium's increased rearmament:
&lt;blockquote&gt;a) German rearmament, following upon the complete re-militarisation of Italy and Russia (the Soviet Union), caused most other states, even those that were deliberately pacifistic, like Switzerland and the Netherlands, to take exceptional precautions.&lt;br/&gt;
b) There has been such a vast change in the methods of warfare as a result of technical progress, particularly in aviation and mechanization, that the initial operations of armed conflict could now be of such force, speed and magnitude as to be particularly alarming to small countries like Belgium.&lt;br/&gt;
c) Our anxieties have been increased by the lightning reoccupation of the Rhineland and the fact that bases for the start of a possible German invasion have been moved near to our frontier.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=53}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

On 24 April 1937, the French and British delivered a public declaration that Belgium's security was paramount to the [[Western Allies]] and that they would defend their frontiers accordingly against aggression of any sort, whether this aggression was directed solely at Belgium, or as a means of obtaining bases from which to wage war against "other states". The British and French, under those circumstances, released Belgium from her Locarno obligations to render mutual assistance in the event of German aggression toward Poland, while the British and French maintained their military obligations to Belgium.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|pp=4–5}}

Militarily, the Belgians considered the ''Wehrmacht'' to be stronger than the Allies, particular the British Army, and engaging in overtures to the Allies would result in Belgium becoming a battleground without adequate Allies.{{sfn|Bond|1990|pp=24–25}}
The Belgians and French remained confused about what was expected of each other if or when hostilities commenced. The Belgians were determined to hold the border fortifications along the Albert Canal and the Meuse, without withdrawing, until the French Army arrived to support them. Gamelin was not keen on pushing his Dyle plan that far. He was concerned that the Belgians would be driven out of their defences and would retreat to Antwerp, as in 1914. In fact, the Belgian divisions protecting the border were to withdraw and retreat southward to link up with French forces. This information was not given to Gamelin.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=25}}
As far as the Belgians were concerned, the Dyle Plan had advantages. Instead of the limited Allied advance to the Scheldt, or meeting the Germans on the Franco-Belgian border, the move to the Dyle river would reduce the Allied front in central Belgium by {{convert|70|km|mi}}, freeing more forces for use as a strategic reserve. It was felt it would save more Belgian territory, in particular the eastern industrial regions. It also had the advantage of absorbing Dutch and Belgian Army formations (including some 20 Belgian divisions). Gamelin was to justify the Dyle Plan after the defeat using these arguments.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=28}}

On 10 January 1940, in an episode known as the [[Mechelen Incident]], a German Army [[Major]] Hellmuth Reinberger crash-landed in a [[Messerschmitt Bf 108]] near [[Maasmechelen|Mechelen-aan-de-Maas]].{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=35}} Reinberger was carrying the first plans for the German invasion of western Europe which, as Gamelin had expected, entailed a repeat of the 1914 [[Schlieffen Plan]] and a German thrust through Belgium (which was expanded by the ''Wehrmacht'' to include the Netherlands) and into France.{{sfn|Bond|1990|pp=28–36}}

The Belgians suspected a ruse, but the plans were taken seriously. Belgian intelligence and the military attaché in [[Cologne]] correctly suggested the Germans would not commence the invasion with this plan. It suggested that the Germans would try an attack through the Belgian Ardennes and advance to [[Calais]] with the aim of encircling the Allied armies in Belgium. The Belgians had correctly predicted the Germans would attempt a ''Kesselschlacht'' (literally "Cauldron battle", meaning encirclement), to destroy its enemies. The Belgians had predicted the exact German plan as offered by [[Erich von Manstein]].{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=36}}

The Belgian High Command warned the French and British of their concerns. They feared that the Dyle plan would put not just the Belgian strategic position in danger, but also the entire left wing of the Allied front. King Leopold and General Raoul Van Overstraeten, the King's ''Aide de Camp'', warned Gamelin and the French Army Command of their concerns on 8 March and 14 April. They were ignored.{{sfn|Bond|1990|pp=46–47}}

===Belgian plans for defensive operations===
[[File:Bunker Kanal Nord 2.jpg|thumb|[[Fort Eben-Emael|Eben-Emael]]: the Belgians hoped to severely delay the Germans using such fortifications]]

The Belgian plan, ''in the event of German aggression'' [italics in original] provided for:
&lt;blockquote&gt;(a) A delaying position along the Albert Canal from Antwerp to Liège and the Meuse from Liège to Namur, which was to be held long enough to allow French and British troops to occupy the line Antwerp–Namur–[[Givet]]. It was anticipated that the forces of the guarantor Powers would be in action on the third day of an invasion.&lt;br/&gt;
(b) Withdrawal to the Antwerp–Namur position.&lt;br/&gt;
(c) The Belgian Army was to hold the sector–excluding [[Leuven]], but including Antwerp–as part of the main Allied defensive position.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|pp=32–33}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

In an agreement with the British and French Armies, the [[French Seventh Army|French 7th Army]] under the command of [[Henri Giraud]] was to advance into Belgium, past the Scheldt Estuary in [[Zeeland]] if possible, to [[Breda]], in the Netherlands. The British Army's [[British Expeditionary Force (World War II)|British Expeditionary Force]] or BEF, commanded by General [[John Vereker, 6th Viscount Gort|John Vereker, Lord Gort]], was to occupy the central position in the Brussels–Ghent gap supporting the Belgian Army holding the main defensive positions some {{convert|20|km}} east of Brussels. The main defensive position ringing Antwerp would be protected by the Belgians, barely {{convert|10|km}} from the city. The French 7th Army was to reach the Zeeland or Breda, just inside the Dutch border. The French would then be in a position to protect the left flank of the Belgian Army forces protecting Antwerp and threaten the German northern flank.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|pp=32–33}}

Further east, delaying positions were constructed in the immediate tactical zones along the Albert Canal, which joined with the defences of the Meuse west of Maastricht. The line deviated southward, and continued to Liege. The Maastricht–Liège gap was heavily protected. [[Fort Eben-Emael]] guarded the city's northern flank, the tank country lying in the [[strategic depth]]s of the Belgian forces occupying the city and the axis of advance into the west of the country. Further lines of defence ran south west, covering the Liege–Namur axis. The Belgian Army also had the added benefit of the [[French First Army|French 1st Army]], advancing toward [[Gembloux]] and [[Hannut]], on the southern flank of the BEF and covering the [[Sambre]] sector. This covered the gap in the Belgian defences between the main Belgian positions on the Dyle line with Namur to the south. Further south still, the [[French Ninth Army|French 9th Army]] advanced to the Givet–Dinant axis on the Meuse river. The [[French Second Army|French 2nd Army]] was responsible for the last {{convert|100|km}} of front, covering Sedan, the lower Meuse, the Belgian–Luxembourg border and the northern flank of the Maginot line.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|pp=32–33}}

===German operational plans===
{{Main|Manstein Plan}}
[[File:Eben-Emael.png|thumb|left|Map of the area between Belgium and the Netherlands near Fort Eben-Emael: The fort protected the vital strategic bridgeheads into Belgium]]

The German plan of attack required that [[Army Group B]] would advance and draw in the Allied First Army Group into central Belgium, while [[Army Group A]] conducted the surprise assault through the Ardennes. Belgium was to act as a secondary front with regard to importance. Army Group B was given only limited numbers of armoured and mobile units while the vast majority of the Army Group comprised infantry divisions.{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=313}} After the [[English Channel]] was reached, all [[Panzer division]] units and most [[motorized infantry|motorised infantry]] were removed from Army Group B and given to Army Group A, to strengthen the German lines of communication and to prevent an Allied breakout.{{sfn|Bond|1990|pp=100–101}}

Such a plan would still fail if sufficient ground could not be taken quickly in Belgium to squeeze the allies against two fronts. Preventing this from happening were the defences of Fort Eben-Emael and the Albert Canal. The three bridges over the canal were the key to allowing Army Group B a high operational tempo. The bridges at Veldwezelt, Vroenhoven and [[Kanne]] in Belgium, and [[Maastricht]] on the Dutch border were the target.{{sfn|Dunstan|2005|p=34}} Failure to capture the bridges would leave Reichenau's [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|German 6th Army]], the southern-most army of Group B, trapped in the Maastricht-Albert Canal enclave and subjected to the fire of Eben-Emael. The fort had to be captured or destroyed.{{sfn|Dunstan|2005|p=34}}

Adolf Hitler summoned Lieutenant-General [[Kurt Student]] of the ''[[7th Air Division (Germany)|7. Flieger-Division]]'' (7th Air Division) to discuss the assault.{{sfn|Dunstan|2005|p=34}} It was first suggested that a conventional parachute drop be made by airborne forces to seize and destroy the forts' guns before the land units approached. Such a suggestion was rejected as the [[Junkers Ju 52]] transports were too slow and were likely to be vulnerable to Dutch and Belgian anti-aircraft guns.{{sfn|Dunstan|2005|p=34}} Other factors for its refusal were the weather conditions, which might blow the paratroopers away from the fort and disperse them too widely. A seven-second drop from a Ju 52 at minimum operational height led to a dispersion over 300&amp;nbsp;metres alone.{{sfn|Dunstan|2005|p=34}}

Hitler had noticed one potential flaw in the defences.{{sfn|Dunstan|2005|p=34}} The roofs were flat and unprotected; he demanded to know if a [[Military glider|glider]], such as the [[DFS 230]], could land on them. Student replied that it could be done, but only by 12 aircraft and in daylight; this would deliver 80–90 paratroopers onto the target.{{sfn|Dunstan|2005|p=34}}
Hitler then revealed the tactical weapon that would make this strategic operation work, introducing the ''Hohlladungwaffe'' (hollow-charge) – a {{convert|50|kg|lb}} explosive weapon which would destroy the Belgian gun emplacements. It was this tactical unit that would spearhead the first strategic airborne operation in history.{{sfn|Dunstan|2005|p=36}}

==Forces involved==
{{Main|Battle of Belgium (1940) order of battle|Order of battle of armour units of the Belgian Army in May 1940}}

===Belgian forces===
[[File:The British Army in France and Belgium 1940 F4444.jpg|thumb|Belgian soldiers resting at the roadside]]
The Belgian Army could muster 22 divisions,{{sfn|Bond|Taylor|2001|p=37}} which contained 1,338 [[artillery]] pieces but just 10 [[AMC 35]] tanks. However, the [[Belgian combat vehicles of World War II|Belgian combat vehicles]] included 200 [[T-13 tank destroyer]]s. These had an excellent 47&amp;nbsp;mm antitank gun and a coaxial [[M1919 Browning machine gun#International variants and derivatives|FN30]] machine gun in a turret. The Belgians also possessed 42 [[T-15 light tank|T-15]]s. They were officially described as armoured cars but were actually fully tracked tanks with a [[13.2 mm Hotchkiss machine gun|13.2&amp;nbsp;mm turret machine gun]]. The standard Belgian anti-tank gun was the [[47 mm Anti-tank Gun Model 1931|47&amp;nbsp;mm FRC]], towed either by trucks or by fully tracked armoured Utilitie B-tractors. One report states that a round from a 47&amp;nbsp;mm gun went straight through a Sd kfz 231 and penetrated the armour of the Panzer IV behind it. These Belgian guns were better than the 25&amp;nbsp;mm and 37&amp;nbsp;mm guns of respectively the French and the Germans.{{sfn|Keegan|2005|p=324}}

The Belgians began mobilisation on 25 August 1939 and by May 1940 mounted a field army of 18 infantry divisions, two divisions of partly motorised ''Chasseurs Ardennais'' and two motorised cavalry divisions, a force totaling some 600,000 men.{{sfn|Keegan|2005|p=95}} Belgian reserves may have been able to field 900,000 men.{{sfn|Fowler|2002|p=12}} The army lacked armour and anti-aircraft guns.{{sfn|Keegan|2005|p=95}}{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=36}}

After the completion of the Belgian Army's mobilisation, it could muster five Regular Corps and two reserve Army Corps consisting of 12 regular infantry divisions, two divisions of ''Chasseurs Ardennais'', six reserve infantry divisions, one [[brigade]] of Cyclist Frontier Guards, one Cavalry Corps of two divisions, and one brigade of motorised cavalry.{{sfn|Belgium, ''Ministère des Affaires Étrangères''|1941|p=32}} The Army contained two anti-aircraft artillery and four artillery regiments, and an unknown number of fortress, engineer, and signals force personnel.{{sfn|Belgium, ''Ministère des Affaires Étrangères''|1941|p=32}}

The [[Belgian Naval Component|Belgian Naval Corps]] (''Corps de Marine'') was resurrected in 1939. Most of the Belgian merchant fleet, some 100 ships, evaded capture by the Germans. Under the terms of a Belgian–Royal Navy agreement, these ships and their 3,350 crewmen were placed under British control for the duration of hostilities.{{sfn|Keegan|2005|p=96}} The General Headquarters of the Belgian Admiralty was at [[Ostend]] under the command of [[Major]] Henry Decarpentrie. The First Naval Division was based at Ostend, while the Second and Third divisions were based at [[Zeebrugge]] and Antwerp.{{sfn|Niehorster, ''Order of Battle: Navy''}}

[[File:Fairey Fox.jpg|thumb|left|A [[Fairey Fox]] of the ''Aéronautique Militaire Belge'']]
The ''Aéronautique Militaire Belge'' (Belgian Air Force - AéMI) had barely begun to modernise their aircraft technology. The AéMI had ordered [[Brewster Buffalo]], [[Fiat CR.42]], and [[Hawker Hurricane]] fighters, [[Koolhoven F.K.56]] trainers, [[Fairey Battle]] and [[Caproni]] Ca.312 light bombers, and Caproni Ca.335 fighter-reconnaissance aircraft, but only the Fiats, Hurricanes, and Battles had been delivered. The shortage of modern types meant single-seat versions of the [[Fairey Fox]] light bomber were being used as fighters.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|pp=48-49}} The AéMI possessed 250 combat aircraft. At least 90 were fighters, 12 were bombers and 12 were reconnaissance aircraft. Only 50 were of reasonably modern standard.{{sfn|Keegan|2005|pp=95, 324}} When liaison and transport aircraft from all services are included, the total strength was 377; however only 118 of these were serviceable on 10 May 1940. Of this number around 78 were fighters and 40 were bombers.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|pp=46-47}}

The AéMI was commanded by Paul Hiernaux, who had received his pilot's license just before the outbreak of [[World War I]], and had risen to the position of Commander-in-Chief in 1938.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|pp=48-49}} Hiernaux organised the service into three ''Régiments d'Aéronautique'' (air regiments): the ''1er'' with 60 aircraft, the ''2ème'' with 53 aircraft, and the ''3ème'' with 79 aircraft.{{sfn|Holleman|Rosseels|Welting|2008}}

===French forces===
[[File:SOMUA-S35-2.jpg|thumb|The [[SOMUA S35]] tank was considered one of the most modern types in French service at the time]]
The Belgians were afforded substantial support by the [[French Army]]. The [[French First Army|French 1st Army]] included General René Prioux's Cavalry Corps. The Corps was given the [[2nd Light Mechanized Division]] (2&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; Division Légère Mécanique, or 2&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM) and the [[3rd Light Mechanized Division]] (3&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM), which were allocated to defend the [[Battle of Gembloux (1940)#French|Gembloux gap]]. The armoured forces consisted of 176 of the formidable [[SOMUA S35]]s and 239 [[Hotchkiss H35]] light tanks. Both of these types, in armour and firepower, were superior to most German types.{{sfn|Healy|2008|p=37}} The 3&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM contained 90 S35s and some 140 H35s alone.{{sfn|Healy|2008|p=37}}

The French 7th Army was assigned to protect the northernmost part of the Allied front. It contained the [[1st Light Mechanized Division]] (1&lt;sup&gt;re&lt;/sup&gt; DLM), the [[25th Motorized Division (France)|25th Motorised Infantry Division]] (25&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; Division d'Infanterie Motorisée, or 25&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DIM) and the [[9th Motorized Division (France)|9th Motorised Infantry Division]] (9&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DIM). This force would advance to [[Breda]] in the Netherlands.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=58}}

The third French army to see action on Belgian soil was the [[French Ninth Army|9th]]. It was weaker than both the 7th and the 1st Armies. The 9th Army was allocated infantry divisions, with the exception of the [[5th Motorized Division (France)|5th Motorised Infantry Division]] (5&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DIM). Its mission was to protect the southern flank of the Allied armies, south of the [[Sambre]] river and just north of [[Sedan, Ardennes|Sedan]]. Further south, in France, was the French 2nd Army, protecting the Franco-Belgian border between Sedan and [[Montmédy]]. The two weakest French armies were thus protecting the area of the main German thrust.&lt;ref&gt;Foot 2005, p. 322. (map of French dispositions is available in Keegan's book)&lt;/ref&gt;

===British forces===
{{see also|British Expeditionary Force order of battle (1940)}}
The British contributed the weakest force to Belgium. The BEF, under the command of General [[John Vereker, 6th Viscount Gort|Lord Gort]] VC, consisted of just 152,000 men in two [[corps]] of two [[Division (military)|divisions]] each. It was hoped to field two armies of two Corps each, but this scale of mobilisation never took place. The [[I Corps (United Kingdom)|I Corps]] was commanded by [[Lieutenant-General (United Kingdom)|Lt-Gen.]] [[John Dill]], later Lt-Gen. [[Michael Barker (British Army officer)|Michael Barker]], who was in turn replaced by [[Major-General]] [[Harold Alexander, 1st Earl Alexander of Tunis|Harold Alexander]]. Lt-Gen. [[Alan Brooke, 1st Viscount Alanbrooke|Alan Brooke]] commanded [[II Corps (United Kingdom)|II Corps]]. Later the [[III Corps (United Kingdom)|III Corps]] under Lt-Gen. [[Sir Ronald Forbes Adam, 2nd Baronet|Ronald Adam]] was added to the British [[order of battle]]. A further 9,392 [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) personnel of the [[RAF Advanced Air Striking Force]] under the command of [[Air Vice-Marshal]] [[Patrick Playfair]] was to support operations in Belgium. By May 1940 the BEF had grown to 394,165 men, of whom more than 150,000 were part of the logistical rear area organisations and had little military training.&lt;ref&gt;Foot 2005, p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt; On 10 May 1940, the BEF comprised just 10 divisions (not all at full strength), 1,280 artillery pieces and 310 tanks.&lt;ref&gt;Foot 2005, p. 324.&lt;/ref&gt;

===German forces===
[[Army Group B]] was commanded by [[Fedor von Bock]]. It was allocated 26 infantry and three Panzer divisions for the invasion of the Netherlands and Belgium.{{sfn|Bond|1975|p=20}} Of the three Panzer Divisions, the [[3rd Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|3rd]] and [[4th Panzer Division|4th]] were to operate in Belgium under the command of the 6th Army's [[XVI Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XVI Corps]]. The [[9th Panzer Division]] was attached to the [[18th Army (Wehrmacht)|18th Army]] which, after the [[Battle of the Netherlands]], would support the push into Belgium alongside the 18th Army and cover its northern flank.{{sfn|Bond|1975|p=20}}

Armour strength in Army Group B amounted to 808 tanks, of which 282 were [[Panzer I]]s, 288 were [[Panzer II]]s, 123 were [[Panzer III]]s and 66 were [[Panzer IV]]s;{{sfn|Healy|2008|p=32}} 49 [[SdKfz 265 Panzerbefehlswagen|command tanks]] were also operational.{{sfn|Healy|2008|p=32}} The 3rd Panzer Division's armoured regiments consisted of 117 Panzer Is, 128 Panzer IIs, 42 Panzer IIIs, 26 Panzer IVs and 27 command tanks.{{sfn|Healy|2008|p=32}} The 4th Panzer Division had 136 Panzer Is, 105 Panzer IIs, 40 Panzer IIIs, 24 Panzer IVs and 10 command tanks.{{sfn|Healy|2008|p=32}} The 9th Panzer, scheduled initially for operations in the Netherlands, was the weakest division with only 30 Panzer Is, 54 Panzer IIs, 123, 66 Panzer IIIs and 49 Panzer IVs.{{sfn|Healy|2008|p=32}}
The elements drawn from the [[7th Air Division (Germany)|7th Air Division]] and the [[22nd Air Landing Division (Wehrmacht)|22nd Airlanding Division]], that were to take part in the attack on Fort Eben-Emael, were named ''[[Sturmabteilung Koch]]'' (Assault Detachment Koch); named after the commanding officer of the group, [[Hauptmann]] [[Walter Koch (Fallschirmjäger)|Walter Koch]].{{sfn|Harclerode|2006|p=51}} The force was assembled in November 1939. It was primarily composed of parachutists from the 1st Parachute Regiment and engineers from the 7th Air Division, as well as a small group of ''Luftwaffe'' pilots.&lt;ref name=Tug52&gt;Tugwell 2006, p. 52.&lt;/ref&gt; The ''Luftwaffe'' allocated 1,815 combat, 487 transport aircraft and 50 gliders for the assault on the Low Countries.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=47}}

The initial air strikes over Belgian air space were to be conducted by ''[[4th Air Corps (Germany)|IV. Fliegerkorps]]'' under ''General der Flieger'' ''[[Generaloberst]]'' [[Alfred Keller]]. Keller's force consisted of ''[[Lehrgeschwader 1]]'' (Stab. I., II., III., IV.), ''[[Kampfgeschwader 30]]'' (Stab. I., II., III.) and ''[[Kampfgeschwader 27]]'' (III.).{{sfn|Hooton|2007|pp=45–46}} On 10 May Keller had 363 aircraft (224 serviceable) augmented by ''[[Generalmajor]]'' [[Wolfram von Richthofen]]'s ''[[8th Air Corps (Germany)|VIII. Fliegerkorps]]'' with 550 (420 serviceable) aircraft. They in turn were supported by ''[[Oberst]]'' [[Kurt-Bertram von Döring]]'s ''[[Jagdfliegerführer 2]]'', with 462 fighters (313 serviceable).{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=48}}

Keller's ''IV. Fliegerkorps'' headquarters would operate from [[Düsseldorf]], LG 1. [[Kampfgeschwader 30|''Kampfgeschwader'' 30]] which was based at [[Oldenburg (city)|Oldenburg]] and its III. Gruppe were based at Marx. Support for Döring and Von Richthofen came from present-day [[North Rhine-Westphalia]] and bases in [[Grevenbroich]], [[Mönchengladbach]], [[Dortmund]] and [[Essen]].{{sfn|Hooton|2007|pp=45–46}}

==Battle==

===''Luftwaffe'' operations: 10 May===
During the evening of 9 May, the Belgian Military attaché in Berlin intimated that the Germans intended to attack the following day. Offensive movement of enemy forces were detected on the border.
At 00:10 on 10 May 1940, at General Headquarters an unspecified squadron in Brussels gave the alarm.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=33}} A full state of alert was instigated at 01:30&amp;nbsp;am.{{sfn|Sebag-Montefiore|2006|pp=50–51}} Belgian forces took up their deployment positions.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=33}} The Allied armies had enacted their Dyle plan on the morning of 10 May, and were approaching the Belgian rear. King Leopold had gone to his Headquarters near Briedgen, Antwerp.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=35}}

The ''Luftwaffe'' was to spearhead the [[Aerial warfare|aerial battle]] in the low countries. Its first task was the elimination of the Belgian air contingent. Despite an overwhelming numerical superiority of 1,375 aircraft, 957 of which were serviceable, the air campaign in Belgium had limited success overall on the first day.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=48}} At roughly 04:00, the first [[Strategic bombing|air raids]] were conducted against airfields and communication centres.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=33}} It still had a tremendous impact on the AéMI, which had only 179 aircraft on 10 May.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=52}}

Much of the success achieved was down to Richthofen's subordinates, particularly [[Kampfgeschwader 77|''Kampfgeschwader'' 77]] and its commander ''[[Oberst]]'' Dr. Johann-Volkmar Fisser whose attachment to ''VIII. Fliegerkorps'', was noted by ''[[Generalmajor]]'' Wilhelm Speidel. He commented it "...was the result of the well-known tendency of the commanding general to conduct his own private war".{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=52}} Fisser's KG 77 destroyed the AéMI main bases, with help from KG 54.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=52}} Fighters from [[Jagdgeschwader 27|''Jagdgeschwader'' 27]] (''JG'' 27) eliminated two Belgian squadrons at Neerhespen, and during the afternoon, I./St.G 2 destroyed nine of the 15 Fiat CR.42 fighters at Brusthem.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=52}} At Schaffen-Diest, three [[Hawker Hurricane]]s of Escadrille 2/I/2 were destroyed and another six damaged when a wave of He 111s caught them as they were about to take off. A further two were lost in destroyed hangars. At Nivelles airfield, 13 CR42s were destroyed.{{sfn|Cull|1999|p=19}} The only other success was KG 27s destruction of eight aircraft at Belesle.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=52}}

In aerial combat the battles were also one-sided. Two He 111s, two Do 17s and three [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]]s were shot down by [[Gloster Gladiator]]s and Hurricanes. In return, eight Belgian Gladiators, five [[Fairey Fox]]s and one CR42 were shot down by JG 1, 21 and 27. [[No. 18 Squadron RAF]] sent two [[Bristol Blenheim]]s on operations over the Belgian front, but lost both to Bf 109s. By the end of the 10 May, the official German figures indicate claims for 30 Belgian aircraft destroyed on the ground, and 14 (plus the two RAF bombers) in the air for 10 losses.{{sfn|Cull|1999|pp=19–20}} The victory claims are likely an undercount. A total of 83 Belgian machines–mostly trainers and "squadron hacks", were destroyed.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=52}} The AéMI flew only 146 sorties in the first six days.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=53}} Between 16 May and 28 May, the AéMI flew just 77 operations.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=53}} It spent most of its time retreating and fuel withdrawing in the face of ''Luftwaffe'' attacks.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=53}}

===10–11 May: The border Battles===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Billd 146-1971-011-27, Belgien, Eben Emael, Fallschirmjäger.jpg|thumb|left|The victors of Eben-Emael: ''Fallschirmjäger'' of [[Walter Koch (Fallschirmjäger)|Sturmabteilung Koch]].]]
The German planners had recognised the need to eliminate Fort Eben-Emael if their army was to break into the interior of Belgium. It decided to deploy airborne forces (''[[Fallschirmjäger]]'') to land inside the fortress perimeter using [[military glider|gliders]].Using special explosives (and [[flamethrower]]s) to disable the defences, the ''Fallschirmjäger'' then entered the fortress. In [[Battle of Fort Eben-Emael|the ensuing battle]], German infantry overcame the defenders of the I Belgian Corps' 7th Infantry Division in 24 hours.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=34}} The main Belgian defence line had been breached and German infantry of the [[18th Army (Wehrmacht)|18th Army]] had passed through it rapidly. Moreover, German soldiers had established bridgeheads across the Albert Canal before the British were able to reach it some 48 hours later. The ''Chasseurs Ardennais'' further south, on the orders of their commander, withdrew behind the Meuse, destroying some bridges in their wake.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=59}} The German airborne forces were assisted by [[Junkers Ju 87]] ''Stukas'' of III./''[[Sturzkampfgeschwader 2|''Sturzkampfgeschwader'' 2]]'' (''StG'' 2) and I./''[[Sturzkampfgeschwader 77]]'' (''StG'' 77) helped suppress the defences. [[Henschel Hs 123]]s of II.(S)./[[Lehrgeschwader 2|''Lehrgeschwader '' 2]] (LG 2) which assisted in the capture of the bridges at Vroenhoven and Veldwezelt in the immediate area.&lt;ref&gt;Cull 1999, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;

Further successful German airborne offensive operations were carried out in Luxembourg which seized five crossings and communication routes leading into central Belgium. The offensive, carried out by 125 volunteers of the 34th Infantry Division under the command of Wenner Hedderich, achieved their missions by flying to their objectives using [[Fieseler Fi 156]] ''Störche''. The cost was the loss of five aircraft and 30 dead.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=54}} With the fort breached, the Belgian 4th and 7th Infantry Divisions were confronted by the prospect of fighting an enemy on relatively sound terrain (for armour operations). The 7th Division, with its 2nd and 18th Grenadier Regiments and 2nd Carabineers, struggled to hold their positions and contain the German infantry on the west bank.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=35}} The Belgian tactical units engaged in several counterattacks. At one point, at Briedgen, they succeeded in retaking the bridge and blowing it up.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=35}} At the other points, Vroenhoven and Veldwezelt, the Germans had had time to establish strong bridgeheads and repulsed the attacks.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=35}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-125-0251-08A, Belgien, Einmarsch deutscher Truppen.jpg|thumb|German soldiers are welcomed into [[Eupen-Malmedy]], a German border region annexed by Belgium in the [[Treaty of Versailles]] (1919)]]
A little known third airborne operation, [[Operation Niwi]], was also conducted on 10 May in southern Belgium. The objectives of this operation was to land two [[companies]] of the 3rd [[battalion]] [[Grossdeutschland Division|Grossdeutschland Infantry Regiment]] by Fi 156 aircraft at [https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nives Nives] and [https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Witry Witry] in the south of the country, in order to clear a path for the [[1st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|1st]] and [[2nd Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|2nd Panzer]] divisions which were advancing through the Belgian–Luxembourg Ardennes. The original plan called for the use of [[Junkers Ju 52]] transport aircraft, but the short landing capability of the Fi 156 (27&amp;nbsp;metres) saw 200 of these aircraft used in the assault. The operational mission was to:

&lt;blockquote&gt;1. Cut signal communications and message links on the [[Neufchâteau, Luxembourg Province|Neufchâteau]]–[[Bastogne]] and Neufchâteau–Martelange roads. [Neufchâteau being the largest southern-most city in Belgium] &lt;br/&gt;
2. Prevent the approach of reserves from the Neufchâteau area&lt;br/&gt;
3. Facilitate the capture of pillboxes and the advance by exerting pressure against the line of pillboxes along the border from the rear.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=123}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The German infantry were engaged by several Belgian patrols equipped with [[Belgian armoured fighting vehicles of World War II|T-15]] armoured cars. Several Belgian counterattacks were repulsed, among them an attack by the 1st Light ''Chasseurs Ardennais'' Division. Unsupported, the Germans faced a counterattack later in the evening by elements of the French 5th Cavalry Division, dispatched by General [[Charles Huntziger]] from the French 2nd Army, which had a significant tank strength. The Germans were forced to retreat. The French, however, failed to pursue the fleeing German units, stopping at a dummy barrier.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|pp=126–127}} By the next morning, the 2nd Panzer Division had reached the area, and the mission had largely been accomplished. From the German perspective, the operation hindered rather than helped [[Heinz Guderian]]'s Panzer Corps.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|pp=126–127}} The regiment had blocked the roads and, against the odds, prevented French reinforcements reaching the Belgian–Franco-Luxembourg border, but it also destroyed Belgian telephone communications.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|pp=126–127}} This inadvertently prevented the Belgian field command recalling the units along the border. The 1st Belgian Light Infantry did not receive the signal to retreat and engaged in a severe fire-fight with the German armour, slowing down their advance.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|pp=126–127}}

The failure of the Franco–Belgian forces to hold the Ardennes gap was fatal. The Belgians had withdrawn laterally upon the initial invasion and had demolished and blocked routes of advance, which held up the French 2nd Army units moving north toward Namur and [[Huy]]. Devoid of any centre of resistance, the German assault engineers had cleared the obstacles unchallenged. The delay that the Belgian Ardennes Light Infantry, considered to be an elite formation, could have inflicted upon the advancing German armour was proved by the fight for Bodange, where the 1st Panzer Division was held up for a total of eight hours. This battle was a result of a breakdown in communications and ran contrary to the operational intentions of the Belgian Army.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|pp=138–139}}

[[File:The British Army in France and Belgium 1940 F4353.jpg|thumb|British troops cross the Franco-Belgian border at [[Mouscron|Herseaux]] on 10 May]]
Meanwhile, in the central Belgian sector, having failed to restore their front by means of ground attack, the Belgians attempted to bomb the bridges and positions that the Germans had captured intact and were holding on 11 May. Belgian [[Fairey Battle]]s of 5/III/3 escorted by six [[Gloster Gladiator]]s attacked the Albert Canal bridges. Bf 109s from I./[[Jagdgeschwader 1 (World War II)|''Jagdgeschwader'' 1]] (''JG'' 1) and I./''JG'' 27 intercepted and ''JG'' 1 shot down four Gladiators and both units destroyed six Battles and heavily damaged the remaining three. Eight CR.42s were evacuated from [[Brustem]] to [[Grimbergen]] near Brussels but seven Gladiators and the last remaining Hurricanes from 2/I/2 ''Escadrille'' were destroyed at [[Beauvechain Air Base]] and [[Le Culot]] by He 111s and I./''JG'' 27 respectively.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=35}}&lt;ref&gt;Cull 1999, p. 61.&lt;/ref&gt; The RAF contributed to the effort to attack the bridges. The British dispatched [[Bristol Blenheim]]s from [[No. 110 Squadron RAF|110]] and [[No. 21 Squadron RAF|21 Squadron]]—the first squadron lost two, one to I./''JG'' 27. 21 Squadron suffered damage to most of the bombers because of intense ground-fire. The French ''[[French Air Force|Armée de l'air]]'' dispatched [[LeO 451]]s from GBI/12 and GBII/12 escorted by 18 [[Morane-Saulnier M.S.406]] of GCIII/3 and GCII/6. The operation failed and one bomber was lost while four M.S.406s fell to I.''JG'' 1. The French claimed five. Meanwhile, [[No. 114 Squadron RAF|114 Squadron]] lost six Blenheims destroyed when [[Dornier Do 17]]s of [[Kampfgeschwader 2|''Kampfgeschwader'' 2]] bombed their airfield at [[Vraux]]. Another Battle of [[No. 150 Squadron RAF]] was lost in another raid.&lt;ref&gt;Cull 1999, pp. 61–62.&lt;/ref&gt;

The German counter-air operations were spearheaded by ''[[Jagdgeschwader 26]]'' (''JG'' 26) under the command of Hans-Hugo Witt, which was responsible for 82 of the German claims in aerial combat between 11 and 13 May.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=56}} Despite the apparent success of the German fighter units, the air battle was not one-sided.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=56}} On the morning of 11 May ten Ju 87s of ''StG'' 2 were shot down attacking Belgian forces in the Namur–Dinant gap, despite the presence of two ''Jagdgeschwader''—''27'' and ''[[Jagdgeschwader 51|51]]''.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=56}} Nevertheless, the Germans reported a weakening in Allied air resistance in northern Belgium by 13 May.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=56}}

During the night of 11 May, the British [[3rd Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|3rd Infantry Division]] under the command of General [[Bernard Montgomery|Bernard Law Montgomery]], reached its position on the Dyle river at [[Leuven]]. As it did so the Belgian [[10th Infantry Division (Belgium)|10th Infantry Division]], occupying the position, mistook them for German parachutists and [[Friendly fire|fired on them]]. The Belgians refused to yield but Montgomery claimed to have got his way by placing himself under the command of the Belgian forces, knowing that when the Germans came within artillery range the Belgians would withdraw.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=58}}

[[Alan Brooke]], commander of the [[II Corps (United Kingdom)|British II Corps]] sought to put the matter of cooperation right with King Leopold. The King discussed the matter with Brooke, who felt a compromise could be reached. Van Overstraeten, the King's military aide, stepped in and said that the 10th Belgian Infantry Division could not be moved. Instead, the British should move further south and remain completely clear of Brussels. Brooke told the King that the 10th Belgian Division was on the wrong side of the Gamelin line and was exposed. Leopold deferred to his advisor and chief of staff. Brooke found Overstaeten to be ignorant of the situation and the dispositions of the BEF. Given that the left flank of the BEF rested on its Belgian ally, the British were now unsure about Belgian military capabilities.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=58}}
The Allies had more serious grounds for complaint about the Belgian anti-tank defences along the Dyle line, that covered the Namur–Perwez gap which was not protected by any natural obstacles.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=58}}{{sfn|Ellis|1993|p=37}} Only a few days before the attack, General Headquarters had discovered the Belgians had sited their anti-tank defences (''de Cointet'' defences) several miles east of the Dyle between Namur–Perwez.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=58}}

After holding onto the Albert Canal's west bank for nearly 36 hours, the 4th and 7th Belgian infantry divisions withdrew. The capture of Eben-Emael allowed the Germans to force through the Panzers of the 6th Army. The situation for the Belgian divisions was either to withdraw or be encircled. The Germans had advanced beyond [[Tongeren]] and were now in a position to sweep south to Namur, which would threaten to envelop the entire Albert Canal and Liège positions. Under the circumstances, both divisions withdrew.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=36}} On the evening of 11 May, the Belgian Command withdrew its forces behind the Namur–Antwerp line. The following day, the French 1st Army arrived at Gembloux, between Wavre and Namur, to cover the "Gembloux gap". It was a flat area, devoid of prepared or entrenched positions.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=36}}

The French 7th Army, on the northern flank of the Belgian line, protected the [[Bruges]]–[[Ghent]]–[[Ostend]] axis and, covering the Channel ports, had advanced into Belgium and into the Netherlands with speed. It reached [[Breda]] in the Netherlands, on 11 May. But German parachute forces had seized the [[Moerdijk]] bridge on the [[Hollands Diep]] river, south of Rotterdam, making it impossible for the French to link up with the [[Dutch Army]]. The Dutch Army withdrew north to [[Rotterdam]] and [[Amsterdam]].{{sfn|Jackson|2003|p=37}}
The French 7th Army turned east and met the 9th Panzer Division about {{convert|20|km}} east of Breda at [[Tilburg]]. The battle resulted in the French retiring, in the face of ''Luftwaffe'' air assaults, to Antwerp. It would later help in the defence of the city.{{sfn|Shepperd|1990|p=38}} The ''Luftwaffe'' had given priority to attacking the French 7th Army's spearhead into the Netherlands as it threatened the Moerdijk bridgehead. [[Kampfgeschwader 40|''Kampfgeschwader'' 40]] and [[Kampfgeschwader 54|''54'']] supported by Ju 87s from ''[[8th Air Corps (Germany)|VIII. Fliegerkorps]]'' helped drive them back.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=51}} Fears of Allied reinforcements reaching Antwerp forced the ''Luftwaffe'' to cover the Scheldt estuary. ''KG 30'' bombed and sank two Dutch gunboats and three Dutch destroyers, as well as badly damaging two Royal Navy destroyers. But overall the bombing had a limited effect.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=51}}

===12–14 May: Battles of the central Belgian plain===
[[File:British troops and Belgian refugees on the Brussels-Louvain road, 12 May 1940. F4422.jpg|thumb|Belgian civilians fleeing westwards away from the advancing German army, 12 May 1940]]

During the night of 11/12 May, the Belgians were fully engaged in withdrawing to the Dyle line, covered by a network of demolitions and rearguards astride Tongeren.
During the morning of 12 May, King Leopold III, General van Overstraeten, [[Édouard Daladier]], General Alphonse Georges (commander of the First Allied army Group, comprising the BEF, French 1st, 2nd, 7th and 9th Armies), General Gaston Billotte (coordinator of the Allied Armies) and General [[Henry Royds Pownall]], Gort's chief of staff, met for a military conference near [[Mons]]. It was agreed the Belgian Army would man the Antwerp–Leuven line, while its allies took up the responsibility of defending the extreme north and south of the country.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|pp=36–37}}

The Belgian III Corps, and its 1st ''Chasseurs Ardennais'', 2nd Infantry and 3rd Infantry Divisions had withdrawn from the [[Fortified Position of Liège|Liège fortifications]] to avoid being encircled. One regiment, the Liège Fortress Regiment, stayed behind to disrupt German communications. Further to the south, the [[Fortified Position of Namur|Namur fortress]], manned by VI Corps' 5th Infantry Division and the 2nd ''Chasseurs Ardennais'' with the 12th French Infantry Division, fought delaying actions and participated in a lot of demolition work while guarding the position.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=37}}
As far as the Belgians were concerned, it had accomplished the only independent mission assigned to it: to hold the Liège–Albert Canal line long enough for the Allied units to reach friendly forces occupying the Namur–Antwerp–Givet line. For the remainder of the campaign, the Belgians would execute their operations in accordance with the overall Allied plan.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=37}}

Belgian soldiers fought rearguard actions while other Belgian units already on the Dyle line worked tirelessly to organise better defensive positions in the Leuven–Antwerp gap. The 2nd Regiment of Guides and the 2nd Carabineers Cyclists of the 2nd Belgian Cavalry Division covered the retreat of the 4th and 7th Belgian divisions and were particularly distinguished at the [[Battle of Tirlemont]] and the Battle of Halen.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=38}}{{sfn|Niehorster, ''Order of Battle, Army''}}

In support of Belgian forces in the area, the RAF and French flew air defence operations in the Tirlemont and Louvain area. The [[RAF Advanced Air Striking Force]] committed [[No. 3 Squadron RAF|3]], [[No. 504 Squadron RAF|504]], [[No. 79 Squadron RAF|79]], [[No. 57 Squadron RAF|57]], [[No. 59 Squadron RAF|59]], [[No. 85 Squadron RAF|85]], [[No. 87 Squadron RAF|87]], [[No. 605 Squadron RAF|605]], and [[No. 242 Squadron RAF|242 squadrons]] to battle. A series of air battles were fought with ''JG'' 1, [[Jagdgeschwader 2|2]], 26, 27 and 3. [[Messerschmitt Bf 110]]s from [[Zerstörergeschwader 26|''Zerstörergeschwader'' 26]] (''ZG'' 26), and bomber units ''LG'' 1, 2 and ''KG'' 27 were also involved.&lt;ref&gt;Cull 1999, pp. 116–121.&lt;/ref&gt; Over Belgium and France, the day was disastrous for the British: 27 Hurricanes were shot down.&lt;ref&gt;Cull 1999, p. 135.&lt;/ref&gt;   
In light of the withdrawal to the main defensive line, which was now being supported by the British and French Armies, King Leopold issued the following proclamation to improve morale after the defeats at the Albert Canal:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Soldiers&lt;br/&gt;
The Belgian Army, brutally assailed by an unparalleled surprise attack, grappling with forces that are better equipped and have the advantage of a formidable air force, has for three days carried out difficult operations, the success of which is of the utmost importance to the general conduct of the battle and to the result of war.&lt;br/&gt;
These operations require from all of us – officers and men – exceptional efforts, sustained day and night, despite a moral tension tested to its limits by the sight of the devastation wrought by a pitiless invader. However severe the trial may be, you will come through it gallantly.&lt;br/&gt;
Our position improves with every hour; our ranks are closing up. In the critical days that are ahead of us, you will summon up all your energies, you will make every sacrifice, to stem the invasion.&lt;br/&gt;
Just as they did [[Battle of the Yser|in 1914 on the Yser]], so now the French and British troops are counting on you: the safety and honour of the country are in your hands.&lt;br/&gt;
Leopold.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=38}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-127-0396-13A, Im Westen, deutsche Panzer.jpg|thumb|German [[Panzer II]] tanks in western Belgium, May 1940]]
To the Allies, the Belgian failure to hold onto its eastern frontiers (they were thought to be capable of holding out for two weeks), was a disappointment. The Allied Chiefs of Staff had sought to avoid an encounter mobile battle without any strong fixed defences to fall back on and hoped Belgian resistance would last long enough for a defensive line to be established.{{sfn|Bond|1990|pp=59–60}} Nevertheless, a brief lull fell on the Dyle front on 11 May which enabled the Allied armies to get into position by the time the first major assault was launched the following day. Allied cavalry had moved into position and infantry and artillery were reaching the front more slowly, by rail. Although unaware of it, the First Allied army Group and the Belgian Army outnumbered and outgunned [[Walther von Reichenau]]'s German 6th Army.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=60}}

On the morning of 12 May, in response to Belgian pressure and necessity, the [[Royal Air Force]] and the ''[[Armée de l'Air]]'' undertook several air attacks on the German-held Maastricht and Meuse bridges to prevent German forces flowing into Belgium. 74 sorties had been flown by the Allies since 10 May. On 12 May, eleven out of eighteen French [[Breguet 693]] bombers were shot down. The [[RAF Advanced Air Striking Force]], which included the largest Allied bomber force, was reduced to 72 aircraft out of 135 by 12 May. For the next 24 hours, missions were postponed as the German anti-aircraft and fighter defences were too strong.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=55}}

The results of the bombing is difficult to determine. The German XIX Corps [[war diary]]'s situation summary at 20:00 on 14 May noted:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The completion of the military bridge at Donchery had not yet been carried out owing to heavy flanking artillery fire and long bombing attacks on the bridging point … Throughout the day all three divisions have had to endure constant air attack — especially at the crossing and bridging points. Our fighter cover is inadequate. Requests [for increased fighter protection] are still unsuccessful.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The ''Luftwaffe's'' operations includes a note of "vigorous enemy fighter activity through which our close reconnaissance in particular is severely impeded". Nevertheless, inadequate protection was given to cover RAF bombers against the strength of German opposition over the target area.{{sfn|Ellis|1993|pp=56–57}} In all, out of 109 [[Fairey Battle]]s and [[Bristol Blenheim]]s which had attacked enemy columns and communications in the Sedan area, 45 had been lost.{{sfn|Ellis|1993|pp=56–57}} On 15 May, daylight bombing was significantly reduced.{{sfn|Ellis|1993|pp=56–57}} Of 23 aircraft employed, four failed to return. Equally, owing to the Allied fighter presence, the German XIX Corps War Diary states, "Corps no longer has at its disposal its own long-range reconnaissance … [Reconnaissance squadrons] are no longer in a position to carry out vigorous, extensive reconnaissance, as, owing to casualties, more than half of their aircraft are not now available."{{sfn|Ellis|1993|pp=56–57}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1971-068-10, Erich Hoepner.jpg|thumb|upright|left|General [[Erich Hoepner]] commanded XVI Army Corps at the [[Battle of Hannut]] and the Gembloux gap offensive]]
The most serious combat to evolve on 12 May 1940 was the beginning of the [[Battle of Hannut]] (12–14 May). While the German [[Army Group A]] advanced through the Belgian Ardennes, [[Army Group B]]'s 6th Army launched an offensive operation toward the Gembloux gap. Gembloux occupied a position in the Belgian plain; it was an unfortified, untrenched space in the main Belgian defensive line.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=240}} The Gap stretched from the southern end of the Dyle line, from [[Wavre]] in the north, to Namur in the south, {{convert|20|km}} to {{convert|30|km}}. After attacking out of the Maastricht bulge and defeating the Belgian defences at Liege, which compelled the [[I Corps (Belgium)|Belgian I Corps]] to retreat, the German 6th Army's XVI Panzer-Motorized Corps, under the command of General [[Erich Hoepner]] and containing the 3rd and 4th Panzer Divisions, launched an offensive in the area where the French mistakenly expected the main German thrust.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=239}}{{sfn|Ellis|1993|pp=37–38}}

The Gembloux gap was defended by the French 1st Army, with six elite divisions including the [[2nd Light Mechanized Division|2nd]] (2e Division Légère Mécanique, or 2&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM) and [[3rd Light Mechanized Division]]s.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=240}} The Prioux Cavalry Corps, under the command of [[René Prioux|Rene-Jacques-Adolphe Prioux]], was to advance {{convert|30|km}} beyond the line (east) to provide a screen for the move. The French 1st and 2nd Armoured Divisions were to be moved behind the French 1st Army to defend its main lines [[strategic depth|in depth]].{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=240}} The Prioux Cavalry Corps was equal to a German Panzer Corps and was to occupy a screening line on the [[Tirlemont]]–[[Hannut]]–[[Huy]] axis. The operational plan called for the Corps to delay the German advance on Gembloux and Hannut until the main elements of the French 1st Army had reached Gembloux and dug in.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=240}}

Hoepner's Panzer Corps and Prioux' Cavalry clashed head-on near Hannut, Belgium, on 12 May. Contrary to popular belief, the Germans did not outnumber the French.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=241}} Frequently, figures of 623 German and 415 French tanks are given.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=241}} The German 3rd and 4th Panzer Divisions numbered 280 and 343 respectively.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=241}} The 2&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM and 3&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM numbered 176 [[Somua S-35|Somuas]] and 239 [[Hotchkiss H35]]s.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=241}} Added to this force were the considerable number of [[Renault R35|Renault AMR-ZT-63s]] in the Cavalry Corps. The R35 was equal or superior to the [[Panzer I]] and [[Panzer II]]s in armament terms.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=241}} This applies all the more to the 90 [[Panhard 178]] armoured cars of the French Army. Its 25mm main gun could penetrate the armour of the [[Panzer IV]]. In terms of tanks that were capable of engaging and surviving a tank-vs-tank action, the Germans possessed just 73 Panzer IIIs and 52 Panzer IVs.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=241}} The French had 176 SOMUA and 239 Hotchkisses.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=241}} German tank units also contained 486 Panzer I and IIs, which were of dubious combat value given their losses in the [[Polish Campaign]].{{sfn|Healy|2008|p=37}}

The German forces were able to communicate by radio during the battle and they could shift the point of the main effort unexpectedly. The Germans also practiced [[combined arms]] tactics, while the French tactical deployment was a rigid and linear leftover from the First World War. French tanks did not possess radios and often the commanders had to dismount to issue orders.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=242}} Despite the disadvantages experienced by the Germans in armour, they were able to gain the upper hand in the morning battle on 12 May, encircling several French battalions. The combat power of the French 2&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM managed to defeat the German defences guarding the pockets and freeing the trapped units.{{sfn|Gunsburg|1992|pp=221–224}} Contrary to German reports, the French were victorious on that first day, preventing a Wehrmacht break-through to Gembloux or seizing Hannut.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=242}} The result of the first day's battle was:
&lt;blockquote&gt;The effect on the German light tanks was catastrophic. Virtually every French weapon from 25mm upward penetrated the 7-13mm of the Panzer I. Although the Panzer II fared somewhat better, especially those that had been up-armoured since the Polish Campaign, their losses were high. Such was the sheer frustration of the crews of these light Panzers in [the] face of heavier armoured French machines that some resorted to desperate expedients. One account speaks of a German Panzer commander attempting to climb on a Hotchkiss H-35 with a hammer, presumably to smash the machine's periscopes, but falling off and being crushed by the tank's tracks. Certainly by day's end, Prioux had reason to claim that his tanks had come off best. The battlefield around Hannut was littered with knocked-out tanks–the bulk of which were German Panzers–with by far and away the bulk of them being Panzer Is and IIs.{{sfn|Healy|2008|pp=37–38}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-127-0362-14, Belgien, belgischer Panzer T13.jpg|thumb|German soldiers inspect an abandoned Belgian [[T-13 tank destroyer]]]]
The following day, 13 May, the French were undone by their poor tactical deployment. They strung their armour out in a thin line between Hannut and Huy, leaving no defence in depth, which was the point of sending the French armour to the Gembloux gap in the first place. This left Hoepner with a chance to mass against one of the French Light Divisions (the 3&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM) and achieve a breakthrough in that sector. Moreover, with no reserves behind the front, the French denied themselves the chance of a counterattack. The victory saw the Panzer Corps out-manoeuvre the 2&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM on its left flank.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=242}} The [[Belgian III Corps]], retreating from Liege, offered to support the French front held by the 3&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM. This offer was rejected.{{sfn|Gunsburg|1992|p=228}}

On 12 and 13 May, 2&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM lost no AFVs, but the 3&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; DLM lost 30 SOMUAs and 75 Hotchkisses. The French had disabled 160 German tanks.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=243}} But as the poor linear deployment had allowed the Germans the chance of breaking through in one spot, the entire battlefield had to be abandoned,{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=243}} the Germans repaired nearly three quarters of their tanks; 49 were destroyed and 111 were repaired. They had 60 men killed and another 80 wounded.{{sfn|Gunsburg|1992|p=237}} In terms of battlefield casualties, the Hannut battle had resulted in the French knocking-out 160 German tanks, losing 105 themselves. Prioux had achieved his tactical mission and withdrew.{{sfn|Healy|2008|p=38}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-382-0201-09, Belgien, Beaumont, Häuserruinen.jpg|thumb|Destroyed French tanks in [[Beaumont, Belgium|Beaumont]] on 16 May]]
Hoepner now pursued the retreating French. Being impatient, he did not wait for his infantry divisions to catch up. Instead, he hoped to continue pushing the French back and not give them time to construct a coherent defence line. German formations pursued the enemy to Gembloux. The Panzer Corps ran into retreating French columns and inflicted heavy losses on them. The pursuit created severe problems for the French artillery. The combat was so closely fought that the danger of friendly fire incidents were very real. Nevertheless, the French, setting up new anti-tank screens and Hoepner, lacking infantry support, caused the Germans to attack positions head-on. During the following [[Battle of Gembloux (1940)|Battle of Gembloux]] the two Panzer Divisions reported heavy losses during 14 May and were forced to slow their pursuit. The German attempts to capture Gembloux were repulsed.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|pp=243–244}}

Although suffering numerous tactical reverses, operationally the Germans diverted the Allied First Army Group from the lower Ardennes area. In the process his forces, along with the ''Luftwaffe'' depleted Prioux' Cavalry Corps. When news of the German breakthrough at [[Battle of Sedan (1940)|Sedan]] reached Prioux, he withdrew from Gembloux. With the Gembloux gap breached, the German Panzer Corps, the 3rd and 4th Panzer Divisions, were no longer required by Army Group B and were handed over to Army Group A. Army Group B would continue its own offensive to force the collapse of the Meuse front. The Army Group was in a position to advance westward to [[Mons]], outflank the BEF and Belgian Army protecting the Dyle–Brussels sector, or turn south to outflank the French 9th Army.
German losses had been heavy at Hannut and Gembloux.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=246}} The 4th Panzer Division was down to 137 tanks on 16 May, including just four Panzer IVs. The 3rd Panzer Division was down by 20–25 percent of its operational force, while the 4th Panzer Division 45–50 percent of its tanks were not combat ready.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=246}} Damaged tanks were quickly repaired, but its strength was initially greatly weakened.{{sfn|Frieser|Greenwood|2005|p=246}}
The French 1st Army had also taken a battering and despite winning several tactical defensive victories it was forced to retreat on 15 May owing to developments elsewhere, leaving its tanks on the battlefield, while the Germans were free to recover theirs.{{sfn|Sebag-Montefiore|2006|p=71}}

===15–21 May: Counterattacks and retreat to the coast===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-127-0391-21, Im Westen, deutsche Soldaten mit getarnter Pak.jpg|thumb|left|German infantry with a [[3.7 cm Pak 36|Pak 36]] anti-tank gun in western Belgium in May 1940.]]
On the morning of 15 May, German Army Group A [[Battle of Sedan (1940)|broke the defences at Sedan]] and was now free to drive for the [[English Channel]]. The Allies considered a wholesale withdrawal from the Belgian trap. The withdrawal would reflect three stages: the night of 16/17 May to the River [[Zenne|Senne]], the night of 17/18 May to the river [[Dendre]] and the night of 18/19 May to the river [[Scheldt]].{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=64}}{{sfn|Ellis|2004|p=59}} The Belgians were reluctant to abandon Brussels and Leuven, especially as the Dyle line had withstood German pressure well.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=64}}
The Belgian Army, the BEF and the French 1st Army, in a domino effect, was ordered/forced to retire on 16 May to avoid their southern flanks from being turned by the German armoured forces advancing through the French Ardennes and the German 6th Army advancing through Gembloux. The Belgian Army was holding the German Fourteenth Army on the [[KW-line]], along with the French 7th and British armies. Had it not been for the collapse of the French 2nd Army at Sedan, the Belgians were confident that they could have checked the German advance.{{sfn|Belgian American Educational Foundation|1941|p=30}}

The situation called for the French and British to abandon the Antwerp–Namur line and strong positions in favour of improvised positions behind the Scheldt, without facing any real resistance.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=39}} In the South, General Deffontaine of the [[Belgian VII Corps]] retreated from the Namur and Liège regions,{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=39}} the Liège fortress region put up stiff resistance to the German 6th Army.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=40}} In the North, the 7th Army was diverted to Antwerp after the surrender of the Dutch on 15 May, but was then diverted to support the French 1st Army.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=39}} In the centre, the Belgian Army and the BEF suffered little German pressure. On 15 May, the only sector to really be tested was around Leuven, which was held by the British 3rd Division. The BEF was not pursued vigorously to the Scheldt.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=64}}

After the withdrawal of the French Army from the northern sector, the Belgians were left to guard the fortified city of Antwerp. Four infantry divisions (including the [[Belgian 13th Reserve Infantry Division|13th]] and [[Belgian 17th Reserve Infantry Division|17th Reserve Infantry Divisions]]) engaged the German Eighteenth Army's [[208th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|208th]], [[225th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|225th]] and [[526th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|526th Infantry Divisions]].{{sfn|Bloock|2003}} The Belgians successfully defended the northern part of the city, delaying the German infantry forces while starting to withdraw from Antwerp on 16 May. The city fell on 18/19 May after considerable Belgian resistance. On 18 May the Belgians received word that Namur's Fort [[Marchovelette]] had fallen; Suarlee fell on 19 May; St. Heribert and Malonne on 21 May; Dave, Maizeret and Andoy on 23 May.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=40}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1971-040-60, Belgien, Antwerpen, belg. Pzkpfw..jpg|thumb|upright|A Belgian [[AMC 35|Renault ACG1 tank]], knocked out during the Battle for Antwerp, 19 May 1940]]
Between 16 and 17 May, the British and French withdrew behind the [[Willebroek Canal]], as the volume of Allied forces in Belgium fell and moved toward the German armoured thrust from the Ardennes. The Belgian [[I Corps (Belgium)|I Corps]] and [[V Corps (Belgium)|V Corps]] also retreated to what the Belgians called the [[Ghent]] bridgehead, behind the [[Dendre]] and [[Scheldt]]. The Belgian [[Artillery Corps]] and its infantry support defeated attacks by the Eighteenth Army's infantry and in a communiqué from London, the British recognized the "Belgian Army has contributed largely toward the success of the defensive battle now being fought.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=40}}
Nevertheless, the now-outnumbered Belgians abandoned [[Brussels]] and the Government fled to Ostend. The city was occupied by the German Army on 17 May. The very next morning, Hoepner, the German XVI Corps commander, was ordered to release the 3rd and 4th Panzer Divisions to [[Army Group A]].{{sfn|Sebag-Montefiore|2006|pp=70–71}} This left the 9th Panzer Division attached to the Eighteenth Army as the only armoured unit on the Belgian front.

By 19 May, the Germans were hours away from reaching the French Channel coast. Gort had discovered the French had neither plan nor reserves and little hope for stopping the German thrust to the channel. He was concerned that the French 1st Army on its southern flank had been reduced to a disorganized mass of "[[Cigarette filter|fag-ends]]", fearing that German armour might appear on their right flank at [[Arras, France|Arras]] or [[Péronne, Somme|Péronne]], striking for the channel ports at [[Calais]] or [[Boulogne]] or north west into the British flank. Their position in Belgium massively compromised, the BEF considered abandoning Belgium and retreating to [[Ostend]], [[Bruges]] or [[Dunkirk]], the latter lying some {{convert|10|km}} to {{convert|15|km}} inside the French border.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=67}}

The proposals of a British strategic withdrawal from the continent was rejected by the [[War Cabinet]] and the [[Chief of the Imperial General Staff]] (CIGS). They dispatched [[Edmund Ironside, 1st Baron Ironside|General Ironside]] to inform Gort of their decision and to order him to conduct an offensive to the south-west "through all opposition" to reach the "main French forces" in the south [the strongest French forces were actually in the north]. The Belgian Army was asked to conform to the plan, or should they choose, the British Royal Navy would evacuate what units they could.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=67}} The British cabinet decided that even if the "Somme offensive" was carried out successfully, some units may still need to be evacuated, and ordered Admiral Ramsay to assemble a large number of vessels. This was the beginning of [[Operation Dynamo]].{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=67}}
Ironside arrived at British General Headquarters at 06:00&amp;nbsp;am on 20 May, the same day that continental communications between France and Belgium was cut.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=69}} When Ironside made his proposals known to Gort, Gort replied such an attack was impossible. Seven of his nine divisions were engaged on the Scheldt and even if it was possible to withdraw them, it would create a gap between the Belgians and British which the enemy could exploit and encircle the former. The BEF had been marching and fighting for nine days and was now running short of ammunition.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=69}} The main effort had to be made by the French to the south.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=69}}

[[File:16May-21May Battle of Belgium.PNG|thumb|left|Strategic situation in Belgium and France on 21 May]]
The Belgian position on any offensive move was made clear by Leopold III. As far as he was concerned, the Belgian Army could not conduct offensive operations as it lacked tanks and aircraft; it existed solely for defence.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=70}}{{sfn|Ellis|2004|p=105}} The King also made clear that in the rapidly shrinking area of Belgium still free, there was only enough food for two weeks.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=70}} Leopold did not expect the BEF to jeopardize its own position in order to keep contact with the Belgian Army, but he warned the British that if it persisted with the southern offensive the Belgians would be overstretched and their army would collapse.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=70}}{{sfn|Ellis|2004|p=105}} King Leopold suggested the best recourse was to establish a beach-head covering Dunkirk and the Belgian channel ports.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=70}} The will of the CIGS won out. Gort committed just two infantry battalions and the only armoured battalion in the BEF to the attack, which despite some initial tactical success, failed to break the German defensive line at the [[Battle of Arras (1940)|Battle of Arras]] on 21 May.{{sfn|Bond|1990|pp=71–72}}

In the aftermath of this failure, the Belgians were asked to fall back to the [[Yser]] river and protect the Allied left flank and rear areas. The King's aide, General Overstraten said that such a move could not be made and would lead to the Belgian Army disintegrating. Another plan for further offensives was suggested. The French requested the Belgians withdraw to the [[Leie]] and the British to the French frontier between [[Maulde]] and [[Halluin]], the Belgians were then to extend their front to free further parts of the BEF for the attack. The French 1st Army would relieve two more divisions on the right flank. Leopold was reluctant to undertake such a move because it would abandon all but a small portion of Belgium. The Belgian Army was exhausted and it was an enormous technical task that would take too long to complete.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=72}}

At this time, the Belgians and the British concluded that the French were beaten and the Allied Armies in the pocket on the Belgian–Franco border would be destroyed if action was not taken. The British, having lost confidence in their Allies, decided to look to the survival of the BEF.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=73}}

===22–28 May: Last defensive battles===
[[File:21May-6June Battle of Belgium.PNG|thumb|The Germans advance to the English Channel after 21 May]]

The Belgian battle-front on the morning of 22 May extended some {{convert|90|km}} from north to south, beginning with the [[Belgian Cavalry Corps|Cavalry Corps]], which checked its advance at [[Terneuzen]]. [[Belgian V Corps|V]], [[Belgian II Corps|II]], [[Belgian VI Corps|VI]], [[Belgian VII Corps|VII]] and [[Belgian IV Corps|IV Corps]] (all Belgian) were drawn up side by side. Two further signal Corps were guarding the coast.{{sfn|Belgian American Educational Foundation|1941|p=54}} These formations were then largely holding the eastern front as the BEF and French forces withdrew to the west to protect Dunkirk, which was vulnerable to German assault on 22 May. The eastern front remained intact, but the Belgians now occupied their last fortified position at Leie.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=75}} The [[I Corps (Belgium)|Belgian I Corps]], with only two incomplete divisions, had been heavily engaged in the fighting and their line was wearing thin. On that day, [[Winston Churchill]] visited the front and pressed for the French and British Armies to break out from the north-east. He assumed that the Belgian Cavalry Corps could support the offensives' right flank. Churchill dispatched the following message to Gort:
&lt;blockquote&gt;1. That the Belgian Army should withdraw to the line of the Yser and stand there, the sluices being opened.&lt;br/&gt;
2. That the British Army and French 1st Army should attack south-west toward Bapaume and Cambrai at the earliest moment, certainly tomorrow, with about eight divisions, and with the Belgian Cavalry Corps on the right of the British.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=76}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Such an order ignored the fact that the Belgian Army could not withdraw to the Yser, and there was little chance of any Belgian Cavalry joining in the attack.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=76}} The plan for the Belgian withdrawal was sound; the Yser river covered Dunkirk to the east and south, while the La Bassée Canal covered it from the west. The ring of the Yser also dramatically shorted the Belgian Army's area of operations. Such a move would have abandoned [[Passchendaele Ridge|Passchendaele]] and [[Ypres]] and would have certainly meant the capture of Ostend while further reducing the amount of Belgian territory still free by a few square miles.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=78}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1985-037-23A, Belgien, Albertkanal, Flüchtlinge.jpg|left|thumb|German troops watch Belgian civilian refugees fleeing the fighting]]
On 23 May, the French tried to conduct a series of offensives against the German defensive line on the Ardennes–Calais axis but failed to make any meaningful gains. Meanwhile, on the Belgian front, the Belgians, under pressure, retreated further, and the Germans captured Terneuzen and Ghent that day. The Belgians also had trouble moving the oil, food and ammunition that they had left.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=43}} The ''Luftwaffe'' had air superiority and made everyday life hazardous in [[Military logistics|logistical]] terms. Air support could only be called in by "wireless" and the RAF was operating from bases in southern England which made communication more difficult.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=43}} The French denied the use of the Dunkirk, [[Bourbourg]] and [[Gravelines]] bases to the Belgians, which had initially been placed at its disposal. The Belgians were forced to use the only harbours left to them, at [[Nieuport]] and Ostend.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=43}}

Churchill and [[Maxime Weygand]], who had taken over command from Gamelin, were still determined to break the German line and extricate their forces to the south. When they communicated their intentions to King Leopold and van Overstraten on 24 May, the latter was stunned.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=84}} A dangerous gap was starting to open between the British and Belgians between Ypres and [[Menen]], which threatened what remained of the Belgian front.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=84}} The Belgians could not cover it; such a move would have overstretched them. Without consulting the French or asking permission from his government, Gort immediately and decisively ordered the British [[5th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|5th]] and [[50th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|50th Infantry Divisions]] to plug the gap and abandon any offensive operations further south.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=84}}{{sfn|Ellis|1993|p=172}}

On the afternoon of 24 May, [[Fedor von Bock|von Bock]] had thrown four divisions, of Reichenau's 6th Army, against the [[Belgian IV Corps]] position at the [[Kortrijk]] area of the Leie during the [[Battle of the Lys (1940)]]. The Germans managed, against fierce resistance, to cross the river at night and force a one-mile penetration along a 13-mile front between [[Wervik]] and Kortrijk. The Germans, with superior numbers and in command of the air, had won the bridgehead.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=84}} Nevertheless, the Belgians had inflicted many casualties and several tactical defeats on the Germans. The [[Belgian 1st Infantry Division|1st]], [[Belgian 3rd Infantry Division|3rd]], [[Belgian 9th Infantry Division|9th]] and [[Belgian 10th Infantry Division|10th Infantry Divisions]], acting as reinforcements, had counterattacked several times and managed to capture 200 German prisoners.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=44}} Belgian artillery and infantry were then heavily attacked by the ''Luftwaffe'', which forced their defeat. The Belgians blamed the French and British for not providing air cover.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=44}} The German bridgehead dangerously exposed the eastern flank of the southward stretched BEF's 4th Infantry Division. Montgomery dispatched several units of the 3rd Infantry Division (including the heavy infantry of the 1st and 7th Middlesex battalions and the 99th Battery, 20th Anti-Tank Regiment), as an improvised defence.{{sfn|Ellis|2004|pp=135–136}}

A critical point of the "Weygand Plan" and the British government and French Army's argument for a thrust south, was the withdrawal of forces to see the offensive through which had left the Belgian Army over-extended and was instrumental in its collapse. It was forced to cover the areas held by the BEF in order to enable the latter to engage in the offensive.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=84}} Such a collapse could have resulted in the loss of the Channel ports behind the Allied front, leading to a complete strategic encirclement. The BEF could have done more to counterattack von Bock's left flank to relieve the Belgians as von Bock attacked ''across'' the fortified British position at Kortrijk.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=85}} The Belgian High Command made at least five appeals for the British to attack the vulnerable left flank of the German divisions between the [[Scheldt]] and the [[Leie]] to avert disaster.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=85}}

[[Roger Keyes, 1st Baron Keyes|Admiral Sir Roger Keyes]] transmitted the following message to GHQ:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Van Overstraten is desperately keen for strong British counterattack. Either north or south of Leie could help restore the situation. Belgians expect to be attacked on the Ghent front tomorrow. Germans already have a bridgehead over canal west of Eecloo. There can be no question of the Belgian withdrawal to Yser. One battalion on march NE of Ypres was practically wiped out today in attack by sixty aircraft. Withdrawal over open roads without adequate fighter support very costly. Whole of their supplies are east of Yser. They strongly represent attempt should be made to restore the situation on Leie by British counter-attack for which opportunity may last another few hours only.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=86}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

No such attack came. The Germans brought fresh reserves to cover the gap (Menen–Ypres). This nearly cut the Belgians off from the British. The [[Belgian 2nd Infantry Division|2nd]], [[Belgian 6th Infantry Division|6th]] and [[Belgian 9th Infantry Division|10th Cavalry Divisions]] frustrated German attempts to exploit the gap in depth but the situation was still critical.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|p=44}}
On 26 May, Operation Dynamo officially commenced, in which large French and British contingents were to be evacuated to the United Kingdom. By that time, the Royal Navy had already withdrawn 28,000 British non-fighting troops. Boulogne had fallen and Calais was about to, leaving Dunkirk, Ostend and Zeebrugge as the only viable ports which could be used for evacuation. The advance of the 14th German Army would not leave Ostend available for much longer. To the west, the German [[Army Group A]] had reached Dunkirk and were {{convert|4|mi}} from its centre on the morning of 27 May, bringing the port within artillery range.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=88}}

The situation on 27 May had changed considerably from just 24 hours earlier. The Belgian Army had been forced from the Leie line on 26 May, and [[Nevele]], [[Vynckt]], [[Tielt]] and [[Iseghem]] had fallen on the western and central part of the Leie front. In the east, the Germans had reached the outskirts of Bruges, and captured [[Ursel Airfield|Ursel]]. In the west, the Menen–Ypres line had broken at Kortrijk and the Belgians were now using railway trucks to help form anti-tank defences on a line from Ypres–Passchendaele–[[Roulers]]. Further to the west the BEF had been forced back, north of [[Lille]] just over the French border and was now in danger of allowing a gap to develop between themselves and the Belgian southern flank on the Ypres–Lille axis.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|pp=44–45}} The danger in allowing a German advance to Dunkirk would mean the loss of the port which was now too great. The British withdrew to the port on 26 May. In doing so, they left the French 1st Army's north-eastern flank near Lille exposed. As the British moved out, the Germans moved in, encircling the bulk of the French Army. Both Gort and his Chief of Staff, General [[Henry Pownall]], accepted that their withdrawal would mean the destruction of the French 1st Army, and they would be blamed for it.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=89}}

The fighting of 26–27 May had brought the Belgian Army to the brink of collapse. The Belgians still held the Ypres–Roulers line to the west, and the Bruges–Thelt line to the east. However, on 27 May, the central front collapsed in the Iseghem–Thelt sector. There was now nothing to prevent a German thrust to the east to take Ostend and Bruges, or west to take the ports at Nieuport or [[La Panne]], deep in the Allied rear.{{sfn|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941|pp=44–45}} The Belgians had practically exhausted all available means of resistance. The disintegration of the Belgian Army and its front caused many erroneous accusations by the British.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=92}} In fact, on numerous occasions, the Belgians had held on after British withdrawals.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=92}} One example was the taking over of the Scheldt line, where they relieved the British [[4th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|44th Infantry Division]], allowing it to retire through their ranks.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=92}} Despite this, Gort and to a greater extent Pownall, showed anger at the Belgian King's decision to surrender on 28 May, considering it undercut the war effort. .{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=92}} When it was inquired if any Belgians were to be evacuated, Pownall was reported to have replied, "We don't care a bugger what happens to the Belgians".{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=92}}

===Belgian surrender===
[[File:Belgische Propaganda Poster Van Koning Leopold III met opschrifft "28 Mei 1940, Halt, Sire Dat Vergeten Wij Nooit" naar aanleiding van de 18 daagse veldtocht.jpg|thumb|Belgian Propaganda Poster from King Leopold III with title "28 May 1940, Halt, Sire We will never forget this" in response to the Battle Of Belgium.]]
{{see also|German occupation of Belgium during World War II}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1974-061-61, Belgien, Kapitulation der belg. Armee.jpg|thumb|Negotiating the Belgian capitulation]]

The Belgian Army was stretched from [[Cadzand]] south to [[Menen]] on the river Leie, and west, from Menin, to Bruges without any sort of reserves. With the exception of a few RAF sorties, the air was exclusively under the control of the ''Luftwaffe'', and the Belgians reported attacks against all targets considered an objective, with resulting casualties. No natural obstacles remained between the Belgians and the German Army; retreat was not feasible. The ''Luftwaffe'' had destroyed most of the rail networks to Dunkirk, just three roads were left: Bruges–[[Torhout]]–[[Dixmude]], Bruges–[[Ghistelles]]–Nieuport and Bruges–Ostend–Nieuport. Using such axes of retreat was impossible without losses owing to German [[air supremacy]] (as opposed to [[air superiority]]). Water supplies were damaged and cut off, gas and electricity supplies were also cut. Canals were drained and used as supply dumps for whatever ammunition and food-stuffs were left. The total remaining area covered just 1,700&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, and compacted military and civilians alike, of which the latter numbered some 3&amp;nbsp;million people.{{sfn|Belgian American Educational Foundation|1941|p=60}} Under these circumstances Leopold deemed further resistance useless. On the evening of 27 May, he requested an armistice.{{sfn|Shirer|1990|p=729}}

Churchill sent a message to Keyes the same day, and made clear what he thought of the request:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Belgian Embassy here assumes from King's decision to remain that he regards the war as lost and contemplates [a] separate peace. It is in order to dissociate itself from this that the constitutional Belgian Government has reassembled on foreign soil. Even if present Belgian Army has to lay down its arms, there are 200,000 Belgians of military age in France, and greater resources than Belgium had in 1914 which to fight back. By present decision the King is dividing the Nation and delivering it into Hitler's protection. Please convey these considerations to the King, and impress upon him the disastrous consequences to the Allies and to Belgium of his present choice.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=93}} &lt;/blockquote&gt;

The Royal Navy evacuated General Headquarters at [[Middelkerke]] and [[Sint-Andries]], east of Bruges, during the night. Leopold III, and his mother [[Elisabeth of Bavaria (1876–1965)|Queen Mother Elisabeth]], stayed in Belgium to endure five years of self-imposed captivity.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=93}} In response to the advice of his government to set up a government-in-exile Leopold said, "I have decided to stay. The cause of the Allies is lost."{{sfn|Shirer|1990|p=729}}
The Belgian surrender came into effect at 04:00 on 28 May. Recriminations abounded with the British and French claiming the Belgians had betrayed the alliance. In Paris, the French Premier [[Paul Reynaud]] denounced Leopold's surrender, and the Belgian Premier [[Hubert Pierlot]] informed the people that Leopold had taken action against the unanimous advice of the government. As a result, the king was no longer in a position to govern and the [[Belgian government in exile]] that was located in Paris (later moved to London following the fall of France) would continue the struggle.{{sfn|Shirer|1990|p=729}} The chief complaint was that the Belgians had not given any prior warning that their situation was so serious as to capitulate. Such claims were largely unjust. The Allies had known, and admitted it privately on 25 May through contact with the Belgians, that the latter were on the verge of collapse.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=94}}{{sfn|Sebag-Montefiore|2006|p=304}}

Churchill's and the British response was officially restrained. This was due to the strong-willed defence of the Belgian defensive campaign presented to the cabinet by Sir Roger Keyes at 11:30&amp;nbsp;am 28 May.{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=95}} The French and Belgian ministers had referred to Leopold's actions as treacherous, but they were unaware of the true events: Leopold had not signed an agreement with Hitler in order to form a collaborative government, but an unconditional surrender as Commander-in-Chief of the [[Belgian Armed Forces]].{{sfn|Bond|1990|p=96}}

==Casualties==

The casualty reports include total losses at this point in the campaign. The figures for the Battle of Belgium, 10–28 May 1940, cannot be known with any certainty.

===Belgian===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1970-048-11, Belgien, Brügge, Entwaffnung.jpg|thumb|German soldiers pile up Belgian weapons in Bruges after the surrender]]
Belgian casualties stood at:
* Killed in action: 6,093 and 2,000 [[Belgian prisoners of war in World War II|Belgian prisoners]] died in captivity{{sfn|Keegan|2005|p=96}}
* Missing: more than 500{{sfn|Keegan|2005|p=96}}
* Captured: 200,000{{sfn|Ellis|1993|p=255}}
* Wounded: 15,850{{sfn|Ellis|1993|p=255}}
* Aircraft: 112 destroyed{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=52}}

===French===
Numbers for the Battle of Belgium are unknown, but the French suffered the following losses throughout the entire western campaign, 10 May – 22 June:
* Killed in action: 90,000{{sfn|Keegan|2005|p=326}}
* Wounded: 200,000{{sfn|Keegan|2005|p=326}}
* Prisoners of War: 1,900,000.{{sfn|Keegan|2005|p=326}}
* Total French losses in aircraft numbered 264 from 12 to 25 May, and 50 for 26 May to 1 June.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=57}}

===British===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-125-0277-09, Im Westen, zerstörter französischer Panzer Char B1.jpg|thumb|A destroyed French heavy [[Char B1]] in [[Beaumont, Belgium|Beaumont]]]]
Numbers for the Battle of Belgium are unknown, but the British suffered the following losses throughout the entire campaign, 10 May – 22 June:
* 68,111 killed in action, wounded or captured.{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=130}}
* 64,000 vehicles destroyed or abandoned{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=130}}
* 2,472 guns destroyed or abandoned{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=130}}
* RAF losses throughout the entire campaign (10 May – 22 June) amounted to 931 aircraft and 1,526 casualties. Casualties to 28 May are unknown.{{sfn|Holmes|2001|p=130}} Total British losses in the air numbered 344 between 12 and 25 May, and 138 between 26 May and 1 June.{{sfn|Hooton|2007|p=57}}

===German===
The consolidated report of the ''[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]'' regarding the operations in the west from 10 May to 4 June (German: ''Zusammenfassender Bericht des Oberkommandos der Wehrmacht über die Operationen im Westen vom 10. Mai bis 4. Juni'') reports:{{sfn|Oberkommando der Wehrmacht|1941|p=189}}
* Killed in action: 10,232 officers and soldiers{{sfn|Oberkommando der Wehrmacht|1941|p=189}}
* Missing: 8,463 officers and soldiers{{sfn|Oberkommando der Wehrmacht|1941|p=189}}
* Wounded: 42,523 officers and soldiers{{sfn|Oberkommando der Wehrmacht|1941|p=189}}
* Losses of the ''Luftwaffe'' from 10 May to 3 June: 432 aircraft{{sfn|Oberkommando der Wehrmacht|1941|p=189}}
* Losses of the Kriegsmarine: none{{sfn|Oberkommando der Wehrmacht|1941|p=189}}

==See also==
{{Portal|Belgium|World War II}}
* [[German invasion of Luxembourg in World War II|German invasion of Luxembourg]]
* [[Mechelen incident]]

==References==

===Notes===
{{notelist
| notes =
{{efn
| name = Divisions
| The Belgian Army consisted of 22 divisions, the French provided 104, the British provided 10, and the Dutch 8 divisions. {{harvnb|Holmes|2001|p=324}}.
}}
{{efn
| name = Netherlands
|Contributed lightly armed infantry units retreating from Dutch territory. Also committed the Dutch Air Force on few, ineffective and costly missions. {{harvnb|Gunsburg|1992|p=216}}.
}}
{{efn
| name = Guns
| The Belgian Army had 1,338 guns, the French 10,700, the British 1,280, and the Dutch 656. {{harvnb|Holmes|2001|p=324}}.
}}
{{efn
| name = tanks
| The Belgian Army had 10 tanks, the French 3,063, the British 310 and the Dutch 1 tank. {{harvnb|Holmes|2001|p=324}}.
}}
{{efn
| name = Aircraft
| The Belgian Air Force consisted of 250 aircraft, the French Air Force 1,368, the British Royal Air Force provided 456 aircraft and the Dutch Air Force 175. {{harvnb|Holmes|2001|p=324}}.
}}
{{efn
| name = Men lost
| The Belgian Army sustained 6,093 men killed, 15,850 men wounded in action, more than 500 men missing and 200,000 men captured, of which 2,000 died in captivity. {{harvnb|Keegan|2005|p=96}}; {{harvnb|Ellis|1993|p=255}}. French and British losses on Belgian territory are unknown. {{harvnb|Keegan|2005|p=96}}.
}}
{{efn
| name = Aircraft lost
| The Belgian Air Force lost 83 planes on the ground on 10 May, 25 lost in aerial combat between 10–15 May, and four lost in the air between 16–28 May. {{harvnb|Hooton|2007|pp=49, 52, 53}}.  French and British losses are not certain, however the French Air Force lost 264 aircraft between 12–25 May and 50 for 26 May – 1 June while the British Royal Air Force lost 344 and 138 aircraft in these respective periods. {{harvnb|Hooton|2007|p=57}}.
}}
{{efn
| name = German casualties
| German air units doubled up and flew missions over the Netherlands and Belgium. Case specific loss totals for Belgium only cannot be certain. Total German losses in the air numbered 469 in 12–25 May, and 126 for 26 May – 1 June, but at least 43 paratroopers were killed and a further 100 wounded. {{harvnb|Hooton|2007|p=57}};   {{harvnb|Dunstan|2005|p=57}}.
}}
}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin|40em}}
* {{citation | author = Belgian American Educational Foundation | title = The Belgian Campaign and the Surrender of the Belgian Army, 10–28 May 1940 | edition = Third | year = 1941 | publisher = University of Michigan | ref = {{sfnRef|Belgian American Educational Foundation|1941}} }}
* {{citation | author = Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères | title = Belgium : The Official Account of What Happened 1939–1940 | publisher = Evans Brothers | year = 1941 | oclc = 42016037 | ref = {{sfnRef|Belgium, Ministère des Affaires Étrangères|1941}} }}
* {{citation |last=Bloock |first=Bernard |title=Belgian Fortifications, May 1940 |year=2003 |url=http://niehorster.org/021_belgium/forts/_forts-part_02.htm |accessdate=10 May 2014 |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6BBOdRB7c?url=http://niehorster.orbat.com/021_belgium/forts/_forts-part_02.htm |archivedate=5 October 2012 |url-status=live |df=dmy }}
* {{Citation | last = Bond | first = Brian | authorlink = Brian Bond | title = France and Belgium, 1939–1940 | publisher = Davis-Poynter | location = London | year = 1975 | isbn = 978-0-7067-0168-5 }}
* {{Citation | last = Bond | first = Brian | title = Britain, France, and Belgium, 1939–1940 | publisher = Brassey's (UK) Riverside, N.J | location = London | year = 1990 | isbn = 978-0-08-037700-1 }}
* {{Citation | last1 = Bond | first1 = Brian | last2 = Taylor | first2 = Michael | title = The Battle of France and Flanders 1940 | publisher = Leo Cooper | location = London | year = 2001 | isbn = 978-0-85052-811-4 }}
* {{Citation | last = Cull | first = Brian | title = Twelve Days in May | publisher = Grub Street Publishing (UK) | location = London | year = 1999 | isbn = 978-1902304120 }}
* {{Citation | last = Dunstan | first = Simon | title = Fort Eben Emael | publisher = Osprey Publishing (UK) | location = Oxford | year = 2005 | isbn = 978-1-84176-821-2 }}
* {{Citation | last = Ellis | first = John | title = The World War II Data Book | publisher = Aurum Press | year = 1993 | isbn = 978-1-85410-254-6}}
* {{Citation | last = Ellis | first = Major L.F. | editor-last = Butler | editor-first = J.R.M | editor-link = James Ramsay Montagu Butler | series = History of the Second World War United Kingdom Military Series | title = The War in France and Flanders 1939–1940 | publisher = Naval &amp; Military Press | year = 2004 |origyear = 1954 | isbn=978-1-84574-056-6}}
* {{Citation | last = Fowler | first = Will | title = France, Holland, and Belgium 1940 | publisher = Ian Allan | location = Hersham | year = 2002 | isbn = 978-0-7110-2944-6 }}
* {{Citation | last1 = Frieser | first1 = Karl-Heinz | last2 = Greenwood | first2 = John T. | title = The Blitzkrieg Legend: The 1940 Campaign in the West | publisher = Naval Institute Press | location = Annapolis | year = 2005 | isbn = 978-1-59114-294-2 }}
* {{citation | last = Gunsburg |first= Jeffrey A. | title = The Battle of the Belgian Plain, 12–14 May 1940: The First Great Tank Battle | journal = The Journal of Military History | volume = 56 | issue = 2 | date = April 1992 | pages = 207–244 | doi=10.2307/1985797}}
* {{Citation | last = Harclerode  | first = Peter | authorlink = Peter Harclerode | title = Wings Of War: Airborne Warfare 1918-1945 | publisher = Phoenix | location = Arizona | year = 2006 | isbn = 978-0304367306 }}
* {{Citation | last = Healy | first = Mark | editor-last = Prigent | editor-first =  John | title = Panzerwaffe: The Campaigns in the West 1940 | volume = 1 | publisher = Ian Allan | location = Shepperton | year = 2008 | isbn = 978-0-7110-3240-8 }}
* {{citation | last1 = Holleman | first1 = Leendert | last2 = Rosseels | first2 = Alain |last3 = Welting | first3 = Henk | title = Traces of World War 2: The Belgian Air Force | year = 2008 | url = http://www.epibreren.com/ww2/belgium/af/index.html#ep | accessdate = 10 May 2014}}
* {{Citation | last = Holmes | first = Richard | authorlink = Richard Holmes (military historian) | title = The Oxford Companion to Military History | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford | year = 2001 | isbn = 978-0-19-866209-9 }}
* {{Citation | last = Hooton | first = Edward R. | title = Luftwaffe at War; Blitzkrieg in the West 1939 -1940 | publisher = Midland Publishing | location = Leicester | year = 2007 | isbn = 978-1-85780-272-6 }}
* {{Citation | last = Jackson | first = Julian T. | authorlink = Julian T. Jackson | title = The Fall of France | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford | year = 2003 | isbn = 978-0-19-280550-8 }}
* {{citation | last = Keegan | first = John | authorlink = John Keegan |title = The Second World War | publisher = Penguin Books | location = New York | year = 2005 | isbn = 978-0-14-303573-2 }}
* {{citation | last = Niehorster | first = Leo | title = Belgian Order of Battle: Army | url = http://niehorster.org/021_belgium/1940_organ/40_div-cav/div-cav_.html | accessdate = 10 May 2014 | ref = {{sfnRef|Niehorster, ''Order of Battle, Army''}} }}
* {{citation | last = Niehorster | first = Leo | title = Belgian Order of Battle: Navy | url = http://niehorster.org/021_belgium/1940_oob/ghq_navy.html | accessdate = 10 May 2014 | ref = {{sfnRef|Niehorster, ''Order of Battle: Navy''}} | archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20160531025659/http://niehorster.org/021_belgium/1940_oob/ghq_navy.html | archive-date = 31 May 2016 | url-status = dead }}
* {{Citation | author = Oberkommando der Wehrmacht | authorlink = Oberkommando der Wehrmacht | title = Die Wehrmachtberichte, 1939–1945 – Band 1, 1. September 1939 bis 31. Dezember 1941 | publisher = Deutscher Taschenbuch Verlag | location = München | language = German | year = 1985 | isbn = 978-3-423-05944-2 | ref = {{sfnRef|Oberkommando der Wehrmacht|1941}} }}
* {{Citation | last = Sebag-Montefiore | first = Hugh | authorlink = Hugh Sebag-Montefiore| title = Dunkirk: Fight to the Last Man | publisher = Viking | location = New York | year = 2006 | isbn = 978-0-670-91082-3 }}
* {{Citation | last = Shepperd | first = Alan | title = France 1940: Blitzkrieg in the West | publisher = Osprey Publishing | location = Oxford | year = 1990 | isbn = 978-0-85045-958-6 }}
* {{citation | last = Shirer | first = William L. | authorlink = William L. Shirer | title = The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich: A History of Nazi Germany | publisher = Simon and Schuster | year = 1990 | origyear = 1960 | isbn = 978-0-671-72868-7 }}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{commons category|Battle for Belgium (1940)}}
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book | last = Blatt | first = Joel | title = The French Defeat of 1940: Reassessments | publisher = Berghahn Books | location = Providence | year = 1998 | isbn = 978-1-57181-109-7 }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Dear | first1 = Ian | author1-link = I. C. B. Dear | last2 = Foot | first2 = M. R. D. | author2-link = M. R. D. Foot | title = The Oxford Companion to World War II | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford | year = 2001 | isbn = 978-0-19-860446-4 }}
* {{cite book | last = Harman | first = Nicholas | title = Dunkirk | url = https://archive.org/details/dunkirknecessary0000harm | url-access = registration | publisher = Hodder and Stoughton | location = London | year = 1980 | isbn = 978-0-340-24299-5 }}
* {{cite book | last1 = Krause | first1 = Michael | last2 = Cody | first2 = P. | title = Historical Perspectives of the Operational Art | publisher = Center of Military History Publication – Dept. of the Army | location = Washington | year = 2006 | isbn = 978-0-16-072564-7 }}
* {{cite book | last = Powaski | first = Ronald E. | authorlink = Ronald E. Powaski | title = Lightning War: Blitzkrieg in the West, 1940 | publisher = John Wiley | year = 2003 | isbn = 978-0-471-39431-0 | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/lightningwarblit0000powa }}
* {{cite book |editor1-last=Taylor |editor1-first=A. J. P. |editor1-link=A. J. P. Taylor |editor2-last=Mayer |editor2-first=S. L. |title=A History of World War Two |publisher=Octopus Books |location=London |year=1974 |isbn=978-0-7064-0399-2 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/historyofworldwa00tayl }}
* {{cite book | last = Weal | first = John | title = Junkers Ju 87 Stukageschwader 1937–1941 | publisher = Osprey | location = Oxford | year = 1997 | isbn = 978-1-85532-636-1}}
{{refend}}

{{World War II}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2012}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Belgium, Battle of}}
[[Category:Battle of Belgium| ]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1940]]
[[Category:1940 in Belgium|Battle of Belgium]]
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Western European Theatre|Belgium]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Belgium]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Belgium–Germany military relations|Battle of Belgium]]
[[Category:Invasions of Belgium|Battle of Belgium]]
[[Category:Invasions by Germany|Battle of Belgium]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]</text><sha1>f5lcmuqlym43rncanockty18fqbtjqa</sha1></revision></page>