<page><title>Battle of Dunkirk</title><ns>0</ns><id>73246</id><revision><id>964864667</id><parentid>963373355</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-28T01:21:01Z</timestamp><contributor><username>InternetArchiveBot</username><id>27015025</id></contributor><comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0.1</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="41223" xml:space="preserve">{{About|the Second World War battle in 1940|details about the major evacuation of Allied troops from Dunkirk|Dunkirk evacuation|the other battles of the same name|Battle of Dunkirk (disambiguation)}}
{{short description|1940 battle between the Allies and Germany in France}}
{{EngvarB|date=February 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Battle of Dunkirk
|partof = the [[Battle of France]] in the [[Second World War]]
|image = File:Dunkirksoldier1.JPG
|image_size = 300px
|caption = ''Soldiers from the British Expeditionary Force fire at low flying German aircraft during the Dunkirk evacuation'' – Soldiers were [[strafe]]d and bombed by German aircraft while awaiting transport.{{sfn|Shirer|1960|loc=Footnote, p. 736}}
|date = 26 May – 4 June 1940
|place = [[Dunkirk]], [[French Third Republic|France]]
|result = German tactical victory
* Success of [[Operation Dynamo]]
* Allies evacuate approx. 85% of stranded troops
|territory = Allied foothold in France lost
*Allies withdraw to Britain
|combatant1 = {{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagcountry|French Third Republic}}
* {{flagicon image|Civil ensign of French Morocco.svg}} [[French protectorate in Morocco|Morocco]]
* {{flagdeco|Poland|1928}} [[Polish Army in France (1939–40)|Polish exiles]]
{{flag|Belgium}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Canada|1921}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Netherlands}}
|combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1 = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[John Vereker, 6th Viscount Gort|Lord Gort]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|French Third Republic}} [[Maxime Weygand]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|French Third Republic}} [[Georges Blanchard]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|French Third Republic}} [[René Prioux]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|French Third Republic}} [[Jean-Marie Charles Abrial|J.M. Charles Abrial]]&lt;ref name="FF"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/UK-NWE-Flanders/UK-NWE-Flanders-12.html|title=HyperWar: The War in France and Flanders 1939–1940 [Chapter XII]|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170809051740/http://www.iwm.org.uk/collections/item/object/30011354|archivedate=9 August 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|commander2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Gerd von Rundstedt]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Fedor von Bock]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Paul Ludwig Ewald von Kleist|Ewald von Kleist]] (Panzergruppe von Kleist)
|strength1 = approx. 400,000 &lt;br /&gt;338,226 evacuated
|strength2 = approx. 800,000
|casualties1 =
* '''(Estimated total)'''&lt;br /&gt;61,774 total killed and wounded 
* British &lt;br /&gt;*~3,500 killed during the evacuation &lt;br /&gt; *63,879 vehicles including tanks and motorcycles&lt;br /&gt;*2,472 field guns&lt;br /&gt;6 destroyers&lt;br /&gt;*23 destroyers damaged&lt;ref name="Hooton 2010, p. 71"&gt;Hooton 2010, p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;*89 transport ships&lt;ref name="Hooton 2010, p. 71"&gt;Hooton 2010, p. 71.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;*177 aircraft destroyed or damaged in total&lt;ref&gt;Murray 2002 (1985 ed.) p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;*127 belonged to [[RAF Fighter Command]].&lt;ref&gt;Frank's 2008, ok. 33–39.&lt;/ref&gt;
* French&lt;br /&gt;*18,000 killed, 35,000 captured&lt;br /&gt;*3 destroyers
|casualties2 = '''(Estimated total)'''&lt;br /&gt;*20,000 killed and wounded&lt;br /&gt;*100 tanks&lt;br /&gt;*240 aircraft in theatre&lt;ref&gt;Murray 2002 (1985 ed.''strategy for defeat'') p. 42.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;*156 aircraft on Dunkirk front&lt;ref&gt;Frank's 2008, p. 160.&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties3 ='''Civilian casualties''': 1,000 civilians killed during air raids
}}
{{Campaignbox Western Front (World War II)}}
{{Campaignbox Battle of France}}

The '''Battle of Dunkirk'''  ({{lang-fr|Bataille de Dunkerque|link=no}}) was fought in [[Dunkirk|Dunkirk (Dunkerque)]], [[French Third Republic|France]], during the [[Second World War]], between the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] and [[Nazi Germany]]. As the Allies were losing the [[Battle of France]] on the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]], the Battle of Dunkirk was the defence and evacuation to Britain of British and other Allied forces in Europe from 26 May to 4 June 1940.

After the [[Phoney War]], the [[Battle of France]] began in earnest on 10 May 1940. To the east, the German [[Army Group B]] invaded the [[Netherlands]] and advanced westward. In response, the Supreme Allied Commander—French General [[Maurice Gamelin]]—initiated "Plan D" and entered [[Belgium]] to engage the Germans in the Netherlands. The plan relied heavily on the [[Maginot Line]] fortifications along the German–French border, but German forces had already crossed through most of the Netherlands before the French forces arrived. Gamelin instead committed the forces under his command, three mechanised armies, the French [[French First Army|First]] and [[French Seventh Army|Seventh]] Armies and the [[British Expeditionary Force (World War II)|British Expeditionary Force]] (BEF), to the [[Dyle (river)|River Dyle]]. On 14 May, German [[Army Group A]] burst through the [[Ardennes]] and advanced rapidly to the west toward [[Sedan, France|Sedan]], then turned northward to the [[English Channel]], using [[Field Marshal (Germany)|''Generalfeldmarschall'']] [[Erich von Manstein]]'s plan ''[[Manstein Plan#Sichelschnitt|Sichelschnitt]]'' under the German strategy [[Battle of France#Fall Gelb .28Case Yellow.29|Fall Gelb]], effectively flanking the Allied forces.&lt;ref name="MacDonald 1986, p. 8"&gt;MacDonald 1986, p. 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

A series of Allied counter-attacks—including the [[Battle of Arras (1940)|Battle of Arras]]—failed to sever the German spearhead, which reached the coast on 20 May, separating the BEF near [[Armentières]], the French [[First Army (France)|First Army]], and the [[Belgian Army]] further to the north from the majority of French troops south of the German penetration. After reaching the Channel, the German forces swung north along the coast, threatening to capture the ports and trap the British and French before they could evacuate to Britain.

In one of the most debated decisions of the war, the Germans halted their advance on Dunkirk. Contrary to popular belief, what became known as the "Halt Order" did not originate with [[Adolf Hitler]]. ''[[Generaloberst]]en'' (Colonel-Generals) [[Gerd von Rundstedt]] and [[Günther von Kluge]] suggested that the German forces around the Dunkirk [[pocket (military)|pocket]] should cease their advance on the port and consolidate to avoid an Allied breakout. Hitler sanctioned the order on 24 May with the support of the ''[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]''. The army was to halt for three days, which gave the Allies sufficient time to organise the [[Dunkirk evacuation]] and build a defensive line. While more than 330,000 Allied troops were rescued,&lt;ref&gt;Frieser 2005, pp. 291–292.&lt;/ref&gt; British and French military forces nonetheless sustained heavy casualties and were forced to abandon nearly all their equipment. The British Expeditionary Force alone lost some 68,000 soldiers during the French campaign.

==Prelude==
On 10 May 1940, [[Winston Churchill]] became [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]] of the United Kingdom. By 26 May, the BEF and the French 1st Army were bottled up in a corridor to the sea, about {{convert|60|mi|km}} deep and {{convert|15|mi|km|}} wide. Most of the British forces were still around [[Lille]], over {{convert|40|mi|km}} from Dunkirk, with the French farther south. Two massive German armies flanked them. General [[Fedor von Bock]]'s Army Group B was to the east, and General [[Gerd von Rundstedt]]'s Army Group A to the west. Both officers were later promoted to field marshal.&lt;ref name="MacDonald 1986, p. 8"/&gt;

==Halt order==
{{See also|Battle of Arras (1940)}}
&lt;!-- Sidebar starts here --&gt;
&lt;div class="infobox" style="width:298px; margin: 4px; padding: 0.5em;"&gt;&lt;center&gt;'''Quotes on the halt order'''&lt;/center&gt;

{{quote|During the following days... it became known that Hitler's decision was mainly influenced by Goering. To the dictator the rapid movement of the Army, whose risks and prospects of success he did not understand because of his lack of military schooling, became almost sinister. He was constantly oppressed by a feeling of anxiety that a reversal loomed...|Halder, in a letter of July 1957.&lt;ref&gt;Shirer 1959, p. 879.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[Lionel Ellis|Major L. F. Ellis]] wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;The day's entry concludes with the remark: "The task of Army Group A can be considered to have been completed in the main"—a view which further explains Rundstedt's reluctance to employ his armoured divisions in the final clearing-up stage of this first phase of the campaign.&lt;ref&gt;Butler 2009, p. 151.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

[[Franz Halder]] wrote in his diary on 30 May:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Brauchitsch is angry ... The pocket would have been closed at the coast if only our armour had not been held back. The bad weather has grounded the ''Luftwaffe'' and we must now stand and watch countless thousands of the enemy get away to England right under our noses.&lt;ref&gt;Shirer 1959, p. 883.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- End of sidebar--&gt;

On 24 May, Hitler visited General von Rundstedt's headquarters at [[Charleville-Mézières|Charleville]]. The terrain around Dunkirk was thought unsuitable for armour. Von Rundstedt advised him the infantry should attack the British forces at Arras, where the British had proved capable of significant action, while Kleist's armour held the line west and south of Dunkirk to pounce on the Allied forces retreating before Army Group B. Hitler, who was familiar with Flanders' marshes from the [[World War I|First World War]], agreed. This order allowed the Germans to consolidate their gains and prepare for a southward advance against the remaining French forces.

''[[Luftwaffe]]'' commander [[Hermann Göring]] asked for the chance to destroy the forces in Dunkirk. The Allied forces' destruction was thus initially assigned to the air force while the German infantry organised in [[Army Group B]]. Von Rundstedt later called this "one of the great turning points of the war."&lt;ref name="Taylor and Mayer p. 60"&gt;Taylor and Mayer 1974, p. 60.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shirer 1959, p. 877.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="atkin1990"&gt;Atkin 1990, p. 120.&lt;/ref&gt;

The true reason for the decision to halt the German armour on 24 May is still debated. One theory is that Von Rundstedt and Hitler agreed to conserve the armour for ''[[Fall Rot]]'' ("Case Red"), an operation to the south. It is possible that the Luftwaffe's closer ties than the army's to the Nazi Party contributed to Hitler's approval of Göring's request. Another theory—which few historians have given credence—is that Hitler was still trying to establish diplomatic peace with Britain before [[Operation Barbarossa]] (the invasion of the Soviet Union). Although von Rundstedt after the war stated his suspicions that Hitler wanted "to help the British", based on alleged praise of the British Empire during a visit to his headquarters, little evidence that Hitler wanted to let the Allies escape exists apart from a self-exculpatory statement by Hitler himself in 1945.&lt;ref name="Taylor and Mayer p. 60"/&gt;&lt;ref name="atkin1990"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw 2008, p. 27.&lt;/ref&gt; The historian [[Brian Bond]] wrote:

&lt;blockquote&gt;Few historians now accept the view that Hitler's behaviour was influenced by the desire to let the British off lightly in [the] hope that they would then accept a compromise peace. True, in his political testament dated 26 February 1945 Hitler lamented that Churchill was "quite unable to appreciate the sporting spirit" in which he had refrained from annihilating [the] British Expeditionary Force, at Dunkirk, but this hardly squares with the contemporary record. Directive No. 13, issued by the Supreme Headquarters on 24 May called specifically for the annihilation of the French, English and Belgian forces in the pocket, while the ''Luftwaffe'' was ordered to prevent the escape of the English forces across the channel.&lt;ref&gt;Bond 1990, pp. 104–105.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Whatever the reasons for Hitler's decision, the Germans confidently believed the Allied troops were doomed. American journalist [[William Shirer]] reported on 25 May, "German military circles here tonight put it flatly. They said the fate of the great Allied army bottled up in Flanders is sealed." BEF commander [[Lord Gort]] agreed, writing to [[Anthony Eden]], "I must not conceal from you that a great part of the BEF and its equipment will inevitably be lost in the best of circumstances".&lt;ref name="atkin1990"/&gt;

Hitler did not rescind the Halt Order until the evening of 26 May. The three days thus gained gave a vital breathing space to the [[Royal Navy]] to arrange the evacuation of the British and Allied troops. About 338,000 men were rescued in about 11 days. Of these some 215,000 were British and 123,000 were French, of whom 102,250 escaped in British ships.&lt;ref&gt;Lord 1983, p. 148.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

==="Fight back to the west"===
[[File:21May-4June1940-Fall Gelb.svg|thumb|Map of the battle]]
On 26 May, [[Anthony Eden]] told [[General (United Kingdom)|General]] [[John Vereker, 6th Viscount Gort|Lord Gort]], [[Commander-in-chief|Commander-in-Chief]] (C-in-C) of the BEF, that he might need to "fight back to the west", and ordered him to prepare plans for the evacuation, but without telling the French or the Belgians. Gort had foreseen the order and preliminary plans were already in hand. The first such plan, for a defence along the Lys Canal, could not be carried out because of German advances on 26 May, with the [[2nd Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|2nd]] and [[50th (Northumbrian) Infantry Division|50th Division]]s pinned down, and the [[1st Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|1st]], [[5th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|5th]] and [[48th (South Midland) Division|48th Division]]s under heavy attack. The 2nd Division took heavy casualties trying to keep a corridor open, being reduced to brigade strength, but they succeeded; the 1st, [[3rd Division (United Kingdom)|3rd]], [[4th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|4th]] and [[42nd (East Lancashire) Infantry Division|42nd Division]]s escaped along the corridor that day, as did about one-third of the French First Army. As the Allies fell back, they disabled their artillery and vehicles and destroyed their stores.&lt;ref&gt;Liddell Hart 1970, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="MacDonald p.12"&gt;MacDonald 1986, p. 12.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sebag-Montefiore 2006, p. 250.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 May, the British fought back to the Dunkirk perimeter line. The [[Le Paradis massacre]] took place that day, when the [[3rd SS Division Totenkopf|3rd SS Division ''Totenkopf'']] machine-gunned 97 British and French prisoners near the La Bassée Canal. The British prisoners were from the 2nd Battalion, [[Royal Norfolk Regiment]], part of the [[4th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|4th Brigade]] of the 2nd Division. The SS men lined them up against the wall of a barn and shot them all; only two survived. Meanwhile, the Luftwaffe dropped bombs and leaflets on the Allied armies. The leaflets showed a map of the situation. They read, in English and French: "British soldiers! Look at the map: it gives your true situation! Your troops are entirely surrounded&amp;nbsp;– stop fighting! Put down your arms!" To the land- and air-minded Germans, the sea seemed an impassable barrier, so they believed the Allies were surrounded; but the British saw the sea as a route to safety.&lt;ref&gt;Lord 1982, pp. 74–76.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shirer 1959, p. 882.&lt;/ref&gt;

Besides the ''Luftwaffe''{{'}}s bombs, German heavy artillery (which had just come within range) also fired high-explosive shells into Dunkirk. By this time, over 1,000 civilians in the town had been killed. This bombardment continued until the evacuation was over.&lt;ref name="MacDonald p.12"/&gt;

===Battle of Wytschaete===
Gort had sent [[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant General]] [[Ronald Forbes Adam|Ronald Adam]], commanding [[III Corps (United Kingdom)|III Corps]], ahead to build the defensive perimeter around Dunkirk. Lieutenant General [[Alan Brooke, 1st Viscount Alanbrooke|Alan Brooke]], commanding [[II Corps (United Kingdom)|II Corps]], was to conduct a holding action with the 3rd, 4th, 5th, and 50th Divisions along the Ypres-Comines canal as far as Yser, while the rest of the BEF fell back. The battle of [[Wytschaete]], over the border in Belgium, was the toughest action Brooke faced in this role.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2009, pp. 174–178.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 May, the Germans made a [[reconnaissance in force]] against the British position. At mid-day on 27 May, they launched a full-scale attack with three divisions south of [[Ypres]]. A confused battle followed, where visibility was low because of forested or urban terrain and communications were poor because the British at that time used no radios below battalion level and the telephone wires had been cut. The Germans used infiltration tactics to get among the British, who were beaten back.&lt;ref name="Thomp179"&gt;Thompson 2009, p. 179.&lt;/ref&gt;

The heaviest fighting was in the 5th Division's sector. Still on 27 May, Brooke ordered the 3rd Division commander, [[Major-general (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[Bernard Montgomery]], to extend his division's line to the left, thereby freeing the [[10th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|10th]] and [[11th Infantry Brigade and Headquarters South East|11th Brigade]]s, both of the 4th Division, to join the 5th Division at Messines Ridge. The 10th Brigade arrived first, to find the enemy had advanced so far they were closing on the British field artillery. Between them, the 10th and 11th Brigades cleared the ridge of Germans, and by 28 May they were securely dug in east of Wytschaete.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2009, pp. 182–183.&lt;/ref&gt;

That day, Brooke ordered a counterattack. This was to be spearheaded by two battalions, the 3rd [[Grenadier Guards]] and 2nd [[North Staffordshire Regiment]], both of Major-General [[Harold Alexander, 1st Earl Alexander of Tunis|Harold Alexander]]'s 1st Division. The North Staffords advanced as far as the Kortekeer River, while the Grenadiers reached the canal itself, but could not hold it. The counterattack disrupted the Germans, holding them back a little longer while the BEF retreated.&lt;ref name="Thomp184"&gt;Thompson 2009, pp. 183–184.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Action at Poperinge===
The route back from Brooke's position to Dunkirk passed through the town of [[Poperinge]] (known to most British sources as "Poperinghe"), where there was a bottleneck at a bridge over the Yser canal. Most of the main roads in the area converged on that bridge. On 27 May, the ''Luftwaffe'' bombed the resulting traffic jam thoroughly for two hours, destroying or immobilising about 80 percent of the vehicles. Another ''Luftwaffe'' raid, on the night of 28–29 May, was illuminated by flares as well as the light from burning vehicles. The British [[44th (Home Counties) Division|44th Division]] in particular had to abandon many guns and lorries, losing almost all of them between Poperinge and the Mont.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2009, pp. 186–192, 215.&lt;/ref&gt;

The German 6. ''Panzerdivision'' could probably have destroyed the 44th Division at Poperinge on 29 May, thereby cutting off the 3rd and 50th Divisions as well. The historian and author Julian Thompson calls it "astonishing" that they did not, but they were distracted, investing the nearby town of [[Cassel, Nord|Cassel]].&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2009, p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Belgian surrender===
Gort had ordered Lieutenant General Adam, commanding III Corps, and French [[Bertrand Fagalde|General Fagalde]] to prepare a perimeter defence of Dunkirk. The perimeter was semicircular, with French troops manning the western sector and British troops the eastern. It ran along the Belgian coastline from [[Nieuwpoort, Belgium|Nieuwpoort]] in the east via [[Veurne]], [[Bulskamp]] and [[Bergues]] to [[Gravelines]] in the west. The line was made as strong as possible under the circumstances. On 28 May the Belgian army [[Battle of the Lys (1940)|fighting on the Lys river]] under the command of [[Leopold III of Belgium|King Leopold III]] surrendered. This left a {{convert|20|mi|km|abbr=on}} gap in Gort's eastern flank between the British and the sea. The British were surprised by the Belgian capitulation, despite King Leopold warning them in advance.&lt;ref name="BBC p.6"&gt;Anderson, Professor Duncan. [https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwtwo/dunkirk_spinning_06.shtml "Day of National Prayer."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090619141546/http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwtwo/dunkirk_spinning_06.shtml |date=19 June 2009 }} ''BBC''. Retrieved: 30 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Sebag-Montefiore 2006, p. 303.&lt;/ref&gt; As a constitutional monarch, Leopold's decision to surrender without consulting the [[Belgian government in exile|Belgian government]] led to his condemnation by the Belgian and French Prime Ministers, [[Hubert Pierlot]] and [[Paul Reynaud]]. Gort sent the battle-worn 3rd, 4th and 50th Divisions into the line to fill the space the Belgians had held.&lt;ref name="LH p.41"&gt;Liddell Hart 1970, p. 41.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Defence of the perimeter===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-B14898, Calais, britische Kriegsgefangene.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Black and white photo of soldiers with a small tank|British prisoners of war with a [[Panzer I]] German tank]]
While they were still moving into position, they ran headlong into the [[256th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|German 256th Division]], who were trying to outflank Gort. Armoured cars of the [[12th Royal Lancers|12th Lancers]] stopped the Germans at Nieuport itself. A confused battle raged all along the perimeter throughout 28 May. Command and control on the British side disintegrated, and the perimeter was driven slowly inwards toward Dunkirk.&lt;ref name="LH p.41"/&gt;

Meanwhile, [[Erwin Rommel]] had surrounded five divisions of the French First Army near Lille. Although completely cut off and heavily outnumbered, the French fought on for four days under General Molinié in the [[Siege of Lille (1940)]], thereby keeping seven German divisions from the assault on Dunkirk and saving an estimated 100,000 Allied troops.&lt;ref name="LH p.41"/&gt; In recognition of the garrison's stubborn defence, German general Kurt Waeger granted them the [[honours of war]], saluting the French troops as they marched past in parade formation with rifles shouldered.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Fermer|first1=Douglas|title=Three German Invasions of France: The Summer Campaigns of 1870, 1914, and 1940|date=2013|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Military|location=Barnsley|isbn=9781781593547|page=208}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The defence of the Dunkirk perimeter held throughout 29–30 May, with the Allies falling back by degrees. On 31 May, the Germans nearly broke through at Nieuport. The situation grew so desperate that two British battalion commanders manned a [[Bren light machine gun|Bren gun]], with one colonel firing and the other loading. A few hours later, the 2nd Battalion, [[Coldstream Guards]] of the 3rd Division, rushed to reinforce the line near Furnes, where the British troops had been routed. The Guards restored order by shooting some of the fleeing troops and turning others around at bayonet point. The British troops returned to the line and the German assault was beaten back.&lt;ref name="Lord p.199"&gt;Lord 1982, p. 199.&lt;/ref&gt;

In the afternoon, the Germans breached the perimeter near the canal at [[Bulskamp]], but the boggy ground on the far side of the canal and sporadic fire from the [[Durham Light Infantry]] halted them. As night fell, the Germans massed for another attack at Nieuport. Eighteen RAF bombers found the Germans while they were still assembling and scattered them with an accurate bombing run.&lt;ref&gt;Lord 1982, p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Retreat to Dunkirk===
Also on 31 May, General Von Kuechler assumed command of all the German forces at Dunkirk. His plan was simple: launch an all-out attack across the whole front at 11:00 on 1 June. Strangely, Von Kuechler ignored a radio intercept telling him the British were abandoning the eastern end of the line to fall back to Dunkirk itself.&lt;ref&gt;Lord 1982, p. 210.&lt;/ref&gt; During the night of 31 May/1 June 1940, [[Marcus Ervine-Andrews]] won the [[Victoria Cross]] in the battle when he defended 1,000 yards (910 m) of territory.&lt;ref name=LIMus&gt;http://www.lancashireinfantrymuseum.org.uk/captain-later-lieutenant-colonel-harold-marcus-ervine-andrews-vc/&lt;/ref&gt;

The morning of 1 June was clear—good flying weather, in contrast to the bad weather that had hindered air operations on 30 and 31 May (there were only two-and-a-half good flying days in the whole operation.) Although Churchill had promised the French that the British would cover their escape, on the ground it was the French who held the line whilst the last remaining British soldiers were evacuated. Enduring concentrated German artillery fire and ''Luftwaffe'' strafing and bombs, the French stood their ground. On 2 June (the day the last of the British units embarked onto the ships),{{refn|Major General Harold Alexander, commanding [[I Corps (United Kingdom)|I Corps]], was one of the last to leave. Just before midnight on 2 June, Ramsay received the signal: "BEF evacuated".&lt;ref&gt;MacDonald 1986, p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;|group="Notes"}} the French began to fall back slowly, and by 3 June the Germans were about {{Convert|2|mi|km|abbr=|spell=}} from Dunkirk. The night of 3 June was the last night of evacuations. At 10:20 on 4 June, the Germans hoisted the swastika over the docks from which so many British and French troops had escaped.&lt;ref name="MacDonald p.16"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lord 1982, p. 246.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="LH p.46"&gt;Liddell Hart 1970, p. 46.&lt;/ref&gt;

The desperate resistance of Allied forces, especially the [[12th Infantry Division (France)|French 12th Motorised Infantry Division]] from the [[Fort des Dunes]], had bought time for the evacuation of the bulk of the troops. The Wehrmacht captured some 35,000 soldiers, almost all of them French. These men had protected the evacuation until the last moment and were unable to embark. The same fate was reserved for the survivors of the French 12th Motorised Infantry Division (composed in particular of the French [[150th Infantry Regiment (France)|150th Infantry Regiment]]); they were taken prisoner on the morning of 4 June on the beach of Malo-les-Bains. The flag of this regiment was burnt so as not to fall into enemy hands.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=SeofAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=The+150th+Infantry+Regiment+stood+at+attention+while+its+flag+was+burned.&amp;dq=The+150th+Infantry+Regiment+stood+at+attention+while+its+flag+was+burned.&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;redir_esc=y Page 180 – Dunkirk, 1940: a history, Robert Carse, Prentice-Hall, 1970 – Biography &amp; Autobiography – 214 pages] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170801002619/https://books.google.com/books?id=SeofAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=The%20150th%20Infantry%20Regiment%20stood%20at%20attention%20while%20its%20flag%20was%20burned.&amp;dq=The%20150th%20Infantry%20Regiment%20stood%20at%20attention%20while%20its%20flag%20was%20burned.&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;redir_esc=y |date=1 August 2017 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Evacuation==
{{Main|Dunkirk evacuation}}
The War Office made the decision to evacuate British forces on 25 May. In the nine days from 27 May to 4 June, 338,226 men escaped, including 139,997 French, Polish, and Belgian troops, together with a small number of Dutch soldiers, aboard 861 vessels (of which 243 were sunk during the operation). [[B. H. Liddell Hart]] wrote that Fighter Command lost 106 aircraft over Dunkirk and the ''Luftwaffe'' lost about 135, some of which were shot down by the French Navy and the Royal Navy. MacDonald wrote in 1986 that the British losses were 177 aircraft and German losses 240.&lt;ref name="MacDonald p.16"&gt;MacDonald 1986, p. 16.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="LH p.46"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shirer 1959, p. 884.&lt;/ref&gt;

The docks at Dunkirk were too badly damaged to be used, but the east and west [[mole (architecture)|moles]] (sea walls protecting the harbour entrance) were intact. Captain [[William Tennant (Royal Navy officer)|William Tennant]]—in charge of the evacuation—decided to use the beaches and the east mole to land the ships. This highly successful idea hugely increased the number of troops that could be embarked each day, and on 31 May, over 68,000 men were embarked.&lt;ref name="MacDonald p.12"/&gt;&lt;ref name="MacDonald p.16"/&gt;

The last of the British Army left on 3 June, and at 10:50, Tennant signalled Ramsay to say "Operation completed. Returning to Dover". Churchill insisted on coming back for the French and the Royal Navy returned on 4 June, to rescue as many as possible of the French rearguard. Over 26,000 French soldiers were evacuated on that last day, but between 30,000 and 40,000 more were left behind and captured by the Germans. Around 16,000 French soldiers and 1,000 British soldiers died during the evacuation. 90% of Dunkirk was destroyed during the battle.&lt;ref&gt;Lord 1982, pp. 267–269.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Wounded British soldiers evacuated from Dunkirk make their way up the gangplank from a destroyer at Dover, 31 May 1940. H1623.jpg|thumb|Troops evacuated from Dunkirk, [[Dover]], 31 May 1940]]
[[File:Memorial at Dunkerque.jpg|thumb|Battle of Dunkirk memorial]]
Following the events at Dunkirk, the German forces regrouped before commencing operation ''[[Fall Rot]]'', a renewed assault southward, starting on 5 June. Although the French soldiers who had been evacuated at Dunkirk returned to France a few hours later to stop the German advance and two fresh British divisions had begun moving to France in an attempt to form a [[British Expeditionary Force (World War II)#The Second BEF and Operation Ariel|Second BEF]], the decision was taken on 14 June to withdraw all the remaining British troops, an evacuation called [[Operation Ariel]]. By 25 June, almost 192,000 Allied personnel, 144,000 of them British, had been evacuated through various French ports.&lt;ref&gt;Butler 2009, pp. 296–305.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the French Army fought on, German troops entered Paris on 14 June. The French government was forced to negotiate an [[Second Armistice at Compiègne|armistice at Compiègne]] on 22 June.

The loss of [[materiel]] on the beaches was enormous. The British Army left enough equipment behind to fit out about eight to ten divisions.{{Citation needed|date=January 2019}} Discarded in France were, among other things, huge supplies of ammunition, 880 field guns, 310 guns of large calibre, some 500 anti-aircraft guns, about 850 anti-tank guns, 11,000 machine guns, nearly 700 tanks, 20,000 motorcycles and 45,000 motor cars and lorries. Army equipment available at home was only just sufficient to equip two divisions.{{Citation needed|date=January 2019}} The British Army needed months to re-supply properly, and some planned introductions of new equipment were halted while industrial resources concentrated on making good the losses. Officers told troops falling back from Dunkirk to burn or otherwise disable their trucks (so as not to let them benefit the advancing German forces). The shortage of army vehicles after Dunkirk was so severe that the [[Royal Army Service Corps]] (RASC) was reduced to retrieving and refurbishing obsolete buses and coaches from British scrapyards to press them into use as troop transports.{{According to whom|date=January 2019}} Some of these antique workhorses were still in use as late as the North African campaign of 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Postan 1952, Chapter IV.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 2 June, the [[Dean of St Paul's]], [[Walter Matthews (priest)|Walter Matthews]], was the first to call the evacuation the "Miracle of Dunkirk".

{{quote|It was remembered that the Archbishop of Canterbury had announced that the Day of National Prayer might well be a turning point, and it was obvious to many that God had answered the nation's collective prayer with the 'miracle of Dunkirk'. The evidence of God's intervention was clear for those who wished to see it; papers had written of calm seas and the high mist which interfered with the accuracy of German bombers.&lt;ref&gt;Anderson, Professor Duncan. [https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwtwo/dunkirk_spinning_01.shtml#seven "Miracle' at Dunkirk/"] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20161031200152/http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwtwo/dunkirk_spinning_01.shtml |date=31 October 2016 }}, writing ''BBC''. Retrieved: 30 July 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

A marble memorial to the battle stands at Dunkirk. The French inscription is translated as: "To the glorious memory of the pilots, mariners, and soldiers of the French and Allied armies who sacrificed themselves in the Battle of Dunkirk, May–June 1940."

The missing dead of the BEF are commemorated on the [[Dunkirk Memorial]].

=={{Anchor|Dunkirk Spirit|Dunkirk spirit}} "Dunkirk Spirit"==
{{further|Little ships of Dunkirk}}
[[File:DUNKIRK1940.jpg|thumb|175px|British troops embarking from Dunkirk's beaches]]

British press later exploited the successful evacuation of Dunkirk in 1940, and particularly the role of the "Dunkirk little ships", very effectively. Many of them were private vessels such as fishing boats and pleasure cruisers, but commercial vessels such as ferries also contributed to the force, including a number from as far away as the [[Isle of Man]] and [[Glasgow]]. These smaller vessels—guided by naval craft across the Channel from the [[Thames Estuary]] and from Dover—assisted in the official evacuation. Being able to move closer into the beachfront shallows than larger craft, the "little ships" acted as shuttles to and from the larger ships, lifting troops who were queuing in the water, many waiting shoulder-deep in water for hours. The term "Dunkirk Spirit" refers to the solidarity of the British people in times of adversity.&lt;ref&gt;Rodgers, Lucy. [http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/8689964.stm "The men who defined the 'Dunkirk spirit'."] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100524132445/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/8689964.stm |date=24 May 2010 }} ''BBC'', 14 May 2010. Retrieved: 30 July 2010.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Dunkirk Medal==
{{main|Dunkirk Medal}}
A commemorative medal was established in 1960 by the French National Association of Veterans of the Fortified Sector of Flanders and Dunkirk on behalf of the town of Dunkirk.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.gov.uk/guidance/medals-campaigns-descriptions-and-eligibility#unofficial-medals|title=Medals: campaigns, descriptions and eligibility|website=www.gov.uk|language=en|access-date=2017-06-02|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170623150944/https://www.gov.uk/guidance/medals-campaigns-descriptions-and-eligibility#unofficial-medals|archivedate=23 June 2017|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; The medal was initially awarded only to the French defenders of Dunkirk, but in 1970 the qualification was expanded to include British forces who served in the Dunkirk sector and their rescue forces, including the civilians who volunteered to man the "little ships".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.iwm.org.uk/collections/item/object/30011354 |title=Dunkirk Medal (1940) |accessdate=2017-07-11 |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20170809051740/http://www.iwm.org.uk/collections/item/object/30011354 |archivedate=9 August 2017 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The design of the bronze medal included the arms of the town of Dunkirk on one side, and "''Dunkerque 1940"'' on the reverse side.

==See also==
{{Portal|United Kingdom|War|France|Military of Germany|World War II}}
* [[1940 Dunkirk Veterans' Association]]
* [[Military history of the United Kingdom during World War II]] 
* [[British Army during the Second World War]]

==References==

===Notes===
{{Reflist|group="Notes"}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|20em}}

===Bibliography===
{{Refbegin}}
* Atkin, Ronald. ''Pillar of Fire: Dunkirk 1940''. Edinburgh: Birlinn Limited, 1990. {{ISBN|1-84158-078-3}}.
* Bond, Brian. ''Britain, France and Belgium 1939–1940''. London: Brasseys, 1990. {{ISBN|0-08-037700-9}}.
* Butler, J. R. M., ed. ''The War in France and Flanders 1939–1940: Official Campaign History''. Uckfield, UK: Naval &amp; Military Press Ltd., 2009. {{ISBN|978-1-84574-056-6}}.
* Franks, Norman L.R. ''Royal Air Force Fighter Command Losses of the Second World War, Volume 1. Operational Losses: Aircraft and crews, 1939–1941''. London: Midland Publishing Limited, 2008. {{ISBN|978-1-85780-286-3}}
* Franks, Norman. ''The Air Battle of Dunkirk'' (2008 [1983], William Kimber, London) {{ISBN|0-7183-0349-0}} 
* Frieser, Karl-Heinz. ''The Blitzkrieg Legend: The 1940 Campaign in the West''. Annapolis, Maryland: Naval Institute Press. 2005. {{ISBN|978-1-59114-294-2}}
* Holland, James. ''The Rise of Germany''. New York, NY: Atlantic Monthly Press, 2015. {{ISBN|978-0-8021-2397-8}}
* Holmes, Richard, ed. "France: Fall of". ''The Oxford Companion to Military History''. New York: Oxford University Press, 2001. {{ISBN|0-19-866209-2}}.
* Hooton, E.R. ''Luftwaffe at War; Blitzkrieg in the West''. London: Chevron/Ian Allan, 2007. {{ISBN|978-1-85780-272-6}}.
* Hooton, E.R. (2010), ''The Luftwaffe: A Study in Air Power, 1933–1945'', London: Classic Publications, {{ISBN|978-1-906537-18-0}}
* Keegan, John. ''The Second World War''. New York: Viking Penguin, 1989. {{ISBN|0-670-82359-7}}.
* Kershaw, Ian. ''Fateful Choices: Ten Decisions That Changed the World, 1940–1941''. London: Penguin Books, 2008. {{ISBN|978-0-14-101418-0}}.
* Kilzer, Louis. ''Hitler's Traitor: Martin Bormann and the Defeat of the Reich''. New York: Presidio Press, 2000. {{ISBN|0-89141-710-9}}.
* Liddell Hart, B.H. ''History of the Second World War''. New York: G.P. Putnam, 1970. {{ISBN|0-306-80912-5}}.
* Lord, Walter. ''The Miracle of Dunkirk''. New York: The Viking Press, 1982 / London: Allen Lane, 1983. Citations from the Wordsworth Military Library reprint of 1998. {{ISBN|1-85326-685-X}}.
* MacDonald, John. ''Great Battles of World War II''. Toronto, Canada: Strathearn Books Limited, 1986. {{ISBN|0-86288-116-1}}.
* McEwan, Ian. ''Atonement''. London: Jonathan Cape, 2001. {{ISBN|0-224-06252-2}}.
* McGlashan, Kenneth B. with Owen P. Zupp. ''Down to Earth: A Fighter Pilot Recounts His Experiences of Dunkirk, the Battle of Britain, Dieppe, D-Day and Beyond''. London: Grub Street Publishing, 2007. {{ISBN|1-904943-84-5}}.
* Murray, Willamson. ''Strategy for Defeat: The Luftwaffe 1935–1945''. Princeton, New Jersey: University Press of the Pacific, 2002. {{ISBN|0-89875-797-5}}.
* Murray, Williamson and Allan R. Millett. ''A War to Be Won: Fighting the Second World War''. Cambridge, Massachusetts: Belknap Press, 2000. {{ISBN|0-674-00163-X}}.
* Postan Michael M.''History of the Second World War: British War Production'', London: HMSO, 1952.
* Salmaggi, Cesare and Alfredo Pallavisini. ''2194 Days of War: An Illustrated Chronology of the Second World War''. New York: Gallery Books, 1993. {{ISBN|0-8317-8885-2}}.
* Sebag_Montefiore, Hugh. ''Dunkirk: Fight to the Last Man''. London: Penguin Books, 2006. {{ISBN|978-0-141-02437-0}}.
* Shirer, William L. ''The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich: A History of Nazi Germany''. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1959. {{ISBN|0-330-70001-4}}.
* Smith, Peter C (2011). ''The Junkers Ju 87 Stuka: A Complete History''. London: Crecy Publishing Limited. {{ISBN|978-0-85979-156-4}}.
* Taylor, A.J.P. and S.L. Mayer, eds. ''A History Of World War Two''. London: Octopus Books, 1974. {{ISBN|0-7064-0399-1}}.
* Thomas, Nick. ''RAF Top Gun: Teddy Donaldson CB, DSO, AFC and Bar, Battle of Britain Ace and World Air Speed Record Holder''. London: Pen and Sword, 2008. {{ISBN|1-84415-685-0}}.
* Thompson, Major General Julian. ''Dunkirk: Retreat to Victory''. London: Pan Books, 2009. {{ISBN|978-0-330-43796-7}}.
* Weinberg, Gerhard L. ''A World at Arms''. New York: Cambridge University Press, 1994. {{ISBN|0-521-44317-2}}.
* Wilmot, Chester. ''The Struggle for Europe''. Old Saybrook, Connecticut: Konecky &amp; Konecky, 1952. {{ISBN|1-56852-525-7}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{commons|Operation Dynamo}}
* [http://www.dynamo-dunkerque.com/ War Museum of Dunkirk]
*[https://www.parliament.uk/about/living-heritage/transformingsociety/private-lives/yourcountry/collections/churchillexhibition/churchill-the-orator/fight-on-the-beaches/ Churchill: We shall fight on the beaches - UK Parliament Living Heritage]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20121006080927/http://spitfiresite.com/2010/05/battle-of-britain-1940-dunkirk-operation-dynam.html Dunkirk, Operation Dynamo – A post-blog of the Battle of Britain 1940]
* [http://www.britishpathe.com/record.php?id=84564 Battle of Dunkirk short documentary with footage], from [[British Pathé]]
* [http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/8701830.stm Maps of the battle from the BBC]
* [http://dunkirk1940.org/ Dunkirk 1940] (museum)

{{Authority control}}

{{coord|51.0343|N|2.37682|E|source:kolossus-glwiki|display=title}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Dunkirk, Battle of}}
[[Category:1940 in France]]
[[Category:Battle of France]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1940]]
[[Category:Dunkirk evacuation]]
[[Category:History of Dunkirk]]
[[Category:History of Nord (French department)]]
[[Category:June 1940 events]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles in Hauts-de-France]]
[[Category:May 1940 events]]
[[Category:Military history of Canada during World War II]]</text><sha1>ram6x8ibxg2t8686i8dososg1rcoj2r</sha1></revision></page>