<page><title>Operation Windsor</title><ns>0</ns><id>19954445</id><revision><id>961824182</id><parentid>948179715</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-10T16:12:58Z</timestamp><contributor><username>FrescoBot</username><id>9021902</id></contributor><minor /><comment>Bot: [[User:FrescoBot/Links|link syntax]] and minor changes</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="19337" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2016}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Operation Windsor
| partof      = [[Battle for Caen]]
| image       = File:Bombcarpiquet.jpg
|image_size = 300px
| caption     = [[RP-3|Rockets]] fired from a [[Hawker Typhoon]] of No 181 Squadron, RAF, at buildings on Carpiquet airfield. The 3rd Canadian Division took Carpiquet on 4 July.
| date        = 4–5 July 1944
| place       = [[Carpiquet]], [[Normandy]], France
| result      = Allied victory
| territory   = Carpiquet captured by Canadians
| combatant1  = {{flag|Canada|1921}} &lt;br /&gt; {{flag|United Kingdom}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|Nazi Germany|name=Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[Rod Keller]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Kurt Meyer (Panzermeyer)|Kurt Meyer]]
| strength1   = 4 Infantry Battalions&lt;br /&gt;1 Machine Gun Battalion&lt;br /&gt;2 Armoured Regiments
| strength2   = 1 battalion each from SS Panzergrenadier Regiments 26 and 1 &lt;br /&gt;1 ''Flak'' Battery&lt;br /&gt;15 tanks initially
| casualties1 = 377 casualties&lt;br /&gt;17 tanks
| casualties2 = {{circa|270 infantry}}  and {{circa|20 tanks}}
| notes       =
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Normandy}}
}}
'''Operation Windsor''' {{nowrap|(4–5 July 1944),}} was a Canadian attack, which was part of the [[operation Overlord|Battle of Normandy]] during the [[World War II|Second World War]]. The attack was undertaken by the [[3rd Canadian Infantry Division]] to take [[Carpiquet]] and the adjacent airfield, from troops of the {{lang|de|12th SS-Panzer Division Hitler Jugend}} of {{lang|de|[[5th Panzer Army|Panzergruppe West]]}}. The attack was originally intended to take place during the later stages of [[Operation Epsom]], to protect the eastern flank of the main assault but was postponed for a week.

On 4 July, the [[8th Canadian Infantry Brigade]] and an attached battalion of the 3rd Canadian Infantry Division attacked Carpiquet, supported on the flanks by the [[2nd Canadian Armoured Brigade]]. The village was captured by mid-afternoon but German resistance in the south defeated two attacks on the airfield, despite significant Allied tank and air support. Next day the Canadians repulsed German counter-attacks and held the village, which served as a base for [[Operation Charnwood]], a Second Army attack on Caen, involving the rest of the 3rd Canadian Infantry Division on 8 July and the airfield was captured by the Canadians on 9 July.

==Background==
[[Caen]] was an [[Operation Overlord]] goal for [[I Corps (United Kingdom)|I Corps]] of the Anglo-Canadian [[British Second Army|Second Army]], which landed forces on two [[Normandy]] beaches on 6 June 1944, to capture the city and the Carpiquet area.&lt;ref name= vandervat112&gt;Van Der Vat, p. 112&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, pp. 170–171&lt;/ref&gt; German resistance prevented the town from being captured on D-Day, a result considered possible by Lieutenant-General [[Miles Dempsey]] the Second Army commander.&lt;ref&gt;Van Der Vat, p. 114&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Buckley 2004, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; For the next three weeks, positional warfare took place around Caen as both sides attacked and counter-attacked for minor tactical advantage on the Anglo-Canadian front and as part of a strategic intent to force the Germans to keep their most powerful armoured units away from the US First Army, as it captured Cherbourg and then pushed southwards through the [[bocage]] towards St. Lô.&lt;ref&gt;Roy, pp. 42–43&lt;/ref&gt;

From {{nowrap|26–30 June,}} the Second Army conducted [[Operation Epsom]], with the [[VIII Corps (United Kingdom)|VIII Corps]] which had recently arrived from Britain, to outflank Caen from the west and seize the high ground across the Orne near [[Bretteville-sur-Laize]] to the south.&lt;ref name="Clark3132"&gt;Clark, pp. 31–32&lt;/ref&gt; VIII Corps advanced {{convert|6|mi|km}} through extensive field fortifications but the Germans were able to contain the offensive, after committing their last reserves.&lt;ref name="Jackson57"&gt;Jackson, p. 57&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Hart108"&gt;Hart, p. 108&lt;/ref&gt; Depending on the success of VIII Corps, the 3rd Canadian Infantry Division and the [[2nd Canadian Armoured Brigade]] were to capture the village and airfield of Carpiquet in Operation Ottawa, which was postponed.&lt;ref&gt;Stacey 1960 p. 150&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jackson, p. 60&lt;/ref&gt;

After the Allied advance to the west of Caen, the [[I SS Panzer Corps]] held positions to the north and west of the city. Field defences on the [[River Orne]] and the vicinity of Carpiquet, {{convert|3.5|mi|km|abbr=on}} north-west of the Caen town centre, obstructed an advance toward Caen from the north.&lt;ref name= roy45&gt;Roy, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; The village was made an objective of the 3rd Canadian Infantry Division, under the command of [[Major General#Canada|Major-General]] [[Rod Keller|R. F. L. Keller]]. The Allied need for additional airfields on the Normandy mainland, ensured that the capture of the Carpiquet area was a priority for the Allies and an equally important defensive position for the Germans.&lt;ref name=roy45/&gt;

==Prelude==

===German defences===
[[File:Second Battle of Odon EN.svg|thumb|upright=1.5|&lt;center&gt;Topography of the area west of Caen&lt;/center&gt;]]
Carpiquet airfield was on a {{convert|1.2|mi|km|abbr=on}} expanse of level ground, which offered a "killing ground" for the defenders.&lt;ref name="Roy 1984 p. 46"&gt;Roy 1984 p. 46&lt;/ref&gt; The airfield had been fortified with [[minefield]]s, [[field gun]] and [[machine gun]] emplacements, manned by I Battalion, SS-Panzergrenadier Regiment 26, an anti-aircraft battery and fifteen tanks.&lt;ref name="Roy 1984 p. 46"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Van Der Vat, p. 139&lt;/ref&gt;

===Allied forces===
Keller selected the [[8th Canadian Infantry Brigade]], comprising [[The Queen's Own Rifles of Canada]] (QOR), ''[[Le Régiment de la Chaudière]]'' and [[The North Shore (New Brunswick) Regiment]]; [[The Royal Winnipeg Rifles]] (RWR) were attached from the [[7th Canadian Infantry Brigade]] to lead the assault.&lt;ref name="Roy 1984 p. 46"/&gt; Tank and machine-gun support was to be provided by [[The Fort Garry Horse|Canadian 10th Armoured Regiment (The Fort Garry Horse)]], [[Sherbrooke Fusiliers Regiment|The Sherbrooke Fusiliers]] and the [[The Queen's Own Cameron Highlanders of Canada|Cameron Highlanders Support Battalion]]. Two squadrons of [[Hawker Typhoon]] [[fighter-bomber]]s and three squadrons of [[Hobart's Funnies|specialized tanks]] from the [[79th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|British 79th Armoured Division]] were added later.&lt;ref name="Roy 1984 p. 46"/&gt; On the evening of 3 July, the [[battleship]] {{HMS|Rodney|29|6}} bombarded the buildings around Carpiquet from the [[Baie de la Seine|Bay of the Seine]] at {{convert|26200|yd|m}} range, with fifteen shells from its {{convert|16|in|mm|adj=on}} guns.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, 1962 p. 309&lt;/ref&gt;

Operation Windsor was planned to commence at 05:00 on 4 July, following a bombardment by 21 artillery regiments, with ''Le Régiment de la Chaudière'' and The North Shore Regiment attacking Carpiquet, as a squadron of the Sherbrooke Fusiliers protected the northern flank with a diversionary attack on Franqueville.&lt;ref name="Roy 1984 p. 46"/&gt;&lt;ref name=copp98&gt;Copp, p. 98&lt;/ref&gt; To the south, the RWR was to advance and seize the hangars of Carpiquet airfield. At the same time as the Canadian attack, the 43rd Division was to attack further south down the north side of the Odon to capture Verson.&lt;ref name=copp99&gt;Copp, p. 99&lt;/ref&gt; Once the regiments had captured Carpiquet, the QOR would push through and take control of the airfield control buildings. The capture of the airfield would enable further Anglo-Canadian attacks against Caen.&lt;ref name="Roy 1984 p. 46"/&gt;&lt;ref name=vandervat150&gt;Van Der Vat, p. 150&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===4 July===
[[File:Map commune FR insee code 14137.png|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Map of Carpiquet area, commune FR insee code 14137&lt;/center&gt;]]
As dawn broke on 4 July the artillery regiments opened fire on German positions in and around Carpiquet, firing a creeping barrage {{convert|1|mi|km|abbr=on}} wide and {{convert|400|yd|m|abbr=on}} deep.&lt;ref name=roy47&gt;Roy, p. 47&lt;/ref&gt; At 05:00 two Canadian infantry battalions advanced on Carpiquet, while the Sherbrooke Fusilier squadron staged the diversion to the north.&lt;ref name= copp98/&gt; The Sherbooke Fusiliers broke through the German minefields and attacked Chateau-St-Louet and Gruchy before withdrawing but the defensive positions of SS Panzergrenadier Regiment 26 remained intact and continued to fire on the North Shores.&lt;ref name=copp98/&gt; In the centre, the Chaudières avoided much of the fire directed at the North Shores as they advanced on Carpiquet.&lt;ref name=copp100&gt;Copp, p. 100&lt;/ref&gt; By 06:32, both battalions had reached the outskirts of the village and met tanks of the 12th SS Panzer Division.&lt;ref name=roy47/&gt; In the village, a house-to-house fight began and tanks of the 10th Canadian Armoured Regiment assisted the infantry in overrunning German positions.&lt;ref name=roy48&gt;Roy, p. 48&lt;/ref&gt;

To the south, the RWR advanced slowly towards the airfield, with German mortar fire inflicting many casualties on the infantry and tanks.&lt;ref name=copp100/&gt; With a squadron of the Fort Garry Horse only available for indirect fire, it took the RWR ninety minutes to advance the {{convert|1.5|mi|km|abbr=on}} from Marcelet to the airfield hangars, under fire from the south bank of the Odon.&lt;ref name=copp100/&gt;&lt;ref name=roy48/&gt;&lt;ref name=roy48/&gt; Several Sherman tanks were knocked out and by mid-day the RWR were forced to withdraw halfway to their original positions.&lt;ref name=roy48/&gt;

Unaware that the RWR had failed to gain control of the airfield, Keller sent the QOR to begin the second phase of the assault. The battalion moved forward into Carpiquet village, which was occupied by the Chaudières and The North Shore, who attacked German strong points bypassed in the initial assault.&lt;ref name=roy49&gt;Roy, p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; Infantry attacks, flame-throwers, petard-tanks (Churchill tanks mounted with a {{convert|290|mm|in|0|abbr=on}} spigot mortar) and the immolation of one strong point forced twelve surviving defenders to surrender; the remaining garrison surrendered after determined resistance.&lt;ref name=roy49/&gt; The QOR reached the edge of Carpiquet as the RWR withdrew and was ordered to hold their positions until the RWR reorganized for a second attack.&lt;ref name=copp100/&gt;

For the second attack on the airfield, Keller obtained the support of two squadrons of Typhoon fighter-bombers.&lt;ref name=roy49/&gt; The survivors of the RWR were ordered to "execute a sweeping attack by the lower ground around the enemy's left flank", with tank and artillery support, under the impression that the 43rd Division had reached Verson, although this position could not prevent a counter-attack from the south-east.&lt;ref name=copp100/&gt; In the late afternoon, the RWR resumed the attack on the airfield and reached the hangars but were unable to dislodge the German defenders.&lt;ref name=roy49/&gt; The Fort Garry tanks encountered a battlegroup of Panther tanks and was overwhelmed, the RWR was ordered to withdraw to their start-line under the cover of darkness.&lt;ref name=copp100/&gt;&lt;ref name=roy49/&gt; In Carpiquet, the 8th Canadian Infantry Brigade rapidly consolidated its positions, which were the closest to Caen of any Allied unit.&lt;ref name=roy50&gt;Roy, p. 50&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Canadians had control of Carpiquet and the northern hangars, the southern hangars and control buildings remained in German hands.&lt;ref name=roy50/&gt;

===5 July===
Less than {{convert|1|mi|km}} from the outskirts of Caen, the 8th Canadian Infantry Brigade posed a threat to German positions in the town.&lt;ref name=roy50/&gt; With most of the defence concentrated north of Caen and by the River Odon, it was feared that Anglo-Canadian forces could attack from Carpiquet and bypass the majority of the defences.&lt;ref name=roy50/&gt; Despite growing misgivings about the effectiveness of immediate counter-attacks, [[Kurt Meyer (soldier)|Kurt Meyer]] ordered the SS to retake Carpiquet.&lt;ref name=copp100/&gt; Units from the {{lang|de|1st SS-Panzer Division}} prepared to counter-attack Carpiquet from Francqueville with tanks, artillery, mortars and infantry.&lt;ref name=roy50/&gt;

Shortly after midnight, the first of the SS counter-attacks began and although thirteen tanks had been lost the previous day, the 10th Canadian Armoured Regiment and the mortars of the Cameron Highlanders, defeated the attack and inflicted many casualties.&lt;ref name=roy50/&gt; By dawn, almost no ground had been gained by the attackers and by noon, the 8th Canadian Infantry Brigade and 10th Canadian Armoured Regiment had defeated three counter-attacks, with the assistance of artillery and Typhoon fighter-bombers.&lt;ref name=copp100/&gt; The village remained firmly in Canadian occupation,although subject to frequent [[Nebelwerfer]] and mortar bombardment.&lt;ref name=roy50/&gt;

==Aftermath==

===Analysis===
[[File:Charnwood.svg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Operation Charnwood, 8–9 July 1944&lt;/center&gt;]]
Windsor was the first set-piece attack by the 3rd Canadian Division and left the Germans in control of Carpiquet airport, which obliged the 43rd Division to retire from Verson and Fontaine-Etoupefour. In 2005, Reid wrote that the attack should have been made by two brigades rather than one and an extra battalion. The attached battalion managed to reach the hangars and fight their way through them but were ordered to withdraw twice. The success of the Germans defenders in maintaining their hold on the airfield, except for the north end and Carpiquet village, left the Canadians in a salient which was counter-attacked several times. The failure of the brigade to reach all its objectives, led to doubts about the fitness of Keller for his command, although the preparations for Operation Charnwood might have been the reason for Keller delegating planning for Operation Windsor to the 8th Canadian Infantry Brigade commander, Brigadier K. G. Blackader.{{sfn|Reid|2005|pp=43–44}}

Three days after Operation Windsor, the 3rd Canadian Infantry Division took part in [[Operation Charnwood]]. On 9 July, the 8th Canadian Infantry Brigade captured Carpiquet airfield and by nightfall, the northern half of Caen had been captured.&lt;ref name=vandervat150/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Van Der Vat, p. 151&lt;/ref&gt; On 18 July British and Canadian forces launched [[Operation Atlantic]] and [[Operation Goodwood]] in which the Canadians captured the Caen districts on the south bank and the British captured ground to the east and south of the city.&lt;ref&gt;Stacey, p. 169&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trew, p. 48&lt;/ref&gt; Canadian forces then attacked German positions on [[Battle of Verrières Ridge|Verrières Ridge]] in [[Operation Spring]].&lt;ref&gt;Van Der Vat, p. 157&lt;/ref&gt;

===Casualties===
Canadian casualties for the operation totalled {{nowrap|377,}} of which {{nowrap|127 men}} were killed, most on 4 July.&lt;ref name=copp100/&gt; The RWR and The North Shores each lost {{nowrap|132 casualties.}}&lt;ref name=roy50/&gt; The 10th Canadian Armoured Regiment lost {{nowrap|17 tanks}} and an unknown number of tanks were lost by the Sherbrooke Fusiliers.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, p. 98–100&lt;/ref&gt; The I Battalion, {{lang|de|Panzer-grenadier Regiment 26}} had {{nowrap|155 infantry}} casualties and the {{lang|de|1st SS-Panzer Division (Leibstandarte Adolf Hitler)}}, which counter-attacked on 5 July, lost {{circa|20 tanks.}}&lt;ref name=copp100/&gt; II Battalion, {{lang|de|Panzer-grenadier Regiment 1}} had {{nowrap|115 casualties.}}&lt;ref&gt;Zuehlke 2011, p. 45&lt;/ref&gt;

==Citations==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book |first=L. |last=Clark |series=Battle Zone Normandy |title=Operation Epsom |publisher=The History Press |year=2004 |isbn=0-7509-3008-X}}
* {{cite book |first=Terry |last=Copp |authorlink=Terry Copp |title=Fields of Fire: The Canadians in Normandy |url=https://archive.org/details/fieldsoffirecana0000copp |url-access=registration |location=Toronto |publisher=University of Toronto Press |year=2003 |isbn=0-8020-3780-1|oclc=56329119}}
* {{cite book |series=Stackpole Military History |title=Colossal Cracks: Montgomery's 21st Army Group in Northwest Europe, 1944–45 |last=Hart |first=S. A. |authorlink= |year=2007 |publisher=Greenwood Press |location=Westport, CT |edition=Stackpole Books, 2007 |isbn=978-0-8117-3383-0}}
* {{cite book |title=Operations of Eighth Corps: Account of Operations From Normandy to the River Rhine |last=Jackson |first=G. S. |authorlink= |year=1948 |publisher=St Clements Press |location=London |edition=MLRS 2006 |isbn=1-90569-625-6}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Reid|2005}}
|title=No Holding Back: Operation Totalize, Normandy, August 1944 |last=Reid |first=B. A. |authorlink= |year=2005 |publisher=Robin Brass Studio |location=Toronto |edition= |isbn=1-896941-40-0}}
* {{cite book |last=Roy |first=R. |year=1984 |title=1944–The Canadians in Normandy |publisher=Macmillan of Canada |location=Toronto |isbn=0-7715-9796-7}}
* {{cite book |last=Stacey |authorlink= |author2=Bond, Major C. C. J. |series=Official History of the Canadian Army in the Second World War |volume=III |title=The Victory Campaign: The operations in North-West Europe 1944–1945 |publisher=The Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery Ottawa |year=1960 |oclc=606015967 |url=http://www.dnd.ca/dhh/collections/books/files/books/Victory_e.pdf |first=Colonel C. P. |accessdate=2008-08-20 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080912012732/http://www.dnd.ca/dhh/collections/books/files/books/Victory_e.pdf |archivedate=12 September 2008 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}
* {{cite book |last=van der Vat |first=D. |year=2003 |title=D-Day; The Greatest Invasion, A People's History |url=https://archive.org/details/ddaygreatestinva0000vand |url-access=registration |publisher=Bloomsbury-Madison Press |location=New York |isbn=1-55192-586-9}}
* {{cite book |last=Zuehlke |first=M. |title=Breakout from Juno: First Canadian Army and the Normandy campaign, July 4 – August 21, 1944 |year=2011 |publisher=Douglas &amp; McIntyre |location=Vancouver BC |isbn=978-1-55365-972-3}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite web |author=The Laurier Centre for Military, Strategic and Disarmament Studies |title=Canadian Military History Article Index |year=2014 |url=http://canadianmilitaryhistory.ca/archived-articles/ |accessdate=19 May 2014 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140219174438/http://canadianmilitaryhistory.ca/archived-articles/ |archivedate=19 February 2014 |df=dmy-all }}

{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Portal|Canada|War|World War II}}
* [http://canadianmilitaryhistory.ca/wp-content/uploads/2012/08/op-windsor1.pdf HQ 8 Cdn Inf Bde, Operation Windsor]
* [http://www.historynet.com/world-war-ii-12th-ss-hitlerjugend-panzer-division-fought-in-normandy.htm 12th SS-Panzer Division in Normandy]

{{coord|49.186|-0.443|display=title}}

{{World War II}}

{{Battle of Normandy}}

{{good article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Windsor}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:1944 in France]]
[[Category:Battle for Caen]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Military history of Canada during World War II]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of Europe]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:July 1944 events]]
[[Category:Canada–Germany relations]]</text><sha1>19uq5823uyhhi9r2vstt4x7twcjrm5u</sha1></revision></page>