<page><title>Operation Charnwood</title><ns>0</ns><id>2001345</id><revision><id>955220140</id><parentid>955218643</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-06T16:19:01Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Keith-264</username><id>925588</id></contributor><comment>/* Operation Jupiter */ Copyedit (minor)</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="61735" xml:space="preserve">{{About|the Anglo-Canadian offensive that was part of the [[Invasion of Normandy]] during the [[Second World War]]||Charnwood (disambiguation){{!}}Charnwood}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
 |conflict    = Operation Charnwood
 |partof      = the [[Battle for Caen]]
 |image       = Caenruins.jpg
 |image_size  = 250px
 |caption     = British troops of [[I Corps (United Kingdom)|I Corps]] pick their way through the rubble of Caen, 9 July 1944
 |alt         = A line of soldiers clambering over the heaped rubble of destroyed buildings in a badly-damaged street.
 |date        = 8–9 July 1944
 |place       = Northern [[Caen]], [[Normandy]], France
 |coordinates = {{Coord|49|10|59|N|0|22|10|W|type:city|display=title|name=Operation Charnwood}}
 |result      = Allied victory
 |combatant1  = {{ubl|{{flagcountry|UKGBI|23px}}
                     |{{flag|Canada|1921|23px}}}}
 |combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany|23px}}
 |commander1  = {{ubl|{{flagdeco|United Kingdom|23px}} [[Miles Dempsey]]&lt;ref&gt;Trew, p. 40&lt;/ref&gt;
                     |{{flagdeco|United Kingdom|23px}} [[John Crocker]]&lt;ref name="Trew32"/&gt;}}
 |commander2  = {{ubl|{{flagdeco|Nazi Germany|23px}} [[Heinrich Eberbach]]&lt;ref name="Trew39"/&gt;
                     |{{flagdeco|Nazi Germany|23px}} [[Sepp Dietrich]]&lt;ref&gt;Trew, p. 42&lt;/ref&gt;}}
 |strength1   = {{ubl|3 infantry divisions&lt;ref name="Trew32"/&gt;
                     |3 armoured brigades&lt;ref name="Trew32"/&gt;}}
 |strength2   = {{ubl|Elements of 1 infantry division&lt;ref name="Trew35"/&gt;
                     |1 armoured division&lt;ref name="Trew35"/&gt;
                     |61 tanks{{#tag:ref|The 12th SS Panzer Division's tank strength on 7 July was 24 Panthers and 37 Panzer IVs.&lt;ref name="Trew35"/&gt;|group=nb}}}}
 |casualties1 = {{ubl|3,817 casualties&lt;ref name="Trew46"&gt;Trew, p. 46&lt;/ref&gt;
                     |~80 tanks&lt;ref name="Trew46"/&gt;&lt;ref name="buck31"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2001), p. 156&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Major Ellis, the British official campaign historian, states that about 80 tanks were either destroyed or put out of action during the operation.&lt;ref name="Ellis316"/&gt;|group=nb}}}}
 |casualties2 = {{ubl|Over 2,000 casualties&lt;ref name="Trew46"/&gt;
                     |18–32 tanks{{#tag:ref|The 12th SS Panzer Division recorded the loss of 11 Panthers and 7 Panzer IVs.&lt;ref name="Trew46"/&gt;|group=nb}}{{#tag:ref|Buckley and Reynolds report that the 12th SS Panzer lost 10 Panthers and 22 Panzer IVs destroyed during the operation; Reynolds specifically stating these losses were for 8 July only.&lt;ref name="buck31"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2001), p. 155&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}}}
 |casualties3 = 300–400 French civilian casualties&lt;ref name="Stacey160"/&gt;
 |campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Normandy}}
}}

'''Operation Charnwood''' was an Anglo-Canadian offensive that took place from 8 to 9 July 1944, during the [[Battle for Caen]], part of the larger [[Operation Overlord]] (code-name for the Battle of Normandy) in the [[Second World War]]. The operation was intended to capture the German-occupied city of [[Caen]] ({{IPA-fr|kɑ̃}}), which was an important objective for the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] during the opening stages of Overlord. It was also hoped that the attack would forestall the transfer of German [[Panzer division|armoured units]] from the Anglo-Canadian sector to the American sector to the west, where an offensive was being prepared. The British and Canadians advanced on a broad front and by the evening of the second day had taken Caen up to the [[Orne (river)|Orne]] and [[Odon (river)|Odon]] rivers.

Preceded by a controversial bombing raid that destroyed much of the historic Old City of Caen, Operation Charnwood began at dawn on 8 July, with three infantry divisions attacking German positions north of Caen, behind a [[Rolling barrage#Moving barrage|creeping barrage]]. Supported by three armoured brigades, the British [[I Corps (United Kingdom)|I Corps]] made gradual progress against the [[12th SS Panzer Division Hitlerjugend]] and the 16th [[Luftwaffe Field Division]]. By the end of the day the [[3rd Canadian Division]] and the British [[3rd Division (United Kingdom)|3rd Infantry Division]] and [[59th (Staffordshire) Infantry Division]] had cleared the villages in their path and reached the outskirts of the city. Moving into Caen at dawn the following morning, the Allies encountered resistance from remnants of German units who were beginning a withdrawal across the Orne. Carpiquet airfield fell to the Canadians during the early morning and by 18:00, the British and Canadians had linked up along the north bank of the Orne. The remaining bridges were defended or impassable and with German reserves positioned to oppose their crossing, I Corps ended the operation.

Operation Charnwood was mutually costly and a tactical success for the Allies. The Germans retired from north of the Orne River but did not stop sending formations to the American front. The Germans established another defensive line along two ridges to the south of the city. The Allies maintained the initiative and began [[Operation Jupiter (1944)|Operation Jupiter]] the next day and [[Operation Goodwood]] and [[Operation Atlantic]]  a week later, in which the rest of Caen was secured.

==Background==
{{Further|Invasion of Normandy|Operation Overlord}}

The Norman city of [[Caen]] was one of the [[Normandy landings|D-Day]] objectives for the British [[3rd Division (United Kingdom)|3rd Infantry Division]] which landed on [[Sword Beach]] on 6 June 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, p. 24&lt;/ref&gt; The capture of Caen, while "ambitious", was the most important D-Day objective assigned to [[I Corps (United Kingdom)|British I Corps]] ([[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Sir]] [[John Crocker]]).

{{quote|The quick capture of that key city [Caen] and the neighbourhood of Carpiquet was the most ambitious, the most difficult and the most important task of Lieutenant-General J. T. Crocker's I Corps.|[[Lionel Ellis|Ellis]]&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, p. 171&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The initial Overlord plan called for the British [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|Second Army]] to secure the city and then form a front line from [[Caumont-l'Éventé]] to the south-east of [[Caen]], to acquire space for airfields and to protect the left flank of the [[First United States Army|United States First Army]] while it moved on [[Cherbourg]].&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; Possession of Caen and its environs would give the Second Army a suitable staging area for a push south to capture [[Falaise, Calvados|Falaise]], which could then be used as the pivot for a swing left to advance on [[Argentan]] and then towards the [[Touques River]].&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; The terrain between Caen and [[Vimont, Calvados|Vimont]] was especially attractive to Allied planners, being open, dry and conducive to swift offensive operations. Since the Allies greatly outnumbered the Germans in tanks and mobile units, creating the conditions for a fluid, fast moving battle was to their advantage.&lt;ref&gt;Van Der Vat, p. 146&lt;/ref&gt;

The 3rd Infantry Division came ashore as planned but was hampered by congestion in its beachhead, diversions en route and the late arrival of much of its armoured support. The division was unable to assault Caen in force and its lead elements were brought to a halt short of the outskirts.&lt;ref&gt;Cawthorne, p. 41&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=VdV114&gt;Van der Vat, p. 114&lt;/ref&gt; Later attacks failed as the German defenders were reinforced by the [[12th SS Panzer Division Hitlerjugend]].&lt;ref name=VdV114/&gt; On 7 June the British began [[Operation Perch]], a [[pincer attack]] by I Corps and [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]], to encircle Caen from the east and west flanks.&lt;ref name=ellis250&gt;Ellis, p. 250&lt;/ref&gt; The I Corps attack south of the [[Orne River]] was halted by the [[21st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|21st Panzer Division]] and the XXX Corps attack to the west of Caen was contained near [[Tilly-sur-Seulles]] by the [[Panzer Lehr Division|''Panzer-Lehr'' Division]].&lt;ref name=VdV139&gt;Van der Vat, p. 139&lt;/ref&gt; To force the Panzer-Lehr Division to withdraw the British [[7th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|7th Armoured Division]] attacked the western flank of the division on 13 June, through a gap created by the [[1st Infantry Division (United States)|1st US Infantry Division]], to reach high ground near [[Villers-Bocage, Calvados|Villers-Bocage]].&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 172&lt;/ref&gt; In the [[Battle of Villers-Bocage]], the 7th Armoured Division vanguard was ordered to retire and the Panzer-Lehr Division held its positions until XXX Corps captured Tilly-sur-Seulles on 19 June.&lt;ref&gt;Taylor, p. 76&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Clay, pp. 262–263&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Normandy map.png|thumb|left|upright=1.1|Normandy]]
The next British offensive, codenamed [[Operation Epsom]], was launched by [[VIII Corps (United Kingdom)|VIII Corps]] on 26 June, after [[Operation Martlet]] (also known as Operation Dauntless) a preliminary attack on 25 June, to secure the right flank of VIII Corps.&lt;ref name="Clark21"&gt;Clark, p. 21&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ellis275"&gt;Ellis, p. 275&lt;/ref&gt; VIII Corps advanced to the west of Caen on a {{convert|4|mi|km|adj=on}} front from Rauray to [[Carpiquet]].&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 138&lt;/ref&gt; Once across the Odon and Orne rivers, VIII Corps was to make for high ground near [[Bretteville-sur-Laize]] and encircle Caen.&lt;ref&gt;Clark, pp. 31–33&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans managed to contain the offensive by committing all their strength, including the [[9th SS Panzer Division Hohenstaufen|9th SS-Panzer Division ''Hohenstaufen'']] and [[10th SS Panzer Division Frundsberg|10th SS-Panzer Division ''Frundsberg'']] of the [[II SS Panzer Corps]], which had been sent from the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] soon after the D-Day and had been intended for a counter-offensive against Bayeux.&lt;ref&gt;Hart, p. 108&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot, p. 334&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2002), p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 June, the [[8th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|8th Infantry Brigade]] (1st [[Suffolk Regiment]], 2nd [[East Yorkshire Regiment]], 1st [[South Lancashire Regiment]]) of the 3rd Infantry Division, supported by the [[Staffordshire Yeomanry]], of the [[27th Armoured Brigade]], and specialist armour from the [[79th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|79th Armoured Division]], began Operation Mitten. The objective was to seize the German-occupied Château la Londe and Château le Landel. The initial evening assault, led by the 1st Battalion, South Lancashire Regiment was repulsed but the following morning further attacks gained the objectives and destroyed several German tanks. Operation Mitten cost at least three British tanks and 268 men.&lt;ref name="Scarfe6869"&gt;Scarfe, pp. 68–69&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Fortin30"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Copp113"&gt;Copp (2003), p. 113&lt;/ref&gt; Had it succeeded quicker, the [[9th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|9th Brigade]], supported by the [[9th Infantry Brigade (Canada)|9th Canadian Infantry Brigade]], would have launched Operation Aberlour, to capture the villages of la Bijude, [[Épron]], Galmache, St. Contest, [[Authie, Calvados|Authie]] and [[Cussy]] but this follow-up operation was cancelled by Crocker. The area of the Châteaux was later called the "bloodiest square mile in Normandy".&lt;ref name="Scarfe6869"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Fortin30"&gt;Fortin, p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'' [[Gerd von Rundstedt]], supreme commander of the German forces in the west ([[OB West]]), directed on 1 July that Caen should be gradually abandoned and the bulk of the German armoured divisions be shifted to the west end of the beachhead against the US First Army but the city and its surroundings were considered by ''[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]'' (''OKW'', Armed Forces High Command) to be fundamental to the defence of Normandy.&lt;ref name=keegan187&gt;Keegan, p. 187&lt;/ref&gt; ''OKW'' wanted an arc of defensible terrain from the English Channel to the western banks of the Orne to be held and [[Adolf Hitler]] sacked Rundstedt and replaced him with ''Generalfeldmarschall'' [[Günther von Kluge]].&lt;ref&gt;Daglish, p. 36&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 251&lt;/ref&gt; Learning of this through [[Ultra]], the Allied ground forces commander, [[General (United Kingdom)|General]] [[Bernard Montgomery, 1st Viscount Montgomery of Alamein|Bernard Montgomery]], planned an offensive to capture Caen and to prevent a large redeployment of German forces from the Anglo-Canadian sector to the American front.&lt;ref name="Deste305"&gt;D'Este, p. 305&lt;/ref&gt;

On 4 July, the [[3rd Canadian Division|3rd Canadian Infantry Division]] conducted [[Operation Windsor]], to seize Carpiquet and the adjacent airfield from the 12th SS-Panzer Division.&lt;ref&gt;Copp (2003), p. 99&lt;/ref&gt; Carpiquet fell on 5 July, the airfield remained in German hands.&lt;ref name=VdV150&gt;Van der Vat, p. 150&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==

===Allies===
[[File:Charnwood.svg|right|thumb|upright=1.0|alt=Map of Caen and its immediate surroundings as described in the article text|Caen and the aiming points of the heavy bombers]]
Having failed to take Caen through successive flanking manoeuvres, Montgomery decided the next attack would be a frontal assault.&lt;ref name=DE298&gt;D'Este, p. 298&lt;/ref&gt; Although Caen's strategic importance had vastly diminished since D-Day,&lt;ref name=DE298/&gt; he sought control of [[Bourguébus]] and the commanding high ground to the south.&lt;ref name=hastings222&gt;Hastings, p. 222&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 July the orders for Operation Charnwood were issued; it was to be launched at 04:20, an hour and a half before dawn on 8 July.&lt;ref name="Trew32"&gt;Trew, p. 32&lt;/ref&gt;

The objective of Charnwood was to clear Caen of its defenders up to the Orne river and if possible to secure bridgeheads in southern Caen.&lt;ref name="Stacey157"&gt;Stacey, p. 157&lt;/ref&gt; To achieve the latter it was planned to send an armoured column through the city to rush the bridges;&lt;ref name="Wilmot351"&gt;Wilmot, p. 351&lt;/ref&gt; it was hoped that I&amp;nbsp;Corps could exploit the situation to sweep on through southern Caen towards the Verrières and Bourguébus ridges, paving the way for the British Second Army to advance towards Falaise.&lt;ref name=keegan-82-188/&gt; Historian Roger Cirillo argued the operation was designed to only clear the city of German forces; due to it being cut by both a river and a canal any attempts to make rapid progress through and beyond, were "in all probability, impossible."&lt;ref&gt;Cirillo, p. 99&lt;/ref&gt;

Crocker's 115,000-strong I&amp;nbsp;Corps&lt;ref name="Trew32"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Ellis310"&gt;Ellis, p. 310&lt;/ref&gt; was assigned the task of penetrating to the Orne and Odon rivers.&lt;ref name="Trew32"/&gt; The 3rd Infantry Division would attack on a one brigade front from the north-east, supported by the [[33rd Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|33rd Armoured Brigade]]; the 59th (Staffordshire) Infantry Division would attack on a two brigade front from the north, supported by the 27th Armoured Brigade; and the 3rd Canadian Infantry Division would attack on a one brigade front from the northwest, supported by the [[2nd Canadian Armoured Brigade]].&lt;ref name="Trew32"/&gt; To maintain the maximum possible pressure on German forces in the sector,&lt;ref name="Jackson61"&gt;Jackson, p. 61&lt;/ref&gt; VIII Corps was placed on 24 hours notice to launch further attacks to the west of Caen.&lt;ref name="Ellis310"/&gt;

In the light of lessons learned from the partial Canadian success during Operation Windsor, Charnwood was to be launched on a broad front to increase the pressure on the German defences and disperse their defensive fire.&lt;ref name="buck31"&gt;Buckley (2004), p. 31&lt;/ref&gt; [[Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force|SHAEF]] planners had advised, on 10 June, that the best way to break a stalemate was to use air power to support an attack; this method was to be used&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2006), p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; for Charnwood as Montgomery enlisted the aid of [[RAF Bomber Command]].&lt;ref name=VdV150/&gt; Heavy bombers would attack Caen on the night preceding the assault, with 15% of the total bomb load being delayed action bombs set to explode when the ground attack was launched. A second wave of light bombers would follow the heavies and a third wave of American bombers would attack on the morning of the operation.&lt;ref&gt;Trew, pp. 34, 36, 37&lt;/ref&gt;

Additional support would be provided by rocket firing Typhoon fighter-bombers,&lt;ref name="Scarfe, p. 70"&gt;Scarfe, p. 70&lt;/ref&gt; the monitor {{HMS|Roberts|F40|6}}, the light cruisers {{HMS|Belfast|C35|6}} and {{HMS|Emerald|D66|6}} and the 16-inch guns of the battleship {{HMS|Rodney|29|2}}.&lt;ref name="Ellis311"&gt;Ellis, p. 311&lt;/ref&gt; Five divisions would contribute 656 guns for bombarding German positions to the south.&lt;ref name="Copp101"&gt;Copp (2003), p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; In all, it was planned that 2,000 tons of bombs would be dropped on Caen before the infantry assault began.&lt;ref name=keegan187/&gt; Due to the proximity of the target area to the Allied lines and the resulting risk of friendly casualties, the aiming point for the bombers was shifted {{convert|6000|yd|m}} to the south—beyond most of the main German defences screening the city.&lt;ref name=keegan-82-188&gt;Keegan, p. 188&lt;/ref&gt; Following a long saturation bombardment, the three infantry divisions were to push through the fortified villages in their path and advance directly into Caen's northern suburbs.&lt;ref name=H2223&gt;Hastings, pp. 222–223&lt;/ref&gt;

===Germans===
[[File:Dug-in panzer IV.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.0|alt=A frontal view of a knocked out German tank in a hull-down position, protected by earth entrenchments.|A [[Panzer IV]] of the 1/22nd Panzer Regiment in a [[hull down|dug-in defensive position]], near Lébisey]]
Caen's defence fell to two divisions; the 12th SS Panzer Division of [[I SS Panzer Corps]], and the 16th [[Luftwaffe Field Division]] of [[LXXXVI Corps (Germany)|LXXXVI Corps]]. An assault on the city was expected, and it was assumed that further attacks in the Odon valley towards the Orne river would quickly follow suit.&lt;ref name="Meyer473"&gt;Meyer (v.I), p. 473&lt;/ref&gt; The 12th SS Panzer Division, commanded by [[Kurt Meyer]], consisted of three [[panzergrenadier]] regiments including one—the 1st SS Panzergrenadier Regiment—borrowed from the [[1st SS Division Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler]] (1st SS Panzer Division).&lt;ref name="Roy46"&gt;Reginald, p. 46&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Reynolds152"&gt;Reynolds (2001), p. 152&lt;/ref&gt;  With its 61 surviving tanks&lt;ref name="Trew35"&gt;Trew, p. 35&lt;/ref&gt; 12th SS Panzer was holding the northwest approaches to Caen, defending the city and Carpiquet airfield from the 3rd Canadian and 59th British Infantry Divisions.&lt;ref name=copp102&gt;Copp (2003), p. 102&lt;/ref&gt;

The main German defensive line, a {{convert|9|km|mi|adj=on}} arc of villages from the northeast to the west, was held by the 25th SS Panzergrenadier Regiment&lt;ref name="Trew35"/&gt; and elements of the 12th SS Panzer Regiment.&lt;ref&gt;Swanston, p. 278&lt;/ref&gt; Troops from the 26th SS Panzergrenadier Regiment were holding the western flank,&lt;ref name="Trew35"/&gt; concentrating their strength, which included mortar batteries and a few tanks, in the area around Carpiquet airfield.&lt;ref name="Roy46"/&gt; The 1st SS Panzergrenadier Regiment was occupying a line from Franqueville to the western end of [[Éterville]];&lt;ref name="Reynolds152"/&gt; the villages formed mutually-supporting strongpoints with dug-in tanks and assault guns, and the defensive line was 2–3 miles (3.2–4.8&amp;nbsp;km) in depth, supplemented by anti-tank ditches, weapons pits, minefields and other obstacles.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, pp. 310–311&lt;/ref&gt; The rest of the division, with 35 tanks of the 12th SS Panzer Regiment, were held in reserve, with elements located north, west and south of the city.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2001), pp. 152–153&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the division's artillery had been moved back across the Orne, and the divisional command centre had been relocated from the [[Ardenne Abbey]] to Abbaye-aux-Dames in the centre of Caen.&lt;ref name="Trew35"/&gt;

The 16th Luftwaffe Field Division was an inexperienced infantry division that had only recently arrived in Normandy to relieve the 21st Panzer Division of its defence of Caen and its positions east of the Caen canal.&lt;ref name="Trew32"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Meyer (v.I), pp. 472–473&lt;/ref&gt; The division was under-trained&lt;ref name="Trew32"/&gt; and lacked sufficient anti-tank weapons; to remedy the latter it was reinforced with a tank battalion from 21st Panzer.&lt;ref name="Meyer473"/&gt; The Luftwaffe division was deployed on both sides of the Orne, with three battalions holding the villages to the immediate north of the city.{{#tag:ref|Two battalions of the 31st Luftwaffe Rifles Regiment and the divisional fusilier battalion.&lt;ref name="Trew35"/&gt;|group=nb}} The 1st SS Panzer Division was roughly {{convert|5|mi|km}} south of Caen with a regiment of dual purpose [[8.8 cm Flak 18/36/37/41|88 mm guns]] from the III [[Flak corps|Flak Corps]].&lt;ref name="Ellis311"/&gt; The II ''SS Panzer Corps'' was to the west, with the 10th SS Panzer Division ''Frundsberg'' around {{convert|2|mi|km}} south-west of the city.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, pp. 311–312&lt;/ref&gt;

===Air attack, 7 July===

[[File:Bombing of caen.jpg|thumb|upright=1.0|alt=An overhead view of a bomber aircraft, flying over a pall of smoke|A [[Handley Page Halifax]] bomber of [[No. 4 Group RAF]] over northern Caen after the bombing of 7 July]]
On the night of 7 July, 467 [[Avro Lancaster|Lancaster]] and [[Handley Page Halifax|Halifax]] aircraft of [[RAF Bomber Command]] attacked Caen, dropping over {{convert|2000|LT|MT}} of bombs on the city.{{#tag:ref|The quantity of munitions dropped on Caen is subject to some degree of dispute. Keegan estimates the tonnage at {{convert|2000|LT|MT}}, while Cawthorne puts the figure at {{convert|2300|LT|MT}}.&lt;ref name=keegan189&gt;Keegan, p. 189&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=cawthorne120&gt;Cawthorne, p. 120&lt;/ref&gt; D'Este wrote that "Bomber Command dropped some 6,000 bombs in a narrow area of northern Caen".&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 313&lt;/ref&gt; Simon Trew wrote of   {{convert|2562|LT|MT}}.&lt;ref name="Trew36"&gt;Trew, p. 36&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} Although intended mainly to facilitate the Anglo-Canadian advance and to prevent German reinforcements from reaching the battle or retreating through Caen, a secondary consideration was the suppression of the German defences.&lt;ref name="Ellis313"&gt;Ellis, p. 313&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Trew37"&gt;Trew, p. 37&lt;/ref&gt; In this the bombing largely failed, the main German armour and infantry positions to the north of Caen remained intact.&lt;ref name=keegan-82-188/&gt; Several tanks were hit and temporarily disabled but only two Panzer IV of the 12th SS Panzer Division were destroyed.&lt;ref name="Trew37"/&gt; General [[Miles Dempsey]], in command of the British Second Army, was more concerned with the morale-boosting effect of the bombing on his troops, than any material losses it might inflict on the Germans.&lt;ref name="Wilmot351"/&gt;

The pathfinders of [[No. 625 Squadron RAF|625 Squadron]], dropping the target markers for the bombers, were instructed not to allow the target zone to "drift back" towards the Allied lines as had been the tendency in earlier operations.&lt;ref name=keegan-82-188/&gt; Together with the cautious shifting of the target zone during the planning stage, many of the markers were dropped too far forward, pushing the bombed zone well into Caen, further away from the German defences. By 22:00 on 7 July, the bombers had departed, leaving 80 percent of the north of Caen destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;Van der Vat, p. 153&lt;/ref&gt; Caen University was particularly hard hit, starting chemical fires that soon spread.&lt;ref name=hastings222/&gt; At 22:50, six squadrons of [[de Havilland Mosquito]] bombers attacked individual targets and ten minutes later the 636 guns of the assaulting divisions opened fire, with the battleship {{HMS|Rodney|29|6}} and other ships adding their support.&lt;ref name=Copp101/&gt;&lt;ref name="Trew36"/&gt; The bombardment was intensified by the artillery of VIII Corps against the villages north of Caen, to eliminate German strong points before the infantry assault began.&lt;ref name="Jackson61"/&gt;&lt;ref name=Copp101/&gt;

==Battle==

===8 July===
At 04:30 on 8 July, the artillery of I and VIII Corps shifted their fire deeper into the German defensive belt, along the axes of advance of the 3rd Canadian Division and the [[59th (Staffordshire) Infantry Division]].&lt;ref name=cawthorne120/&gt; As the infantry and armour moved off their start-lines, the barrage slowly crept forward, concentrating its fire on positions in front of the Anglo-Canadian troops;&lt;ref name=copp103&gt;Copp (2003), p. 103&lt;/ref&gt; four battalions and two armoured regiments advancing on a two brigade front.&lt;ref name=copp103/&gt; At 07:00, 192 [[B-26 Marauder]] medium bombers arrived over the battlefield but finding it obscured by cloud only 87 aircraft were able to drop their bombs, totalling {{convert|133|LT|MT}}. Some bombs landed on the 12th SS Headquarters at Abbaye-aux-Dames.&lt;ref name="Trew37"/&gt;

[[File:Charnwood advance.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.0|alt=A dispersed group of infantry moving through a field|Men of the 2nd Battalion, [[Royal Warwickshire Regiment]], of the [[185th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|185th Brigade]] of the 3rd Infantry Division, advancing through a wheat field during the final assault on Caen.]]
Crocker launched the second phase of Operation Charnwood at 07:30, although neither division had yet reached its objectives.&lt;ref name=copp103/&gt; The 26th SS Panzergrenadier Regiment was still in control of high ground around the Carpiquet airfield on the right flank of the advance. On the left, facing the relatively weak defences of the 16th Luftwaffe Field Division, the 3rd Infantry Division made good progress. They attacked Lébisey and rapidly pushed through the village, although fighting intensified as the division reached [[Hérouville]].&lt;ref name=DE318&gt;D'Este, p. 318&lt;/ref&gt; Concerned about the state of the Luftwaffe division, General [[Heinrich Eberbach]], in command of [[5th Panzer Army|Panzer Group West]] ordered the 21st Panzer Division to redeploy north-east of Caen in support.&lt;ref name="Trew39"&gt;Trew, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; The manoeuvre was spotted and when 21st Panzer attempted to cross the Caen Canal, a naval bombardment was directed against them. Facing the possibility of heavy losses, the move was abandoned.&lt;ref name=Trew39/&gt; In the centre, the [[176th (2/1st Staffordshire) Brigade|176th Brigade]] of the 59th Division was encountering much stiffer resistance from the 12th SS Panzer Regiment in Galmanche and la Bijude.&lt;ref name=ellis314-15&gt;Ellis, pp. 314–315&lt;/ref&gt; The [[197th (Lancashire Fusiliers) Brigade|197th Brigade]] bypassed Galmanche and by noon had reached St-Contest.&lt;ref name=copp103/&gt;

Further to the west, the 9th Infantry Brigade of the 3rd Canadian Division had been involved in heavy fighting in [[Buron]], which was defended by 200 men from the 12th SS. With support from the [[10th Armoured Regiment (The Fort Garry Horse)]], by noon Buron had been taken, although the Canadian assault companies suffered 60% casualties.&lt;ref name=copp104&gt;Copp (2003), p. 104&lt;/ref&gt; South of Buron, a counter-attack by [[Panzer IV]] and [[Panther tank]]s of the 12th SS Panzer Regiment was defeated by [[17pdr SP Achilles]] self-propelled anti-tank guns and [[Ordnance QF 17-pounder|17-pounder]] anti tank guns of the 245th Battery, 62nd Antitank Regiment. Thirteen German tanks were destroyed in one of the most successful antitank engagements of the campaign, for the loss of four tank destroyers and a further four damaged.&lt;ref&gt;Copp (2003), pp. 103–104, 296–297&lt;/ref&gt; Gruchy was captured with relatively less difficulty, with the [[7th Canadian Infantry Brigade]] encountering only mortar and artillery fire in their drive to Authie. The capture of Authie facilitated the 59th Infantry Division assault on St-Contest and that village fell too, clearing the way for an advance on Caen.&lt;ref name=copp104/&gt; In Phase 3 of the operation, the 7th Brigade pushed towards the former headquarters of the 12th SS Panzer Division at Ardenne Abbey, securing the position before midnight.&lt;ref name=copp105&gt;Copp (2003), p. 105&lt;/ref&gt;

The British 3rd Division brushed aside 16th Luftwaffe and approached the outskirts of Caen from the north-east. At 19:15, Meyer and Eberbach authorised the withdrawal of the 12th SS Panzer Division heavy weapons and the remnants of the Luftwaffe division across the Orne to the southern side of Caen.&lt;ref name=copp105/&gt; In the early evening, the 12th SS fought a rearguard action against elements of the 59th and 3rd Canadian divisions, as it pulled back from positions no longer considered tenable.&lt;ref&gt;Wood, p. 92&lt;/ref&gt; Reports of this withdrawal came into the Anglo-Canadian command but patrols probing German positions, created a false perception that no withdrawal was taking place.&lt;ref name=ellis314-15/&gt;

===9 July===
[[File:Snipercaen.jpg|thumb|upright=1.0|alt=A soldier lies prone, rife at the ready by a building in a city street. Beside him is a sign reading "Caen centre", pointing back the way he has come.|A soldier from I Corps takes cover in the streets of Caen during Operation Charnwood]]
British and Canadian patrols began to infiltrate the city at dawn on 9 July.&lt;ref name=cawthorne120/&gt; The airfield at Carpiquet finally fell into Allied hands during the early morning, when the 3rd Canadian Infantry Division discovered that the 26th SS Panzergrenadier Regiment had withdrawn during the night.&lt;ref name=VdV150/&gt; With the German situation north of the river becoming increasingly precarious, 21st Panzer Division battle groups and the remaining regiments of the 12th SS Panzer Division conducted a slow withdrawal across the Orne, making for the Verrières and Bourguébus Ridges.&lt;ref name=wood93&gt;Wood, p. 93&lt;/ref&gt;

By noon the 3rd British Infantry Division had reached the Orne's north bank, virtually destroying the elements of the 16th Luftwaffe Field Division, positioned west of the Orne, in the process.{{#tag:ref|These elements were reported to have sustained 75% losses.&lt;ref name=DE318/&gt;|group=nb}} A few hours later the British and Canadians met in the centre of the city and by 18:00 the northern half of Caen was firmly under Allied control; all I Corps's objectives had been achieved. A few of Caen's bridges were intact but these were either blocked by rubble or defended by German troops on the south bank and the 1st SS Panzer Division had by now positioned itself to oppose any further advance.&lt;ref name="Ellis316"&gt;Ellis, p. 316&lt;/ref&gt;

The 12th SS Panzer Division (by the end of the battle the division's infantry strength had been reduced to that of a battalion)&lt;ref name=DE318/&gt;—claimed over the course of two days to have destroyed 103 British and Canadian tanks&lt;ref name=Wood99&gt;Wood, p. 99&lt;/ref&gt; for the loss of 20.&lt;ref name=DE318/&gt; On entering Caen the Anglo-Canadian troops found it in ruins, with four-fifths of the Old City reduced to rubble by the 7 July bombings.&lt;ref name=VdV150/&gt; The debris that choked the streets made it almost impossible for British armour to manoeuvre through the northern half of the city, preventing Second Army from exploiting I Corps's success.&lt;ref name=DE319&gt;D'Este, p. 319&lt;/ref&gt; Without possession of the terrain flanking the south of the city, no further gains could be made within Caen&lt;ref name=copp106&gt;Copp (2003), p. 106&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Hasting223"&gt;Hastings, p. 223&lt;/ref&gt; so by mid-afternoon on 9 July, Operation Charnwood was over.&lt;ref name=cawthorne120/&gt;

==Aftermath==
===Analysis===

[[File:Caen girl.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.2|alt=Two soldiers in a rubble-filled street bordered by badly-damaged buildings; one is clambering over the debris with a young child on his shoulder|A British soldier carries a little girl through the devastation of Caen, 10 July 1944.]]
The German were forced to withdraw from the north of the Orne but Allied forces were unable to push beyond the Orne.&lt;ref name="Wilmot351"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Stacey162"&gt;Stacey, p.162&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Trew44"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds, p. 154&lt;/ref&gt; German forces were dug-in on the opposite bank in position to block a move south.&lt;ref name="Buckley31"&gt;Buckley, p. 31&lt;/ref&gt; Montgomery called off an advance beyond the Orne as further attacks would be too costly for the gains made, which had inflicted much attrition on the defenders.&lt;ref name=copp106/&gt;&lt;ref name="Hart, p. 63"&gt;Hart, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Stacey, p. 165&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Meyer505"&gt;Meyer (v.II), p. 505&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Clark and Hart, p. 14&lt;/ref&gt; For French public opinion the operation was a coup; civilians now believed the liberation of France had begun.&lt;ref name="Trew4748"/&gt;

[[Antony Beevor]] called Operation Charnwood a partial success, because although much of Caen was taken, the British and Canadians failed to secure enough ground to expand the Allied build-up; the bulk of the [[First Canadian Army]] was still waiting in the United Kingdom for transfer to Normandy.&lt;ref name="Beevor273"/&gt; [[Carlo D'Este]] wrote that Charnwood did improve the Second Army's position but without the high ground to the south, Caen was useless, the capture of the city was too little too late a hollow victory.&lt;ref name="Deste318319"&gt;D'Este, pp. 318–319&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chester Wilmot]] wrote that for Montgomery to maintain a threat to German-occupied Paris, Caen's southern suburbs with their factories and communications network would have been a more significant prize.&lt;ref name="Wilmot351"/&gt; [[John Buckley (historian)|Buckley]] and Copp note that by the time the city was captured, the Germans—weakened by the battles of late June and early July—had already established defensive positions on the high ground to the south of the Orne, which blocked the route to the Falaise plain&lt;ref name="buck31"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Wilmot351"/&gt;&lt;ref name="copp106"/&gt;

Copp also wrote that the British Second Army won an important operational victory during Charnwood and the [[Society for Army Historical Research]] recorded that the attacks were a tactical and operational success.&lt;ref name="Copp94"&gt;Copp (2004), p. 94&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Delaney200"&gt;Delaney, p. 200&lt;/ref&gt; In the aftermath, the Supreme Allied Commander, General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] expressed his concern that a breakout was unlikely. Montgomery differed; the tenacity of the German defence was no barometer of its longevity.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot, p. 352&lt;/ref&gt; Field Marshal [[Erwin Rommel]] mentioned to Lieutenant-Colonel [[Caesar von Hofacker]] that the front-line in France could only be held for another three weeks. Hofacker was a member of the German resistance and linked with the Hitler assassination plot and according to Trew, Rommel's comment led to the plot timetable being decided.&lt;ref name="Trew4748"&gt;Trew, pp. 47–48&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Tankscaencenter.jpg|thumb|upright=1.0|alt=An intersection; an anti-tank gun is covering the crossroads in the foreground and in the street behind are some soldiers and two tanks|A [[Ordnance QF 6 pounder|6-pounder anti-tank gun]] of the 1st Battalion, [[King's Own Scottish Borderers]], part of the [[9th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|9th Brigade]] of the [[3rd Division (United Kingdom)|British 3rd Division]], along with two [[M4 Sherman|Sherman tanks]] near St-Pierre Church, 10 July 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Trew, p. 41&lt;/ref&gt;]]
The serious losses sustained in maintaining a static defence during June led to fractures in the German high command. On 1 July, Panzer Group West commander [[Leo Geyr von Schweppenburg]] had been replaced by Heinrich Eberbach, following disagreements with Hitler over how the campaign should be conducted.&lt;ref name="Ellis320322"&gt;Ellis, pp. 320– 322&lt;/ref&gt; Gerd von Rundstedt, soon followed, that evening, in a telephone conversation with ''Generalfeldmarschall'' [[Wilhelm Keitel]], head of OKW, von Rundstedt said "Make peace, you fools."&lt;ref name="Wilmot347"&gt;Wilmot. p. 347&lt;/ref&gt; Taken to task over his endorsement of von Schweppenburg's recommendation for a withdrawal, he replied "If you doubt what we're doing, get up here and take over this shambles yourself".&lt;ref name="Hastings207"&gt;Hastings, p. 207&lt;/ref&gt; The following morning, informed that perhaps his health was "no longer up to the task", von Rundstedt resigned and was succeeded as OB West by Günther von Kluge.&lt;ref name="Hastings207"/&gt; The costly battles in and around Caen and Saint-Lô convinced both Eberbach and von Kluge that their predecessors had been correct.&lt;ref&gt;Copp (2003), p. 109&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans had suffered heavily, leading Hitler to order Army Group B to temporarily abandon big counter-attacks and go over to the defensive until more reinforcements could arrive to bolster the front.&lt;ref name="Trew4748"/&gt;

Trew contends that the capture of northern Caen had a psychological impact on the French population, convincing them the Allies were there to stay and that the liberation of France could not be far off.&lt;ref name="Trew4748"/&gt; By Operation Charnwood's conclusion, Allied losses since 6 June had amounted to over 30,000 men, excluding those who had been evacuated due to sickness and those suffering from battle exhaustion.&lt;ref&gt;Copp (2003), p. 110&lt;/ref&gt; Buckley believes Charnwood to have been a good idea but one that proved better in concept than in execution, influenced as it was by the mounting political pressure on 21st Army Group to produce results.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2006), p. 8&lt;/ref&gt; Copp wrote that the broad-based assault plan across the entire front worked, preventing the Germans bringing to bear superior firepower on any one formation.&lt;ref name=copp106/&gt;

[[File:Caenliberated.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.0|alt=A mixed group of soldiers and civilians in front of some damaged shops; the street is littered with debris|Some of the first troops to enter Caen pose with local inhabitants outside wrecked shops, 9 July 1944.]]
Copp wrote that Charnwood should have produced a rapid breakthrough but concedes that the battle was one of the most difficult of the campaign.&lt;ref&gt;Copp (2003), p. 101–103&lt;/ref&gt; Buckley singles out poor cooperation between armoured and infantry units as one of the reasons for such high Allied losses; he is critical of the habit of tanks standing off from German positions and firing the infantry onto the objective like artillery, instead of moving forward to give close support. He further notes that from the German perspective, the Anglo-Canadian forces apparently lacked the desire or ability to press home their advantages, citing Kurt Meyer's opinion that during the battle the Allies allowed the opportunity of destroying his 12th SS Panzer Division to elude them. Buckley comments on the defensive power of the British and Canadian formations. The German practice of conducting immediate local counter-attacks to retake lost ground cost them many of their best troops, losses they could ill-afford. He illustrates this with a typical action during which the Germans lost 13 tanks to British self-propelled anti-tank guns.&lt;ref name="buck31"/&gt;

With Caen north of the River Orne in Allied hands, mine-clearance operations were launched, bulldozers were set to work to clear the streets and a convoy of trucks carrying supplies for the civilian population was brought in. On 10 July, the [[Flag of France|French flag]] was raised over the city and three days later a parade was held in the Place Saint-Martin during which a second flag was raised to the strains of Scottish [[Bagpipes|bagpipers]] playing [[La Marseillaise]].&lt;ref name="Beevor273"&gt;Beevor, p. 273&lt;/ref&gt;

Rommel and Eberbach consolidated defensive positions in and around southern Caen,&lt;ref name=copp106/&gt; the 1st, 9th and 12th SS Panzer Divisions turning the Bourguébus and Verrières Ridges into formidable barriers.&lt;ref name=DE319/&gt; Having committed all of his armoured reserves, Rommel transferred the remainder of his infantry divisions—the 708th, 276th, 277th and [[272nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|272nd]]—to the Anglo-Canadian front.&lt;ref name=keegan-82-188/&gt; On 8 July, he released the remnants of the ''Panzer Lehr'' Division and the [[2nd SS Panzer Division Das Reich|2nd SS Panzer Division ''Das Reich'']] to the American sector.&lt;ref name=keegan-82-188/&gt; At the start of the campaign, ''Panzer-Lehr''  was one of the most powerful armoured formations in the German army, by this stage it had been reduced to a number of battlegroups and was no longer operational as a division.&lt;ref name="Forty29"&gt;Forty, p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Copp (2003), p. 86&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 July, Rommel's staff car was strafed by British fighters, severely injuring the Field Marshal and confining him to hospital.&lt;ref name=cawthorne120/&gt; Two days later he was replaced as Army Group B commander by Field Marshal Günther von Kluge.&lt;ref&gt;Wood, p. vii&lt;/ref&gt; Rommel never returned to Normandy; implicated in the [[20 July plot]] against Hitler, on 14 October he was forced to commit suicide.&lt;ref name=cawthorne121&gt;Cawthorne, p. 121&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Royal Engineers in Caen.jpg|thumb|upright=1.0|alt=A file of soldiers walking through a blasted cityscape; only a few buildings are standing|[[Royal Engineers]] move through the ruins of Caen, looking for mines and booby-traps, 10 July 1944.]]
Caen's partial capture allowed [[General (United States)|General]] [[Omar Bradley]], commander of the First US Army, to accelerate his plans for a breakout.&lt;ref name=cawthorne120/&gt; Shortly after Charnwood the US [[VII Corps (United States)|VII Corps]] attacked German positions in [[Saint-Lô]],&lt;ref name=VdV158&gt;Van der Vat, p. 158&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=DE339-41&gt;D'Este, pp. 339–341&lt;/ref&gt; which the 2nd SS Panzer Division had been ordered to "hold at all costs".&lt;ref name="Wood99" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wood, p. 100&lt;/ref&gt; On 18 July, after eight days of fighting during which 95 percent of the town was destroyed and VII Corps had more than 5,000 casualties,&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 249&lt;/ref&gt; Saint-Lô fell to the Americans.&lt;ref&gt;Van der Vat, p. 159&lt;/ref&gt;

The same day, the Second Army began [[Operation Goodwood]] with from {{nowrap|1,100–1,300 tanks}} in the largest armoured battle in British military history.&lt;ref name=VdV158/&gt; VIII Corps (Lieutenant-General [[Richard O'Connor]]) spearheaded the drive towards the Bourguébus Ridge with three armoured divisions, supported by I Corps. After a preliminary attack by 1,056 heavy bombers,&lt;ref&gt;Trew, pp. 71–72&lt;/ref&gt; elements of the [[11th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|11th]], [[Guards Armoured Division|Guards]] and 7th Armoured Division assaulted the positions of LXXXVI Corps north of Bourguébus&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2001) pp. 170–171&lt;/ref&gt; but despite early gains of around {{convert|12000|yd|km}}, strong resistance prevented VIII Corps taking the ridge. Simultaneously, [[Lieutenant-general (Canada)|Lieutenant General]] [[Guy Simonds]]'s newly activated [[II Canadian Corps]] launched an offensive on the Verrières Ridge, codenamed [[Operation Atlantic]].&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 357&lt;/ref&gt; II Corps ran into fierce opposition; during the [[Battle of Verrières Ridge|seven-day battle]] that followed the Canadians sustained 2,800 casualties. Verrières Ridge would remain in German hands until 8 August.&lt;ref&gt;Zuehlke, p. 168&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 296&lt;/ref&gt;

===Battle honours===
The British and Commonwealth system of [[battle honours]] recognises the battle by the award to 55 units of the honour ''Caen'', for participation in the capture of Caen between 4–18 July 1944. Awarded from 1956 to 1959, the recognition was accompanied by honours for taking part in Operation Charnwood. For participating in the capture of Caen between 8–9 July three units were awarded the honour ''Orne'', nine the honour ''The Orne'', and two the honour ''The Orne (Buron)''.&lt;ref&gt;Rodger, pp. 243–244&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bombing===
[[Max Hastings|Hastings]] wrote that the bombing came to be seen by many as "one of the most futile air attacks of the war" and Beevor called the attack a "disaster".&lt;ref name=hastings222/&gt;&lt;ref name="Beevor269"/&gt; Reynolds judged the results of the bombing as "pathetic" and D'Este wrote that the bombing hindered the Allied push into the city.&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds (2001), p. 153&lt;/ref&gt; Air Commodore E. J. Kingston-McCloughry and [[Solly Zuckerman, Baron Zuckerman|Solly Zuckerman]] conducted a survey and concluded that no targets of military value had been attacked, nor were there any gun positions, tanks or German dead in the target zone. They interviewed men of the 3rd Infantry Division, who were reportedly bewildered as to why the bombers had been employed.&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 315&lt;/ref&gt; The 3rd Division historian, wrote that in the wake of the air-raid the men

{{quotation|... for the first time for weeks breathed freely. The full support of the Air Force gave them full hearts ... and the men were encouraged.&lt;ref&gt;Scarfe, pp. 69–70&lt;/ref&gt;|Norman Scarfe}}

[[File:Britsoldiercaen.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.0|alt=A soldier holding the arm of an elderly lady in a debris-strewn street, with ruined buildings in the background|A British soldier helps an old woman through the ruins of Caen after its capture.]]
The Canadian Official Historian, C. P. Stacey wrote that several Canadian formations reported an increase in morale.&lt;ref name="stacey158"&gt;Stacey, p. 158&lt;/ref&gt; Wilmot wrote that the bombing was essential because it raised the morale of the Second Army and depressed that of the German defenders.&lt;ref name="Wilmot351"/&gt; A 21st Army Group intelligence report, based on the interrogation of German prisoners recorded that the raid was "decisive" and had apparently destroyed the headquarters of the Luftwaffe infantry regiment based north of Caen and deprived the German troops north of the city of ammunition and rations the following morning.&lt;ref name="stacey158"/&gt; Gray wrote that the bombing had an effect on the morale of both sides but that this was temporary.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2006), p. 166&lt;/ref&gt; [[Lionel Ellis|L. F. Ellis]], the British Official Historian, Trew and Badsey all wrote that the raid was intended to cut off German reinforcements from the battlefield and hinder an attempt to withdraw south of the Orne river.&lt;ref name="Ellis313"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Trew37"/&gt; Stacey wrote that it was "obvious and desirable" that for maximum advantage, the Allied ground forces should have advanced on the heels of the attack.&lt;ref name="stacey158"/&gt; Gray concluded that no-one "can[not] satisfactorily answer the question 'why'" the city was bombed.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2006), p. 167&lt;/ref&gt;

Analysis by [[Operations research#Second World War|Operational Research Section Number 2]] (ORS2) concluded that the bombing of the first aiming point north-west of Caen was accurate, finding that the centre of the 90 percent zone (the area where 90 percent of the bombs fell) was {{convert|200|–|300|yd|m}} east of the aiming point, with some spillage to the south and west. Examination of the area after its capture, indicated some destruction of German equipment, including the wreckage of ten of the forty trucks believed to be in the area at the time of the raid. The 48 hours that elapsed between the bombing and the Allied occupation of the area, allowed the Germans time to recover from any shock and disorientation and to salvage some damaged equipment. Examination of the second aiming point, "Northern Caen", failed to reveal a 90 percent zone but it was noted that the obstructive effect of bombing a suburb was significant and had caused substantial delays to vehicles of both sides, by cratering and blocking roads. ORS2 concluded that the success of Charnwood owed little to the bombing and made recommendations including changing to instantly fused bombs, dropping larger numbers of smaller anti-personnel bombs and rapidly following-up a bombardment with ground forces to take advantage of its main effect, which was the temporary suppression of German will to resist. In Operation Goodwood, [[Operation Bluecoat]], [[Operation Cobra]], [[Operation Totalize]] and [[Operation Tractable]] the 21st Army Group exploited better the effect of preparatory attacks by strategic bombers by following-up the attacks immediately.&lt;ref&gt;Copp (2000), pp. 71–77&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Destroyedcaen.jpg|thumb|upright=1.0|alt=A scenic cityscape showing destroyed and badly-damaged buildings|The aftermath of the bombing of Caen on 7 July 1944.]]
The British initially announced that around 6,000 civilians had been killed during the air-raid and a Soviet war correspondent attached to the 21st Army Group, Lieutenant-Colonel Kraminov, put the figure as high as 22,000, a claim that was used by French communists in post-war anti-British propaganda.&lt;ref name="Beevor269"&gt;Beevor, p. 269&lt;/ref&gt; It was later found that 300–400 civilians were killed in the raid.&lt;ref name="Stacey160"&gt;Stacey, p. 160&lt;/ref&gt; Caen citizens were relieved and provided their liberators with a welcome that the troops found very moving; French accounts of the time claim that "All [of] Caen was in the streets to greet them". Although Ellis called the French welcome "pathetic", no Allied unit recorded any complaints about the reception they were given.&lt;ref name="Ellis316"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Trew44"&gt;Trew, p. 44&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Stacey163"&gt;Stacey, p. 163&lt;/ref&gt; Stacey wrote that the populace were "particularly delighted to find their city freed in part by men from Canada".&lt;ref name="Stacey163"/&gt; Beevor wrote that most of the population were numb from the shock and quoted a British soldier who recalled that "most ... women were crying, grief-stricken and anguished".&lt;ref name="Beevor273"/&gt; As early as 12 June, the French Resistance had sent messengers to the British, informing them that refugees were gathering in the areas around the [[Abbaye-aux-Hommes]] and the Hôpital du Bon Sauveur and requested that these locations not to be bombed; British assurances were given and these locations were nearly untouched.&lt;ref name="Stacey163"/&gt; Gray wrote that after the war, the city population regarded itself as being [[martyr]]ed, which could be seen on the war memorial.&lt;ref&gt;Buckley (2006), pp. 158, 168&lt;/ref&gt;

==Subsequent operations==

===Operation Jupiter===
{{Main|Operation Jupiter (1944)}}

[[File:Jupitermortar.jpg|thumb|left|upright=1.0|alt=A group of soldiers crouching beside a roadside hedge|Soldiers of the 43rd (Wessex) Infantry Division take cover from German mortar fire during ''Jupiter'']]
On 10 July, the [[43rd (Wessex) Infantry Division]] attacked the positions of the 10th SS Panzer Division to the southwest of Caen on [[Hill 112]].&lt;ref name="Hasting223"/&gt; Preceded by a two-day bombardment that included support from naval vessels and [[Hawker Typhoon]]s, the assault was designed to threaten Caen from the west and push back the 10th SS Panzer Division, securing an avenue for future offensives.&lt;ref name=cawthorne120/&gt; The 43rd Wessex began their assault at dawn on 10 July, supported by two armoured brigades.&lt;ref name=copp106/&gt; By 08:00, British tanks and infantry were engaged with the 10th SS Panzer and "well up" the slopes of Hill 112. Eterville was taken around mid-morning; as the 4th Armoured Brigade and 43rd Wessex pressed their attack, Panzer Group West commander General Eberbach insisted that "Hill 112 is the pivotal point of the whole position West of Caen, and must therefore be held".&lt;ref name="Hasting223"/&gt;&lt;ref name=copp106/&gt;

The [[102nd SS Heavy Panzer Battalion]] and the 1st SS Panzer Division were committed to its defence.&lt;ref name=copp106/&gt; The 4th Armoured Brigade reached the summit but in the evening were counter-attacked by remnants of the 1st and 12th SS Panzer Divisions.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 225&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 226&lt;/ref&gt; The British offensive resumed the following day with the support of anti-tank regiments from the Second Army; these had heavy losses in a counter-attack by the 102nd SS Heavy Panzer Battalion.&lt;ref name=hastings227&gt;Hastings, p. 227&lt;/ref&gt; Hill 112 was briefly taken by a battalion of the [[Duke of Cornwall's Light Infantry]], only to be lost to further German counter-attacks in the late afternoon.&lt;ref name=hastings227/&gt; By the evening of 11 July, with both sides exhausted and having suffered heavily the offensive had reached a stalemate.&lt;ref name=copp106/&gt; The 43rd (Wessex) Infantry Division and its supporting armour had suffered two thousand casualties in the two days of fighting.&lt;ref name="Hasting223"/&gt;

{{Commons category|Operation Charnwood}}

==References==

===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|group=nb}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|20em}}

==Bibliography==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book|first=Antony|last=Beevor|authorlink=Antony Beevor|title=D-Day: The Battle for Normandy |publisher=Viking |year=2009 |isbn=978-0-670-88703-3}}
* {{Cite book|first=John|last=Buckley|authorlink=John Buckley (historian)|title =British Armour in the Normandy Campaign 1944|publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis|year=2006|origyear=2004|isbn=978-0-415-40773-1|oclc=154699922}}
* {{Cite book|first=|last=|authorlink=|editor-last=Buckley|editor-first=John|title=The Normandy Campaign 1944: Sixty Years on|publisher=Routledge|year=2007|origyear=2006|isbn=978-0-415-44942-7}}
* {{Cite book |first=Nigel |last=Cawthorne |authorlink=Nigel Cawthorne |title=Victory in World War II |location=London |publisher=Capella |year=2005 |origyear=|isbn=978-1-84193-351-1|oclc=222830404}}
* {{Cite thesis |first=Roger |last=Cirillo |authorlink=|title=The Market Garden Campaign: Allied Operational Command in Northwest Europe, 1944 |type=PhD |publisher=Cranfield University: College of Defence Technology, Department of Defence Management and Security Analysis |year=2001 |url=http://ethos.bl.uk/OrderDetails.do?did=1&amp;uin=uk.bl.ethos.396504|oclc=59172331}}
* {{Cite book| first=Lloyd|last=Clark|authorlink=Lloyd Clark| series=Battle Zone Normandy| title=Operation Epsom|publisher=The History Press | year=2004 | isbn=978-0-7509-3008-6}}
* {{Cite book| first=Major Ewart W|last=Clay| title=The path of the 50th: The story of the 50th (Northumbrian) Division in the Second World War|location=Aldershot|publisher=[[Gale and Polden]]| year=1950| oclc=12049041}}
* {{Cite book| editor-first=Terry|editor-last=Copp|authorlink=| series=| title=Montgomery's Scientists: Operational Research in Northwest Europe. The work of No.2 Operational Research Section with 21 Army Group June 1944 to July 1945|location=Waterloo Ontario|publisher=LCMSDS| year=2000 |isbn=978-0-9697955-9-9}}
* {{Cite book| first=Terry|last=Copp|authorlink=Terry Copp| series=| title=Fields of Fire: The Canadians in Normandy|location=Toronto|publisher=University of Toronto Press| year=2004| origyear=2003| isbn=978-0-8020-3780-0|oclc=56329119}}
* {{Cite book |first=Terry |last=Copp |title=A Nation at War, 1939–1945: essays from Legion Magazine |location=Waterloo, Ont |publisher=Laurier Centre for Military, Strategic and Disarmament Studies |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-96887-505-6}}
* {{Cite book |first=Ian |last=Daglish |authorlink=Ian Daglish |series=Over the Battlefield |title=Operation Goodwood |location=Barnsley |publisher=Pen &amp; Sword |year=2005 |isbn=978-1-84415-153-0 |oclc=68762230}}
* {{cite journal|last=Delaney|first=Douglas|title=A Quiet Man of Influence: General Sir John Crocker|year=2007|volume=85|issue=343|pages=185–207|journal=[[Society for Army Historical Research|J. Soc. Army. Hist. Res.]]|issn=0037-9700|jstor=44231490}}
* {{Cite book|first1=Major L. F. | last1=Ellis |authorlink1=Lionel Ellis |first2=Captain G. R. G. |last2=with Allen |first3=Lieutenant-Colonel A. E. |last3=Warhurst |first4=Air Chief-Marshal Sir James |last4=Robb |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=J. R. M. |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |series=[[History of the Second World War#United Kingdom Military Series|History of the Second World War United Kingdom Military Series]] |title=Victory in the West: The Battle of Normandy |volume=I |location=Uckfield, East Sussex|publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |year=2004 |origyear=1st. pub. [[HMSO]], 1962 |isbn=978-1-84574-058-0 |oclc=276814706 |lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{Cite book|first=Carlo|last=D'Este|authorlink=Carlo D'Este |title=Decision in Normandy: The Real Story of Montgomery and the Allied Campaign|location=London|publisher=Penguin |year=2004 |origyear=1983 |isbn=978-0-14-101761-7 |oclc=44772546}}
* {{Cite book| first1=Ken|last1=Ford|first2=Howard|last2=Gerrard (Illustrator)|authorlink=| series=D-Day 1944| title=Gold and Juno Beaches |publisher=Osprey Publishing| year=2002| origyear= | isbn=978-1-84176-368-2}}
* {{Cite book |first=George |last=Forty |authorlink=George Forty |series=Battle Zone Normandy |title=Villers Bocage |publisher=Sutton Publishing |year=2004 |isbn=978-0-7509-3012-3}}
* {{Cite book |first=Stephen Ashley |last=Hart |authorlink= |title=Colossal Cracks: Montgomery's 21st Army Group in Northwest Europe, 1944–45|location=Mechanicsburg |publisher=Stackpole Books |year=2007 |origyear=2000 |isbn=978-0-8117-3383-0 |oclc=70698935}}
* {{Cite book| first=Max|last=Hastings|authorlink=Max Hastings |title=Overlord: D-Day and the Battle for Normandy |location=New York |publisher=Vintage Books USA |edition=Reprint |year=2006|origyear=1985 |isbn=978-0-307-27571-4 |oclc=62785673}}
* {{Cite book| first=Major J. J. |last=How [[Military Cross|MC]] |title=Hill 112: Cornerstone of the Normandy Campaign |location=Winnipeg, Canada |publisher=[[J.J. Fedorowicz Publishing]] |year=2004 |origyear=1984 |isbn=978-0-921991-81-6}}
* {{Cite book| first=G. S. |last=Jackson |author2=Staff, 8 Corps |title=8 Corps: Normandy to the Baltic |location=Smalldale |publisher=MLRS Books | year=2006 |origyear=1945 |isbn=978-1-905696-25-3}}
* {{Cite book |first=John |last=Keegan |authorlink=John Keegan |title=Six Armies in Normandy: From D-Day to the Liberation at Paris |location=London |publisher=Pimlico |year=2004 |origyear=1982 |isbn=978-1-84413-739-8 |oclc=56462089}}
* {{Cite book|first=Hubert|last=Meyer|author-link=Hubert Meyer|series=|title=The 12th SS: The History of the Hitler Youth Panzer Division |volume=I |location=Mechanicsburg |publisher=Stackpole Books |year=2005 |origyear=1994 |isbn=978-0-8117-3198-0}}
* {{Cite book |first=Hubert |last=Meyer |title=The 12th SS: The History of the Hitler Youth Panzer Division |volume=II |location=Mechanicsburg |publisher=Stackpole |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-8117-3199-7}}
* {{Cite book |first=Michael |last=Reynolds |authorlink= |title=Steel Inferno: I SS Panzer Corps in Normandy |publisher=Da Capo Press |year=2001 |origyear=1997 |isbn=978-1-885119-44-5}}
* {{Cite book| first=Michael|last=Reynolds|title=Sons of the Reich: The History of II SS Panzer Corps in Normandy, Arnhem, the Ardennes and on the Eastern Front |location=Havertown |publisher=Casemate Publishers and Book Distributors |year= 2002 |isbn=978-0-9711709-3-3 |oclc=50208471}}
* {{Cite book |first=Reginald H.|last=Roy|title=1944: The Canadians in Normandy |location=Toronto |publisher=Macmillan of Canada |year=1984 |isbn=978-0-7715-9796-1 |oclc=10942225}}
* {{Cite book |first=Norman |last=Scarfe |authorlink= |title=Assault Division: A History of the 3rd Division from the Invasion of Normandy to the Surrender of Germany |location=Stroud, Gloucestershire |publisher=Spellmount |year=2006 |origyear=1947 |isbn=978-1-86227-338-2}}
* {{Cite book |first1=Colonel Charles Perry |last1=Stacey |authorlink1=Charles Perry Stacey |last2=Bond |first2=Major C. C. J. |series=Official History of the Canadian Army in the Second World War |volume=III |title=The Victory Campaign: The Operations in North-West Europe 1944–1945 |publisher=The Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery Ottawa |year=1960 |oclc=256471407}}
* {{Cite book|first1=Alexander|last1=Swanston|first2=Malcolm|last2=Swanston|title=The Historical Atlas of World War II |location=London |publisher=Cartographica Press |year=2007 |isbn=978-1-84573-240-0 |oclc=83913300}}
* {{Cite book |first=Daniel |last=Taylor |title=Villers-Bocage Through the Lens |location=Old Harlow |publisher=Battle of Britain International |year=1999 |isbn=978-1-870067-07-2 |oclc=43719285}}
* {{Cite book| first1=Simon|last1=Trew|first2=Stephen|last2=Badsey|series=Battle Zone Normandy| title=Battle for Caen|location=Stroud|publisher=Sutton Publishing|year=2004|origyear=|isbn=978-0-7509-3010-9|oclc=56759608}}
* {{Cite book| first=Dan|last=Van Der Vat|authorlink=Dan van der Vat|title=D-Day; The Greatest Invasion, A People's History |location=Toronto|publisher=Madison Press Limited |year=2003 |isbn=978-1-55192-586-8|oclc=51290297}}
* {{Cite book|first=Andrew|last=Williams|authorlink=Andrew Williams (novelist)|title=D-Day to Berlin|location=London|publisher=[[Hodder &amp; Stoughton]]|year=2004|isbn=978-0-340-83397-1|oclc=60416729|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/ddaytoberlin0000will}}
* {{Cite book |first=Chester |last=Wilmot |authorlink=Chester Wilmot |author2=Christopher Daniel McDevitt |title=The Struggle For Europe |location=Ware, Hertfordshire |publisher=Wordsworth Editions |year=1997 |origyear=1952 |isbn=978-1-85326-677-5 |oclc=39697844}}
* {{Cite book |first=James A. |last=Wood |title=Army of the West: The Weekly Reports of German Army Group B from Normandy to the West Wall |location=Mechanicsburg |publisher=Stackpole Books |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-8117-3404-2 |oclc=126229849}}
* {{Cite book|first=Mark|last=Zuehlke| title=The Canadian Military Atlas: Canada's Battlefields from the French and Indian Wars to Kosovo |location=Toronto and Niagara Falls, New York|publisher=Stoddart| year=2001 |isbn=978-0-7737-3289-6 |oclc=48680462}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.wwii.ca/page21.html Canada at War: The Battle of Caen, 1944]

{{World War II}}
{{Battle of Normandy}}
{{Portal bar|United Kingdom|War|Canada|World War II}}
{{Featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Charnwood}}
[[Category:1944 in France]]
[[Category:Airstrikes]]
[[Category:Battle for Caen]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:July 1944 events]]
[[Category:Military history of Canada during World War II]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|O]]</text><sha1>h7p73j2i3vg7pqw505jjnelxlxel479</sha1></revision></page>