<page><title>Battle of Cherbourg</title><ns>0</ns><id>5111566</id><revision><id>967118922</id><parentid>964861114</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-11T07:36:47Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Mathglot</username><id>2544398</id></contributor><comment>Add nav template {{Liberation of France}}.</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="11561" xml:space="preserve">{{other meanings}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Cherbourg
| partof      = the [[Operation Overlord|Normandy Campaign]], [[World War II]]
| image       = Cotentin Peninsula.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = Cotentin peninsula and port of Cherbourg, 1944
| date        = 6–30 June 1944
| place       = [[Normandy]], France
| result      = Allied victory
| combatant1  = {{Flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br&gt;{{Flag|United Kingdom}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[J. Lawton Collins]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Matthew Ridgway]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Friedrich Dollmann]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Karl-Wilhelm von Schlieben]]
| strength1   = unknown
| strength2   = 40,000
| casualties1 = 2,800 killed&lt;br&gt;5,700 missing&lt;br&gt;13,500 wounded&lt;br&gt;'''Total''':&lt;br&gt;22,000 
| casualties2 = 7,000-8,000 killed or missing&lt;br&gt;30,000 captured&lt;br&gt;'''Total''':&lt;br&gt;37,000-38,000 
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Normandy}}
}}

The '''Battle of Cherbourg''' was part of the [[Operation Overlord|Battle of Normandy]] during [[World War II]]. It was fought immediately after the successful [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[Normandy landings|landings on 6 June 1944]]. Allied troops, mainly [[United States Army|American]], isolated and captured the fortified port, which was considered vital to the [[Western Front (World War II)|campaign in Western Europe]], in a hard-fought, month-long campaign.

==Allied plans==
When they drew up their plans for the invasion of France, the Allied staff considered that it would be necessary to secure a deep-water port to allow reinforcements to be brought directly from the United States. (Without such a port, equipment packed for transit would first have to be unloaded at a port in Great Britain, unpacked, waterproofed and then reloaded onto landing craft to be transferred to France). [[Cherbourg-Octeville|Cherbourg]], at the end of the [[Cotentin Peninsula]], was the largest port accessible from the landings.

The Allied planners decided at first not to land directly on the Cotentin Peninsula, since this sector would be separated from the main Allied landings by the [[Douve River]] valley, which had been flooded by the [[Germany|Germans]] to deter [[Airborne forces|airborne]] landings. On being appointed overall land commander for the invasion in January 1944, [[British Army]] [[General (United Kingdom)|General]] [[Bernard Montgomery, 1st Viscount Montgomery of Alamein|Bernard Montgomery]] reinstated the landing on the Cotentin peninsula, partly to widen the front and therefore prevent the invaders becoming sealed into a narrow lodgement, but also to enable a rapid capture of Cherbourg.

==Landings==
[[File:Cherbourgair.jpg|thumb|left|An aerial photograph of Cherbourg taken in 1944]]
In the early hours of 6 June [[paratrooper]]s (the US [[82nd Airborne Division|82nd]] and [[101st Airborne Division]]s) landed at the base of the Cotentin Peninsula. Although the [[American airborne landings in Normandy|landings were scattered]], they nevertheless secured most of the routes by which the [[VII Corps (United States)|US VII Corps]] would advance from [[Utah Beach]]. The [[4th Infantry Division (United States)|US 4th Infantry Division]] landed on Utah Beach shortly after dawn with few casualties.

In the immediate aftermath of the landings the priority for the invasion forces at Utah Beach was to link up with the main Allied landings further east. On 9 June the 101st Airborne Division managed to cross the [[Douve river|Douve River valley]] and [[Battle of Carentan|captured Carentan]] the next day. After vicious house-to-house fighting during the [[Battle of Carentan]], the airborne troops were able to take the town, ensuring the Allies a continuous front. The front was maintained despite a German counterattack reinforced by armored units on the 13th, known as the [[Battle of Bloody Gulch]].
{{Clear}}

==Move across the Cotentin Peninsula==
[[File:Map10.jpg|thumb|German forces on the [[Cotentin Peninsula]] prior to [[Operation Overlord]]]]
This success allowed VII Corps to advance westwards to cut off the Cotentin Peninsula. An additional three infantry divisions had landed to reinforce the Corps. [[Major general (United States)|Major General]] [[J. Lawton Collins]], the Corps Commander, drove his troops hard, replacing units in the front lines or sacking officers if progress was slow.

The Germans facing VII Corps were a mix of regiments and battlegroups from several divisions, many of which had already suffered heavy casualties fighting the American airborne troops in the first days of the landings. Very few German armored or mobile troops could be sent to this part of the front because of the threat to [[Battle for Caen|Caen]] further east. Infantry reinforcements arrived only slowly. Tactically, the Germans' flooding of the Douve worked against them because it secured the Allied southern flank.{{Citation needed|date=October 2013}}

By 16 June there were no further natural obstacles in front of the American forces. The German command was in some confusion. [[Erwin Rommel]] and other commanders wished to withdraw their troops in good order into the [[Atlantic Wall]] fortifications of Cherbourg, where they could have withstood a siege for some time. [[Adolf Hitler]] demanded that they hold their present lines even though this risked disaster.

Late on 17 June Hitler agreed that the troops might withdraw but specified that they were to occupy a new, illogical defensive line, spanning the entire peninsula just south of Cherbourg. Rommel protested against this order, but he nevertheless dismissed General Farmbacher, commanding the [[LXXXIV Corps]], who he thought was trying to circumvent it.

==Assault on Cherbourg==
[[File:Canoncherbourg.jpg|thumb|A German gun emplacement]]

On 18 June the [[9th Infantry Division (United States)|US 9th Infantry Division]] reached the west coast of the peninsula, isolating the Cherbourg garrison from any potential reinforcements. Within 24 hours, the [[4th Infantry Division (United States)|4th Infantry]], 9th and [[79th Infantry Division (United States)|79th Infantry Divisions]] were driving north on a broad front. There was little opposition on the western side of the peninsula and on the eastern side, the exhausted defenders around [[Montebourg]] collapsed. Several large caches of [[V-1 flying bomb]]s were discovered by the Americans in addition to a [[V-2 rocket]] installation at [[Brix, Manche|Brix]].

In two days, the American divisions were within striking distance of Cherbourg. The garrison commander, Lieutenant General [[Karl-Wilhelm von Schlieben]], had 21,000 men but many of these were hastily drafted naval personnel or from labour units.{{Citation needed|date=October 2013}} The fighting troops who had retreated to Cherbourg (including the remnants of von Schlieben's own division, the [[709th Static Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|709th]]), were tired and disorganised. Food, fuel and ammunition were short. The [[Luftwaffe]] dropped a few supplies, but these were mostly items such as [[Iron Cross]]es, intended to bolster the garrison's morale.{{Citation needed|date=October 2013}} Nevertheless, von Schlieben rejected a summons to surrender and began carrying out demolitions to deny the port to the Allies.

Collins launched a general assault on 22 June. Resistance was stiff at first, but the Americans slowly cleared the Germans from their bunkers and concrete pillboxes. Allied naval ships [[Bombardment of Cherbourg|bombarded fortifications near the city]] on 25 June. On 26 June, the British elite force [[No. 30 Commando]] also known as 30 Assault Unit launched an assault on Octeville – a suburb to the south west of Cherbourg. This was the location of the Kriegsmarine naval intelligence HQ at Villa Meurice which the Commandos captured along with 20 officers and 500 men. On the same day the 79th Division captured Fort du Roule, which dominated the city and its defenses. This finished any organised defense. Von Schlieben was captured. The harbor fortifications and the arsenal surrendered on 29 June, after a ruse by Allied officers, Capt Blazzard and [[Olin E. Teague|Col Teague]], who convinced the German officers to surrender the peninsula, bluffing about their manpower and ordnance. Some German troops cut off outside the defenses held out until 1 July.

==Aftermath==
[[File:Liberation de Cherbourg le maire felicite les americains.jpg|thumb|The mayor of Cherbourg, Paul Renault, thanks General Collins for liberating the city.]]
The Germans had so thoroughly wrecked and mined the port of Cherbourg  that Hitler awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross|Knight's Cross]] to Rear Admiral [[Walter Hennecke]] the day after he surrendered for "a feat unprecedented in the annals of coastal defense."{{sfn|Harrison|1951|p=441}} The port was not brought into limited use until the middle of August; although the first ships were able to use the harbor in late July. Nevertheless, the Germans had suffered a major defeat as a result of a rapid Allied build up on their western flank and Hitler's rigid orders. General [[Friedrich Dollmann]], commanding the [[7th Army (Wehrmacht)|German Seventh Army]], died on 28 June, having just been informed of a [[court martial]] pending as a result of the capture of Cherbourg, reportedly from a heart attack but possibly by suicide by poisoning.{{citation needed|date=June 2020}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Harrison|1951}}
|series=United States Army in World War II: The European Theater of Operations |title=Cross-Channel Attack |last=Harrison |first=Gordon A. |authorlink= |year=1951 |publisher=[[Office of the Chief of Military History]], Department of the Army |location=Washington, DC |edition=1993 |url=http://www.history.army.mil/html/books/007/7-4-1/CMH_Pub_7-4-1.pdf |accessdate=9 June 2014 |oclc=606012173}}
* [[Wilmot, Chester]]. ''The Struggle for Europe'', Hertfordshire, United Kingdom: Wordsworth Editions Limited, 1997. {{ISBN|1-85326-677-9}}.

{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{Cite book |url=http://www.history.army.mil/BOOKS/WWII/utah/utah.htm |title=Utah Beach to Cherbourg |publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]] |id=CMH Pub 100-12 |year=1990 |series=American Forces in Action |origyear=1948}}
* {{Cite book |url=http://battlestory.org/index.php?p=1_115_-D-Day-Doctor-s-Diary |title=Diary, January 29, 1944 To July 17, 1944, Walter E. Marchand, Capt. M.C., Bn. Surgeon with the 4th Infantry Division at Utah Beach |year=1944 |access-date=June 7, 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130728214911/http://battlestory.org/index.php?p=1_115_-D-Day-Doctor-s-Diary |archive-date=July 28, 2013 |url-status=dead }}

{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Portal|World War II}}
* [http://www.historyofwar.org/articles/battles_cherbourg.html History of War, Cherbourg, 1944]

{{World War II}}
{{Liberation of France}}
{{Battle of Normandy}}

{{coord|49|38|20|N|1|36|58|W|region:FR_source:kolossus-eswiki|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cherbourg, Battle of}}
[[Category:1944 in France]]
[[Category:Operation Overlord]]
[[Category:Cherbourg-Octeville]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:History of Manche]]
[[Category:June 1944 events]]</text><sha1>3tlfc0kwnub9rawrilh51fqgn446nt4</sha1></revision></page>