<page><title>Battle of Saint-Lô</title><ns>0</ns><id>48528505</id><revision><id>967119278</id><parentid>962111818</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-11T07:40:52Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Mathglot</username><id>2544398</id></contributor><comment>Add nav template {{Liberation of France}}.</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="10587" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Saint-Lô
|partof= the [[Operation Overlord|Normandy Campaign]], [[World War II]]
|image=Saint-Lo 1944 - Capitale des Ruines - couleurs.jpg
|image_size=300px
|caption=Saint-Lô, 95% destroyed after the 1944 bombardments, known as ''The Capital of Ruins''.
|combatant1={{flag|United States|1912}}
|combatant2={{flag|Nazi Germany|name=Germany|1935}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Charles H. Corlett]] &lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Charles H. Gerhardt]] &lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Leland Hobbs]] &lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Paul W. Baade]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} [[Dietrich Kraiß]] &lt;br /&gt; {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} [[Eugen Meindl]] &lt;br /&gt; {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} [[Otto Baum]] 
|place=[[Saint-Lô]], [[France]]
|date=July 7–19, 1944
|result=Allied victory
| casualties1 = For the period July 7–22&lt;br&gt; 29th Infantry Division: 3,706 &lt;br&gt; 30th Infantry Division: 3,934 &lt;br&gt; 35th Infantry Division: 2,437 &lt;br&gt; Total XIX Corps: 11,000+
| casualties2 = Unknown
| casualties3 = 352 French civilians&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://beaucoudray.free.fr/bombardements.htm|title=Les bombardements de Saint-Lô|website=beaucoudray.free.fr|access-date=2018-05-26|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120627053113/http://beaucoudray.free.fr/bombardements.htm|archive-date=2012-06-27|url-status=live|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Normandy}}
}}

The '''Battle of [[Saint-Lô]]''' is one of the three conflicts in the {{Interlanguage link multi|Battle of the Hedgerows|fr|3=Bataille des Haies}}, which took place between July 7–19, 1944, just before [[Operation Cobra]]. Saint-Lô had fallen to Germany in 1940, and, after the [[Invasion of Normandy]], the Americans targeted the city, as it served as a strategic crossroads. American bombardments caused heavy damage (up to 95% of the city was destroyed) and a high number of casualties, which resulted in the martyr city being called "The Capital of Ruins", popularized in a [[The Capital of the Ruins|report]] by [[Samuel Beckett]].

==Background==
{{main|Battle of France}}
[[FILE:Bocagenormandy.jpg|thumb|right|300px|Front lines shortly before the battle]]
France was invaded in 1940 and the [[7th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|7th Panzer Division]], commanded by [[Erwin Rommel]], entered [[Normandy]], with the objective of capturing [[Cherbourg Harbor]]. Saint-Lô fell under German control on the night of June 17, 1940. During the occupation, the statue of ''la Laitière normande'' (the [[Normans|Norman]] milkmaid), created by [[Arthur Le Duc]] was dismantled and melted down to make cannons, despite opposition from local politicians.

In 1943, the Germans began digging an underground hospital, which remains today, using the slave labor of the [[Service du travail obligatoire|STO]].

A German soldier was shot in January 1944, and many Saint-Lô residents were detained. The movie theater, theater, and bars were closed, radios were confiscated, and the curfew was moved to 8 p.m.&lt;ref&gt;Source: Monsieur Mignon Jean, Saint-Lô&lt;/ref&gt;

==American bombardment==
Due to its strategic importance as a crossroads, a bombardment by the Americans, focusing on the railway station and the power plant,&lt;ref name="Nor44"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://normandie44.canalblog.com/archives/2014/04/12/29649471.html|title=Normandie-1944, L'été de la Liberté - La Campagne 7 juin/25 août - La Bataille de Saint-Lô.|publisher=|access-date=2015-11-17|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151119170725/http://normandie44.canalblog.com/archives/2014/04/12/29649471.html|archive-date=2015-11-19|url-status=live|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; began on the night of June 6, and lasted into the morning of June 7. The objective was to cut off German reinforcements in [[Brittany]] from the front.

Warning leaflets were dropped the day before, but high winds dispersed them to neighboring communities, failing to alert local residents. Over two hundred prisoners were killed at the local prison, including seventy-six imprisoned French patriots (all that remains of the prison today is the gate).

&lt;gallery widths="200px" heights="160px"&gt;
File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1984-043-03, Frankreich, St. Lô, Zerstörungen.jpg|Saint-Lô after U.S. bombing, July 1944
File:Saint-Lô Railway station destroyed.jpg|Saint-Lô Train Station ruins
File:Saint-Lô - Porte de la prison.jpg|The old prison gate
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==The capital of ruins==
[[File:Photograph of the Flag-Draped Body of Major Thomas D. Howie on the Rubble of the St. Lo Cathedral - NARA - 12518083.jpg|right|thumb|Major Howie's flag-draped body on the cathedral rubble]]
The task of taking control of Saint-Lô was entrusted to the [[XIX Corps (United States)|XIX Corps]] of the [[First United States Army]], under [[Charles H. Corlett|General Charles H. Corlett]]. As of July 15, 1944, the corps included:

* The [[29th Infantry Division (United States)|29th Infantry Division]], located on the Bayeux road from [[La Luzerne]] to [[Saint-André-de-l'Épine]] and moving southwest into the city. It was commanded by Major General [[Charles H. Gerhardt]].
* The [[30th Infantry Division (United States)|30th Infantry Division]], located on the road to [[Périers, Manche|Périers]] to the west of Saint-Lô, near [[Le Mesnil-Durand]], commanded by Major General [[Leland S. Hobbs]].
* The [[35th Infantry Division (United States)|35th Infantry Division]], located on the [[Isigny-le-Buat|Isigny]] road and fighting south to Saint-Lô in a line extending from [[Pont-Hébert]] to the vicinity of Hill 122, commanded by Major General [[Paul W. Baade]].

Opposing them, the German army had two divisions protecting the Saint-Lô front:

* The [[352nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|352nd Infantry Division]], commanded by ''Generalleutnant'' [[Dietrich Kraiß]].
* The 3rd Division of the [[2nd Parachute Corps (Germany)|2nd Parachute Corps]], commanded by ''General der Fallschirmtruppe'' [[Eugen Meindl]].

===The 29th Infantry Division enters the city===

The 29th Infantry Division attacked through the hedgerows to the northeast sector of Saint-Lô, near the [[Madeleine (river)|Madeleine]] river, taking heavy casualties. On July 15, the 1st Battalion of the [[116th Infantry Regiment (United States)|116th Infantry Regiment]], led by Major Sidney Bingham (called the "lost battalion"), unwittingly advanced ahead of other division elements and found itself isolated 1,000 yards east of Saint-Lô for an entire day without ammunition and with little food. They had 25 wounded, with only three nurses, and were surrounded by German forces. Planes were called in to drop [[blood plasma|plasma]]. Martainville hill was continuously showered by German artillery. On July 17, the 3rd Battalion, 116th Infantry, under [[Thomas D. Howie|Major Thomas D. Howie]], joined up with the "lost battalion" around 4:30 in the morning. Hidden by dense vegetation, the 3rd Battalion had orders not to return enemy fire, and use only their bayonets. The mission was successful, but Howie was fatally wounded by a mortar shell explosion. Their position was then heavily attacked, preventing any further movement that day.

On July 17, Captain William Puntenney, Major Howie's [[executive officer]], requested artillery and air support to disperse the German troops. Short of munitions, still at the crossroads of the Madeleine, they found themselves at a mine depot, abandoned by the Germans. Meanwhile, the [[115th Infantry Regiment]] passed through [[La Luzerne]], deploying at the bottom of the Dollée Valley. On July 18, a company from the 116th established position along the Madeleine and the Germans retreated west to [[Rampan]]. An operations group was placed under the direction of General [[Norman Cota]] to form Task Force C. Around 3:00&amp;nbsp;p.m., the tanks along the road to Isigny were followed by ranks of soldiers. They fought their way into the Bascule district of Saint-Lô, near the Saint-Croix (Holy Cross) church.

When Major Howie died of wounds, room was needed in the ambulance for the living wounded, and his body was placed on the hood of the lead jeep, symbolically making him the first American soldier to enter the city. His body was then placed on some rubble and draped in a flag, in a photo that was widely circulated. [[Andy Rooney]], who witnessed the event as a ''[[Stars and Stripes (newspaper)|Stars and Stripes]]'' reporter, called this "one of the truly heartwarming and emotional scenes of a gruesome and frightful war".

==Legacy==
In memory of this battle, the name of Saint-Lô was given to an [[escort carrier]] of the [[United States Navy]] on October 10, 1944, the [[USS St. Lo (CVE-63)|USS ''St. Lo'' (CVE-63)]]. The ship suffered a dismal fate: after entering service as the ''Midway'' on October 23, 1943 (having been renamed from ''Chapin Bay'' while being built), it was sunk just a year later, on October 25, 1944, during the [[Battle of Leyte Gulf]], by a [[kamikaze]] attack.

In 1946, [[Samuel Beckett]] wrote a piece of reportage called "[[The Capital of the Ruins]]", in which he referred to the city as having been "bombed out of existence in one night". On 2 June 1948, the city was decorated with both the [[Legion of Honour]] and the [[Croix de Guerre]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://memorialdormans.free.fr/CommunesCroixDeGuerre39-45.pdf|title=Communes décorées de la croix de guerre 1939-1945|language=fr|trans-title=Communes decorated with the Croix de Guerre 1939–1945|work=Mémorial Dormans|accessdate=11 December 2015|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304023227/http://memorialdormans.free.fr/CommunesCroixDeGuerre39-45.pdf|archive-date=2016-03-04|url-status=live|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A monument to Major Howie, the "Major of St-Lô", was erected in the city (see photo on the right), near the cemetery.

&lt;gallery widths="200px" heights="160px"&gt;
Image:USS St. Lo Cve63.jpg|[[USS St. Lo (CVE-63)|USS ''St. Lo'']]
Image:Monument Major Howie.jpg|[[Thomas D. Howie|Major Howie]] Memorial Monument
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
* {{Portal-inline|World War II}}

==References==
{{Reflist|refs = The Clay Pigeons of St. Lo by Glover S. Johns Jr.}}

==External links==
{{commons category}}

{{World War II}}
{{Liberation of France}}
{{Battle of Normandy}}

{{coord missing|France}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Saint-Lo}}
[[Category:1944 in France]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Operation Overlord]]
[[Category:July 1944 events]]</text><sha1>gwwbz59km37efgq9m2858d2f01mmde6</sha1></revision></page>