<page><title>Battle of Gazala</title><ns>0</ns><id>1067633</id><revision><id>961027885</id><parentid>958496453</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-06T07:19:29Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Mathglot</username><id>2544398</id></contributor><comment>/* External links */ Add nav template {{French resistance}}.</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="62230" xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=September 2019}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Battle of Gazala
| partof = the [[Western Desert Campaign]] of the [[Second World War]]
| image = File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-784-0246-22A, Nordafrika, Rommel im Befehlsfahrzeug "Greif".jpg
| image_size = 250px
| caption = Panzer III and Rommel's command vehicle in the western desert at the time of the Gazala battles.
| date = 26 May – 21 June 1942 (25 days)
| place = [[Gazala]], near [[Tobruk]], [[Libya]]
| coordinates = {{Coord|32|08|43|N|23|21|27|E|type:event_region:LY|display=inline,title}}
| result = Axis victory
| combatant1 = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| combatant2 = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
* {{flagcountry|British India}}
{{flagcountry|Union of South Africa}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Free French Forces|name=Free French}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United States|1912}}{{efn|A volunteer squadron of three [[M3 Grant]]s from the American [[1st Armored Division (United States)|1st Armored Division]] under Major [[Henry Cabot Lodge Jr.]] were placed under British command and achieved a number of victories during fighting near Acroma on 11 June.{{sfn|Yeide|2006|p=52}} ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' recorded these as the first Americans to engage German land forces in the war.{{sfn|Time|1942|nopp=y}}}}
| commander1 = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Ettore Bastico]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Erwin Rommel]]
| commander2 = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Claude Auchinleck]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Neil Ritchie]]
| units1 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Deutsches Afrika Korps|Afrika Korps]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[XX Motorised Corps (Italy)|XX Corps]]
| units2 = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]]
| strength1 = 90,000 men &lt;small&gt;(30,000 German, 60,000 Italian)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;560 tanks &lt;small&gt;(228 Italian)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;542 aircraft
| strength2 = 110,000 men&lt;br /&gt;843 tanks&lt;br /&gt;604 aircraft
| casualties1 = '''German'''&lt;br&gt;3,360 men &lt;small&gt;(26 May – 24 June)&lt;/small&gt;{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=274}}{{efn|300 officers, 570 NCOs and 2,490 other ranks.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=274}}}}&lt;br&gt;400 armoured vehicles damaged or destroyed&lt;br&gt;'''Italian'''&lt;br&gt;3,000 men&lt;br&gt;125 tanks&lt;br&gt;44 armoured cars&lt;br&gt;39 guns&lt;br&gt;74 anti-tank guns&lt;br&gt;450 motor vehicles
| casualties2 = 50,000 killed, wounded or captured&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(incl. {{circa|33,000}} prisoners at Tobruk)&lt;/small&gt;{{efn|19,000 British, 10,720 South African and 2,500 Indian troops.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=274}}}}&lt;br&gt;1,188 armoured vehicles damaged or destroyed
| notes  = Many damaged tanks were returned to action by both sides.
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Western Desert}}|
}}

The '''Battle of Gazala''' (near the modern town of {{lang|ar|Ayn al Ghazālah}} عين الغزالة) was fought during the [[Western Desert Campaign]] of the [[Second World War]], west of the port of [[Tobruk]] in [[Libya]], from 26 May to 21 June 1942. [[Axis powers|Axis]] troops of the {{lang|de|[[Panzer Army Africa|Panzerarmee Afrika]]}} ({{lang|de|[[Generaloberst]]}} [[Erwin Rommel]]) consisting of [[Nazi Germany|German]] and [[Kingdom of Italy|Italian]] units fought the British [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]] ([[General (United Kingdom)|General]] Sir [[Claude Auchinleck]], also [[Commander-in-chief|Commander-in-Chief]] [[Middle East Command|Middle East]]) composed mainly of British Commonwealth, Indian and Free French troops.

The Axis troops made a decoy attack in the north as the main attack moved round the southern flank of the Gazala position. Unexpected resistance at the south end of the line around the [[Bir Hakeim]] box by the [[Free French]] garrison, left {{lang|de|Panzerarmee Afrika}} with a long and vulnerable supply route around the Gazala Line. Rommel retired to a defensive position backing onto Allied minefields (the Cauldron), forming a base in the midst of the British defences. Italian engineers lifted mines from the west side of the minefields to create a supply route through to the Axis side.

Operation Aberdeen, an attack by the Eighth Army to finish off the {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}}, was poorly co-ordinated and [[defeat in detail|defeated in detail]]; many British tanks were lost and the {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} regained the initiative. The Eighth Army withdrew from the Gazala Line and the Axis troops overran Tobruk in a day. Rommel pursued the Eighth Army into Egypt and forced it out of several defensive positions. The Battle of Gazala is considered the greatest victory of Rommel's career.

As both sides neared exhaustion, the Eighth Army checked the Axis advance at the [[First Battle of El Alamein]]. To support the Axis advance into Egypt, the planned attack on Malta ([[Operation Herkules]]) was postponed. The British were able to revive Malta as a base for attacks on Axis convoys to Libya, greatly complicating Axis supply difficulties at El Alamein.

==Background==

===Benghazi===

[[File:Rommel with his aides.jpg|thumb|upright|{{center|Field Marshal Erwin Rommel, with aides during the desert campaign. 1942}}]]
Following [[Operation Crusader]], in late 1941, the British Eighth Army had relieved Tobruk and driven the Axis forces from [[Cyrenaica]] to [[El Agheila]]. The Eighth Army advance of {{convert|800|km|mi|abbr=on}} over-stretched its supply lines and in January 1942, the Allies reduced the front line garrison for work on lines of communication and supply dumps, preparatory to another westwards advance against [[Tripolitania]]. The elimination of [[Force K]] from Malta, which ran into an Italian minefield off Tripoli in mid-December and the arrival of {{lang|de|Fliegerkorps}} II in Sicily, neutralised Allied air and naval forces in Malta, allowing more Axis supplies to reach Libya.{{sfn|Hinsley|1981|pp=324–325}} After a two-month delay, German and Italian forces in Libya began to receive supplies and reinforcements in men and tanks, which continued until the end of May, when {{lang|de|Fliegerkorps}} II was transferred to the Russian front.{{sfn|Hinsley|1981|pp=348, 418}}

While aware from signals intelligence of these reinforcements, GHQ in Cairo underestimated their significance and Axis fighting strength, having greatly exaggerated the casualties inflicted on the Axis during Operation Crusader.{{sfn|Hinsley|1981|pp=335–336}} In an appreciation made in January 1942, Auchinleck alluded to an Axis fighting strength of 35,000 men, when the true figure was about 80,000 (50,000 German and 30,000 Italian troops). The Eighth Army expected to be ready by February and GHQ Cairo believed that the Axis would be too weak and disorganised to mount a counter-offensive in the meantime.{{sfn|Hinsley|1981|pp=334, 330}} On 21 January, Rommel sent out three strong armoured columns to make a tactical reconnaissance. Finding only the thinnest of screens, Rommel changed his reconnaissance into an offensive, recaptured [[Benghazi]] on 28 January and [[Timimi]] on 3 February. By 6 February, the Allies had fallen back to a line from [[Gazala]] to [[Bir Hakeim]], a few miles west of [[Tobruk]], from which the Italo-Germans had retired seven weeks before. The Allies had {{nowrap|1,309 casualties}} from 21 January, lost {{nowrap|42 tanks}} knocked out, another {{nowrap|30 through}} damage and breakdowns and forty field guns.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 1960, pp. 139–153&lt;/ref&gt;

===Gazala line===

Between Gazala and Timimi, just west of Tobruk, the Eighth Army was able to concentrate its forces sufficiently to turn and fight. By 4 February, the Axis advance had been halted and the front line stabilised from Gazala on the coast {{convert|48|km|mi|abbr=on}} west of Tobruk, to an old Ottoman fortress at Bir Hakeim {{convert|80|km|mi|abbr=on}} inland to the south. The Gazala line was a series of [[defensive box]]es accommodating a [[brigade]] each, laid out across the desert behind minefields and wire, watched by regular patrols between the boxes. The Free French were to the south at the Bir Hakeim box, {{convert|13|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on}} south of the 150th Infantry Brigade box, which was {{convert|6|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on}} south of the 69th Infantry Brigade box. The line was not evenly manned, with a greater number of troops covering the coast road, leaving the south less protected but the line was behind deep minefields and a longer line would make an attack around the southern flank harder to supply. Behind the Gazala line were defensive boxes known as Commonwealth Keep or Hill 209 at [[Ras El Madauur]] on the main defence line of Tobruk, about {{convert|14.5|km|mi|abbr=on}} west-south-west of the port. [[Acroma]], Knightsbridge, {{convert|19|km|mi|abbr=on}} south of Acroma and [[El Adem]], were sited to block tracks and junctions. A box at [[Retma]] was finished just before the Axis offensive but work on boxes at Point 171 {{convert|6.4|km|mi|abbr=on}} south-east of Bir Hakeim and [[Bir el Gubi]] did not begin until 25 May.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair 1960 pp. 197–198, 216–217&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==

===British preparations===

[[File:GenRitchie.jpg|thumb|upright=0.75|{{center|General [[Neil Ritchie|Ritchie]] (holding pipe) addressing his commanders, 31 May 1942. [[Willoughby Norrie, 1st Baron Norrie|Norrie]] holding map, [[William Gott|Gott]] to right of Ritchie.}}]]
Churchill pressed Auchinleck to attack to push the Axis out of Cyrenaica and relieve the pressure on Malta, which Churchill felt was essential to the war effort,

{{quote|...having particular regard to Malta, the loss of which would be a disaster of the first magnitude to the British Empire and probably fatal in the long run to the defence of the Nile delta.|Winston Churchill&lt;ref name=Lewin&gt;Lewin p. 109&lt;/ref&gt;}}

The Eighth Army received new equipment, including {{nowrap|167 American Lend-Lease [[M3 Lee|M3 Grant]]}} tanks equipped with 75&amp;nbsp;mm guns, and large numbers of [[Ordnance QF 6-pounder|6-pounder]] anti-tank guns.&lt;ref name="Lewin 112"&gt;Lewin p. 112&lt;/ref&gt; Rommel thought that Allied minefields ended well north of Bir Hakeim and did not know of the "mine marsh" surrounding the box.&lt;ref name="Lewin 112"/&gt; The Eighth Army was in the process of reorganising, changing the relationship between infantry and artillery, while the RAF commander [[Arthur Tedder, 1st Baron Tedder|Arthur Tedder]] concentrated the efforts of the [[Desert Air Force]] (DAF) on supporting the troops on the ground. Army commanders lost the power to direct air operations, which was reserved for the air commanders. A new fighter-bomber concept was developed and Air Vice-Marshal [[Arthur Coningham (RAF officer)|Arthur Coningham]], commander of the DAF, moved his headquarters to the Eighth Army HQ to improve communication.&lt;ref&gt;Clifford, pp. 237–238&lt;/ref&gt;

Axis commanders knew that the entry of the United States into the war would give the Eighth Army access to an increase in materiel but sought to forestall an Allied offensive before these supplies could influence events. By late May, the [[1st Infantry Division (South Africa)|1st South African Division]] was on the Gazala line nearest the coast, the [[50th (Northumbrian) Infantry Division]] to the south and the [[1st Free French Division|1st Free French Brigade]] furthest south at Bir Hakeim. The 1st and 7th Armoured Divisions waited behind the main line as a mobile counter-attack force, the [[2nd Infantry Division (South Africa)|2nd South African Division]] formed a garrison at Tobruk and the [[5th Infantry Division (India)|5th Indian Infantry Division]] (which had arrived in April to relieve the [[4th Infantry Division (India)|4th Indian Infantry Division]]) was held in reserve. The Allies had {{nowrap|110,000 men,}} {{nowrap|843 tanks}} and {{nowrap|604 aircraft.}}&lt;ref name=Barr13&gt;Barr, p. 13&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Carver167"/&gt;

===Axis preparations===

[[File:WesternDesertBattle Area1941 en.svg|thumb|{{center|Area of Axis advance, El Agheila–El Alamein, 21 January – 21 June 1942}}]]
The Axis retreat to El Agheila after Operation Crusader reduced the supply distance from Tripoli to {{convert|460|mi|km|order=flip}}. The discovery of {{convert|13000|LT|t|order=flip}} of fuel at Tripoli eased the supply crisis, despite the delivery of only {{convert|50000|LT|t|order=flip}} of supplies in January. The {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} had a much shorter supply line and the British were burdened by an over-extended supply line. {{lang|de|Luftflotte}} II in Sicily had also regained air superiority for the Axis. Rommel asked for another {{nowrap|8,000 lorries}} but this unrealistic demand was rejected and Rommel was warned that an advance would cause another supply crisis. On 29 January, the {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} recaptured Benghazi and next day ammunition supply to the front line failed. By 13 February, Rommel agreed to stop at Gazala, {{convert|900|mi|km|order=flip}} from Tripoli.&lt;ref&gt;Creveld, 1977, pp. 192–193&lt;/ref&gt;

Until May, monthly deliveries averaged {{convert|60000|LT|t|order=flip}}, less than the smaller Axis force received from June–October 1941 but sufficient for an offensive. The {{convert|900|mi|km|order=flip}} advance to Gazala succeeded because Benghazi was open, reducing the transport distance for about 33 percent of the supplies of the {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} to {{convert|280|mi|km|order=flip}}. The Italians tried to restrain Rommel by advocating the capture of Malta, which would postpone another offensive in Africa until the autumn but agreed to an attack on Tobruk for late May. An advance would stop at the Egyptian frontier, another {{convert|150|mi|km|order=flip}} east and the {{lang|de|Luftwaffe}} would redeploy for [[Operation Herkules]]. The capture of Malta would not alter the constraints of port capacity and distance; protecting convoys and a large port close to the front, would still be necessary for victory.&lt;ref&gt;Creveld, 1977, pp. 193–195&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Three Italian generals.jpg|thumb|{{center|From left to right: Generals Nicolini, Baldassarre and Lombardi.}}]]
Air attacks directed by Kesselring against Malta greatly reduced its offensive capacity, allowing supply convoys from Italy to reach Axis forces in Africa with increased regularity.&lt;ref&gt;Lewin p. 108&lt;/ref&gt; {{lang|de|Unternehmen Venezia}} (Operation Venice), the Axis plan of attack, was for armoured forces to make a flanking manoeuvre south of the fortified "box" at Bir Hakeim.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair 1960, p. 223&lt;/ref&gt; On the left flank, the [[Italian 132nd Armored Division Ariete|132 Armoured Division ''Ariete'']] would neutralise the Bir Hakeim box and on the right flank, the [[21st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|21st Panzer Division]] and [[15th Panzer Division]] would advance north behind the Eighth Army defences, to destroy the Allied armour and cut off the infantry divisions on the Gazala line. On the far right of the attack, a {{lang|de|kampfgruppe}} (battle group) from the [[German 90th Light Afrika Division|90th Light ''Afrika'' Division]] was to advance to El Adem, south of Tobruk and cut the line of supply from the port to the Gazala line while holding Allied troops at Tobruk.&lt;ref&gt;Toppe, p. A-8-18–19&lt;/ref&gt;

The rest of the [[Italian XX Motorized Corps]], the Italian [[Italian 101 Motorised Division Trieste|101st Motorized Division ''Trieste'']], would open a gap in the minefield north of the Bir Hakeim box near the Sidi Muftah box, to create a supply route to the armour. Rommel anticipated that, having dealt with the Allied armour, he would capture El Adem, Ed Duda, [[Sidi Rezegh]] and "Knightsbridge". The Axis tanks would then be in a position to attack on the following day westwards against the Eighth Army defensive boxes between Gazala and Alem Hamza, meeting the eastwards attack by the Italian X and XXI corps.&lt;ref&gt;Mackenzie, p. 541&lt;/ref&gt; By late May, the Axis forces comprised {{nowrap|90,000 men,}} {{nowrap|560 tanks}} and {{nowrap|542 aircraft.}}&lt;ref name=Barr13/&gt;&lt;ref name="Carver167"&gt;Carver, p. 167&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===Operation Venice===

[[File:Map of siege of Tobruk 1942.jpg|thumb|{{center|Axis advance, opening of Operation Venice}}]]
At 14:00 on 26 May, the Italian X and XXI Corps launched a frontal attack on the central Gazala positions, after a heavy artillery concentration, beginning {{lang|de|Unternehmen Venezia}} (Operation Venice).{{efn |Rommel's plan (issued as "Order for Army Operations", 20 May) to encircle the Allied Army deployed between Gazala and Bir Hakeim and capture the fortress of Tobruk, was initially called Operation Theseus ({{lang|de|Unternehmen Theseus}}).{{lang|de|Venezia}} was the code name ({{lang|de|funk befehl Venezia}}) of the last-minute adjustment (evening of 26 May) for the entire motorised Axis force to advance south of Bir Hakeim. (Most English-language writers refer to the Battle of Gazala as Operation Venice.){{sfn|Stumpf|2001|pp=602–613}}{{sfn|Montanari|1993|p=199}}{{sfn|Rondeau|2013|p=169}}}} A few elements of the {{lang|de|Afrika Korps}} and XX Mobile Corps were attached to these assault groups. During the day, the bulk of the {{lang|de|Afrika Korps}} moved, to give the impression that this was the main Axis assault. When night fell, the armoured formations turned south in a sweeping move around the southern end of the Gazala line.&lt;ref&gt;Toppe, p. A-8-19&lt;/ref&gt;

In the early hours of 27 May, Rommel led the elements of {{lang|de|Panzerarmee Afrika}}, the {{lang|de|[[Deutsches Afrikakorps]]}} (DAK), [[Italian XX Motorised Corps]] and the German 90th Light {{lang|de|Afrika}} Division, in a bold flanking move around the southern end of the Allied line, using the Allied minefields to protect the Axis flank and rear. The {{lang|it|"Ariete"}} Division of XX Motorized Corps was held up for about an hour by the [[3rd Indian Motor Brigade]] of the 7th Armoured Division, dug in about {{convert|6|km|mi|0|abbr=on}} south east of Bir Hakeim at [[Rugbet el Atasc]]. The [[132nd Tank Regiment (Italy)|132nd Tank Infantry Regiment]] of the "Ariete" Division sent its experienced VIII and IX Medium Tank battalions forward, while the fresh X Medium Tank Battalion was in second line. The Indian position was overrun with the loss of {{nowrap|23 tanks,}} some of which were repairable on the field, {{nowrap|30 men}} killed and {{nowrap|50 wounded}}, while the Indians lost {{nowrap|440 men}} killed and wounded and about {{nowrap|1,000 prisoners,}} including Admiral Sir [[Walter Cowan]] and most of its equipment.&lt;ref&gt;Parri, p. 111&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Montanari, p. 208&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Playfair 1960 p. 223&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Carver, 1966, p. 219&lt;/ref&gt; The 21st Panzer Division was advancing south of the position and did not take part in the action.&lt;ref&gt;Ford, p. 35&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Greene and Massignani, p. 156&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Montanari, p. 206&lt;/ref&gt;

Further to the east, the 15th Panzer Division had engaged the 4th Armoured Brigade of the 7th Armoured Division, which had been ordered south to support the 3rd Indian and 7th Motorised brigades. In a mutually costly engagement, the Germans were surprised by the range and power of the {{nowrap|75 mm}} guns on the new M3 (Grant) tanks.&lt;ref name ="Playfair224"&gt;Playfair 1960, p. 224&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Toppe, p. A-8-25&lt;/ref&gt; The 4th Armoured Brigade then withdrew toward El Adem and spent the night near the Belhamed supply base, east of El Adem.&lt;ref name="Playfair224"/&gt; By late morning, the Axis armoured units had advanced more than {{convert|25|mi|km|abbr=on}} north but by noon had been stopped by the 1st Armoured Division in more mutually costly fighting.&lt;ref name="Playfair224"/&gt;

[[File:M3 Grant with knocked out Panzer I 1942.jpg|thumb|upright=0.75|{{center|M3 Grant with knocked out Panzer I, 1942}}]]
On the far right of the Axis advance, the 90th Light {{lang|de|Afrika}} Division engaged the 7th Motorised Brigade at Retma and forced it to withdraw eastwards on Bir el Gubi.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair 1960, pp. 223–224&lt;/ref&gt; Resuming their advance toward El Adem before noon, armoured cars of the 90th Light came upon the advanced HQ of 7th Armoured Division near Bir Beuid, dispersing it and capturing a number of officers including the commander, [[Frank Messervy]], who pretended to be a [[batman (army)|batman]] and escaped.&lt;ref name="Mead298"&gt;Mead, p. 298&lt;/ref&gt; The "inexcusable" lapse in security left the division without effective command for the next two days.&lt;ref name="Playfair224"/&gt; As planned, 90th Light division reached the El Adem area by mid-morning and captured a number of supply dumps. The following day, the 4th Armoured Brigade was sent to El Adem and the 90th Light Division was driven back to the south-west.&lt;ref name="Playfair225"&gt;Playfair 1960, p. 225&lt;/ref&gt;

The tank battle continued for three days; lacking possession of Bir Hakeim, Rommel drew the {{lang|de|Afrika Korps}} into a defensive position, using the extensive Allied mine belts to block an Allied approach from the west. The British tanks attacked several times from the north and east against accurate defensive fire. The Axis supply situation became desperate; defending the German rear, the {{lang|it|Ariete}} Division repulsed attacks by the British armoured brigades on 29 May and during the first week of June.{{sfn|Walker|2003|pp=117–121}}

===Bir Hakeim===
{{main|Battle of Bir Hakeim}}

The Bir Hakeim box was defended by the 1st Free French Brigade under [[Marie-Pierre Koenig]]. On 27 May, the Italian IX Tank Battalion of the 132nd Tank Infantry Regiment ("Ariete" Division), which had not been engaged in the destruction of the 3rd Indian Brigade box and had continued to advance alone at full speed, stumbled in the French positions and launched a hasty attack, which was a costly failure against the French {{nowrap|75 mm}} guns and mines.{{sfn|Walker|2003|pp=116–117}}&lt;ref&gt;Clifford, p. 247&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Montanari|1993|p=211}} On the night of {{nowrap|1/2 June,}} the 90th Light and {{lang|it|Trieste}} divisions were sent south to renew the attack on Bir Hakeim, where the battle continued for another ten days.&lt;ref name="Toppe1"/&gt;

{{quote|Our attacks repeatedly bogged down in the excellent French fortifications. During the first ten days of out {{sic}} attack against the French the British had remained amazingly calm. The "Ariete" Division alone was attacked by them on 2 June but it defended itself stubbornly. After a counter-attack by the 21st Panzer Division the situation there again became quiet.|{{lang|de|Generalmajor}} Alfred Toppe&lt;ref name="Toppe1"&gt;Toppe, p. A-9-1&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Reinforced with a further {{lang|de|kampfgruppe}}, the Axis attacked Bir Hakeim again on 9 June and overran the defences by the following day.&lt;ref&gt;Toppe, pp. A-9-5–A-9-7&lt;/ref&gt; Ritchie ordered the remaining troops to evacuate as best they could, under the cover of darkness.&lt;ref&gt;Clifford, pp. 260–262&lt;/ref&gt; Under fire through the night, many of the French were able to find gaps in the line through which to withdraw. The survivors then made their way some {{convert|8|km|abbr=on}} to the west, to rendezvous with transport from the 7th Motor Brigade.&lt;ref name="Playfair237"&gt;Playfair 1960, p. 237&lt;/ref&gt; About {{nowrap|2,700 troops}} (including {{nowrap|200 wounded)}} of the original garrison of {{nowrap|3,600 escaped}} and about {{nowrap|500 French}} troops, many of whom were wounded, were captured when the 90th Light Division occupied the position on 11 June.&lt;ref name="Playfair237"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Toppe, p. A-9-6&lt;/ref&gt;

===The Cauldron===

Early on 29 May, supply vehicles supported by the {{lang|it|Trieste}} and {{lang|de|Ariete}} divisions, worked through the minefield north of Bir Hakeim and reached the {{lang|de|Afrika Korps}}. On 30 May, Rommel pulled the {{lang|de|Afrika Korps}} back westward against the edge of the minefields, creating a defensive position. A link was formed with elements of the Italian X Corps, which were clearing two routes through the minefields from the west.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 1960, pp. 226–228&lt;/ref&gt; In the process, the Sidi Muftah box was overrun and the [[150th Infantry Brigade]] destroyed,

{{quote|In the afternoon [30th May] I personally reconnoitred the possibilities for an attack on Got el Ualeb [the Sidi Muftah box] and detailed units of the {{lang|de|Afrika Korps}}, 90th Light Division and the Italian Trieste Division for an assault on the British positions next morning. The attack was launched on the morning of the 31st May. German-Italian units fought their way forward yard by yard against the toughest British resistance imaginable.[...] Nevertheless, by the time evening came we had penetrated a substantial distance into the British positions. On the following day the defenders were to receive their quietus. After heavy Stuka attacks, the infantry again surged forward against the British field positions.[...] Piece by piece the elaborate British defences were won until by early afternoon the whole position was ours. The last British resistance was quenched. We took in all {{nowrap|3,000 prisoners}} and destroyed or captured {{nowrap|101 tanks}} and armoured cars, as well as {{nowrap|124 guns}} of all kinds.|Rommel&lt;ref&gt;''The Rommel Papers, US version'', p. 212&lt;/ref&gt;}}

[[File:Ariete tank division on the attack.jpg|left|thumb|{{center|{{lang|it|Ariete}} tanks on the move during the battle}}]]
Acting on mistaken reports about German tank losses, Auchinleck strongly urged Ritchie to counter-attack along the coast, to exploit the absence of German tanks and break through to Timimi and then [[Mechili]]. Ritchie was more concerned by Tobruk, brought reinforcements up to the El Adem box and created new defensive boxes opposite the gaps in the minefield.&lt;ref&gt;Mackenzie, p. 548&lt;/ref&gt; Ritchie ordered the Eighth Army to counter-attack against the {{lang|de|Afrika Korps}} on 5 June but they were met by accurate fire from tank and anti-tank guns positioned in the cauldron. In the north, XIII Corps made no progress but the attack by 7th Armoured and 5th Indian divisions on the eastern flank of the cauldron at 02:50 initially went well. An important element of the plan was the destruction of the Axis anti-tank screen with an artillery bombardment but because of an error in plotting its position, the bombardment fell too far to the east.&lt;ref&gt;Hinsley, p. 373&lt;/ref&gt; When the 22nd Armoured Brigade advanced, it was met by massed anti-tank fire and checked.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair 1960, pp. 232–233&lt;/ref&gt; The 32nd Army Tank Brigade, advancing from the north, joined the attack at dawn but also ran into massed fire, losing fifty of seventy tanks.&lt;ref name= "Playfair233"&gt;Playfair 1960, p. 233&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:BattleGazalaAftermath.gif|thumb|{{center|Axis attack from the Cauldron, 12–13 June}}]]
By early afternoon on 5 June, Rommel split his forces, deciding to attack east with the {{lang|it|Ariete}} and 21st Panzer divisions while he sent elements of 15th Panzer Division northwards against the Knightsbridge Box.&lt;ref name="Playfair234"&gt;Playfair 1960, p. 234&lt;/ref&gt; The eastward thrust towards Bir el Hatmat dispersed the tactical HQs of the two British divisions, as well as the HQs of the [[9th Indian Infantry Brigade]], the [[10th Indian Infantry Brigade]] and other smaller units, which caused command to break down.&lt;ref name="Playfair234"/&gt; The 22nd Armoured Brigade, having lost {{nowrap|60 of}} its {{nowrap|156 tanks,}} was forced from the battlefield by more attacks from the 15th Panzer Division. Three Indian infantry battalions, a reconnaissance regiment and four artillery regiments of the attacking force were left behind, unsupported by armour and overrun.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair 1960, pp. 233–234&lt;/ref&gt; Rommel retained the initiative, maintaining his strength in the cauldron while the number of operational British tanks diminished. A number of probes were sent to test the various opposing strong points and from 6 to 8 June, further attacks were launched on Bir Hakeim and repulsed by the French garrison. The 7th Motor Brigade and [[29th Indian Infantry Brigade]] continued to harass the Axis lines of communications.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair 1960, pp. 235–236&lt;/ref&gt;

===Black Saturday, 13 June===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-784-0247-13, Nordafrika, zerstörte britische Panzer.2.jpg|thumb|left|{{center|Abandoned British Valentines are inspected for maps, code books and tins of food}}]]
On 11 June, Rommel pushed the 15th Panzer Division and 90th Light {{lang|de|Afrika}} Division toward El Adem and by 12 June had begun forcing the 201st Guards Brigade out of the Knightsbridge Box to Tobruk.&lt;ref name="Mead298"/&gt; The 29th Indian Infantry Brigade repulsed an attack on the El Adem box on 12 June but the 2nd and 4th Armoured Brigades on their left were pushed back {{convert|6|km|mi|abbr=on}} by the 15th Panzer Division and had to leave their damaged tanks on the battlefield. On 13 June, the 21st Panzer Division advanced from the west and engaged the 22nd Armoured Brigade. The {{lang|de|Afrika Korps}} demonstrated a superiority in tactics, combining tanks with anti-tank guns in the attack; Rommel acted rapidly on intelligence obtained from Allied radio traffic intercepts.&lt;ref&gt;von Mellenthin p. 107&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the day, the British tank strength had been reduced from {{nowrap|300 tanks}} to about {{nowrap|70 and}} the {{lang|de|Afrika Korps}} had established armour superiority and a dominating line of positions, making XIII Corps on the Gazala line vulnerable to being cut off.&lt;ref&gt;Hoffman p. 77&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of 13 June, the Knightsbridge box was virtually surrounded and it was abandoned by the Guards Brigade later that night,&lt;ref name="Playfair234"/&gt; with their commanding officer [[Thomas Bevan (cricketer)|Thomas Bevan]] having been killed the previous day.&lt;ref&gt;McCrery, 2011, pp. 104–105&lt;/ref&gt; Due to these defeats, 13 June became known as "Black Saturday" to the Eighth Army.&lt;ref&gt;Clifford, p. 264&lt;/ref&gt;

====Rigel Ridge====

On 13 June, the 21st Panzer Division attacked Rigel Ridge in the middle of a sandstorm.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair 1960, pp. 242–243&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans overran part of the 2nd Scots Guards at the Knightsbridge Box at the west end of Rigel Ridge, overlooked by the 6th South African Anti-tank battery of the 2nd Field Regiment, [[Natal Field Artillery]] and a battery of the [[11th Regiment, Royal Horse Artillery (Honourable Artillery Company)|11th Regiment RHA]] nearby. The South African gunners kept firing until their guns were destroyed, allowing the withdrawal of other Allied formations.&lt;ref&gt;Mitcham, 2007, p. 98&lt;/ref&gt; The South African battery commander had decided to stay and maintain fire against the German tanks, to delay the Germans for as long as possible. The remaining guns were commanded individually and fired at the Panzers over open sights. The German tanks took up positions behind the ridge, with anti-tank guns placed between them. A column of Panzers attacked from the rear, surrounding them and cutting off all escape and the gunners kept firing until the eight guns had been destroyed. About half the gun detachments were killed and wounded, including the battery commander and many officers. The last gun in action was manned by Lieutenant Ashley and a signaller; when the battery had been silenced, the Axis tanks approached cautiously and the South African gunners were taken prisoner. (The entire Natal Field Artillery Regiment was captured and was not re-formed until after the war.)&lt;ref&gt;The South African Military History Society Newsletter. [http://samilitaryhistory.org/12/d12janne.html] No. 431. January 2012.&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans captured over {{nowrap|3,000 Allied}} prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;Greene and Massignani 1994, p. 163&lt;/ref&gt;

===Eighth Army retreat===

On 14 June, Auchinleck authorised Ritchie to withdraw from the Gazala Line. The defenders in the El Adem and two neighbouring boxes held on and the 1st South African Division was able to withdraw along the coast road, practically intact.{{sfn|Mackenzie|1951|pp=554–555}} The road could not accommodate two divisions and the remaining two brigades of the 50th (Northumbrian) Division could not retreat eastwards, because of the Axis tanks and attacked south-west, breaking through the lines of the {{lang|it|Brescia}} and {{lang|it|[[Italian 17 Infantry Division Pavia|Pavia]]}} divisions of X Corps; then headed south into the desert, before turning east.{{sfn|Clifford|1943|pp=269–272}} London would not contemplate a withdrawal to the better defensive positions on the Egypt-Libya frontier and on 14 June, Auchinleck ordered to Ritchie to hold a line running south-east from Acroma (west of Tobruk) through El Adem to Bir El Gubi. By the evening of 15 June, the Point 650 box had been overrun and on 16 June, the defenders at Point 187 had been forced by lack of supplies to evacuate. The defensive boxes at El Adem and Sidi Rezegh were also attacked by the {{lang|de|Afrika Korps}}. On 17 June, both boxes were evacuated ending any chance of preventing the encirclement of Tobruk. Ritchie ordered the Eighth Army to withdraw to Mersa Matruh, about {{convert|100|mi|km|abbr=on}} east of the frontier, leaving Tobruk to threaten the Axis lines of communication as in 1941.{{sfn|Mackenzie|1951|pp=556–561}} The retreat became known to some as the Gazala Gallop.{{sfnm|1a1=Nash|1y=2013|1p=182|2a1=Sadler|2y=2015|2p=18}}

===Fall of Tobruk===
{{main|Axis capture of Tobruk}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-785-0294-32A, Tobruk, englische Kriegsgefangene.jpg|thumb|{{center|Allied prisoners are marched out of Tobruk}}]]
In February 1942, the army, navy and air force commanders-in-chief in Cairo had agreed that Tobruk should not stand another siege. The defences at Tobruk had not been maintained and it was garrisoned by inexperienced troops. Auchinleck viewed the defence of Tobruk as a lesser matter and told Ritchie that he did not intend to hold it at all costs.{{sfn|Playfair|1960|p=261}} An immense store of supplies of every description had been accumulated around the port for an Allied offensive and Auchinleck expected it to be able to hold out for two months with the supplies in the fortress. The [[British prime minister]] [[Winston Churchill]] had placed great store on the symbolic value of Tobruk and there was an exchange of ambiguous signals, leading to the port becoming surrounded and besieged, rather than evacuated as originally planned.{{sfn|Mackenzie|1951|pp=561, 559}}

Operation Venice ({{lang|de|Unternehmen Venezia}}) began on 26 May 1942 and drove the Eighth Army east of Tobruk, leaving it vulnerable to attack from the east.{{sfn|Mackenzie|1951|pp=561, 559}} Gott garrisoned Tobruk with the two brigades of 2nd South African Division (Major-General [[Hendrik Klopper]]) along with the [[22nd Guards Brigade|201st Guards (Motorised) Brigade]], [[11th Indian Infantry Brigade]], [[32nd Army Tank Brigade (United Kingdom)|32nd Army Tank Brigade]] and the [[4th Anti-Aircraft Brigade (United Kingdom)|4th Anti-Aircraft Brigade]].{{sfn|Bierman|Smith|2003|p=178}} {{lang|de|Panzerarmee Afrika}} penetrated a weak spot on the eastern defensive perimeter and took the port within twenty-four hours. The garrison of 33,000 men was captured, many of those on the western perimeter not having been engaged.&lt;ref&gt;Harper 2017, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; Over 1,000 vehicles in working order, {{cvt|5000|LT|t|0}} of food and {{cvt|1400|LT|t|0}} of petrol were captured.{{sfn|Carver|2002|p=123}} The surrender was the largest capitulation of British Empire forces in the war after the [[Battle of Singapore]] in February 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Harper 2017, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; Later in the year, a Court of Inquiry ({{lang|la|[[Trial in absentia|in absentia]]}}) found Klopper to be largely blameless for the surrender and ascribed the defeat to failures among the British high command. The findings were kept secret until after the war, doing little to restore the reputation of Klopper and his troops.&lt;ref&gt;Horn &amp; Katz 2016, p. 194&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==

===Analysis===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-443-1582-32, Nordafrika, Generaloberst Erwin Rommel.jpg|thumb|upright=0.75|{{center|Generaloberst Erwin Rommel, west of Tobruk}}]]
With the capture of Tobruk, the Axis gained a port nearer the Aegean–Crete route and a large amount of Allied supplies. If the Allies could not stop the Germans in Egypt, they would take the Suez Canal (forcing Britain to use supply lines twice as long, threatened by U-boats) and potentially drive for the oilfields in the Middle East. Hitler rewarded Rommel with a promotion to the rank of field-marshal, the youngest German officer ever to achieve this rank.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair 1960, p. 275&lt;/ref&gt; Rommel remarked he would have preferred another panzer division.{{sfn|Rommel|1953|p=233}}

Churchill wrote,

{{quote|This was one of the heaviest blows I can recall during the war. Not only were its military effects grievous, but it had affected the reputation of the British armies.|Winston Churchill&lt;ref&gt;Barr, p. 1&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Auchinleck dismissed Ritchie on 25 June and assumed command of the Eighth Army for the [[First Battle of El Alamein]], where he stopped Rommel's advance.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 1960, pp. 285, 331–357&lt;/ref&gt; In August, Auchinleck was replaced as Eighth Army commander by the XIII Corps commander, Lieutenant-General [[William Gott]] and as C-in-C [[Middle East Command]] by General Sir Harold Alexander. Gott was killed when his aircraft was shot down and Lieutenant-General [[Bernard Montgomery, 1st Viscount Montgomery of Alamein|Bernard Montgomery]] was appointed as his replacement.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 1960, pp. 367–370&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2017, James Holland wrote,

{{quote|As Rommel said to a captured British officer, 'What difference does it make if you have two tanks to my one, when you spread them out and let me smash them in detail?' That one sentence really did encapsulate the nub of the matter and the failure of the Auk's approach. Frankly, he and his senior commanders should have known better by now.{{sfn|Holland|2017|p=207}}}}

===Casualties===
The Eighth Army lost {{nowrap|50,000 men killed,}} wounded or captured, including {{circa|35,000 prisoners}} taken at Tobruk&lt;ref&gt;Barr, p. 16&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ford, 2005 p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans suffered {{nowrap|3,360 casualties}}, about 15 per cent of their force.&lt;ref&gt;Carver, p. 249&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=274}} Italian casualties were 3,000 men, 125 tanks, 44 armoured cars, 450 motor vehicles, 39 guns and seventy-four {{nowrap|47 mm}} anti-tank guns.{{sfn|Montanari|1989|p=291}} On 30 June, the Afrika Korps reported that Axis tank losses were {{circa|400 and}} that only {{nowrap|44–55 German}} tanks were operational, the Italian XX Corps was down to fifteen tanks and the 90th Light {{lang|de|Afrika}} Division had only {{nowrap|1,679 men}} left.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, p. 57&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barr, 2005, p. 39&lt;/ref&gt; The Eighth Army lost thousands of tons of supplies, nearly {{nowrap|800,000 rounds}} of artillery ammunition, nearly {{nowrap|13 million}} rounds of small-arms ammunition and a huge number of tanks. Hundreds of damaged tanks had been left behind when armoured regiments retreated and it was estimated that there were {{nowrap|1,188 tank}} casualties in 17 days. On 22 June, the Desert Air Force had {{nowrap|463 operational}} aircraft, {{nowrap|420 of}} them in the Middle East, the Germans {{nowrap|183 and}} the Italians {{nowrap|238, with}} another {{nowrap|174 in}} reserve and {{nowrap|500 in}} the Mediterranean excluding Italy.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair 1960 p. 283&lt;/ref&gt; The Royal Army Ordnance Corps recovered {{nowrap|581 tanks}} up to 19 June, repaired {{nowrap|278 and}} sent {{nowrap|222 back}} to Egypt {{nowrap|(326 being}} US-made tanks). The Eighth Army was reduced to about {{nowrap|185 operational}} tanks by the end of the battle and shuffling operational tanks and crews between units disrupted unit organisation. Seven field artillery regiments, {{nowrap|6,000 lorries}} and two tank repair workshops (which had been moved into Tobruk) were lost. By 1 July, the Eighth Army was back at El Alamein, with {{nowrap|137 serviceable}} tanks, {{nowrap|42 en route}} from workshops and {{nowrap|902 tanks}} waiting to be repaired.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 1960, pp. 238–239&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Barr, 2005, pp. 39–40&lt;/ref&gt;

===Subsequent operations===
{{lang|de|Panzerarmee Afrika}} began {{lang|de|Unternehmen Aïda}} an advance upon Egypt, while the Eighth Army fell back to El Alamein. Auchinleck decided not to hold Mersa Matruh, choosing to fight a delaying action with X and XIII Corps. The {{lang|de|Afrika Korps}} was delayed at the [[Battle of Mersa Matruh]] but signal failures led to disorganisation and the X Corps line of retreat along the coast road being cut off. The corps broke out at night to the south and worked its way around the German positions, collided with Axis forces several times and lost more than {{nowrap|6,000 prisoners,}} forty tanks and a large quantity of supplies.&lt;ref&gt;Panzer Army Africa Battle Report dated 29 June 1942 K.T.B. 812 [http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/a4/Battle_report_of_Panzerarmeeafrika_for_28_June_1942.jpg page 1] and [http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Battle_report_of_Panzerarmeeafrika_for_29_June_1942.jpg page 2]&lt;/ref&gt; Auchinleck had ordered the bulk of the Eighth Army to retire another {{convert|160|km|mi}} to El Alamein, {{convert|100|km|mi}} from Alexandria. The retirements brought the Eighth Army closer to its base and the [[Qattara Depression]] to the south of El Alamein closed the southern flank. The Allied and Axis forces fought the First Battle of El Alamein, the [[Battle of Alam el Halfa]] and the [[Second Battle of El Alamein]]. ([[Operation Agreement]], a British landing at Tobruk during the night of {{nowrap|13/14 September,}} to rescue Allied prisoners, was a failure.)&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 1966, pp. 20–23&lt;/ref&gt;

==Orders of battle==
Allied and Axis forces, Gazala, 26 May – 21 June 1942

===Allies===
{{unref|section|date=May 2020}}
* '''Middle East Command''' ([[Claude Auchinleck]])
;;'''[[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]]''' ([[Neil Ritchie]])
;[[XIII Corps (United Kingdom)|XIII Corps]] ([[William Gott]])
* [[1st Infantry Division (South Africa)|1st South African Division]] ([[Dan Pienaar]])
** South African 1st Infantry Brigade Group
** South African 2nd Infantry Brigade Group
** South African 3rd Infantry Brigade Group
* [[2nd Infantry Division (South Africa)|2nd South African Division]] ([[Hendrik Klopper]]) (in Tobruk)
** South African 4th Infantry Brigade Group
** South African 6th Infantry Brigade Group
** [[9th Indian Infantry Brigade|9th Indian Infantry Brigade Group]] ([[Bernard Campbell Fletcher|Bernard Fletcher]]) (from 5th Indian Division and moved to 7th Armoured Division at the Cauldron in early June)
** [[11th Indian Infantry Brigade]] ([[Andrew Anderson (general)|Andrew Anderson]]) (from Army Reserve to replace 9th Indian Infantry Brigade Group)
* [[50th (Northumbrian) Infantry Division]] ([[William Havelock Ramsden|William Ramsden]])
** [[150th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|150th Infantry Brigade Group]] (Haydon)
** [[151st Infantry Brigade|151st Infantry Brigade Group]] ([[John Nichols (British Army officer)|John Nichols]])
** [[69th Infantry Brigade|69th Infantry Brigade Group]] (Hassall)
* [[1st Army Tank Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Army Tank Brigade]] (O'Carroll)
* [[32nd Army Tank Brigade (United Kingdom)|32nd Army Tank Brigade]] (Willison)
;[[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]] ([[Charles Norrie, 1st Baron Norrie|Charles Norrie]])
* [[1st Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|1st Armoured Division]] ([[Herbert Lumsden]])
** [[2nd Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|2nd Armoured Brigade Group]] (Briggs)
** [[22nd Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|22nd Armoured Brigade Group]] (Carr)
** [[201st Guards Motor Brigade]] ([[John Charles Oakes Marriott|John Marriott]] until 17 June then G. F. Johnson)
* [[7th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|7th Armoured Division]] ([[Frank Messervy]])
** [[4th Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|4th Armoured Brigade Group]] (Gatehouse)
** [[18th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|7th Motor Brigade Group]] ([[James Renton]])
** [[31st Indian Armoured Division|3rd Indian Motor Brigade Group]] (Filose)
** [[29th Indian Infantry Brigade]] Group ([[Denys Whitehorn Reid|Denys Reid]]) from [[5th Indian Infantry Division]]
** [[1st Free French Division|1st Free French Brigade Group]] ([[Marie Pierre Kœnig|Marie Kœnig]]) (under 7th Armoured Division command when defending Bir Hakeim)&lt;ref name="Mead298"/&gt;

'''Army Reserve'''
* [[5th Infantry Division (India)|5th Indian Infantry Division]] ([[Harold Rawdon Briggs|Harold Briggs]])
** [[10th Indian Infantry Brigade]] ([[Charles Hamilton Boucher|Charles Boucher]])
** 2nd Free French Brigade Group
* [[10th Indian Infantry Division]] ([[Thomas Wynford Rees|Thomas Rees]]) (arriving from Iraq)
** [[20th Indian Infantry Brigade]] (MacGregor)
** [[21st Indian Infantry Brigade]] (Purves)
** [[25th Indian Infantry Brigade]] ([[Ronald Gervase Mountain|Ronald Mountain]])
* [[11th Indian Infantry Brigade]] (Andrew Anderson) (from [[4th Infantry Division (India)|4th Indian Infantry Division]])
* [[1st Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Armoured Brigade]]
* [[5th Indian Infantry Brigade]] from mid-June ([[Dudley Russell]]) (from [[4th Indian Infantry Division]])

===Axis===
Details from Pitt 2001 unless indicated.{{sfn|Pitt|2001|pp=347–348}}
* {{lang|it|Comandante Superiore: Generale d'Armata}} [[Ettore Bastico]]

'''{{lang|de|[[Panzer Army Africa|Panzer Armee Afrika]]}}''' ({{lang|de|Generaloberst}} [[Erwin Rommel]])
* '''{{lang|de|[[Afrika Korps|Deutsches Afrika Korps]]}}''' ({{lang|de|Generalleutnant}} [[Walter Nehring]])
** [[33rd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|15th Panzer Division]] ({{lang|de|Generalleutnant}} [[Gustav von Värst]] [wounded 27 May then Oberst [[Eduard Crasemann]]])
** [[21st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|21st Panzer Division]] ({{lang|de|Generalmaor}} [[Georg von Bismarck]])
** [[90th Light Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|90th Light Division]] ({{lang|de|Generalmaor}} [[Ulrich Kleemann]])
* '''{{lang|it|[[Italian XX Motorized Corps|Corpo d'Armata di Manovra XX]]}}''' ({{lang|it|Generale di Corpo d'Armata}} [[Ettore Baldassarre]])
** [[132nd Armoured Division Ariete|132nd Armoured Division ''Ariete'']] ({{lang|it|Generale de Divisione}} [[Giuseppe de Stefanis]])
** [[101st Motorised Division Trieste|101st Motorised Division ''Trieste'']] ({{lang|it|Generale de Divisione}} [[Arnaldo Azzi]])

'''{{lang|de|[[Panzer Army Africa|Infanteriegruppe Crüwell]]}}''' ([[Ludwig Crüwell]]){{efn|{{lang|de|Gruppe Crüwell}} was part of {{lang|de|Panzerarmee Afrika}} but Rommel temporarily split the force in half, Crüwell commanding the infantry formations along the original front line, while Rommel joined the mobile forces in the flanking move. After Crüwell was captured on 29 May 1942, {{lang|de|Gruppe Crüwell}} was placed under the temporary command of Field Marshal [[Albert Kesselring]], who had been visiting the front.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair 1960, pp. 227–228&lt;/ref&gt;}}
* '''{{lang|it|[[Italian X Corps|Corpo d'Armata X]]}}''' ({{lang|it|Generale di Corpo d'Armata}} [[Benvenuto Gioda]])
** [[27th Truck-Moveable Division (Brescia)|27th Infantry Division ''Brescia'']] ({{lang|it|Generale de Divisione}} [[Giacomo Lombardi]])
** [[17th Infantry Division Pavia|17th Infantry Division ''Pavia'']] ({{lang|it|Generale de Divisione}} [[Antonio Franceschini]])
* '''{{lang|it|[[Italian XXI Corps|Corpo d'Armata XXI]]}}''' ({{lang|it|Generale di Corpo d'Armata}} [[Enea Navarini]])
** [[102nd Motorised Division Trento|102nd Motorised Division ''Trento'']] ({{lang|it|Generale de Divisione}} [[Francesco Scotti (Italian soldier)|Francesco Scotti]])
** [[60th Infantry Division Sabratha|60th Infantry Division ''Sabratha'']] ({{lang|it|Generale de Divisione}} [[Mario Soldarelli]])
** Light Infantry Regiment 155 (detached from 90th Light Division)

==See also==
{{Portal|World War II}}
* [[Battle of Bir Hakeim]]
* [[North African Campaign timeline]]
* [[List of World War II Battles]]

==Footnotes==
{{notelist|50em}}

==Citations==
{{reflist|20em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
'''Books'''
* {{cite book |first=Niall |last=Barr |title=Pendulum of War: The Three Battles of El Alamein |publisher=Overlook |edition=|location=Woodstock NY |year=2005 |isbn=1-58567-738-8}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Bierman|Smith|2003}}
|first1=John |last1=Bierman |last2=Smith |first2=Colin |title=Alamein; War Without Hate |publisher=Penguin Books |location=New York |orig-year=2002 |year=2003 |isbn=0-670-91109-7}}
* {{cite book |first=Michael |last=Carver |authorlink=Michael Carver |title=Tobruk |publisher=[[Pan Books]] |edition=|location=London |year=1964 |isbn=0-330-23376-9}}
* {{cite book |first=Michael |last=Carver |authorlink=Michael Carver |title=Tobruk |publisher=[[Baldini e Castoldi]] |edition=|location=Milano |year=1966 |oclc=879879855}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Carver|2002}}
|title=Dilemmas of the Desert War: The Libyan Campaign 1940–1942 |last=Carver |first=M. |authorlink= |year=2002 |orig-year=1986 |publisher=Batsford |location=Staplehurst |edition=2nd pbk. Spellmount |isbn=978-1-86227-153-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Clifford|1943}}
|title=Three Against Rommel: The Campaigns of Wavell, Auchinleck and Alexander |first=Alexander |last=Clifford |authorlink=Alexander Clifford |year=1943 |publisher=Harrap |location=London |oclc=186758297}}
* {{cite book |last=Creveld |first=M. van |authorlink=Martin van Creveld |title=Supplying War: Logistics from Wallenstein to Patton |year=1977 |location=Cambridge |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=0-521-29793-1}}
* {{cite book |first=Chris |last=Ellis |title=21st Panzer Division: Rommel's Afrika Korps Spearhead |publisher=Ian Allan |edition=|location=Shepperton |year=2001 |isbn=0-7110-2853-2}}
* {{cite book |first=David |last=French |title=Raising Churchill's Army: The British Army and the War against Germany 1939–1945 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=Oxford |year=2000 |isbn=0-19-820641-0}}
* {{cite book |first=Ken |last=Ford |title=Gazala 1942: Rommel's Greatest Victory |publisher=Osprey |location=Oxford |year=2005 |isbn=978-1-84603-264-6}}
* {{cite book |last1=Greene |first=J. |last2=Massignani |first2=A. |title=Rommel's North Africa Campaign: September 1940 – November 1942 |year=1994 |publisher=Combined Books |location=Conshohocken, PA |isbn=0-58519-391-6}}
* {{cite book |last=Hoffman |first=Karl |title=Erwin Rommel |year=2004 |publisher=Brassey's |location=London |isbn=1-85753-374-7}}
* {{cite book |last=Harper |first=Glyn |year=2017 |title=The Battle for North Africa: El Alamein and the Turning Point for World War II |url=https://books.google.com/?id=1lA0DwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA9 |location=Bloomington, IN |publisher=Indiana University Press |isbn=978-0-253-03142-6}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Holland|2017}}
|last=Holland |first=James |year=2017 |title=The War in the West, A New History: The Allies fight back 1941–1943 |volume=II |publisher=Bantam Press |location=London |isbn=978-0-593-07167-0}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Hinsley|1981}}
|last1=Hinsley |first1=F. H. |last2=Thomas |first2=E. E. |last3=Ransom |first3=C. F. G. |last4=Knight |first4=R. C. |display-authors=1 |series=History of the Second World War |title=British Intelligence in the Second World War. Its Influence on Strategy and Operations |volume=II |location=London |publisher=[[HMSO]] |year=1981 |isbn=0-11-630934-2}}
* {{cite book |last=Lewin |first=Ronald |year=1998 |orig-year=1968 |title=Rommel As Military Commander |publisher=B&amp;N Books |location=New York |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/rommelasmilitary0000lewi |isbn=978-0-7607-0861-3}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Mackenzie|1951}}
|first=Compton |last=Mackenzie |authorlink=Compton Mackenzie |title=Eastern Epic: September 1939 – March 1943 Defence |volume=I |publisher=Chatto &amp; Windus |location=London |year=1951 |oclc=59637091}}
* {{cite book |last=Marshall |first=Charles F. |title=The Rommel Murder: The Life and Death of the Desert Fox |publisher=Stackpole Books |location=Mechanicsburg, PA |year=2002 |orig-year=1994 |isbn=0-8117-2472-7}}
* {{cite book |last=McCrery |first=Nigel |title=The Coming Storm: Test and First-Class Cricketers Killed in World War Two |year=2011 |publisher=Pen and Sword |volume=II |isbn=978-1-5267-0698-0}}
* {{cite book |first=Richard |last=Mead |title=Churchill's Lions: A Biographical Guide to the Key British Generals of World War II |year=2007 |publisher=Spellmount |location=Stroud |isbn=978-1-86227-431-0}}
* {{cite book |first=Friedrich von |last=Mellenthin |authorlink=Friedrich von Mellenthin |title=Panzer Battles: 1939–1945: A Study of the Use of Armor in the Second World War |title-link=Panzerschlachten |publisher=Ballantine Books |year=1971 |location=New York |orig-year=1956 |isbn=0-345-24440-0}}
* {{cite book |last=Mitcham |first=S. |title=Rommel's Lieutenants: The Men who Served the Desert Fox, France, 1940 |publisher=Praeger |location=Westport, CN |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-27599-185-2}}
* {{cite book |first1=Andrea |last1=Molinari |last2=Anderson |first2=Duncan |title=Desert Raiders: Axis and Allied Special Forces 1940–43 |publisher=Osprey |location=Oxford |year=2007 |isbn=978-1-84603-006-2}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Montanari|1989}}
|first=Mario |last=Montanari |authorlink= |series=Le operazioni in Africa Settentrionale |volume=III |title=El Alamein (gennaio – novembre 1942) |trans-title=El Alamein (January–November 1942) |language=Italian |publisher=Stato Maggiore dell'esercito, Ufficio Storico |location=Roma |edition=online |via=issuu |url=https://issuu.com/rivista.militare1/docs/volume-iii-parte1-singola-testo |year=1989 |oclc=313319483 |accessdate=24 January 2020}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Montanari|1993}}
|first=Mario |last=Montanari |series=Le operazioni in Africa Settentrionale |volume=III |title=El Alamein (gennaio – novembre 1942) |trans-title=El Alamein (January–November 1942) |language=Italian |publisher=Stato Maggiore dell'esercito, Ufficio Storico |edition= |location=Roma |year=1993 |oclc=313319483}}
* {{cite book |first=N.S. |last=Nash |title= Strafer Desert General: The Life and Killing of Lieutenant General WHE Gott CB CBE DSO MC |publisher=Pen and Sword |location=Barnsley |year=2013 |isbn=978-1-78159-090-4 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Parri |first=Maurizio |title=Tracce di Cingolo - Storia dei Carristi 1917–2009 |trans-title=Track Traces - History of the Tankers 1917–2009 |via=docplayer |year=2009 |publisher=Associazione Nazionale Carristi d'Italia/Commandante 132° Reggimento Carri |location=Roma |url=https://docplayer.it/11926199-Maurizio-parri-tracce-di-cingolo-compendio-generale-di-storia-dei-carristi.html |accessdate=6 December 2019}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Pitt|2001}}
|last=Pitt |first=Barrie |title=The Crucible of War: Auchinleck's Command |year=2001 |orig-year=1980 |publisher=Jonathan Cape |location=London |edition=2nd pbk. Cassell, London |isbn=0-304-35951-3}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Playfair|1960}}
|first1=I. S. O. |last1=Playfair |authorlink1=Ian Stanley Ord Playfair |last2=Flynn |first2=F. C. |last3=Molony |first3=C. J. C. |last4=Gleave |first4=T. P. |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=Sir James |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |series=History of the Second World War, United Kingdom Military Series |title=The Mediterranean and Middle East: British Fortunes reach their Lowest Ebb (September 1941 to September 1942) |volume=III |publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |location=Uckfield, UK |year=2004 |orig-year=1960 [[HMSO]] |isbn=1-845740-67-X |display-authors=1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Playfair|2004}}
|first1=I. S. O. |last1=Playfair |authorlink1=Ian Stanley Ord Playfair |last2=Flynn |first2=F. C. |last3=Molony |first3=C. J. C. |last4=Gleave |first4=T. P. |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=Sir James |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |series=History of the Second World War, United Kingdom Military Series |title=The Mediterranean and Middle East: British Fortunes reach their Lowest Ebb (September 1941 to September 1942) |volume=III |publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |location=Uckfield, UK |year=2004 |orig-year=1960 [[HMSO]] |isbn=1-845740-67-X |display-authors=1}}
* {{cite book |first1=I. S. O. |last1=Playfair |last2=Flynn |first2=F. C. |last3=Molony |first3=C. J. C. |last4=Gleave |first4=T. P. |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=Sir James |series=History of the Second World War, United Kingdom Military Series |title=The Mediterranean and Middle East: The Destruction of the Axis Forces in Africa |volume=IV |publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |location=Uckfield, UK |year=2004 |orig-year=1966 HMSO |isbn=978-184574-068-9 |lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Rommel|1953}}
|last=Rommel |first=Erwin |edition=1982 |year=1953 |editor-last=Liddell Hart |editor-first=B. H. |title=The Rommel Papers |location=New York |publisher=Da Capo Press |isbn=978-0-306-80157-0}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Rondeau|2013}}
|first=Benoit |last=Rondeau |title=Afrikakorps, L'Armée de Rommel |trans-title=Afrikakorps, The Army of Rommel |publisher=Tallandier |location=Paris |year=2013 |language=French |oclc=851936614}}
* {{cite book |first=John |last=Sadler |title=Ghost Patrol: A History of the Long Range Desert Group, 1940–1945 |publisher=Casemate |edition=|location=Oxford |year=2015 |isbn=978-1-61200-336-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Stumpf|2001}}
|first=Reinhard |last=Stumpf |translator-last1=Osers |translator-first1=Ewald |translator-last2=Brownjohn |translator-first2=John |translator-last3=Crampton |translator-first3=Patricia |translator-last4=Willmot |translator-first4=Louise |title=The Global War Widening of the Conflict into a World War and the Shift of the Initiative 1941–1943 |chapter=Part V The War in the Mediterranean 1942–43: Operations in North Africa and in the Central Mediterranean |volume=VI |series=Das Deutsche Reich und der Zweite Weltkrieg |publisher=Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt for the Militärgeschichtlichen Forschungsamt |location=Stuttgart |year=2001 |orig-year=1990 |edition=eng. trans. Cambridge University Press, London |isbn=0-19-822888-0}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Walker|2003}}
|first=I. W. |last=Walker |title=Iron Hulls, Iron Hearts: Mussolini's Elite Armoured Divisions in North Africa |year=2003 |publisher=Crowood Press |location=Marlborough |isbn=978-1-86126-646-0}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Yeide|2006}}
|last=Yeide |first=Harry |year=2006 |title=Weapons of the Tankers: American Armor in World War II |location=St. Paul, MN |publisher=Zenith Press |isbn=978-0-7603-2329-8}}

'''Journals'''
* {{cite journal |last1=Horn |first1=Karen |last2=Katz |first2=David |year=2016 |title=The Surrender of Tobruk in 1942: Press Reports and Soldiers' Memories |url=https://www.ajol.info/index.php/smsajms/article/viewFile/151031/140609 |journal=Scientia Militaria  |volume=44 |issue=1 |pages=190–208 |doi=10.5787/44-1-1167 |access-date=10 November 2019|doi-access=free }}
* {{cite journal |last=Jenner |first=C. J. |date=1 April 2008 |url=http://dh.oxfordjournals.org/content/32/2/165 |accessdate=2 April 2018 |title=Turning the Hinge of Fate: Good Source and the UK–U.S. Intelligence Alliance, 1940–1942 |journal=Diplomatic History |volume=II |issue=32 |pages=165–205 |doi=10.1111/j.1467-7709.2008.00688.x |issn=0145-2096}}

'''Magazines'''
* {{cite magazine |ref={{harvid|Time|1942}}
|author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |title=Massachusetts: For Services Rendered |magazine=Time |date=20 July 1942 |url=http://content.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,795996,00.html |accessdate=19 May 2018 |publisher=Time Inc |location=New York |url-access=subscription  |oclc=910607431}}

'''Websites'''
* {{cite web |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |title=The History of the British 7th Armoured Division: The Desert Rats: Engagements 1942 |url=http://www.desertrats.org.uk/battles1942.htm#Gazala |date=May–June 1942 |accessdate=13 March 2015 |url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20150810080033/http://www.desertrats.org.uk/battles1942.htm#Gazala |archive-date=10 August 2015 }}
* {{cite web |last=Toppe |first=''Generalmajor'' Alfred |title=German Experiences in Desert Warfare During World War II |volume=II |orig-year=~1947 |year=1990 |publisher=Washington: US Marine Corps |id=FMFRP 12-96-II |url=http://www.theblackvault.com/documents/wwii/marine1/1296ii.pdf |accessdate=1 December 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071202105325/http://www.theblackvault.com/documents/wwii/marine1/1296ii.pdf |archivedate=2 December 2007 &lt;!--DASHBot--&gt;|url-status=dead}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite thesis |last=Dando |first=N. |title=The Impact of Terrain on British Operations and Doctrine in North Africa 1940–1943 |type=PhD |url=https://pearl.plymouth.ac.uk//handle/10026.1/3035 |year=2014 |publisher=Plymouth University |accessdate=25 March 2015 |oclc=885436735}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Battle of Gazala}}
* [https://www.theblackvault.com/documents/wwii/marine1/1296ii.pdf German Experiences during The Battle of Gazala]
* [https://www.esercito.difesa.it/storia/Ufficio-Storico-SME/Documents/150312/fondoN-1-11-relazioni-repertorio.pdf Italian commanders 1940–1945 (in Italian)]
* [https://www.ibiblio.org/pha/policy/1942/420702a.html Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons Official Report 2 July 1942]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20151119232943/http://www.theartofbattle.com/battle-of-gazala-1942/ Battle of Gazala animated battle map (Mark Cannon)]

{{World War II}}
{{French Resistance}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Gazala, Battle Of}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:1942 in Libya]]
[[Category:Western Desert Campaign]]
[[Category:Libya in World War II]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving South Africa]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving India]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battle honours of the King's Royal Rifle Corps]]
[[Category:Erwin Rommel]]
[[Category:May 1942 events]]
[[Category:June 1942 events]]</text><sha1>5561wo59i3r68b7iwwn26hrnge40fep</sha1></revision></page>