<page><title>Falaise Pocket</title><ns>0</ns><id>664348</id><revision><id>965157809</id><parentid>965111522</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-29T18:45:37Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>82.132.234.37</ip></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="46971" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2017}}
{{Use British English|date=August 2017}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Falaise Pocket
| partof      = the [[Operation Overlord|Normandy Campaign]]
| image       = Falaise Pocket map.svg
| image_size  = 300
| caption     = Map showing the course of the battle from 8–17 August 1944
| date        = 12–21 August 1944
| place       = [[Normandy]], France
| coordinates = {{Coord|48|53|34|N|0|11|31|W|type:event_region:FR_scale:50000|display=inline,title}}
| result      = Decisive Allied victory&lt;ref name="Williams204"/&gt;
* [[Liberation of Paris]]
| combatant1  = {{flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Canada|1921}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Poland|1928}} [[Polish Army in the West|Poland]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|France}} [[Provisional Government of the French Republic|France]]
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany|1935}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Bernard Montgomery]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Omar Bradley]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[Harry Crerar]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Miles Dempsey]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Courtney Hodges]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United States |1912}} [[George S. Patton]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} [[Günther von Kluge]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} [[Walter Model]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} [[Paul Hausser]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany|1935}} [[Heinrich Eberbach]]
| units1      = {{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[First United States Army|1st Army]]

{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[United States Army Central|3rd Army]]

{{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[First Canadian Army|1st Army]]

{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|2nd Army]]
| units2      = [[5th Panzer Army]]

[[7th Army (Wehrmacht)|7th Army]]

[[5th Panzer Army|Panzergruppe Eberbach]]
| strength1   = up to 17 divisions
| strength2   = 14–15 divisions
| casualties1 = '''United States''': &lt;br /&gt;Unknown&lt;br /&gt;'''United Kingdom''': &lt;br /&gt;Unknown&lt;br /&gt;'''Free French''': &lt;br /&gt;Unknown&lt;br /&gt;'''Canada''': &lt;br /&gt;5,679 casualties{{refn|From 8 until 21 August: 1,479 killed or died of wounds, 4,023 wounded or injured, and 177 captured.&lt;ref&gt;Stacey, p. 271&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}&lt;br /&gt;'''Poland''': &lt;br /&gt;{{circa|5,150 casualties in total}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.historynet.com/world-war-ii-closing-the-falaise-pocket.htm|title=World War II: Closing the Falaise Pocket|website=History Net|date=12 June 2006|accessdate=12 August 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;of which 2,300 for the ''1st. Armoured Division.''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://info-poland.buffalo.edu/search-all/web/history/WWII/falaise/cached.html|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100702184708/http://info-poland.buffalo.edu/search-all/web/history/WWII/falaise/cached.html|title=The Canadians in the Falaise Pocket|work=Info-Poland|archivedate=2 July 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = {{circa|60,000:}}
* {{circa|10,000 killed}}
* {{circa|50,000 captured}}
500 tanks/assault guns
}}
{{Campaignbox Normandy}}

The '''Falaise Pocket''' or '''Battle of the Falaise Pocket''' ({{Lang-de|[[Pocket (military)#Kessel|Kessel]] von Falaise}}; 12–21 August 1944) was the decisive engagement of the [[Operation Overlord|Battle of Normandy]] in the [[World War II|Second World War]]. A [[pocket (military)|pocket]] was formed around [[Falaise, Calvados]], in which the German [[Army Group B]], with the [[7th Army (Wehrmacht)|7th Army]] and the [[5th Panzer Army (Germany)|Fifth Panzer Army]] (formerly {{lang|de|Panzergruppe West}}) were encircled by the [[Allies of World War II|Western Allies]]. The battle is also referred to as the Battle of the '''Falaise Gap''' (after the corridor which the Germans sought to maintain to allow their escape).{{#tag:ref|The engagement is also sometimes referred to as the Chambois pocket, the Falaise-Chambois pocket, the Argentan-Falaise pocket,&lt;ref name="Keegan"&gt;Keegan, p. 136&lt;/ref&gt; or the Trun-Chanbois gap.&lt;ref&gt;Ellis, p. 448&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} The battle resulted in the destruction of most of Army Group B west of the [[Seine]], which opened the way to Paris and the [[France–Germany border|Franco-German border]] for the Allied armies on the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]].

Six weeks after [[Normandy landings|D-Day]], the Allied [[invasion of Normandy]] on 6 June 1944, the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German Army]] was in turmoil. The [[Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force|Allied Army]] had experienced great difficulty in breaking through the German lines; the city of [[Caen]] was supposed to have been captured on the first day of the invasion and was not [[Battle of Caen|taken until late in July]], and the town of [[St Lo]] was to be taken by US forces on the second day, but was not taken until well after Caen had fallen. However, the German Army's defence of this area of Normandy was expending irreplaceable resources. The [[Allied Expeditionary Air Force|Allied air forces]] controlled the skies (up to 100&amp;nbsp;km behind enemy lines), bombing and strafing [[Axis powers|Axis]] troops, reinforcements, and necessary army supplies, such as fuel and ammunition.&lt;ref&gt;Liddell-Hart, pp. 476–478&lt;/ref&gt; On the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]], the Soviet Union's [[Operation Bagration]] and the [[Lvov–Sandomierz Offensive]] were in the midst of destroying the [[German Army Group Centre]]. In France, the German Army had used its available reserves (especially its armour reserves) to buttress the front lines around Caen, and there were few additional troops available to create successive lines of defence. To make matters worse, the [[20 July plot]]—in which officers of the German Army, including some stationed in France, tried to assassinate [[Adolf Hitler]] and seize power—had failed, and in its aftermath there was very little trust between Hitler and his generals.

In order to break out of Normandy, the Allied armies developed a multi-stage operation. It started with a [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|British]] and [[First Canadian Army|Canadian]] attack along the eastern battle line around Caen in [[Operation Goodwood]] on 18 July. The German Army responded by sending a large portion of its [[5th Panzer Army|armoured reserves]] to defend. Then, on 25 July thousands of American bombers [[carpet bombing|carpet bombed]] a 6,000-metre hole on the western end of the German lines around [[Saint-Lô]] in [[Operation Cobra]], allowing the Americans to push forces through this gap in the German lines. After some initial resistance, the German forces were overwhelmed and the Americans broke through. On 1 August, Lieutenant General [[George S. Patton]] was named the commanding officer of the newly recommissioned [[U.S. Army Central|US Third Army]]—which included large segments of the soldiers that had broken through the German lines—and with few German reserves behind the front line, the race was on. The Third Army quickly pushed south and then east, meeting very little German resistance. Concurrently, the British and Canadian troops pushed south ([[Operation Bluecoat]]) in an attempt to keep the German armour engaged. Under the weight of this British and Canadian attack, the Germans withdrew; the orderly withdrawal eventually collapsed due to lack of fuel.

Despite lacking the resources to defeat the US breakthrough and simultaneous British and Canadian offensives south of [[Caumont-l'Éventé|Caumont]] and Caen, Field Marshal [[Günther von Kluge]], the commander of Army Group B, was not permitted by Hitler to withdraw but was ordered to conduct a counter-offensive at [[Mortain]] against the US breakthrough. Four depleted [[panzer division]]s were not enough to defeat the [[First United States Army|First US Army]]. The disastrous [[Operation Lüttich]] drove the Germans deeper into the Allied envelopment.

On 8 August, the Allied ground forces commander, General [[Bernard Montgomery]], ordered the Allied armies to converge on the Falaise, Chambois area to envelop Army Group B, with the First US Army forming the southern arm, the British the base, and the Canadians the northern arm of the encirclement. The Germans began to withdraw on 17 August, and on 19 August the Allies linked up in Chambois. Gaps were forced in the Allied lines by German counter-attacks, the biggest being a corridor forced past the [[1st Armoured Division (Poland)|1st Polish Armoured Division]] on Hill 262, a commanding position at the mouth of the pocket. By the evening of 21 August, the pocket had been sealed, with {{circa|50,000 Germans}} trapped inside. Many Germans escaped, but losses in men and equipment were huge. A few days later, the Allied [[Liberation of Paris]] was completed, and on 30 August the remnants of Army Group B retreated across the Seine, which ended [[Operation Overlord]].

==Background==

===Operation Overlord===
{{main|Operation Overlord}}

Early Allied objectives in the wake of the D-Day invasion of [[Nazi occupation of France|German-occupied France]] included the [[deep water port]] of [[Cherbourg-Octeville|Cherbourg]] and the area surrounding the town of [[Caen]].&lt;ref&gt;Van der Vat, p. 110&lt;/ref&gt; Allied attacks to expand the bridgehead had rapidly defeated the initial German attempts to destroy the invasion force, but bad weather&lt;ref group=nb&gt;The [[Mulberry harbour]]s built off the landing beaches were damaged in a storm on 19 June&lt;/ref&gt; in the [[English Channel]] delayed the Allied build-up of supplies and reinforcements, while enabling the Germans to move troops and supplies with less interference from the Allied air forces.&lt;ref name="Williams114"&gt;Williams, p. 114&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Griess, pp. 308–310&lt;/ref&gt; Cherbourg was not captured by the [[VII Corps (United States)|VII US Corps]] until 27 June, and the German defence of Caen lasted until 20 July, when the southern districts were taken by the British and Canadians in [[Operation Goodwood]] and [[Operation Atlantic]].&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 165&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Trew, p. 48&lt;/ref&gt;

General [[Bernard Montgomery]], the Allied ground forces commander, had planned a strategy of attracting German forces to the east end of the bridgehead against the British and Canadians, while the [[First United States Army|US First Army]] advanced down the west side of the [[Cotentin Peninsula]] to [[Avranches]].&lt;ref&gt;Hart, p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt; On 25 July the US First Army commander, Lieutenant-General [[Omar Bradley]], began [[Operation Cobra]].&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot, pp. 390–392&lt;/ref&gt; The US First Army broke through the German defences near [[Saint-Lô]] and by the end of the third day had advanced {{convert|15|mi|km|abbr=on}} south of its start line at several points.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 257.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot, p. 393.&lt;/ref&gt; Avranches was captured on 30 July and within 24 hours the [[VIII Corps (United States)|US VIII Corps]] of the US Third Army crossed the bridge at [[Pontaubault]] into Brittany and continued south and west through open country, almost without opposition.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, p. 185&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot, p. 394&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 280&lt;/ref&gt;

===Operation Lüttich===
{{Main|Operation Lüttich}}

The US advance was swift and by 8 August, [[Le Mans]], the former headquarters of the German [[7th Army (Wehrmacht)|7th Army]], had been captured.&lt;ref&gt;Williams, p. 194&lt;/ref&gt; After Operation Cobra, [[Operation Bluecoat]] and [[Operation Spring]], the German army in Normandy was so reduced that "only a few [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] fanatics still entertained hopes of avoiding defeat".&lt;ref name=Hastings277&gt;Hastings, p. 277&lt;/ref&gt; On the Eastern Front, Operation Bagration had begun against [[Army Group Centre]] which left no possibility of reinforcement of the Western Front.&lt;ref name=Hastings277/&gt; [[Adolf Hitler]] sent a directive to Field Marshal [[Günther von Kluge]], the replacement commander of [[Army Group B]] after the sacking of [[Gerd von Rundstedt]], ordering "an immediate counter-attack between Mortain and Avranches" to "annihilate" the enemy and make contact with the west coast of the Cotentin peninsula.&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 414&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Williams196&gt;Williams, p. 196&lt;/ref&gt;

Eight of the nine [[Panzer division]]s in Normandy were to be used in the attack, but only four could be made ready in time.&lt;ref name=Wilmot401&gt;Wilmot, p. 401&lt;/ref&gt; The German commanders protested that their forces were incapable of an offensive, but the warnings were ignored and [[Operation Lüttich]] commenced on 7 August around Mortain.&lt;ref name=Williams196/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 283&lt;/ref&gt; The first attacks were made by the [[2nd Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|2nd Panzer Division]], [[SS Division Leibstandarte]] and the [[SS Division Das Reich]], but they had only 75 [[Panzer IV]]s, 70 [[Panther tank|Panthers]] and 32 [[self-propelled gun]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 285&lt;/ref&gt; The Allies were forewarned by [[Ultra]] signals intercepts, and although the offensive continued until 13 August, the threat of Operation Lüttich had been ended within 24 hours.&lt;ref name="illustrated-ww2"&gt;Messenger, pp. 213–217&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bennett 1979, pp. 112–119&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 286&lt;/ref&gt; Operation Lüttich had led to the most powerful remaining German units being defeated at the west side of the Cotentin Peninsula by the US First Army, and the Normandy front on the verge of collapse.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 335&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Williams197/&gt; Bradley said

{{quote|This is an opportunity that comes to a commander not more than once in a century. We're about to destroy an entire hostile army and go all the way from here to the German border.&lt;ref name=Williams197&gt;Williams, p. 197&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Operation Totalize===
{{Main|Operation Totalize}}

[[File:Totalise88gun.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;A [[Cromwell tank]] and [[Willys MB]] jeep passing an abandoned German [[8.8 cm PaK 43|{{convert|88|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} PaK 43 anti-tank gun]] during Totalize&lt;/center&gt;]]
The [[First Canadian Army]] was ordered to capture high ground north of Falaise to trap Army Group B.&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 404&lt;/ref&gt; The Canadians planned [[Operation Totalize]], with attacks by strategic bombers and a novel night attack using [[Kangaroo (armoured personnel carrier)|Kangaroo]] armoured personnel carriers.&lt;ref name=Hastings296&gt;Hastings, p. 296&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Zuehlke, p. 168&lt;/ref&gt; Operation Totalize began on the night of 7/8 August; the leading infantry rode on the Kangaroos, guided by electronic aids and illuminants, against the {{lang|de|[[12th SS Panzer Division|12th SS Panzer Division Hitlerjugend]]}}, which held a {{convert|14|km|mi|abbr=on}} front, supported by the [[101 SS Heavy Panzer Battalion|101st SS Heavy Panzer Battalion]] and remnants of the [[89th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|89th Infantry Division]].&lt;ref name=Hastings296/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Williams, p. 198&lt;/ref&gt; [[Battle of Verrières Ridge|Verrières Ridge]] and [[Cintheaux]] were captured on 9 August, but the speed of the advance was slowed by German resistance and some poor Canadian unit leadership, which led to many casualties in the [[4th Canadian Division|4th Canadian (Armoured) Division]] and [[1st Armoured Division (Poland)|1st Polish Armoured Division]].&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 299&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hastings301/&gt;&lt;ref name="Bercuson 230"&gt;Bercuson, p. 230&lt;/ref&gt; By 10 August, Anglo-Canadian forces had reached Hill 195, north of Falaise.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 230"/&gt; The following day, Canadian commander [[Guy Simonds]] relieved the armoured divisions with infantry divisions, ending the offensive.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 300&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==

===Allied plan===
Still expecting Kluge to withdraw his forces from the tightening Allied noose, Montgomery had for some time been planning a "long envelopment", by which the British and Canadians would pivot left from Falaise toward the River Seine while the US Third Army blocked the escape route between the Seine and the [[Loire]], trapping all surviving German forces in western France.&lt;ref name=Hastings353&gt;Hastings, p. 353.&lt;/ref&gt;{{refn|Divisions around the Falaise Pocket on 16 August 1944: [[First Canadian Army]], [[1st Armoured Division (Poland)|1st Polish Armoured Division]], [[2nd Canadian Infantry Division]], [[3rd Canadian Division|3rd Canadian Infantry Division]], [[4th Canadian Division|4th Canadian Armoured Division]]; [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|Second British Army]]: [[3rd Division (United Kingdom)|3rd Infantry Division]], [[11th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|11th Armoured Division]], [[43rd (Wessex) Infantry Division]], [[50th (Northumbrian) Infantry Division]], [[53rd (Welsh) Infantry Division]], [[59th (Staffordshire) Infantry Division]]; [[First United States Army]]: [[1st Infantry Division (United States)|US 1st Infantry Division]], [[3rd Armored Division (United States)|US 3rd Armored Division]], [[9th Infantry Division (United States)|US 9th Infantry Division]], [[28th Infantry Division (United States)|US 28th Infantry Division]], [[30th Infantry Division (United States)|US 30th Infantry Division]]; [[Third United States Army]]: [[2nd Armoured Division (France)|French 2nd Armoured Division]], [[90th Infantry Division (United States)|90th Infantry Division]].&lt;ref&gt;Copp (2003), p. 234.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} In a telephone conversation on 8 August, the [[Supreme Allied Commander]], [[General (United States)|General]] [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]], recommended an American proposal for a shorter envelopment at [[Argentan]]. Montgomery and Patton had misgivings; if the Allies did not take Argentan, [[Alençon]] and Falaise quickly, many Germans might escape. Believing he could always fall back on the original plan if necessary, Montgomery accepted the wishes of Bradley as the man on the spot, and the proposal was adopted.&lt;ref name=Hastings353/&gt;

==Battle==

===Operation Tractable===
{{main|Operation Tractable}}

[[File:Operation Tractable.svg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;The formation of the Falaise Pocket, from 8–17 August 1944&lt;/center&gt;]]
The Third Army advance from the south made good progress on 12 August; Alençon was captured and Kluge was forced to commit troops he had been gathering for a counter-attack. The next day, the [[5th Armored Division (United States)|US 5th Armored Division]] of the [[XV Corps (United States)|US XV Corps]] advanced {{convert|35|mi|km|abbr=on}} and reached positions overlooking Argentan.&lt;ref name=Wilmot417&gt;Wilmot, p. 417&lt;/ref&gt; On 13 August, Bradley over-ruled orders by Patton for a further push northwards towards Falaise by the 5th Armored Division.&lt;ref name=Wilmot417/&gt; Bradley instead ordered the XV Corps to "concentrate for operations in another direction".&lt;ref name="Essame168"&gt;Essame, p. 168&lt;/ref&gt; The US troops near Argentan were ordered to withdraw, which ended the pincer movement by the XV Corps.&lt;ref name="Essame182"&gt;Essame, p. 182&lt;/ref&gt; Patton objected but complied, which left an exit for the German forces in the Falaise Pocket.&lt;ref name="Essame182"/&gt;{{refn|Bradley later received much blame for "failing" to exploit the opportunity to envelop Army Group B.&lt;ref name=Wilmot417/&gt; General [[Hans Speidel]], Chief of Staff of Army Group B, wrote that they would have been eliminated, if the 5th Armored Division had continued its advance to Falaise, although [[Carlo D'Este|D'Este]] wrote that the order came from Montgomery.&lt;ref name="Essame182"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 441&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}

With the Americans on the southern flank halted and then engaged with [[Panzer Group Eberbach]], and with the British pressing in from the north-west, the First Canadian Army, which included the [[Polish 1st Armoured Division]], was ordered to close the trap.&lt;ref name=Wilmot419&gt;Wilmot, p. 419&lt;/ref&gt; After a limited attack by the [[2nd Canadian Infantry Division]] down the [[Laize-la-Ville|Laize]] valley on 12–13 August, most of the time since Totalize had been spent preparing for [[Operation Tractable]], a set-piece attack on Falaise.&lt;ref name=Hastings301&gt;Hastings, p. 301&lt;/ref&gt; The operation commenced on 14 August at 11:42, covered by an artillery [[smoke screen|smokescreen]] that mimicked the night attack of Operation Totalize.&lt;ref name=Hastings301/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bercuson231&gt;Bercuson, p. 231&lt;/ref&gt; The 4th Canadian Armoured Division and the 1st Polish Armoured Division crossed the Laison, but delays at the River [[Dives (river)|Dives]] gave time for the Tiger tanks of the {{lang|de|[[102nd SS Heavy Panzer Battalion|schwere SS-Panzer Abteilung 102]]}} to counter-attack.&lt;ref name=Bercuson231/&gt;

Navigating through the smoke slowed progress, and the mistaken use by the First Canadian Army of yellow smoke to identify their positions—the same colour strategic bombers used to mark targets—led to some bombing of the Canadians and slower progress than planned.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 354&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hastings302&gt;Hastings, p. 302&lt;/ref&gt; On 15 August, the [[2nd Canadian Infantry Division|2nd]] and [[3rd Canadian Infantry Division]]s and the [[2nd Canadian (Armoured) Brigade]] continued the offensive, but progress remained slow.&lt;ref name=Hastings302/&gt;&lt;ref name=vandervat169&gt;Van Der Vat, p. 169&lt;/ref&gt; The 4th Armoured Division captured [[Soulangy]] against determined German resistance and several German counter-attacks, which prevented a breakthrough to [[Trun, Orne|Trun]].&lt;ref name="Bercuson 232"&gt;Bercuson, p. 232&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, the 2nd Canadian Infantry Division entered Falaise against minor opposition from ''[[Waffen SS]]'' units and scattered pockets of German infantry, and by 17 August had secured the town.&lt;ref name=Copp104&gt;Copp (2006), p. 104&lt;/ref&gt;

At midday on 16 August, Kluge had refused an order from Hitler for another counter-attack, and in the afternoon Hitler agreed to a withdrawal but became suspicious that Kluge intended to surrender to the Allies.&lt;ref name=Hastings302/&gt;&lt;ref name= Wilmot420&gt;Wilmot, p. 420&lt;/ref&gt; Late on 17 August, Hitler sacked Kluge and recalled him to Germany; Kluge then either killed himself or was executed by SS-officer [[Jürgen Stroop]] for his involvement in the [[20 July plot]].&lt;ref name=Hastings303/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Moczarski, 1981, pp. 226–234&lt;/ref&gt; Kluge was succeeded by Field Marshal [[Walter Model]], whose first act was to order the immediate retreat of the 7th Army and Fifth Panzer Army, while the ''[[II SS Panzer Corps]]''—with the remnants of four Panzer divisions—held the north face of the escape route against the British and Canadians, and the ''[[XLVII Panzer Corps (Germany)|XLVII Panzer Corps]]''—with what was left of two Panzer divisions—held the southern face against the Third US Army.&lt;ref name=Hastings303/&gt;

===Encirclement===
{{main|Hill 262}}
[[File:Hill 262 20 Aug 1944.svg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;German counter-attacks against Canadian-Polish positions on 20 August 1944&lt;/center&gt;]]
By 17 August the encirclement was incomplete.&lt;ref name=Hastings303&gt;Hastings, p. 303&lt;/ref&gt; The 1st Polish Armoured Division, part of the First Canadian Army, was divided into three battlegroups and ordered to make a wide sweep to the south-east to meet American troops at Chambois.&lt;ref name=Hastings303/&gt; Trun fell to the 4th Canadian Armoured Division on 18 August.&lt;ref name="Zuehlke 169"&gt;Zuehlke, p. 169&lt;/ref&gt; Having captured [[Champeaux, Manche|Champeaux]] on 19 August, the Polish battlegroups converged on Chambois, and with reinforcements from the 4th Canadian Armoured Division, the Poles secured the town and linked up with the US 90th and French [[2nd Armored Division (France)|2nd Armoured]] divisions by evening.&lt;ref name=Wilmot422&gt;Wilmot, p. 422&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Jarymowycz192&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 192&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hastings304&gt;Hastings, p. 304&lt;/ref&gt; The Allies were not yet astride the 7th Army escape route in any great strength, and their positions were attacked by German troops inside the pocket.&lt;ref name=Hastings304/&gt; An armoured column of the 2nd Panzer Division broke through the Canadians in [[Saint-Lambert, Calvados|St. Lambert]], took half the village and kept a road open for six hours until nightfall.&lt;ref name=Wilmot422/&gt; Many Germans escaped, and small parties made their way through to the Dives during the night.&lt;ref name=Wilmot423&gt;Wilmot, p.423&lt;/ref&gt;

Having taken Chambois, two of the Polish battlegroups drove north-east and established themselves on part of [[Hill 262]] (Mont Ormel ridge), spending the night of 19 August digging in.&lt;ref name="deste 456"&gt;D'Este, p. 456&lt;/ref&gt; The following morning, Model ordered elements of the 2nd SS Panzer Division and [[9th SS Panzer Division Hohenstaufen|9th SS Panzer Division]] to attack from outside the pocket towards the Polish positions.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz195"&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 195&lt;/ref&gt; Around midday, several units of the [[10th SS Panzer Division Frundsberg|10th SS Panzer Division]], 12th SS Panzer Division and [[116th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|116th Panzer Division]] managed to break through the Polish lines and open a corridor, while the 9th SS Panzer Division prevented the Canadians from intervening.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz196"&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 196&lt;/ref&gt; By mid-afternoon, about 10,000 German troops had passed out of the pocket.&lt;ref name="Van-Der-Vat 168"/&gt;

[[Image:Polish hill 262.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Polish infantry moving towards cover on [[Hill 262]], 20 August 1944&lt;/center&gt;]]
The Poles held on to Hill 262 (The Mace), and were able from their vantage point to direct artillery fire on to the retreating Germans.&lt;ref name="D'Este 458"&gt;D'Este, p. 458&lt;/ref&gt; [[Paul Hausser]], the 7th Army commander, ordered that the Polish positions be "eliminated".&lt;ref name="Van-Der-Vat 168"&gt;Van Der Vat, p. 168&lt;/ref&gt; The remnants of the [[352nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|352nd Infantry Division]] and several battle groups from the 2nd SS Panzer Division inflicted many casualties on the 8th and 9th battalions of the Polish Division, but the assault was eventually repulsed at the cost of nearly all of their ammunition, and the Poles watched as the remnants of the XLVII Panzer Corps escaped. During the night there was sporadic fighting, and the Poles called for frequent artillery bombardments to disrupt the German retreat from the sector.&lt;ref name="D'Este 458"/&gt;

[[File:St.-Lambert-surrender.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Germans surrendering in St. Lambert on 19 August 1944&lt;/center&gt;]]
German attacks resumed the next morning, but the Poles retained their foothold on the ridge. At about 11:00, a final attempt on the positions of the 9th Battalion was launched by nearby SS troops, which was defeated at close quarters.&lt;ref name=McGilvray54&gt;McGilvray, p. 54&lt;/ref&gt; Soon after midday, the [[The Canadian Grenadier Guards|Canadian Grenadier Guards]] reached Mont Ormel, and by late afternoon the remainder of the 2nd and 9th SS Panzer Divisions had begun their retreat to the Seine.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 232"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Bercuson 233"/&gt; For the Falaise pocket operation, the 1st Polish Armoured Division listed 1,441 casualties including 466 killed,&lt;ref name=Copp2003249&gt;Copp (2003), p. 249&lt;/ref&gt; while Polish casualties at Mont Ormel were 351 killed and wounded, with eleven tanks lost.&lt;ref name="McGilvray54"/&gt; German losses in their assaults on the ridge were {{circa|500 dead}} and 1,000 men taken prisoner, most from the 12th SS-Panzer Division. Scores of [[Tiger I|Tiger]], Panther and Panzer IV tanks were destroyed, along with many artillery pieces.&lt;ref name="McGilvray54"/&gt;

By the evening of 21 August, tanks of the 4th Canadian Armoured Division had linked with Polish forces at [[Coudehard]], and the 2nd and 3rd Canadian Infantry divisions had secured St. Lambert and the northern passage to Chambois; the Falaise pocket had been sealed.&lt;ref name=Hastings313&gt;Hastings, p. 313&lt;/ref&gt; Approximately 20–50,000 German troops, minus heavy equipment, escaped through the gap and were reorganized and rearmed, in time to slow the Allied advance into the Netherlands and Germany.&lt;ref name="Essame182"/&gt;

==Aftermath==

===Analysis===
[[File:The British Army in Normandy 1944 B9627.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;German prisoners taken during the battle are given tea by their captors.&lt;/center&gt;]]
The Battle of the Falaise Pocket ended the Battle of Normandy with a decisive German defeat.&lt;ref name=Williams204/&gt; Hitler's involvement had been damaging from the first, with his insistence on hopelessly unrealistic counter-offensives, [[micro-management]] of generals, and refusal to countenance withdrawal when his armies were threatened with annihilation.&lt;ref name=Williams205&gt;Williams, p. 205&lt;/ref&gt; More than forty German divisions were destroyed during the Battle of Normandy. No exact figures are available, but historians estimate that the battle cost the German forces {{circa|450,000 men}}, of whom {{nowrap|240,000 were}} killed or wounded.&lt;ref name=Williams205/&gt; The Allies had achieved victory at a cost of {{nowrap|209,672 casualties}} among the ground forces, including {{nowrap|36,976 killed}} and {{nowrap|19,221 missing}}.&lt;ref name=Hastings313/&gt; The Allied air forces lost {{nowrap|16,714 airmen}} killed or missing in connection with Operation Overlord.&lt;ref&gt;Tamelander, Zetterling, p. 341.&lt;/ref&gt; The final battle of Operation Overlord, the [[Liberation of Paris]], followed on 25 August, and Overlord ended by 30 August, with the retreat of the last German unit across the Seine.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 319&lt;/ref&gt;

The area in which the pocket had formed was full of the remains of battle.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 311&lt;/ref&gt; Villages had been destroyed, and derelict equipment made some roads impassable. Corpses of soldiers and civilians littered the area, along with thousands of dead cattle and horses.&lt;ref name=Lucas158&gt;Lucas &amp; Barker, p. 158&lt;/ref&gt; In the hot August weather, maggots crawled over the bodies, and swarms of flies descended on the area.&lt;ref name =Lucas158/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hastings312&gt;Hastings, p. 312&lt;/ref&gt; Pilots reported being able to smell the stench of the battlefield hundreds of feet above it.&lt;ref name=Lucas158/&gt; General Eisenhower recorded that:

{{quote|The battlefield at Falaise was unquestionably one of the greatest "killing fields" of any of the war areas. Forty-eight hours after the closing of the gap I was conducted through it on foot, to encounter scenes that could be described only by [[Dante Alighieri|Dante]]. It was literally possible to walk for hundreds of yards at a time, stepping on nothing but dead and decaying flesh.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eisenhower|1948|p=279}}&lt;/ref&gt;|Dwight Eisenhower}}

Fear of infection from the rancid conditions led the Allies to declare the area an "unhealthy zone".&lt;ref&gt;Lucas &amp; Barker, p. 159&lt;/ref&gt; Clearing the area was a low priority though, and went on until well into November. Many swollen bodies had to be shot to expunge gases within them before they could be burnt, and bulldozers were used to clear the area of dead animals.&lt;ref name=Lucas158/&gt;&lt;ref name=Hastings312/&gt;

Disappointed that a significant portion of the 7th Army had escaped from the pocket, many Allied commanders, particularly among the Americans, were critical of what they perceived as Montgomery's lack of urgency in closing the pocket.&lt;ref name="Wilmot424"/&gt; Writing shortly after the war, [[Ralph Ingersoll (PM publisher)|Ralph Ingersoll]]—a prominent peacetime journalist, who had served as a planner on Eisenhower's staff—expressed the prevailing American view at the time:

{{quote|The international army boundary arbitrarily divided the British and American battlefields just beyond Argentan, on the Falaise side of it. Patton's troops, who thought they had the mission of closing the gap, took Argentan in their stride and crossed the international boundary without stopping. Montgomery, who was still nominally in charge of all ground forces, now chose to exercise his authority and ordered Patton back to his side of the international boundary line. For ten days, however, the beaten but still coherently organized German Army retreated through the Falaise gap.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Ingersoll|1946|pp=190–191}}&lt;/ref&gt;|Ralph Ingersoll}}

Some historians have thought that the gap could have been closed earlier; [[Chester Wilmot|Wilmot]] wrote that despite having British divisions in reserve, Montgomery did not reinforce [[Guy Simonds]] and that the Canadian drive on Trun and Chambois was not "vigorous and venturesome" as the situation demanded.&lt;ref name="Wilmot424"/&gt; The British author and historian Max Hastings wrote that Montgomery, having witnessed what he called a poor Canadian performance during Totalize, should have brought up veteran British divisions to take the lead.&lt;ref name="Hastings353"/&gt; [[Carlo D'Este|D'Este]] and [[Martin Blumenson|Blumenson]] wrote that Montgomery and [[Harry Crerar]] might have done more to impart momentum to the British and Canadians. Patton's post-battle claim that the Americans could have prevented the German escape, had Bradley not ordered him to stop at Argentan, was "absurd over-simplification".&lt;ref name="Hastings369"&gt;Hastings, p. 369&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Chambois1.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;General Eisenhower reviewing damage (including a wrecked [[Tiger II]]) in the pocket at Chambois&lt;/center&gt;]]
Wilmot wrote that "contrary to contemporary reports, the Americans did not capture Argentan until 20 August, the day after the link up at Chambois".&lt;ref name="Wilmot425"&gt;Wilmot, p. 425&lt;/ref&gt; The American unit that closed the gap between Argentan and Chambois, the [[90th Infantry Division (United States)|90th Division]], was according to Hastings one of the least effective of any Allied army in Normandy. He speculated that the real reason Bradley halted Patton was not fear of accidental clashes with the British, but knowledge that, with powerful German formations still operational, the Americans lacked the means to defend an early blocking position and would have suffered an "embarrassing and gratuitous setback" at the hands of the retreating ''[[Fallschirmjäger (Nazi Germany)|Fallschirmjäger]]'' and the 2nd and 12th ''SS-Panzer'' divisions.&lt;ref name="Hastings369"/&gt; Bradley wrote after the war that:

{{quote|Although Patton might have spun a line across the narrow neck, I doubted his ability to hold it. Nineteen German divisions were now stampeding to escape the trap. Meanwhile, with four divisions George was already blocking three principal escape routes through Alencon, Sees and Argentan. Had he stretched that line to include Falaise, he would have extended his roadblock a distance of {{convert|40|mi|km}}. The enemy could not only have broken through, but he might have trampled Patton's position in the onrush. I much preferred a solid shoulder at Argentan to the possibility of a broken neck at Falaise.&lt;ref&gt;Bradley, p. 377&lt;/ref&gt;|Omar Bradley}}

===Casualties===
By 22 August, all German forces west of the Allied lines were dead or in captivity.&lt;ref name=Hastings306&gt;Hastings, p. 306&lt;/ref&gt; Historians differ in their estimates of German losses in the pocket. The majority state that from {{nowrap|80,000–100,000 troops}} were caught in the encirclement, of whom {{nowrap|10,000–15,000 were}} killed, {{nowrap|40,000–50,000 were}} taken prisoner, and {{nowrap|20,000–50,000 escaped}}. [[Milton Shulman|Shulman]], Wilmot and [[Lionel Ellis|Ellis]] estimated that the remnants of {{nowrap|14–15 divisions}} were in the pocket. D'Este gave {{nowrap|80,000 troops}} trapped, of whom {{nowrap|10,000 were killed}}, {{nowrap|50,000 captured}} and {{nowrap|20,000 escaped}}.&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, pp. 430–431&lt;/ref&gt; Shulman gives {{circa|80,000 trapped}}, {{nowrap|10–15,000 killed}} and {{nowrap|45,000 captured}}.&lt;ref&gt;Shulman, pp. 180, 184&lt;/ref&gt; Wilmot recorded {{nowrap|100,000 trapped}}, {{nowrap|10,000 killed}} and {{nowrap|50,000 captured}}.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot, pp. 422, 424&lt;/ref&gt; [[Andrew Williams (novelist)|Williams]] wrote that {{circa|100,000 German}} troops escaped.&lt;ref name=Williams204&gt;Williams, p. 204&lt;/ref&gt; Tamelander estimated that {{nowrap|50,000 German}} troops were caught, of whom {{nowrap|10,000 were}} killed and {{nowrap|40,000 taken}} prisoner, while perhaps another {{nowrap|50,000 escaped}}.&lt;ref&gt;Tamelander, Zetterling, p. 342&lt;/ref&gt; In the northern sector, German losses included {{nowrap|344 tanks}}, self-propelled guns and other light armoured vehicles, as well {{nowrap|as 2,447}} [[soft-skinned vehicle]]s and {{nowrap|252 guns}} abandoned or destroyed.&lt;ref name=Hastings313/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Reynolds, p. 88&lt;/ref&gt; In the fighting around Hill 262, German losses totalled {{nowrap|2,000 men}} killed, {{nowrap|5,000 taken}} prisoner and {{nowrap|55 tanks}}, {{nowrap|44 guns}} and {{nowrap|152 other}} armoured vehicles destroyed.&lt;ref name=mcgilvray55&gt;McGilvray, p. 55&lt;/ref&gt; The 12th SS-Panzer Division had lost {{nowrap|94 percent of}} its armour, nearly all of its artillery and {{nowrap|70 percent of}} its vehicles. With close to {{nowrap|20,000 men}} and {{nowrap|150 tanks}} before the Normandy campaign, after Falaise it was reduced to {{nowrap|300 men}} and {{nowrap|10 tanks}}.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 233"&gt;Bercuson, p. 233&lt;/ref&gt; Although elements of several German formations had managed to escape to the east, even these had left behind most of their equipment.&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, p. 314&lt;/ref&gt; After the battle, Allied investigators estimated that the Germans lost around {{nowrap|500 tanks}} and assault guns in the pocket, and that little of the extricated equipment survived the retreat across the Seine.&lt;ref name="Wilmot424"&gt;Wilmot, p. 424&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Portal|World War II}}

===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|group=nb}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|15em}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book |first=R.|last=Bennett |title=Ultra in the West: The Normandy Campaign of 1944–1945 |publisher=[[Hutchinson (publisher)|Hutchinson]] |location=London|year=1979|isbn=0-09-139330-2}}
* {{cite book|first=D.|last=Bercuson|authorlink=David Bercuson|title=Maple Leaf Against the Axis|publisher=[[Red Deer Press]]|location=Markham, Ontario|year=2004|isbn=0-88995-305-8|origyear=1996|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/mapleleafagainst0000berc}}
* {{cite book |last=Bradley|first=Omar|authorlink=Omar Bradley|title=A Soldier's Story|origyear=1951 |publisher=[[Henry Holt and Company|Holt]] |location=New York|series=Modern Library|year=1999|isbn=978-037-575421-0}}
* {{cite book |first=T. |last=Copp|title=Cinderella Army: The Canadians in Northwest Europe, 1944–1945 |publisher=[[University of Toronto Press]] |location=Toronto|year=2006 |isbn=0-8020-3925-1}}
* {{cite book|first=T.|last=Copp|author-mask=3|title=Fields of Fire: The Canadians in Normandy |publisher=University of Toronto Press|location=Toronto|year=2007|origyear=2003|isbn=978-0-8020-3780-0}}
* {{cite book|first=Carlo|last=D'Este|authorlink=Carlo D'Este|title=Decision in Normandy: The Real Story of Montgomery and the Allied Campaign|publisher=[[Penguin Books]] |location=London|year=2004|isbn=0-141-01761-9|origyear=1983}}
* {{cite book|first=Dwight D.|last=Eisenhower|authorlink=Dwight D. Eisenhower|year=1948|title=[[Crusade in Europe]] |publisher=[[Doubleday (publisher)|Doubleday]] |location=New York}}
* {{cite book|first1=Major L.F.|last1=Ellis|author-link1=Lionel Ellis|first2=Captain G.R.G., R.N. |last2=Allen|first3=Lieutenant-Colonel A.E.|last3=Warhurst|first4=Air Chief-Marshal Sir James|last4=Robb |author-link4=James Robb (RAF officer) |editor-last=Butler|editor-first=J.R.M.|editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler|series=History of the Second World War United Kingdom Military|title=Victory in the West: The Battle of Normandy|volume=I|edition=Naval &amp; Military Press|year=2004|publisher=[[HMSO]] |location=London|origyear=1962 |isbn=1-84574-058-0|lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book|first=H.|last=Essame|authorlink=Hubert Essame|title=Patton: as Military Commander|publisher=[[Da Capo Press]] |location=New York|year=1988|origyear=1973|isbn=978-0-585-10019-7}}
* {{cite book|first=T.|last=Griess|title=The Second World War: Europe and the Mediterranean|location=United States Military Academy West Point, New York|publisher=[[Square One Publishers|Square One]]|year=2002|isbn=0-7570-0160-2}}
* {{cite book|first=S.A. |last=Hart|title=Colossal Cracks: Montgomery's 21st Army Group in Northwest Europe, 1944–45|publisher=[[Stackpole Books]] |location=Mechanicsburg, Pennsylvania|year=2007|origyear=2000 |isbn=978-0-8117-3383-0}}
* {{cite book|first=M.|last=Hastings|authorlink=Max Hastings|title=Overlord: D-Day and the Battle for Normandy|publisher=[[Vintage Books]] USA|edition=reprint|location=New York|year=2006|isbn=0-307-27571-X |origyear=1985}}
* {{cite book|last=Ingersoll|first=Ralph|authorlink=Ralph Ingersoll (PM publisher) |title=Top Secret |publisher=[[Harcourt (publisher)|Harcourt Brace]] |year=1946|location=New York}}
* {{cite book|first=R.|last=Jarymowycz|authorlink=Roman Jarymowycz|title=Tank Tactics: from Normandy to Lorraine|publisher=[[Lynne Rienner Publishers|Lynne Rienner]] |location=Boulder, Colorado|year=2001 |isbn=1-55587-950-0}}
* {{cite book|first=B.H.|last=Liddell Hart|authorlink=B. H. Liddell Hart|title=The Rommel Papers |edition=15|publisher=Harcourt Brace|location=New York|year=1953}}
* {{cite book|last1=Lucas|first1=James|last2=Barker|first2=James|title=The Killing Ground, The Battle of the Falaise Gap, August 1944|publisher=[[Pavilion Books|B T Batsford]] |location=London|year=1978 |isbn=0-7134-0433-7}}
* {{cite book |first=Evan|last=McGilvray|title=The Black Devils' March – A Doomed Odyssey – The 1st Polish Armoured Division 1939–45|publisher=[[Helion (publisher)|Helion]] |location=Solihull|year=2004|isbn=978-1-874622-42-0}}
* {{cite book|last=Messenger|first=Charles|title=The Illustrated Book of World War II|publisher=[[Thunder Bay Press|Thunder Bay]] |year=1999|location=San Diego, California|isbn=1-57145-217-6}}
* {{cite book|first1=K.|last1=Moczarski|authorlink=Kazimierz Moczarski|first2=Mariana|last2=Fitzpatrick |first3=Jürgen|last3=Stroop|title=Conversations with an Executioner|year=1981|publisher=[[Prentice Hall]] |location=New Jersey|isbn=0-13-171918-1}}
* {{cite book|first=Michael|last=Reynolds|title=Sons of the Reich: The History of II SS Panzer Corps in Normandy, Arnhem, the Ardennes and on the Eastern Front|publisher=[[Casemate Publishers|Casemate]] |location=Philadelphia|year=2002|isbn=0-9711709-3-2}}
* {{cite book|first=M.|last=Shulman|authorlink=Milton Shulman|title=Defeat in the West|publisher=[[Kessinger Publishing|Kessinger]] |location=Whitefish, MN|year=2007|origyear=1947|isbn=978-0-548-43948-7}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/his/docs/Victory_e.pdf|accessdate=6 April 2014|first=Colonel C. P.|last=Stacey |authorlink=|author2=Bond, Major C.C.J.|series=Official History of the Canadian Army in the Second World War|volume=III|title=The Victory Campaign: The operations in North-West Europe 1944–1945|publisher=The Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery, Ottawa|year=1960 |oclc=606015967}}
* {{cite book|last1=Tamelander|first1=Michael|last2=Zetterling|first2=Niklas|title=Avgörandes ögonblick: Invasionen i Normandie 1944|trans-title=The moment of decision: The invasion of Normandy 1944|publisher=[[Norstedts förlag]] |location=Stockholm|language=sv|year=2003|origyear=1995|isbn=91-1-301204-5}}
* {{cite book|last1=Trew|first1=Simon|last2=Badsey|first2=Stephen|series=Battle Zone Normandy|title=Battle for Caen|publisher=[[The History Press]] |location=Stroud|year=2004|isbn=0-7509-3010-1}}
* {{cite book|first=Dan|last=van der Vat|authorlink=Dan van der Vat|title=D-Day; The Greatest Invasion, A People's History|publisher=Madison Press|location=Aurora, Illinois|year=2003|isbn=1-55192-586-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Williams|first=A.|authorlink=Andrew Williams (novelist)|title=D-Day to Berlin|publisher=[[Hodder &amp; Stoughton]]|location=London|year=2004|isbn=0-340-83397-1|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/ddaytoberlin0000will}}
* {{cite book|first1=Chester|last1=Wilmot|authorlink=Chester Wilmot|first2=C.D.|last2=McDevitt|title=The Struggle for Europe|publisher=[[Wordsworth Editions]] |location=Ware|year=1997|isbn=1-85326-677-9 |origyear=1952}}
* {{cite book|first=Mark|last=Zuehlke|title=The Canadian Military Atlas: Canada's Battlefields from the French and Indian Wars to Kosovo|publisher=[[Stoddart Publishing|Stoddart]] |location=North York, Ontario |year=2001|isbn=0-7737-3289-6}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book|first=J.|last=Keegan|authorlink=John Keegan|title=Atlas of World War II |publisher=[[HarperCollins]] |location=New York|year=2006|isbn=0-06-089077-0}}

{{Refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Falaise Pocket}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/ww2peopleswar/stories/46/a2450846.shtml|title=Account of the Polish battle on hill 262|last=[[British Broadcasting Corporation]] |accessdate=}}
* {{cite web|url=http://canadiansoldiers.com/history/battlehonours/northwesteurope/falaise.htm |title=canadiansoldiers.com: Falaise|last=|first= |accessdate=}}
* {{cite web |url=http://wwii.ca/page23.html|title=Canada at War: Canadians in the Falaise Gap|last= |first=|accessdate=}}
* {{cite web|url=http://wwii.ca/page51.html|title=Canada at War: The Battle of Hill 195|last=|first= |accessdate=}}
* {{cite web|url=http://wwii.ca/page27.html|title=Canada at War: The Battle at St. Lambert-Sur-dives|last= |first=|accessdate=}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.opusmedia.fr/kazimierzduda/default_gb.asp|title=Captain Kazimierz DUDA – 1st Polish Armoured Division|last1=Richard|first1=Duda|last2=Steven|first2=Duda|access-date=|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070314020958/http://www.opusmedia.fr/kazimierzduda/default_gb.asp|archive-date=14 March 2007|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}
* {{cite web|url=http://www.memorial-montormel.org/?id=50|title=Closing of the Falaise Pocket|last=Wiacek |first=Jacques|access-date=|url-status=dead |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070928103427/https://www.memorial-montormel.org/?id=50 |archive-date=28 September 2007 |df=}}
* {{cite web|url=http://s143.photobucket.com/albums/r134/51highland/?action=view&amp;current=Falaise.flv |title=Film footage of the battle|last= |first=|accessdate=}}
* {{cite web |title=Chapter 4. Polish military operations in West-Europe since 1944 |url=http://www.polishsoldier.nl/chapter-4-polish-military-operations-in-west-europe-since-1944/ |website=Polish forces in the West |access-date=10 January 2016 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160530143215/http://www.polishsoldier.nl/chapter-4-polish-military-operations-in-west-europe-since-1944/ |archive-date=30 May 2016 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}

{{World War II}}
{{Battle of Normandy}}
{{Authority control}}

{{Featured article}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Falaise Pocket}}
[[Category:Operation Overlord]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Poland]]
[[Category:Encirclements in World War II]]
[[Category:Tank battles]]
[[Category:August 1944 events]]
[[Category:1944 in France]]
[[Category:Calvados (department)]]</text><sha1>479sj8vntrzw587t99zfyxz0bfkx2fl</sha1></revision></page>