<page><title>Operation Tractable</title><ns>0</ns><id>4335043</id><revision><id>963117214</id><parentid>921280645</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-17T22:58:28Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Srich32977</username><id>8372814</id></contributor><comment>MOS:DASH; Removed parameters. | You can [[WP:UCB|use this tool]] yourself. [[WP:DBUG|Report bugs here]]. | via #UCB_Gadget  | Cleaned up using [[WP:AutoEd|AutoEd]]</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="33828" xml:space="preserve">{{Use Canadian English|date=April 2016}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Operation Tractable
| partof      = [[Operation Overlord]]
| image       = File:Tractable-offensive.jpg
|image_size = 300px
| caption     = Canadian forces moving toward [[Falaise, Calvados|Falaise]] on 14 August 1944
| date        = 14–21 August 1944
| place       = North of [[Falaise, Calvados|Falaise]], [[Normandy]], [[France]]
| territory   =
| result      = Allied victory
| status      =
| combatant1  = {{flag|Canada|1921}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Poland|1928}} [[Polish Armed Forces in the West|Poland]]&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;ref name="Fortin68"/&gt;
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[Harry Crerar]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[Guy Simonds]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Poland|1928}} [[Stanisław Maczek]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Walter Model]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Kurt Meyer]]
| strength1   = 2 infantry divisions&lt;br&gt;2 armoured divisions&lt;br&gt;1 armoured brigade&lt;br&gt;1 tank brigade&lt;ref name="Fortin68"&gt;Fortin, p. 68&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 1 SS ''panzer'' division&lt;br&gt;2 infantry divisions
| casualties1 = '''Canada''':&lt;br&gt;5,500 casualties&lt;br&gt;'''Poland''':&lt;br&gt;325 killed&lt;br&gt;1,002 wounded&lt;br&gt;114 missing
| casualties2 = 2,000 killed&lt;br&gt;5,000 captured&lt;br&gt;55 tanks destroyed&lt;br&gt;152 armoured vehicles destroyed&lt;br&gt;44 guns destroyed
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Normandy}}
}}

'''Operation Tractable''' was the final attack conducted by [[Canada in World War II|Canadian]] and [[Polish contribution to World War II|Polish]] troops, supported by a British tank brigade, during the [[Operation Overlord|Battle of Normandy]] during [[World War II]]. The operation was to capture the tactically important [[France|French]] town of [[Falaise, Calvados|Falaise]] and then the smaller towns of [[Trun, Orne|Trun]] and [[Chambois, Orne|Chambois]]. This operation was undertaken by the [[First Canadian Army]] with the [[1st Armoured Division (Poland)|1st Polish Armoured Division]] (''[[Generał brygady]]'' [[Stanisław Maczek]]) and a British armoured brigade against [[Army Group B]] of the ''[[Westheer]]'' in what became the largest encirclement on the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]] during the Second World War. Despite a slow start and limited gains north of Falaise, novel tactics by the 1st Polish Armoured Division during the drive for [[Chambois, Orne|Chambois]] enabled the [[Falaise Pocket|Falaise Gap]] to be partially closed by 19 August 1944, trapping about 150,000 German soldiers in the Falaise Pocket.

Although the Falaise Gap was narrowed to a distance of several hundred metres/yards, as a result of attacks and counter-attacks between battle groups of the 1st Polish Armoured Division and the [[II SS Panzer Corps]] on [[Hill 262]] (Mont Ormel) the gap was not closed quickly and thousands of German troops escaped on foot. During two days of nearly continuous fighting, the Polish forces assisted by [[artillery]]-fire, managed to hold off counter-attacks by seven German divisions in hand-to-hand fighting. On 21 August, elements of the First Canadian Army relieved the Polish survivors and sealed the Falaise Pocket by linking up with the [[United States Army Central|Third US Army]]. This led to the surrender and capture of the remaining units of the German [[7th Army (Wehrmacht)|7th Army]] in the pocket.
{{TOC limit|2}}

==Background==
Following break-out by the US [[U.S. First Army|1st]] and [[U.S. 3rd Army|3rd Armies]] from the beachhead during the [[Operation Overlord|Battle of Normandy]] after [[Operation Cobra]] on 25 July 1944, [[Adolf Hitler]] ordered an immediate counterattack against Allied forces in the form of [[Operation Lüttich]]. [[Lieutenant general (United States)|Lieutenant General]] [[Omar Bradley]]—the commanding general of the US [[12th Army Group]]—was notified of the counterattack in advance through signals intercepted via [[Ultra]] radio intercepts and deciphering and thus prepared his troops and their commanders to defeat this counteroffensive and to encircle as much of the ''Wehrmacht'' force as possible.&lt;ref name="VanDerVat163"/&gt; By the afternoon of 7 August, Operation Lüttich had been defeated by concerted, large-scale [[fighter-bomber]] air strikes against the German tanks and trucks. In the process, forces of the [[7th Army (Wehrmacht)|German 7th Army]] became further enveloped by the Allied advance out of Normandy.&lt;ref name="VanDerVat163"&gt;Van der Vat, p. 163&lt;/ref&gt;

Following these failed German offensives, the town of Falaise became a major objective of Commonwealth forces, since its capture would cut off virtually all of ''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'' [[Günther von Kluge]]'s Army Group B.&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 404&lt;/ref&gt; To achieve this, General [[Harry Crerar]], commanding the newly formed Canadian 1st Army and [[Lieutenant-General]] [[Guy Simonds]]—commanding the [[II Canadian Corps|Canadian II Corps]], planned an Anglo-Canadian offensive with the code name of [[Operation Totalize]]. This offensive was designed to break through the defences in the Anglo-Canadian sector of the Normandy front.&lt;ref&gt;Zuehlke, p. 168&lt;/ref&gt; Operation Totalize would rely on an unusual night attack using heavy [[bomber]]s and the new [[Kangaroo (armoured personnel carrier)|Kangaroo armoured personnel carriers]] to achieve a breakthrough of German defences. Despite initial gains on [[Battle of Verrières Ridge|Verrières Ridge]] and near Cintheaux, the [[Canadian Army]]'s offensive stalled on 9 August, with strong ''Wehrmacht'' counterattacks resulting in heavy casualties for the Canadian and Polish armoured and infantry divisions.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 230"&gt;Bercuson, p. 230&lt;/ref&gt; By 10 August, Canadian troops had reached Hill 195, north of Falaise. They were unable to advance farther immediately and they had been unable to capture Falaise.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 230"/&gt;

==Prelude==
===Offensive strategy===
[[File:Operation Tractable.svg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Allied gains during the Canadian offensives of Operations Totalize and Tractable&lt;/center&gt;]]

Operation Tractable incorporated lessons learned from Operation Totalize, notably the effectiveness of mechanized infantry units and tactical bombing raids by heavy bombers.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 231"&gt;Bercuson, p. 231&lt;/ref&gt; Unlike the previous operation, Tractable was launched in daylight. An initial bombing raid was to weaken German defences and was to be followed by an advance by the [[4th Canadian (Armoured) Division|Canadian 4th Armoured Division]] on the western flank of Hill 195, while the [[3rd Canadian Infantry Division|Canadian 3rd Infantry Division]] attacked on the eastern flank with the [[2nd Canadian Armoured Brigade|Canadian 2nd Armoured Brigade]] in support. Their advance would be protected by a large smokescreen laid down by Canadian artillery.&lt;ref name= "Bercuson 231"/&gt; [[Field Marshal]] [[Bernard Montgomery]] hoped that Canadian forces would achieve control of Falaise by midnight on August 14. From there, all three formations would advance towards [[Trun, Orne|Trun]], {{convert|18|km|mi|0}} east of Falaise, with the additional assistance of the [[1st Armoured Division (Poland)|Polish 1st Armoured Division]], numbering approximately 10,000 men.&lt;ref&gt;McGilvray, p. 52&lt;/ref&gt; Once in Trun, a linkup with the [[U.S. Third Army|American 3rd Army]] at Chambois could be quickly accomplished.&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 429&lt;/ref&gt;

The main opposition to Simonds's force was the [[12th SS Panzer Division Hitlerjugend|12th SS Panzer Division]], which included the remnants of two infantry divisions. German forces within the Falaise Pocket approached 350,000 men.&lt;ref&gt;Bercuson, p. 229&lt;/ref&gt; Had surprise been achieved, the Canadians would likely have succeeded in a rapid break-through.&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 430&lt;/ref&gt; However, on the night of 13/14 August, a Canadian officer lost his way while moving between divisional headquarters. He drove into German lines and was promptly killed. The Germans discovered a copy of Simonds' orders on his body.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 231"/&gt; As a result, the 12th SS Panzer Division placed the bulk of its remaining strength—500&amp;nbsp;grenadiers and 15&amp;nbsp;tanks, along with twelve [[8.8 cm PaK 43|8.8 cm PaK 43 anti-tank guns]]—&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot, p. 419&lt;/ref&gt; along the Allies' expected line of approach.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 231"/&gt;

==Battle==
===Initial drive for Falaise===
[[File:Canadian Advance Falaise Ruins.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Canadian troops with armour support advance cautiously through the streets of [[Falaise, Calvados|Falaise]], encountering only light scattered resistance&lt;/center&gt;]]

Operation Tractable began at 12:00 on 14 August, when 800 [[Avro Lancaster]] and [[Handley Page Halifax]] [[heavy bomber]]s of [[RAF Bomber Command]] struck German positions along the front.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 231"/&gt; As with Totalize, many of the bombers mistakenly dropped their bombs short of their targets, causing 400 Polish and Canadian casualties.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 231"/&gt; Covered by a [[smoke screen]] laid down by their artillery, two Canadian divisions moved forwards.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 231"/&gt; Although their line of sight was reduced, German units still managed to inflict severe casualties on the Canadian 4th Armoured Division, which included its Armoured Brigade commander Brigadier Leslie Booth, as the division moved south toward Falaise.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 231"/&gt; Throughout the day, continual attacks by the Canadian 4th and Polish 1st Armoured Divisions managed to force a crossing of the Laison River. Limited access to the crossing points over the Dives River allowed counterattacks by the German [[102nd SS heavy tank battalion|102nd SS Heavy Panzer Battalion]].&lt;ref name="Bercuson 231"/&gt; The town of [[Potigny]] fell to Polish forces in the late afternoon.&lt;ref name="montormel 67"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://montormel.evl.pl/?id=67|title=Operation Tractable|publisher=Memorial Mont-Ormel|accessdate=2008-05-28}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the first day, elements of the Canadian 3rd and 4th Divisions had reached Point 159, directly north of Falaise, although they had been unable to break into the town. To bolster his offensive, Simonds ordered the [[2nd Canadian Infantry Division|Canadian 2nd Infantry Division]] to move toward the front, with the hope that this reinforcement would be sufficient to enable his divisions to capture the town.&lt;ref name= "Copp104"&gt;Copp. p. 104&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the first day's progress was slower than expected, Operation Tractable resumed on 15 August; both armoured divisions pushed southeast toward Falaise.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 188"&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 188&lt;/ref&gt; The Canadian 2nd and 3rd Infantry Divisions—with the support of the [[2nd Canadian (Armoured) Brigade|Canadian 2nd Armoured Brigade]]—continued their drive south towards the town.&lt;ref name="vandervat 169"/&gt; After harsh fighting, the 4th Armoured Division captured Soulangy but the gains made were minimal as strong German resistance prevented a breakthrough to Trun.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 232"&gt;Bercuson, p. 232&lt;/ref&gt; On 16 August, the Canadian 2nd Infantry Division broke into Falaise, encountering minor opposition from ''[[Waffen-SS]]'' units and scattered pockets of German infantry.&lt;ref name="Copp104"/&gt; Although it would take two more days to clear all resistance in the town, the first major objective of Operation Tractable had been achieved. Simonds began to reorganise the bulk of his armoured forces for a renewed push towards Trun to close the Falaise Pocket.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 188"/&gt;

===16–19 August===

====Drives for Trun and Chambois====
The drive for Trun by Polish and Canadian Armoured Divisions began on 16 August, with preliminary attacks in preparation for an assault against Trun and Chambois. On 17 August, both armoured divisions of the Canadian 1st Army advanced.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 231"/&gt; By early afternoon, the Polish 1st Armoured Division had outflanked the 12th SS Panzer Division, enabling several Polish formations to both reach the 4th Armoured Division's objectives and significantly expand the bridgehead northwest of Trun.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 192"&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 192&lt;/ref&gt; [[Stanisław Maczek]]—the Polish divisional commander—split his forces into three battlegroups each of an armoured regiment and an infantry battalion.{{#tag:ref|Jarymowycz gives four battlegroups but this figure is unsupported by other sources.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 192"/&gt;|group=nb}}&lt;ref name= Stacey260&gt;Stacey, p. 260&lt;/ref&gt; One of these struck southwest, cutting off Trun and establishing itself on the high ground dominating the town and the Dives river valley, allowing for a powerful assault by the Canadian 4th Armoured Division on Trun. The town was liberated on the morning of 18 August.&lt;ref name="Zuehlke 169"&gt;Zuehlke, p. 169&lt;/ref&gt;

As Canadian and Polish forces liberated Trun, Maczek's second armoured battlegroup manoeuvred southeast, capturing [[Champeaux-sur-Sarthe|Champeaux]] and anchoring future attacks against Chambois across a {{convert|6|mi|km|0|order=flip|adj=on|abbr=on}} front.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 192"/&gt; At its closest, the front was {{convert|4|mi|km|0|order=flip|abbr=on}}  from forces of the [[V Corps (United States)|US V Corps]] in the town. By the evening of 18 August, all of Maczek's battlegroups had established themselves directly north of Chambois (one outside of the town, one near Vimoutiers and one{{#tag:ref|Jarymowycz states two.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 193"&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 193&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} at the foot of [[Hill 262]]).&lt;ref&gt;Stacey, p. 261&lt;/ref&gt; With reinforcements quickly arriving from the 4th Canadian 4th Armoured Division, Maczek was in an ideal position to close the gap the following day. The presence of the Polish Armoured Division also alerted [[Field Marshal (Germany)|''Generalfeldmarshall'']] [[Walther Model]] of the need to keep the pocket open.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 193"/&gt;

====Closing the Gap====
Early on 19 August, LGen&amp;nbsp;Simonds met with his divisional commanders to finalize plans for closing the gap. The 4th Armoured Division would attack toward Chambois, on the western flank of two battlegroups of the Polish 1st Armoured Division.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 193"/&gt; Two additional Polish battlegroups would strike eastward, securing Hill 262 to cover the eastern flanks of the assault.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 232"/&gt; The 2nd and 3rd Infantry Divisions would continue their grinding offensives against the northern extremities of the Falaise Pocket, inflicting heavy casualties on the exhausted remains of the 12th SS Panzer Division.&lt;ref name="Zuehlke 169"/&gt; The assault began almost immediately after the meeting, with one battlegroup of the Polish 1st advancing toward Chambois and "Currie Task Force" of the 4th Armoured Division covering their advance. Simultaneously, two Polish battlegroups moved for Hill 262. Despite heavy German resistance, Battlegroup Zgorzelski was able to secure Point 137, directly west of Hill 262.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://montormel.evl.pl/?id=69|title=Closing the Falaise Gap|accessdate=2008-06-30| publisher=Memorial Mont-Ormel|date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; By early afternoon, Battlegroup Stefanowicz had captured the hill, annihilating a German infantry company in the process. As a result of the fighting, Polish casualties accounted for nearly 50% of those sustained by the Canadian 1st Army.&lt;ref&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 195. By the night of August 18, Polish fatalities totaled 263, while Canadian fatalities totaled 284&lt;/ref&gt;

By late afternoon of 19 August, Canadian and Polish forces had linked with the US [[80th Division (United States)|80th Division]] and [[90th Sustainment Brigade (United States)|90th Division]] already stationed in the town. The Falaise Gap had been closed, trapping Model's forces. As the linkup occurred, Model's II SS Panzer Corps had begun its counterattack against Polish forces on Hill 262, hoping to reopen the pocket.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 195"/&gt; With American and Canadian forces facing German counterattacks in their sectors, the Polish forces would have to defend against two veteran ''Panzer'' divisions to keep the gap closed.

===20 August===

====St. Lambert-sur-Dives and Hill 117====

[[File:Hill 262 20 Aug 1944.svg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;German counterattacks against Canadian-Polish positions on 20 August 20, 1944&lt;/center&gt;]]
On the morning of 20 August, two German formations—the [[2nd SS Division Das Reich|2nd]] and [[9th SS Panzer Division Hohenstaufen|9th SS Panzer Divisions]], attacked Polish positions on Hill 262.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 195"&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 195&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the [[16th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|16th Infantry]] and 12th SS Panzer Divisions attacked American and Canadian forces from within the pocket, opening small channels through Allied positions. By mid-morning, 2,000 survivors of the German [[2nd Parachute Division (Germany)|2nd Parachute Division]] had managed to breach Canadian positions along the Dives River, as well as at Point&amp;nbsp;117.&lt;ref name="montormel 73"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://montormel.evl.pl/?id=73|title= 2nd SS Panzer Corps counterattack|publisher=Memorial Mont-Ormel|accessdate=2008-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; At approximately noon, several units of the [[10th SS Panzer Division Frundsberg|10th SS]], 12th SS and 116th Panzer Divisions managed to break through these weakened positions.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 196"&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 196&lt;/ref&gt;

By mid afternoon, reinforcements from an armoured battlegroup formed from the [[South Alberta Regiment]] and the [[Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders of Canada]] under Major [[David Vivian Currie]] managed to reach [[St. Lambert-sur-Dives]], denying two German armies evacuation of the pocket. Over the next 36 hours, the battlegroup repulsed almost continual attacks by German forces, destroying seven German tanks, twelve {{convert|88|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} anti-tank guns and 40 vehicles. In the brutal fighting around Lambert-sur-Dives, Currie's battlegroup was able to inflict nearly 2,000 casualties on attacking German forces, including 300 killed and 1,100 captured.&lt;ref name="VAC"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.vac-acc.gc.ca/remembers/sub.cfm?source=history/secondwar/citations/currie|title=David Vivian Currie's Victoria Cross|accessdate=2008-06-30|publisher= Veteran Affairs Canada|date=}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the evening of 20 August, the Germans had exhausted their attack against St. Lambert-sur-Dives; the surviving members of the 84th Corps—commanded by General Elfeld—surrendered to Canadian and American forces near Chambois.&lt;ref name="vandervat 169"/&gt; For his actions at St. Lambert-sur-Dives, Currie was awarded the [[Victoria Cross]], the only Canadian so honoured for service in the Normandy Campaign.&lt;ref name="VAC"/&gt;

====Hill 262 (Mont Ormel)====
{{Main|Hill 262}}

[[File:Polish hill 262.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;Polish Infantry moving towards cover on [[Hill 262|Mont Ormel]], 20 August 1944&lt;/center&gt;]]
While Currie's force stalled German forces outside of St. Lambert, two battlegroups of Maczek's Polish 1st Armoured Division were engaged in a protracted battle with two well-trained SS Panzer divisions. Throughout the night of the 19th, Polish forces had entrenched themselves along the south, southwest and northeastern lines of approach to Hill&amp;nbsp;262.&lt;ref name="deste 456"&gt;D'Este, p. 456&lt;/ref&gt; Directly southwest of Mont Ormel, German units moved along what would later become known as "The Corridor of Death", as the Polish inflicted heavy casualties on German forces moving towards Mont Ormel with a well-coordinated artillery barrage.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 196"/&gt;  The Polish infantry and armour were supported by the guns of the 58th Battery, 4th Medium Regiment, 2nd Canadian Army Group Royal Artillery (AGRA) and assisted by the [[Artillery observer]], [[Pierre Sévigny]]. [https://web.archive.org/web/20100130225325/http://www.artillery.net/new/6rac.html]  Captain Pierre Sévigny's assistance was crucial in defending Hill 262 and he later received the [[Virtuti Militari]] (Poland's highest military decoration) for his exertions during the battle.  [http://www.bbc.co.uk/ww2peopleswar/stories/46/a2450846.shtml]

From the northeast, the 2nd SS Panzer Division planned an assault in force against the four infantry battalions and two armoured regiments of the Polish 1st Armoured Division dug in on Hill 262.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 196"/&gt; The 9th SS Panzer Division would attack from the north, while simultaneously preventing Canadian units from reinforcing the Polish armoured division. Having managed to break out of the Falaise Pocket, the 10th SS, 12th SS and 116th Panzer Divisions would then attack Hill&amp;nbsp;262 from the southwest. If this major obstacle could be cleared, German units could initiate a full withdrawal from the Falaise Pocket.&lt;ref&gt;Fey, p. 175&lt;/ref&gt;

The first attack against Polish positions was by the "''Der Führer''" Regiment of the 2nd SS Panzer Division. Although the [[Podhale Rifles]] battalion was able to repel the attack, it expended a substantial amount of its ammunition in doing so.&lt;ref&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 197&lt;/ref&gt; The second attack was devastating to the dwindling armoured forces of the Polish battlegroups. A single German tank, positioned on Point&amp;nbsp;239 (northeast of Mont Ormel), was able to destroy five [[M4 Sherman|Sherman]] medium tanks within two minutes.&lt;ref name="montormel 73"/&gt; At this time, the 3rd Parachute Division—along with an armoured regiment of the 1st SS Panzer Division—attacked Mont Ormel from inside the Falaise Pocket. This attack was repulsed by the artillery, which "massacred" German infantry and armour closing in on their positions.&lt;ref name="Van-Der-Vat 168"&gt;Van der Vat, p. 168&lt;/ref&gt;

As the assault from the southwest ran out of steam, the 2nd SS Panzer Division resumed its attack on the northeast of the ridge. Since Polish units were now concentrated on the southern edges of the position, the 2nd SS was able to force a path through to the 3rd Parachute Division by noon, opening a corridor out of the pocket.&lt;ref name="Van-Der-Vat 168"/&gt; By mid-afternoon, close to 10,000 German troops had escaped through the corridor.&lt;ref name="Van-Der-Vat 168"/&gt; Despite being overwhelmed by strong counterattacks, Polish forces continued to hold the high ground on Mont Ormel, which they referred to as "The Mace" (''Maczuga''), exacting a deadly toll on passing German forces through the use of well-coordinated artillery fire.&lt;ref name= "D'Este 458"&gt;D'Este, p. 458&lt;/ref&gt; Irritated by the presence of these units, which were exacting a heavy toll on his men, ''Generaloberst'' [[Paul Hausser]]—commanding the 7th Army—ordered the positions to be "eliminated".&lt;ref name="Van-Der-Vat 168"/&gt; Although substantial forces, including the [[352nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|352nd Infantry Division]] and several battlegroups from the 2nd SS Panzer Division inflicted heavy casualties on the 8th and 9th Battalions of the Polish 1st Armoured Division, the counterattack was ultimately fought off. The battle had cost the Poles almost all of their ammunition, leaving them in a precarious position.&lt;ref name="D'Este 458"/&gt;

At 19:00 on 20 August, a 20-minute ceasefire was arranged to allow German forces to evacuate a large convoy of medical vehicles. Immediately following the passage of these vehicles, the fighting resumed and intensified. Although the Germans were incapable of dislodging the Polish forces, the hill's defenders had reached the point of exhaustion.&lt;ref name="montormel 73"/&gt; With ammunition supplies extremely low, the Poles were forced to watch as the remnants of the [[XLVII Panzer Corps (Germany)|XLVII Panzer Corps]] escaped from the pocket. Despite this, Polish artillery continued to bombard every German unit that entered the evacuation corridor. Stefanowicz—commander of the Polish battlegroups on Hill&amp;nbsp;262—was sceptical of his force's chance of survival:&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 201"/&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Gentlemen. Everything is lost. I do not believe [the] Canadians will manage to help us. We have only 110 men left, with 50 rounds per gun and 5 rounds per tank&amp;nbsp;... Fight to the end! To surrender to the SS is senseless, you know it well. Gentlemen! Good luck—tonight, we will die for Poland and civilization. We will fight to the last platoon, to the last tank, then to the last man.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 201"&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 201&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===21 August===
[[File:St.-Lambert-surrender.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;German forces surrendering in [[St. Lambert-sur-Dives]] on 21 August 1944&lt;/center&gt;]]

Night was welcomed by the German and Polish forces surrounding Mont Ormel. Fighting was sporadic, as both sides avoided contact with one another. Frequent Polish artillery barrages interrupted German attempts to retreat from the sector.&lt;ref name="D'Este 458"/&gt; In the morning, German attacks on the position resumed. Although not as coordinated as on the day before,&lt;ref name="montormel 74"&gt;{{cite web|url= http://montormel.evl.pl/?id=74|title=The End of the German 7th Army|publisher=Memorial Mont-Ormel| accessdate=2008-06-13}}&lt;/ref&gt; the attack still managed to reach the last of the Polish defenders on Mont Ormel. As the remaining Polish forces repelled the assault, their tanks were forced to use the last of their ammunition.&lt;ref name="montormel 74"/&gt; At approximately 12:00, the last SS remnants launched a final assault on the positions of the 9th Battalion. Polish forces defeated them at point-blank range. There would be no further attacks; the two battlegroups of the Polish 1st Armoured Division had survived the onslaught, despite being surrounded by German forces for three days. Both Reynolds and McGilvray place the Polish losses on the ''Maczuga'' at 351 killed and wounded and 11 tanks lost,&lt;ref name=mcgilvray54/&gt;&lt;ref name=Reynolds280&gt;Reynolds, p. 280&lt;/ref&gt; although Jarymowycz gives higher figures of 325 killed, 1,002 wounded, and 114 missing—approximately 20% of the division's combat strength.&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 196"/&gt; Within an hour, [[The Canadian Grenadier Guards]] managed to link up with what remained of Stefanowicz's men.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 232"/&gt; By late afternoon, the remainder of the 2nd and 9th SS Panzer Divisions had begun their retreat to the [[Seine]] River.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 233"&gt;Bercuson, p. 233&lt;/ref&gt; The Falaise Gap had been permanently closed, with a large number of German forces still trapped in the pocket.&lt;ref&gt;Fey, p. 176&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
By the evening of 21 August 1944, the vast majority of the German forces remaining in the Falaise Pocket had surrendered.&lt;ref name="vandervat 169"&gt;Van der Vat, p. 169&lt;/ref&gt; Nearly all of the strong German formations that had caused significant damage to the Canadian 1st Army throughout the Normandy campaign had been destroyed. Two panzer divisions—the ''Panzer Lehr'' and 9th SS—now existed in name only.&lt;ref name="Keegan 410"/&gt; The formidable 12th SS Panzer Division had lost 94% of its armour, nearly all of its field-guns and 70% of its vehicles. Several German units, notably the 2nd and the 12th SS Panzer Divisions had managed to escape east toward the Seine River, albeit without most of their motorized equipment. Conservative estimates for the number of German soldiers captured in the Falaise Pocket approach 50,000,&lt;ref&gt;D'Este, p. 455&lt;/ref&gt; although some estimates put total German losses (killed and captured) in the Pocket as high as 200,000.&lt;ref name="Bercuson 233"/&gt;

By 23 August, the remainder of the Wehrmacht's Seventh Army had entrenched itself along the Seine River,&lt;ref name="Keegan 410"&gt;Keegan, p. 410&lt;/ref&gt; in preparation for the defence of [[Paris]]. Simultaneously, elements of [[Army Group G]]—including the [[15th Army (Wehrmacht)|German 15th Army]] and the [[5th Panzer Army]]—moved to engage American forces in the south. In the following week, elements of the Canadian 1st Army repeatedly attacked these German units on the Seine in attempts to break through to the Channel Ports.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, p. 106&lt;/ref&gt; On the evening of 23 August, French and American Army units entered Paris.&lt;ref&gt;Keegan, p. 414&lt;/ref&gt;

===Casualties===
[[File:Mont-Ormel-Scrap.jpg|thumb|&lt;center&gt;German equipment destroyed near Mont Ormel&lt;/center&gt;]]

Due to the successive offensives of early August, exact Canadian casualties for Operation Tractable are not known. Losses during Totalise and Tractable are put at 5,500 men. &lt;ref&gt;Jarymowycz, p. 203&lt;/ref&gt; German casualties during Operation Tractable are also uncertain; approximate figures can be found for casualties within the Falaise Pocket but not for the Canadian operations during Tractable. After the Falaise Pocket, the German 7th Army was severely depleted, having lost from 50,000–200,000 men, over 200 tanks, 1,000 guns and 5,000 other vehicles.&lt;ref name="Keegan 410"/&gt; In the fighting around {{nowrap|Hill 262,}} the Germans lost 2,000 men killed, 5,000 taken prisoner, 55 tanks, 152 other armoured vehicles and 44 guns.&lt;ref name=mcgilvray54&gt;McGilvray, p. 54&lt;/ref&gt; Polish casualties for Operation Tractable (until 22 August) are 1,441 men, of whom 325 were killed (including 21 officers), 1,002 were wounded (35 officers) and 114 missing, which includes 263 men lost before the Chambois and Ormel actions from 14 to 18 August.&lt;ref name=mcgilvray54/&gt;&lt;ref name="Jarymowycz 195"/&gt;

===Battle honours===
In the British and Commonwealth system of [[battle honours]], participation in Operation Tractable (included as part of the honour Falaise for service from 7 to 22 August) was recognized in 1957, 1958, and 1959 by the award of the battle honours Laison (or "The Laison" for Canadian units), for service from 14 to 17 August, Chambois from 18 to 22 August and St Lambert-sur-Dives from 19 to 22 August.&lt;ref&gt;Rodger, 2003, p. 248&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Portal|World War II}}

===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|group=nb}}

===Citations===
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
;Books
* Bercuson, David (1995) ''Maple leaf Against the Axis''. Ottawa: [[Red Deer Press]]. {{ISBN|0-88995-305-8}}
* Bercuson, David (2004). ''M Waffen-SS''. Stackpole Books. Mechanicsburg PA.{{ISBN|978-0-8117-2905-5}}
* D'Este, Carlo (1983). ''Decision in Normandy''. New York: Konecky &amp; Konecky. {{ISBN|1-56852-260-6}}
* Fey, William [1990] (2003). ''Armor battles of the Waffen-SS, 1943–45''. Stackpole Books. Mechanicsburg PA. {{ISBN|0-81172-905-2}}.
* {{cite book |first=Ludovic |last=Fortin |title=British Tanks In Normandy |publisher=Histoire &amp; Collections |year=2004 |isbn=2-915239-33-9 |location=Paris}}
* [[Roman Jarymowycz|Jarymowycz, Roman]] (2001). ''Tank Tactics; from Normandy to Lorraine''. Boulder, Colorado: Lynne Rienner. {{ISBN|1-55587-950-0}}
* [[John Keegan|Keegan, John]] (1989). ''The Second World War''. Penguin Books. {{ISBN|0-14-3035-73-8}}.
* {{cite book |last=McGilvray |first=Evan |title=The Black Devils March, a Doomed Odyssey: The 1st Polish Armoured Division 1939–1945 |publisher=Helion |year=2004 |location=Solihull |isbn=978-1-874622-42-0}}
* {{cite book |title=Armoured Campaign in Normandy June–August 1944 |last=Napier |first=S. |authorlink= |year=2015 |publisher=The History Press |location=Stroud |edition= |isbn=978-0-75096-270-4}}
* {{cite book |first=Michael |last=Reynolds |title=Steel Inferno: I SS Panzer Corps in Normandy |publisher=Da Capo Press |year=2001 |orig-year=1997 |isbn=1-885119-44-5}}
* {{cite book |last=Rodger |first=Alexander |year=2003 |title=Battle Honours of the British Empire and Commonwealth Land Forces |publisher=Crowood Press |location=Marlborough |isbn=1-86126-637-5}}
* {{cite book |url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/his/docs/Victory_e.pdf |first=Colonel C. P. |last=Stacey |author2=Bond, Major C. C. J. |series=Official History of the Canadian Army in the Second World War |volume=III |title=The Victory Campaign: The Operations in North-West Europe 1944–1945 |publisher=The Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery |location=Ottawa |year=1960 |oclc=829337883 |accessdate=2013-05-19}}
* {{cite book |last=Van der Vat |first=D. |authorlink=Dan van der Vat |year=2003 |title=D-Day; The Greatest Invasion, A People's History |location=Toronto |publisher=Madison Press |isbn=1-55192-586-9}}
* {{cite book |last=Wilmot |first=C. |year=1997 |title=The Struggle for Europe |location=Ware, Hertfordshire |publisher=Wordsworth Editions |isbn=1-85326-677-9}}
* {{cite book |last=Zuehlke |first=M. |year=2001 |title=The Canadian Military Atlas |location=London |publisher=Stoddart |isbn=0-7737-3289-6}}

;Journals
* {{cite journal |last=Maczek |first=Stanisław |authorlink=Stanisław Maczek |date=2006 |orig-year=1944 |title=The First Polish Armoured Division in Normandy |url=http://scholars.wlu.ca/cmh/vol15/iss2/7/ |journal=Canadian Military History |publisher=Wilfrid Laurier University Press |volume=15 |issue=2 |pages=51–70 |accessdate=6 March 2014}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.dtic.mil/dtic/tr/fulltext/u2/a156116.pdf Analysis of Operation Cobra and the Falaise Gap Manoeuvres in WWII, Granier, T. R. (1985)]
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/AAF/AAFHS/AAFHS-110.pdf AAF Counter-Air Operations April 1943 – June 1944]
* [http://militarymaps.narod.ru/eur_oper_e.html Situation Maps Western Europe Day-by-Day]

{{World War II}}
{{Battle of Normandy}}

{{featured article}}
{{Coord|48|53|34|N|0|11|31|W|type:landmark|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tractable}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:1944 in France]]
[[Category:Operation Overlord]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Poland]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Military history of Canada during World War II]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|O]]
[[Category:August 1944 events]]
[[Category:Tank battles involving Germany]]
[[Category:Tank battles involving Poland]]</text><sha1>29psmtd4yof5xr5a1v68054wqrhz7du</sha1></revision></page>