<page><title>Battle of Bir Hakeim</title><ns>0</ns><id>189614</id><revision><id>961028215</id><parentid>961028059</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-06T07:22:54Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Mathglot</username><id>2544398</id></contributor><comment>/* top */ Add short description.</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="48823" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Second World War battle in Libya}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict    = Battle of Bir Hakeim
|partof      = the [[Battle of Gazala]] during the [[Second World War]]
|image       = File:Free French Foreign Legionnairs.jpg
|image_size = 250px
|caption     = Free French Foreign Legionnaires assaulting an enemy strong point at Bir Hakeim
|date        = 26 May – 11 June 1942
|coordinates={{coord|31|35|37.93|N|23|28|47.16|E|display=inline|type:event}}
|place       = [[Bir Hakeim]], [[Italian Libya]]
|map_type=Libya#Mediterranean
|map_relief=1
|result      = See ''[[Battle of Bir Hakeim#Aftermath|Aftermath]]'' section&lt;!--Please refer to the [[Template:Infobox military conflict]] guidance copied on the talk page before amending this category--&gt;
|combatant1  = {{flag|Free French Forces}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}
* {{flag|British India}}&lt;!--Please don't delete the UK flag, British forces operated at Bir Hakeim and French forces were under British command. Please comment on the talk page for a discussion instead--&gt;
|combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1  = {{flagicon|Free French}} [[Marie-Pierre Kœnig]]
|commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Erwin Rommel]]
|strength1   = 3,703 men
|strength2   = 37,000 Axis troops
|casualties1 = 141 killed &lt;br /&gt; 229 wounded &lt;br /&gt; 814 captured&lt;br /&gt; 53 guns &lt;br /&gt; 50 vehicles &lt;br /&gt; 110 aircraft
|casualties2 = 3,300 killed or wounded &lt;br /&gt; 227–845 captured &lt;br /&gt; 164 vehicles &lt;br /&gt; 49 aircraft
|notes=Bir Hakeim was attacked by the ''Ariete'' Division, then by mixed force of the ''Trieste'' and 90th Light divisions
|campaignbox =
{{Campaignbox Free French}}
{{Campaignbox Western Desert}}
}}
The '''Battle of Bir Hakeim''' ({{IPA-ar|biʔr ħaˈkiːm}}) took place at [[Bir Hakeim]], an oasis in the Libyan desert south and west of Tobruk, during the [[Battle of Gazala]] (26 May – 21 June 1942). The [[1st Free French Division|1st Free French Brigade]] ({{lang|fr|Général de brigade}} [[Marie-Pierre Kœnig]]) defended the position from {{nowrap|26 May – 11 June}} against much larger Axis forces of {{lang|de|Panzerarmee Afrika}} (''Generaloberst'' [[Erwin Rommel]]). The {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} captured [[Tobruk]] ten days later but the delay imposed on the Axis offensive by the defence of the fortress influenced the cancellation of [[Operation Herkules]], the plan for an Axis invasion of [[Malta]]. Rommel continued to advance and invaded Egypt, slowed by British delaying actions until the [[First Battle of El Alamein]] in July, where the Axis advance was stopped. Both sides used the battle for propaganda, Winston Churchill renamed the [[Free France|Free French]] as the Fighting French and Hitler called the French the second best fighters after the Germans.
{{TOC limit|2}}

==Background==

===Eighth Army===
At the beginning of 1942, after its defeat in western [[Cyrenaica]] during {{lang|de|[[:de:Unternehmen Theseus|Unternehmen Theseus]]}}, the [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]] (Lieutenant-General [[Neil Ritchie]]) faced the Axis troops in [[Libya]] roughly {{convert|30|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on}} west of the port of [[Tobruk]], along a line running from the coast at Gazala, southwards for about {{convert|30|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on}}. Both sides accumulated supplies for an offensive to forestall their opponent and General [[Claude Auchinleck]], Commander in Chief of [[Middle East Command]], hoped for the Eighth Army to be ready by May. British code-breakers tracked the dispatch of convoys to Libya as the British anti-shipping offensive from Malta was neutralised by Axis bombing and forecast that the Axis would attack first.{{sfn|Hinsley|1994|pp=206–207}}

As the Eighth Army was not ready to take the offensive, Ritchie planned to fight a defensive battle on the Gazala line.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=216}} Auchinleck's appreciation of the situation to Ritchie in mid-May anticipated either a frontal attack in the centre of the Gazala line followed by an advance on Tobruk or a flanking move to the south, looping around the Gazala line towards Tobruk.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=218}} Auchinleck saw the former as more likely (with a feint on the flank to draw away the Eighth Army tanks) while Ritchie favoured the latter. Auchinleck suggested that British armour be concentrated near El Adem, where it would be well placed to meet either threat.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=218}}

Since [[Operation Crusader]] in late 1941, the Eighth Army had received [[M3 Lee|M3 Grant]] tanks with a {{nowrap|37mm gun}} in a turret and a {{nowrap|75mm gun}} in a hull [[sponson]], which could penetrate the armour of the {{lang|de|[[Panzer III]] Ausf. H}} and ''J'' and the ''[[Panzer IV]]'' at {{convert|650|–|850|yd|m|order=flip|abbr=on|round=50}}. The frontal armour of the Grant was thick enough to withstand the [[5 cm Pak 38|50 mm Pak 38]] anti-tank gun at {{convert|1000|yd|m|order=flip|abbr=on|round=50}} and the short-barrelled [[5 cm KwK 38|50 mm KwK 38]] gun carried by the {{lang|de|Panzer}} III at {{convert|250|yd|m|order=flip|abbr=on|round=50}}. The first 112 British [[Ordnance QF 6-pounder|6-pounder]] anti-tank guns had arrived and been allotted to the motor brigades of the armoured divisions.{{sfn|Carver|2002|pp=68–69}}

===''Panzerarmee Afrika''===
{{see also|Operation Herkules}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-784-0208-17A, Nordafrika, italienische Panzer.2.jpg|thumb|{{centre|Italian [[Semovente 75/18]], 1942}}]]
At the meeting of Axis leaders at [[Berchtesgaden]] on 1 May, it was agreed that Rommel should attack at the end of the month to capture Tobruk. The {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} was to pause at the Egyptian border, while the Axis captured Malta in [[Operation Herkules]] and then Rommel was to invade Egypt.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=219}} The {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} had finished converting to the up-armoured {{lang|de|Panzer III Ausf. H}} and had {{nowrap|received nineteen}} {{lang|de|Panzer III Ausf. J}} (Mark III Specials), with long-barrelled [[5 cm KwK 39|50 mm KwK 39]] guns. Four {{lang|de|Panzer IV Ausf. G}} (Mark IV Specials) with long-barrelled [[7.5 cm KwK 40]] guns had also arrived.{{sfn|Carver|2002|p=69}} The ''[[Abwehr]]'' (German military intelligence) had [[German code breaking in World War II|broken]] some British military codes and in late 1941 penetrated [[Black (code)|Black]], the code used by [[Bonner Fellers]], a US military attaché. The British divulged much tactical information to Fellers, who unwittingly reported it to the Axis as well as Washington.{{sfn|Latimer|2003|pp=44–45}}

Air attacks by the {{lang|de|Luftwaffe}} and {{lang|it|Regia Aeronautica}} on Malta reduced its offensive capacity and supply convoys from Italy reached the Axis forces in Africa with fewer losses.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=219–223}} Until May, Axis monthly deliveries to Libya averaged {{convert|60000|LT|t|0|order=flip}}, fewer than a smaller Axis force received from June–October 1941 but sufficient for an offensive. The {{convert|900|mi|km|0|order=flip|abbr=on}} advance to Gazala succeeded because the port of Benghazi was open, reducing the transport distance for about {{nowrap|33 percent}} of the supplies of the {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} to {{convert|280|mi|km|0|order=flip|abbr=on}}. The capture of Malta would not alter the constraints of port capacity and distance; protecting convoys and the use of a large port close to the front would still be necessary.{{sfn|Creveld|1977|pp=193–195}}

[[File:Unternehmen Theseus Verlauf.gif|thumb|{{centre|Map of the Gazala line and Operation Venice, May–June, 1942}}]]
''Unternehmen Venezia'' (Operation Venice), the Axis plan of attack, was for tanks to make a flanking advance around the Bir Hakeim box at the southern extremity of the Gazala line. On the left side of the manoeuvre, the Italian [[Italian 132nd Armored Division Ariete|132nd Armoured Division ''Ariete'']] would neutralise the Bir Hakeim box. Further south, the [[21st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|21st Panzer Division]] and [[15th Panzer Division]] would advance through the desert further south, moving east, then turning north behind the Gazala line to destroy the British armour and cut off the infantry divisions in the line. The most southerly part of the attacking formation, a {{lang|de|kampfgruppe}} (battle group) of the [[German 90th Light Afrika Division|90th ''Leichtes Afrika'' Division]] (''[[Generalmajor]]'' [[Ulrich Kleemann]]) was to advance to El Adem south of Tobruk, cut the supply routes from the port to the Gazala line and hold British troops at Tobruk by a ruse; aircraft-engines mounted on trucks were to raise dust, simulating a big armoured force.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=219–223}}

The rest of the Italian [[Italian XX Motorized Corps|XX Motorised Corps]], the [[Italian 101 Motorised Division Trieste|101st Motorized Division ''Trieste'']], would open a gap in the minefield north of Bir Hakeim, near the Sidi Muftah box, to create a supply route to the panzers. Rommel anticipated that having dealt with the British tanks, he would have captured El Adem, Ed Duda and [[Sidi Rezegh]] by nightfall and later the ''Knightsbridge'' defensive box, about {{convert|40|km|mi|abbr=on}} north-east of Bir Hakeim. The Axis tanks would be in a position next day to thrust westwards against the Eighth Army defensive boxes between Gazala and Alem Hamza, meeting the eastwards attack by the Italian X and XXI corps. By late May, the Axis forces comprised {{nowrap|90,000 men,}} {{nowrap|560 tanks}} and {{nowrap|542 aircraft.}}{{sfn|Carver|1964|p=167}}

==Prelude==

===Gazala line===
[[File:M3grantmini.jpg|thumb|{{centre|M3 Lee tank}}]]
Between Gazala and Timimi (just west of Tobruk), the Eighth Army was able to concentrate its forces sufficiently to turn and fight. By 4 February, the Axis advance had been halted and the front line had been stabilised, from Gazala on the coast {{convert|48|km|mi|abbr=on}} west of Tobruk, to the old Ottoman fortress of Bir Hakeim, {{convert|80|km|mi|abbr=on}} to the south. The Gazala line was a series of defensive boxes accommodating a [[brigade]] each, laid out across the desert behind minefields and wire, watched by regular patrols between the boxes. The Free French were in the south at the [[Bir Hakeim]] box, {{convert|13|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on}} south of the [[150th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|150th Infantry Brigade]] box, which was {{convert|6|mi|km|order=flip|sigfig=1}} south of the [[69th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|69th Infantry Brigade]] box. The line was not evenly manned, with a greater number of troops covering the coast road, leaving the south less protected but deep minefields had been laid in front of the boxes.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=197–198}}

The longer line made an attack around the southern flank harder to supply. Behind the Gazala line were the Commonwealth Keep, Acroma, Knightsbridge and El Adem boxes, sited to block tracks and junctions. The box at Retma was finished just before the Axis offensive but work on the Point 171 and Bir el Gubi boxes did not begin until 25 May.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=216–217}} By late May, the [[1st South African Division]] was dug in nearest the coast, with the [[50th (Northumbrian) Infantry Division]] to the south and [[1st Free French Division|1st Free French Brigade]] furthest left at Bir Hakeim. The British 1st and 7th Armoured divisions waited behind the main line as a mobile counter-attack force, the [[2nd South African Division]] garrisoned Tobruk and [[5th Infantry Division (India)|5th Indian Infantry Division]] was in reserve. The British had {{nowrap|110,000 men,}} {{nowrap|843 tanks}} and {{nowrap|604 aircraft.}}{{sfn|Carver|1964|p=167}}

===Bir Hakeim===

[[File:Battle of Bir Hakeim 1942-1.jpg|thumb|{{centre|A German 20 mm anti-aircraft gun in the foreground and a {{lang|de|Luftwaffe}} air raid on Bir Hakeim in the background}}]]
The fortress at Bir Hakeim (Old Man's Well) had been built by the Ottomans and later used as a station by the Italian [[Méhariste|''Meharist'']] (camel corps) to control movement at the crossroads of two Bedouin paths. The wells had long been dry and had been abandoned but Indian troops re-occupied the site to build a strongpoint surrounded by {{nowrap|50,000 mines.}}{{sfn|Walker|2003|p=116}} The fortification was a rough pentagon pointing north, about {{convert|4|×|5|km|mi|abbr=on|round=0.5}} wide.{{sfn|LePage|2008|p=149}} On 14 February, the 150th Infantry Brigade was relieved at the box by the 1st Free French Brigade (''Général'' [[Marie Pierre Kœnig]]), part of [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]] (Lieutenant-General [[Willoughby Norrie, 1st Baron Norrie|Willoughby Norrie]]).{{sfn|Bimberg|2002|pp=109, 101}}{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=413}} With a fighting strength of 3,000 men and a rear echelon of about 600 men based {{convert|15|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on}} to the east behind the line, the brigade was composed of the [[13th Demi-Brigade of the Foreign Legion|13th ''Demi-Brigade'' of the Foreign Legion]] (DBLE), the ''Bataillon de Marche de I'Oubanghi Chari'' and the ''Bataillon du Pacifique''. The Legion comprised the 2nd and 3rd battalions of the 13th DBLE. By mid-May the perimeter and central areas were [[Honeycomb structure|honeycombed]] with {{nowrap|1,200 entrenchments,}} foxholes, gun emplacements and underground bunkers, deep camouflaged hides for vehicles and supply dumps.{{sfn|Windrow|1976|p=41}} The interior of the fort was divided into zones, each the responsibility of a unit, with Kœnig's headquarters near the centre, at the crossroads. The V-shaped anti-tank and anti-personnel minefields were patrolled by the 3rd Foreign Legion Battalion (Lamaze), manning sixty-three [[Universal Carrier|Bren Gun Carriers]] divided into three squadrons. The patrols moved along lanes in the minefields, paying particular attention to the area north to the Sidi Muftah box at Got el Ualeb, held by the 150th Brigade.{{sfn|LePage|2008|p=149}}

===Battle of Gazala===

{{see also|Battle of Gazala|3rd Indian Motor Brigade}}

At {{nowrap|2:00 p.m.}} on 26 May, the Italian X and XXI Corps began a frontal attack on the central Gazala line. A few elements of the ''Afrika Korps'' and the Italian [[Italian XX Motorised Corps|XX Motorised Corps]] participated and during the day the bulk of the ''Afrika Korps'' moved north, to give the impression that it was the main attack. After dark, the armoured formations turned south in a sweeping move around the southern end of the Gazala line. Early on 27 May, the main force of {{lang|de|Panzerarmee Afrika}}, the ''[[Deutsches Afrikakorps|Afrika Korps]]'', XX Motorised Corps and the 90th Light Division, went round the southern end of the Gazala line, using the British minefields to protect the Axis flank and rear. The ''Ariete'' Division was held up for about an hour by the [[3rd Indian Motor Brigade]] (7th Armoured Division), dug in about {{convert|6|km|mi|abbr=on}} south-east of Bir Hakeim.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=223}}

The 15th Panzer Division engaged the 4th Armoured Brigade, which had come south to support the 3rd Indian and 7th Motorised brigades. The Germans were surprised by the range and power of the {{nowrap|75 mm guns}} on the new M3 Grants but by late morning, the 4th Armoured Brigade had withdrawn toward El Adem and Axis armoured units had advanced more than {{convert|25|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on}} north. Their advance was stopped around noon by the 1st Armoured Division, in mutually costly fighting.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=223–224}} On the right, the 90th Light Division forced the 7th Motorised Brigade out of Retma eastwards on Bir el Gubi. Advancing toward El Adem at mid-morning, armoured cars of the 90th Light Division overran and scattered the advanced HQ of the 7th Armoured Division (Major-General [[Frank Messervy]]), near Bir Beuid. Messervy was captured and removed his insignia, persuading the Germans that he was a [[Batman (military)|batman]]; he escaped with several other men to rejoin the division. The 90th Light Division reached the El Adem area by mid-morning and captured several supply bases. The following day, the 4th Armoured Brigade moved on El Adem and forced the 90th Light Division to retire to the south-west.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=224–225}}

==Siege==

===27 May===
[[File:Lot 11588-38 (24338193653).jpg|thumb|left|{{centre|French anti-tank [[Canon de 75 modèle 1897|75 mm gun]] at Bir Hakeim}}]]

The 15th and 21st Panzer divisions, the rest of the 90th Light Division and the ''Ariete'' Division began their large encircling move south of Bir Hakeim as planned. The [[31st Indian Armoured Division|3rd Indian Motor Brigade]] was surprised at {{nowrap|6:30 a.m.}} on 27 May and overrun at Point 171, {{convert|4|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on|round=0.5}} south-east of Bir Hakeim, by the [[132nd Tank Regiment (Italy)|132nd Tank Infantry Regiment]] of the ''Ariete'' Division and some German tanks, losing about {{nowrap|440 men}} and most of its equipment. The 7th Motor Brigade was then attacked at Retma and forced back to Bir el Gubi. The 4th Armoured Brigade advanced in support and collided with the 15th Panzer Division; the 8th Hussars were destroyed and the 3rd Royal Tank Regiment (3rd RTR) lost many tanks. The British inflicted considerable losses in return but then retired to El Adem.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=223–224}}

After over-running the 3rd Indian Motor Brigade, the VIII, IX, and X Medium Tank battalions of the 132nd Tank Infantry Regiment moved to the north-east of Bir Hakeim and the IX Battalion (Colonel Prestisimone) with sixty tanks, changed direction towards the fort.{{sfn|Montanari|1993|pp=209–211}}{{sfn|Ford|2008|p=35}}{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|1999|p=156}} The IX Battalion arrived before the Bir Hakeim minefield and barbed wire at {{nowrap|8:15 a.m.,}} charged and lost {{nowrap|31 tanks}} and a {{lang|it|[[Semovente da 75/18|Semovente]]}} self-propelled gun. Ten tanks got through the minefield and were knocked out by {{nowrap|75 mm anti-tank}} guns, causing {{nowrap|124 Italian}} casualties.{{sfn|Montanari|1993|p=212}} The remnants of the IX Battalion retired on the main body of the ''Ariete'' Division, which moved north towards Bir el Harmat around noon, following Rommel's original plan.{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|1999|p=157}}

===28–30 May===

[[File:Free French Foreign legion OWI photo.jpg|thumb|{{centre|Three soldiers of the French Colonial Artillery who distinguished themselves in the battle at Bir Hakeim, from Senegal, Equatorial Africa and Madagascar, respectively}}]]
On 28 May, the [[Desert Air Force]] (DAF) made a maximum effort to attack Axis columns around El Adem and Bir Hakeim but in the poor visibility, bombed Bir Hakeim and its surroundings, misled by the Italian tank wrecks around the position and Kœnig sent a detachment to destroy the wrecks to avoid any more mistakes.{{sfn|Richards|Saunders|1975|p=199}} A French column was sent to make contact with the [[British 150th Infantry Brigade|150th Infantry Brigade]], stationed further to the north. After a few hours, Italian artillery forced them to retire but the French column destroyed seven half-tracks. On 29 May, the detachment of ''Capitaine'' [[Gabriel Brunet de Sairigné|Gabriel de Sairigné]] destroyed three German tanks, British air attacks intercepted two Stuka raids and fighter-bombers attacked Axis supply lines south and east of Bir Hakeim.{{sfn|Richards|Saunders|1975|p=199}} On 30 May, {{nowrap|620 soldiers}} from the 3rd Indian Motor Brigade, captured by the Axis and then released in the desert, reached the fort and added to the {{nowrap|243 prisoners}} already there, making the water shortage worse. The detachment of ''Capitaine'' Lamaze, at the request of the [[7th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|7th British Armoured Division]], sealed off the breach opened the day before by the Axis tanks in the minefields. Led by Colonel [[Dimitri Amilakhvari]], the legionnaires were ambushed but managed to retreat with the help of the Bren carriers of the 9th Company ''[[Pierre Messmer|Messmer]]''.{{sfn|Liardet|2012|p=2}}

===31 May–1 June===

On 31 May, during a two-day sandstorm, fifty supply trucks of the 101st Motorised Company (''Captaine'' Dulau), reached Bir Hakeim with water and took the Indians, prisoners and seriously wounded back to the British lines. A raid by the detachments ''Messmer'', ''de Roux'' and ''de Sairigné'', led by Amilakhvari, destroyed five tanks and an armoured vehicle repair workshop. The {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} had been forced to retreat westwards, to an area north of Bir Hakeim, which became known as the Cauldron, having attacked the 150th Infantry Brigade box since 28 May. During the day, the DAF lost {{nowrap|sixteen aircraft}} {{nowrap|(fifteen fighters}} and a bomber), {{nowrap|fifteen in}} combat with Axis fighters and one to [[flak]], the worst daily loss of the battle; the Luftwaffe lost nine aircraft.{{sfn|Palermo|2014|pp=255–264}} On the west side of the Cauldron, the 150th Infantry Brigade was overrun late on 1 June despite British relief attempts. The Axis troops that had been trapped gained a supply route through the Eighth Army minefields north of Bir Hakeim and next morning the encirclement of the fort was resumed by the 90th Light Division, ''Trieste'' Division and three armoured reconnaissance regiments from the [[Italian 17 Infantry Division Pavia|17th Infantry Division ''Pavia'']]. At {{nowrap|8:00 a.m.}} German troops approached from the south and Italian forces advanced from the north. Two Italian officers presented themselves at {{nowrap|10:30 a.m.}} to the 2nd Foreign Legion Battalion lines, asking for the capitulation of the fort, which Kœnig refused.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=227–231}}

===2–4 June===

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-443-1589-07, Nordafrika, Rommel in Befehlsfahrzeug.jpg|thumb|{{centre|[[Erwin Rommel]] and [[Fritz Bayerlein]] near Bir Hakeim}}]]
From {{nowrap|10:00 a.m.}} on 2 June, both sides exchanged artillery-fire but the French field guns were out-ranged by German medium artillery and the fort was bombed by German and Italian aircraft. [[Stuka]]s raided Bir Hakeim more than twenty times but the French positions were so well built as to be almost invulnerable. The British were unable to reinforce the French, who repulsed the ''Ariete'' Division attack but on 2 June, the DAF had an easily observed bomb line around the fort and concentrated on the area with fighter patrols and fighter-bomber attacks. The sight of scores of burning vehicles helped to maintain the morale of the defenders, who harassed Axis communications around the fort, as did the 7th Motor Brigade and the 29th Indian Infantry Brigade in the vicinity. On 4 June, DAF fighters and fighter-bombers disrupted Stuka attacks and bombed Axis vehicles, setting off an ammunition wagon in view of the French but losing seven aircraft.{{sfn|Boillot|1945|p=24}}{{sfn|Palermo|2014|pp=255–264}} Kœnig signalled Air Vice-Marshal [[Arthur Coningham (RAF officer)|Arthur Coningham]]: "Bravo! Merci pour la R.A.F." which brought the reply "Merci pour le sport".{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=230–231}}{{sfn|Richards|Saunders|1975|pp=200–201}}

===5–7 June===

From {{nowrap|5–6 June,}} the DAF flew fewer sorties at Bir Hakeim, concentrating on the Knightsbridge Box and around {{nowrap|11:00 a.m.}} on 6 June, the 90th Light Division attacked with the support of pioneers to try to clear a passage through the minefield.{{sfn|Richards|Saunders|1975|p=201}} The pioneers got within {{convert|800|m|yd|abbr=on|sigfig = 1}} of the fort, having breached the outer minefield and during the night they managed to clear several passages into the inner perimeter. German infantry gained a foothold but the French troops in fox holes, dug outs and blockhouses, maintained a great volume of small-arms fire, which forced the Germans under cover. Operation Aberdeen, an attempt to destroy Axis forces in the Cauldron, which had begun on the night of {{nowrap|4/5 June,}} was a disastrous failure. Ritchie considered withdrawing the French from the fort to release the 7th Motor Brigade but decided to keep possession and on 7 June, four DAF raids were made against the Germans in the minefields. That night, a last convoy approached the fort and [[Aspirant]] Bellec got through the German lines, in thick fog to guide the convoy in. The Germans used the fog to prepare a final assault; tanks, [[88 mm gun]]s and Colonel Hecker's pioneers formed up in front of the fort.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=236}}{{sfn|Liardet|2012|p=3}}

===8–9 June===
On the morning of 8 June, after the defeat of Operation Aberdeen released part of the 15th Panzer Division and Group Hecker for the siege, Rommel commanded an attack from the north, approaching as close as possible in thick fog, with artillery firing directly against the fortifications.{{sfn|Pitt|1980|p=220}} The ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' made constant attacks, including a raid by {{nowrap|forty-five Ju 87}} ''Stukas'', three {{nowrap|Ju. 88s and}} {{nowrap|ten Me. 110s,}} escorted by {{nowrap|fifty-four fighters.}} Just before {{nowrap|10:00 a.m.}} the attack began, aiming at a low rise which would overlook the French defences. The Chadian and Congolese defenders held on despite many casualties and in the afternoon, another sixty ''Stukas'' bombed the perimeter and an attack was made all round the northern defences. An ammunition dump was blown up and the perimeter forced back. Kœnig reported that the garrison was exhausted, had suffered many casualties and was down to its reserve supplies; he asked for more air support and a relief operation. The DAF made another maximum effort, flew a record {{nowrap|478 sorties}} and during the night, Hurricanes and Bostons dropped supplies to the garrison.{{sfn|Pitt|1980|p=220}}{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=236}} The DAF lost eight fighters (three to Italian [[Macchi C.202]]s) and two bombers, while the ''Luftwaffe'' lost two aircraft and the ''[[Regia Aeronautica]]'' one.{{sfn|Palermo|2014|pp=255–264}}

On the morning of 9 June, twenty {{nowrap|Ju 88s and}} forty {{nowrap|Ju 87}} ''Stukas'' escorted by fifty {{nowrap|Me 110 and 109}} fighters, attacked Bir Hakeim. The Germans waited for the rest of the 15th Panzer Division to arrive as German artillery and aircraft bombarded the fort. Then a two-prong attack struck the perimeter. Italian infantry fought alongside ''Kampfgruppe Wolz'', the German and native infantry of ''Sonderverband 288'' (Special Commando 288) from the 90th Light Division, elements of the reconnaissance and infantry units of 15th and 21st Panzer Divisions and ''Kampfgruppe Kiehl'' a company of 11 tanks. The objective was Point 186, the top of a gentle rise in the ground which acted as a fire-control position for the garrison. A few skirmishes occurred between the 66th Infantry Regiment of the ''Trieste'' Division and the men of Lieutenant Bourgoin, whose unit was down only to hand grenades. The ''Bataillon de Marche'' made a determined defence but was forced back, despite reinforcements of the 22nd North African Company. In the afternoon, to the south near the old fort, ''Oberstleutnant'' [[Ernst-Günther Baade]] led two battalions of Rifle Regiment 115 into the assault and in a costly advance, they established themselves within {{convert|200|yd|m|abbr=on|sigfig=1|order=flip}} of the fort by nightfall.{{sfn|Windrow|1976|p=46}} At {{nowrap|1:00 p.m.,}} as {{nowrap|130 aircraft}} bombed the north face of the fort, the German infantry and the 15th Panzer Division attacked behind an artillery barrage. The attackers breached the 9th Company lines and the central position of Aspirant Morvan but the situation was restored with a Bren Carrier counter-attack. Many DAF aircraft were unserviceable and the effort for the day was much reduced but two Hurricanes dropped medical supplies; diversions attempted by columns from the 7th Motor Brigade and the 29th Indian Infantry Brigade were too small to have much effect.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=236}} In the afternoon, Messervy, the commander of the 7th Armoured Division, signalled that a break-out might be necessary and Kœnig asked for DAF protection, for an evacuation at {{nowrap|11:00 p.m.}} that night. The request was made at too short notice and the garrison had to wait until the night of 10 June for a rendezvous to be arranged by the British to the south.{{sfn|Pitt|1980|p=221}}

===Retreat, 10–11 June===

[[File:Sortie bir hakeim.jpg|thumb|{{centre|Free French Forces evacuate Bir Hakeim}}]]
During 10 June, the French hung on and suffered many casualties; with only {{nowrap|two hundred 75 mm rounds}} and {{nowrap|seven hundred mortar}} rounds left, another attack on the northern sector against the Oubangui-Chari and 3rd Foreign Legion Battalion lines was contained by a counter-attack by the Messmer and Lamaze units, supported by Bren Carriers and the last mortar rounds. In the afternoon, the biggest air attack of the siege, a raid by {{nowrap|100 Stukas}} dropped {{convert|130|LT|t|0|abbr=on}} of bombs. The last rounds of ammunition were issued and bodies searched for spare cartridges; Rommel predicted that Bir Hakeim would fall the next day but resisted pressure to attack with tanks, fearing that many would be lost in the minefields.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=237}}

As dark fell, sappers began to clear mines from the western face of the fortress, heavy equipment was prepared for demolition and two companies were detailed to stay behind to disguise the retirement. A rendezvous was arranged with the 7th Motorized Brigade, which ran a convoy of lorries and ambulances to a point {{convert|7|km|mi|abbr=on|round=0.5}} south of the fort. Mine clearance by the sappers took longer than expected and they were only able to clear a narrow passage, rather than a {{convert|200|m|yd|abbr=on|sigfig=1}} corridor. Vehicles went astray and the ambulances and walking-wounded left the perimeter {{nowrap|75 minutes}} late at {{nowrap|8:30 p.m.}} Kœnig put the fort under the command of Amilakhvari, the Foreign Legion commander and left the fort at the head of the column in his Ford, driven by Miss [[Susan Travers]], an English woman, the only female member of [[French Foreign Legion]].{{sfn|Pitt|1980|p=222}}

A flare rose, the Axis troops nearby began to fire, the guide of the HQ column got lost and was blown up three times by mines. When Kœnig caught up with the main column, it was blocked by troops of the 90th Light Division and he ordered a rush, regardless of the mines; Lamaze, Captain [[Charles Bricogne]] and Lieutenant Dewey were killed in the ''mêlée''.{{sfn|Pitt|1980|pp=222–223}} The reception was organised by {{nowrap|550 Company}} [[Royal Army Service Corps]] (RASC) which drove lorries and guided field ambulances with inexperienced rear-area crews, escorted by the 2nd [[King's Royal Rifle Corps]] (KRRC) and the 2nd Rifle Brigade on either side. The ambulances became separated in the dark but were found and guided to the rendezvous.{{sfn|Neillands|2005|pp=124–125}} The commander the 3rd Battalion was captured but most of the brigade managed to break out, reach Bir el Gubi, then withdraw to Gasr-el-Arid by {{nowrap|7:00 a.m.}} on 11 June. About {{nowrap|2,700 men}} of the original {{nowrap|3,600 men}} escaped, including {{nowrap|200 wounded;}} during the day British patrols picked up stragglers.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=237}}

==Aftermath==

===Analysis===

[[File:Bir Hacheim 1990.jpg|thumb|{{centre|Bir Hakeim (1990), red flags show land mines}}]]
The Free French occupation of Bir Hakeim had lengthened the Axis supply route around the south end of the Gazala line, caused them losses and gave the British more time to recover in the wake of their defeat at the Cauldron. From {{nowrap|2–10 June}} the DAF had flown about {{nowrap|1,500 sorties}} and lost {{nowrap|19 fighters}} over the fort, against about {{nowrap|1,400 Axis}} sorties in which {{nowrap|15 German}} and five Italian aircraft were shot down; the 7th Motor Brigade ran four supply convoys into Bir Hakeim from {{nowrap|31 May – 7 June.}}{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=237–238}} [[Free France|Free French]] morale was raised by its performance in the battle; a victory had been badly needed to show the Allies that the army of the French was a serious force, that could contribute to the war against Germany. The term Free French was replaced by "Fighting French", after the battle had shown the world that a revival after the defeat in 1940 was under way; De Gaulle used it to undermine co-operation with the [[Vichy regime]]. In 1960, the British official historian [[I. S. O. Playfair]] wrote

{{quote|At the outset it had made longer and more difficult the enemy's temporary supply route; it had caused him many casualties and it gave the British a chance to recover from their defeat in the Cauldron. General Kœnig's brigade made a great impression upon the enemy by their courageous and enterprising resistance and their success gave a well-won fillip to the pride of the Free French, who, for the first time in the Middle East, had fought the Germans and Italians in a complete formation on their own.|I. S. O. Playfair{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=237}}}}

and Auchinleck said on 12 June 1942, "The United Nations need to be filled with admiration and gratitude in respect of these French troops and their brave General Kœnig".{{sfn|De Gaulle|2000|p=260}} After the war, ''Generalmajor'' [[Friedrich von Mellenthin]] wrote, "In the whole course of the desert war, we never encountered a more heroic and well-sustained defence".{{sfn|Pitt|1980|p=223}}

===Casualties===

Buell in 2002 and Ford in 2008 wrote of {{nowrap|141 French}} dead, {{nowrap|229 wounded}} and {{nowrap|814 men}} taken prisoner, with the loss of {{nowrap|53 guns}} and fifty vehicles.{{sfn|Buell|2002|p=169}}{{sfn|Ford|2008|p=64}} The British lost {{nowrap|86 aircraft}} shot down by aircraft and {{nowrap|24 by flak.}}{{sfn|Palermo|2014|pp=255–264}} Axis losses were {{nowrap|3,300 dead}} or wounded, {{nowrap|227 captured,}} {{nowrap|164 vehicles}} destroyed and {{nowrap|49 aircraft}} shot down. The ''Regia Aeronautica'' lost {{nowrap|21 aeroplanes,}} eight in air fighting.{{sfn|Palermo|2014|pp=263–268}} In 2004, Porch recorded that the Axis took {{nowrap|845 prisoners}} at Bir Hakeim, only ten percent of whom were French and that Hitler had ordered that captured German political refugees were to be killed, which Rommel ignored.{{sfn|Porch|2005|p=272}}

==Order of battle==
{| class="toccolours collapsible collapsed" style="width:100%; background:transparent;"
!colspan= | Bir Hakeim garrison | Equipment
|-
|colspan="2" |
;1st Free French Brigade

;Infantry
* [[13th Demi-Brigade of the Foreign Legion|13e Demi-Brigade de Légion Étrangère]] (Colonel [[Dimitri Amilakvari]]){{sfn|LePage|2008|p=149}} (List of infantry units from LePage (2008, p.&amp;nbsp;149) unless indicated.){{sfn|LePage|2008|p=149}}
** 2nd Bataillon (II/13e DBLE)
** 3rd Bataillon (III/13e DBLE) (63 × Bren Gun Carriers)
* 2nd Colonial Demi-Brigade (Lieutenant-Colonel Roux)
** 2nd Bataillon de marche de [[Central African Republic|l'Oubanghi]]
** 1st Bataillon du Pacifique (Lieutenant-Colonel Broche)
** 1st Bataillon ''[[Troupes de Marine|d'infanterie de Marine (Coloniale)]]'' (Major Jacques Savey)
** 22nd North African Company (Captain Lequesne)
** 2nd Anti-tank Company (Captain Jacquin)
** Signal, engineer and medical companies

;Artillery
* [[1st Artillery Regiment (France)|1st Artillery Regiment]] (Colonel Laurent-Champrosay){{sfn|LePage|2008|p=149}}
** 24 × [[Canon de 75 modèle 1897|75mm guns]] (30 × used as anti-tank guns){{sfn|Walker|2003|p=116}}{{sfn|LePage|2008|p=149}}
** 7 × [[47 mm APX anti-tank gun]]{{sfn|Walker|2003|p=116}}
** 18 × [[25 mm Hotchkiss anti-tank gun]]{{sfn|Walker|2003|p=116}}
** 46 × [[Boys anti-tank rifle]]s (British-supplied){{sfn|Walker|2003|p=116}}
** 18 × [[Bofors 40 mm gun]] [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft guns]]{{sfn|Walker|2003|p=116}}
** 44 × {{convert|81|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} and {{convert|90|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} [[Mortar (weapon)|mortars]]{{sfn|Walker|2003|p=116}}
** 72 × [[Hotchkiss gun|Hotchkiss machine guns]]{{sfn|LePage|2008|p=149}}
** 8 × heavy anti-aircraft machine-guns{{sfn|LePage|2008|p=149}}

;Anti-aircraft
* 1 Bataillon de [[Fusiliers Marins (AA)]] (Commander [[Hubert Amyot d'Inville]]){{sfn|LePage|2008|p=149}}
** 12 × Bofors guns{{sfn|LePage|2008|p=149}}
* D Troop, 43rd Battery, 11th [[City of London Yeomanry (Rough Riders)]] Light Anti-Aircraft Regiment RA, 84 gunners{{sfn|Walker|2003|p=116}}
** 6 × Bofors guns{{sfn|Walker|2003|p=116}}
** 2 × [[Ordnance QF 25-pounder|25-pounder guns]]{{sfn|Walker|2003|p=116}}

;Ammunition
** {{nowrap|20,000 × 75 mm}} [[Shell (projectile)|shells]].{{sfn|LePage|2008|p=149}}
|}

==See also==
* [[North African Campaign timeline]]
* [[List of World War II Battles]]

==Citations==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
'''Books'''
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Bimberg|2002}}
|last=Bimberg |first=Edward L. |year=2002 |series=Contributions in Military Studies |number=217 |title=Tricolor over the Sahara |publisher=Greenwood Press |location=Westport, CN |isbn=978-0-313-31654-8}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Boillot|1945}}
|last=Boillot |first=Félix François |title=Bir Hakeim: 26 mai – 10 juin, 1942 |trans-title=Bir Hakeim: 26 May – 10 June 1942 |date=1945 |publisher=Presses universitaires de France |location=Paris |edition=2nd, rev. |oclc=11585533}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Buell|2002}}
|series=The West Point Military History Series |title=The Second World War: Europe and the Mediterranean |first1=Thomas B. |last1=Buell |first2=John N. |last2=Bradley |first3=Thomas E. |last3=Griess |first4=Jack W. |last4=Dice |first5=John H. |last5=Bradley |publisher=Square One |location=New York |year=2002 |isbn=978-0-7570-0160-4}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Carver|1964}}
|first=M. |last=Carver |authorlink=Michael Carver |title=Tobruk |publisher=Batsford |edition=[[Pan Books]] |location=London |year=1964 |isbn=978-0-330-23376-7}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Carver|2002}}
|title=Dilemmas of the Desert War: The Libyan Campaign 1940–1942 |last=Carver |first=M. |authorlink= |year=2002 |orig-year=1986 |publisher=Batsford |location=Staplehurst |edition=Spellmount |isbn=978-1-86227-153-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Creveld|1977}}
|last=Creveld |first=M. van |authorlink=Martin van Creveld |title=Supplying War: Logistics from Wallenstein to Patton |year=1977 |location=Cambridge |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-0-521-29793-6}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|De Gaulle|2000}}
|first=Charles |last=de Gaulle |authorlink=Charles de Gaulle |editor1-first=Marius-François |editor1-last=Guyard |editor2-first=Jean-Luc |editor2-last=Barré |title=Mémoires de guerre |trans-title=War Memoirs |series=Bib. La Pléiade |year=2000 |orig-year=1954 |location=Paris |publisher=Gallimard |language=French |isbn=978-2-07011-583-9}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Ford|2008}}
|last=Ford |first=Ken |title=Gazala 1942: Rommel's Greatest Victory |publisher=Osprey |location=Oxford |year=2008 |isbn=978-1-84603-264-6}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Greene|Massignani|1999}}
|first1=Jack |last1=Greene |first2=Alessandro |last2=Massignani |title=Rommel's North Africa Campaign: September 1940 – November 1942 |publisher=Da Capo |location=Cambridge, MA |year=1999 |orig-year=1994 |isbn=978-1-58097-018-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Hinsley|1994}}
|last=Hinsley |first=H. |authorlink=Harry Hinsley |series=History of the Second World War |title=British Intelligence in the Second World War (abridged) |year=1994 |orig-year=1993 |edition=2nd rev. |publisher=HMSO |location=London |isbn=978-0-11-630961-7}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Latimer|2003}}
|authorlink=Jon Latimer |last=Latimer |first=Jon |title=Alamein |location=London |publisher=John Murray |orig-year=2002 |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-7195-6213-6}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|LePage|2008}}
|last=LePage |first=Jean-Denis G. G. |year=2008 |title=The French Foreign Legion: An Illustrated History |publisher=McFarlane |location=Jefferson, NC |isbn=978-0-7864-3239-4}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Montanari|1993}}
|first=Mario |last=Montanari |authorlink=|series=Le operazioni in Africa Settentrionale |volume=III |title=El Alamein (gennaio – novembre 1942) |trans-title=El Alamein (January–November 1942) |publisher=Stato Maggiore dell'esercito, Ufficio Storico, SME |edition=2nd |location=Roma |year=1993 |oclc=313319483}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Neillands|2005}}
|last=Neillands |first=R. |authorlink=Robin Neillands |title=The Desert Rats: 7th Armoured Division 1940–45 |year=2005 |orig-year=1991 |publisher=Widenfeld &amp; Nicolson |location=London |edition=Aurum Press |isbn=978-1-84513-115-9}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Palermo|2014}}
|last=Palermo |first=Michele |year=2014 |title=Eagles over Gazala: Air Battles in North Africa, May–June 1942 |publisher=IBN Editore |location=Roma |isbn=978-88-7565-168-8}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Pitt|1980}} |last=Pitt |first=B. |title=The Crucible of War: Auchinleck's Command |volume=II |year=1980 |edition=2001 |publisher=Cassell |location=London |isbn=978-0-304-35951-6 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/crucibleofwar00pitt_0 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Porch|2005}}
|last=Porch |first=Douglas |author-link=Douglas Porch |title=Hitler's Mediterranean Gamble |year=2005 |orig-year=2004 |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |edition=Cassell Military Paperbacks |location=London |isbn=978-0-304-36705-4}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Playfair|2004}}
|first1=Major-General I. S. O. | last1=Playfair |authorlink1=Ian Stanley Ord Playfair |last2=with Flynn |first2=Captain F.C. RN |last3=Molony |first3=Brigadier C. J. C. |last4=Gleave |first4=Group Captain T. P. |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=Sir James |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |series=History of the Second World War, United Kingdom Military Series |title=The Mediterranean and Middle East: British Fortunes reach their Lowest Ebb (September 1941 to September 1942) |volume=III |publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |location=Uckfield, UK |year=2004 |orig-year=1st. pub. [[HMSO]] 1960 |isbn=978-1-84574-067-2 |lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Richards|Saunders|1975}}
|last1=Richards |first1=Denis |authorlink1=Denis Richards |last2=Saunders |first2=Hilary St. G. |authorlink2=Hilary Saint George Saunders |volume=II |title=Royal Air Force 1939–1945: The Fight Avails |year=1975 |orig-year=1954 |publisher=HMSO |location=London |isbn=978-0-11-771593-6}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Walker|2003}}
|first=Ian W. |last=Walker |title=Iron Hulls, Iron Hearts: Mussolini's Elite Armoured Divisions in North Africa |publisher=Crowood |year=2003 |location=Marlborough |isbn=978-1-86126-646-0}}

'''Journals'''
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|Windrow|1976}}
|last=Windrow |first=M. |title=Bir Hakeim |issue=32 |year=1976 |journal=War Monthly |publisher=War Monthly Publications |location=London |issn=0307-2886}}

'''Websites'''
* {{cite web |ref={{harvid|Liardet|2012}}
|title=Bir Hakeim 1942, Les Français Libres contrarient les plans de Rommel |trans-title=Bir Hakeim 1942, The Free French Against Rommel |last=Liardet |first=J-P. |date=2012 |website=Net4war |url=http://www.net4war.com/e-revue/dossiers/2gm/birhakeim/birhakeim01.htm |accessdate=24 March 2015 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120204110006/http://www.net4war.com/e-revue/dossiers/2gm/birhakeim/birhakeim01.htm |archivedate=4 February 2012 }}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
'''Books'''
* {{cite book |last=Bergot |first=Erwan |authorlink=Erwan Bergot |title=La Légion au combat: Narvik, Bir-Hakeim, Diên Biên Phu. La 13e demi-brigade de Légion étrangère |trans-title=The Legion in Battle: Narvik, Bir Hakeim, Dien Bien Phu. The 13th Demi-Brigade of the Foreign Legion |language=French |publisher=Presses de la Cité |location=Paris |year=1975 |oclc=476143073}}
* {{cite book |last=Buffetaut |first=Yves |series=La guerre du desert |title=Bir-Hakeim |language=French |volume=II |publisher=Armes Militaria Magazine HS 06 |location=Paris |year=1992 |oclc=463803978}}
* {{cite book |first=Jean-Louis |last=Crémieux-Brilhac |title=La France Libre: de l'appel du 18 juin à la Libération |trans-title=Free France: The Call of June 18 at the Liberation |language=French |publisher=[[Nouvelle Revue Française]] (Gallimard) |location=[[Paris]] |year=1996 |isbn=978-2-07-073032-2}}
* {{cite book |title=1943: The Victory That Never Was |first=John |last=Grigg |authorlink=John Grigg, 2nd Baron Altrincham |publisher=Faber &amp; Faber |location=london |year=2013 |isbn=978-0-571-30374-8}}
* {{cite book |last=Kœnig |first=Marie Pierre |authorlink=Marie Pierre Kœnig |title=Bir Hakeim: 10 Juin 1942 |trans-title=Bir Hakeim: 10 June 1942 |language=French |editor=Robert Laffont |location=Paris |year=1971 |oclc=462985488}}
* {{cite book |series=Europäische Geschichtsdarstellungen |title=Schlachtenmythen: Ereignis, Erzählung, Erinnerung |trans-title=Battle Myths: Events, Narratives, Memory |first1=Gerd |last1=Krumeich |first2=Susanne |last2=Brandt |language=German |year=2003 |publisher=Böhlau |location=Köln |isbn=978-3-412-08703-6}}
* {{cite book |first=Dominique |last=Lormier |title=Rommel: La fin d'un mythe: biographie |trans-title=Rommel: The End of a Myth: Biography |publisher=Le Cherche midi |location=Paris |year= 2003| language=French |isbn=978-2-7491-0108-8}}
* {{cite book |first=Raphaël |last=Onana |title=Un homme blindé à Bir-Hakeim: récit d'un sous-officier camerounais qui a fait la guerre de 39–45 |trans-title=A Tank Man at Bir-Hakeim: Story of a Cameroonian Non-Commissioned Officer who was in the War 39–45 |language=French |year=1996 |publisher= L'Harmattan |location=Paris |isbn=978-2-7384-4239-0}}
* {{cite book |first1=Daniel |last1=Rondeau |first2=Roger |last2=Stephane |title=Des hommes libres: La France Libre par ceux qui l'ont faite |trans-title=Free Men: Free France by those Who Did |language=French |chapter=16 Testimonies |editor=Bernard Grasset |location=Paris |year=1997 |isbn=978-2-246-49011-1}}
* {{cite book |series=Moderne Zeit |volume=XIV |title=Der Mythos des Gaullismus: Heldenkult, Geschichtspolitik und Ideologie 1940 bis 1958 |trans-title=The Myth of Gaullism: Hero Worship, History, Politics and Ideology 1940–1958  |first=Matthias |last=Waechter |publisher=Wallstein Verlag |location=Göttingen |year=2006 |language=German |isbn=978-3-8353-0023-1}}
* {{cite book |last=Zdráhala |first=Richard |title=Válčil jsem v poušti |trans-title=I Fought in the Desert |language=Czech |publisher=Naše vojsko |location=Praha |year=1990 |isbn=80-206-0048-5}} 

'''Journals'''
* {{cite journal |last=Messmer |first=Pierre |authorlink=Pierre Messmer |title=La bataille de Bir Hakeim |trans-title=The Battle of Bir Hakeim |language=French |journal=Espoir, revue de l'institut Charles de Gaulle |publisher=Institut Charles de Gaulle |location=Paris |year=1986 |oclc=29827723}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Portal|World War II|France|War}}
{{commons|Battle of Bir Hakeim}}
* {{in lang|fr}} [https://web.archive.org/web/20150402141840/http://www.france-libre.net/wp-content/uploads/2009/02/pdf_ffl-net1.pdf Fondation de la France Libre, numéro spécial 70e anniversaire de la bataille de Bir Hakeim, n° 44, juin 2012]
* {{in lang|fr}} [https://web.archive.org/web/20150402172143/http://www.cncombattants.org/pdf/52/Bir-Hakeim.pdf Bir Hakeim, Verger, M.]
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/pha/policy/1942/420702a.html Parliamentary Debates, House of Commons Official Report July 2, 1942]
* [http://www.historynet.com/intercepted-communications-for-field-marshal-erwin-rommel.htm Bonner Fellers and the Black Code]

{{French Resistance}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bir Hakeim, Battle of}}
[[Category:French military history task force articles]]
[[Category:Western Desert Campaign]]
[[Category:Libya in World War II]]
[[Category:Free French Forces]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942|Battle of Bir Hakeim]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving India]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:1942 in France]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles involving the French Foreign Legion]]
[[Category:Erwin Rommel]]
[[Category:Last stand battles|Bir Hakeim]]
[[Category:May 1942 events]]
[[Category:June 1942 events]]
[[Category:Tank battles involving Germany]]
[[Category:Tank battles involving Italy]]
[[Category:Tank battles involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:1942 in Libya]]</text><sha1>62rlv1vnnk4k4od23jm1qje6zk96yv1</sha1></revision></page>