<page><title>Clearing the Channel Coast</title><ns>0</ns><id>25444552</id><revision><id>926131355</id><parentid>922800159</parentid><timestamp>2019-11-14T12:26:41Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Shimbo</username><id>201064</id></contributor><comment>Adding local [[Wikipedia:Short description|short description]]: "World War II campaign to liberate northern France", overriding Wikidata description "World War Affairs" ([[User:Galobtter/Shortdesc helper|Shortdesc helper]])</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="23113" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|World War II campaign to liberate northern France}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2018}}
{{Use Canadian English|date=October 2016}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Clearing the Channel Coast
| partof      = [[Allied advance from Paris to the Rhine|Siegfried Line Campaign]]
| image       = File:Strait of Dover map.png
|image_size = 300px
| caption     = The Channel coast
| date        = September–November 1944
| place       = France and Belgium
| result      = Allied victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|Canada|1921}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Poland|1918}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Czechoslovakia}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Belgium}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Netherlands}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|France|1830}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[Harry Crerar]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Gustav-Adolf von Zangen]]
| units1      = {{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[First Canadian Army]]
| units2      = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|army}} [[15th Army (Wehrmacht)|15th Army]]
| strength1   = 2 armoured divisions&lt;br&gt;4 infantry divisions
| strength2   = 3 divisions&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(in France)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;2 divisions&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(in Holland)&lt;/small&gt;
| casualties1 = 14,300 casualties
| casualties2 = 13,100 killed, wounded, missing&lt;br&gt;70,971 captured&lt;br&gt;'''Total''':&lt;br&gt;74,071 casualties
| campaignbox = 
{{Campaignbox Siegfried Line}}
{{Campaignbox Western Europe 1944–1945}}
}}

'''Clearing the Channel Coast''' was a [[World War II]] task undertaken by the [[First Canadian Army]] in August 1944, following the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[Operation Overlord]] and the victory, break-out and pursuit from Normandy.

The Canadian army advanced from [[Normandy]] to the [[Scheldt]] river in Belgium. En route, they were to capture the [[Channel ports]] needed to supply the Allied armies, clear the Germans from the Channel [[littoral]] and launch sites for the [[V-1 (flying bomb)|V-1 flying bombs]]. The German [[15th Army (Wehrmacht)|15th Army]] was able only to oppose the advance with sporadic resistance, wary of being outflanked and isolated by the rapidly advancing British [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|Second Army]] on the right of the Canadians and executed an orderly retreat north-eastwards towards the Scheldt.

On 4 September [[Adolf Hitler]] declared the Channel ports to be [[German World War II strongholds|fortresses]] but [[Dieppe, Seine-Maritime|Dieppe]] and [[Ostend]] were taken without opposition. [[Le Havre]], [[Boulogne]] and [[Calais]] were subjected to set-piece assaults, after massed bombing and an attack on [[Dunkirk]] was cancelled and the garrison contained. Troops investing Dunkirk were freed for the [[Battle of the Scheldt]], where the First Canadian Army reduced the [[Breskens Pocket]], cleared the mouth of the Scheldt and opened [[Antwerp]] to Allied shipping.

==Background==

===Normandy to the Seine===

The German armies had strongly resisted the Allied break-out from Normandy and when the German front collapsed in August they had insufficient reserves of manpower and equipment to resist and no defence lines between Normandy and the [[Siegfried Line]].&lt;ref&gt;Report 183, p.16&lt;/ref&gt; The British [[I Corps (United Kingdom)|I Corps]], with four divisions attached to the Canadian army, had been advancing eastwards from the [[River Dives]] along the coast. The [[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|6th Airborne Division]] and attached units captured [[Troarn]] and overran the German coastal artillery at [[Houlgate]] but deliberate flooding by the Germans, the defences of [[Cabourg]] and positions nearby at [[Dozulé]], slowed the advance across the Dives delta.{{sfn|Ellis|2004|p=448}} On 16 August, as soon as German resistance faltered. Reconnaissance had been ordered on 19 August and the authorization for a full advance and pursuit by the Canadians was issued on 23 August.

General [[Bernard Montgomery]], the [[21st Army Group]] commander issued a directive on 26 August, that all German forces in the [[Pas de Calais]] and [[Flanders]] were to be destroyed and Antwerp was to be captured. The First Canadian Army was required to cross the Seine and capture Dieppe and Le Havre with the minimum of forces and delay, while capturing the coast as far as Bruges. The Canadian army was to advance with a strong right wing and envelop resistance by swinging towards the coast; support could be expected from the First Allied Airborne Army. The [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|Second Army]] was to operate on the inland flank of the Canadians and dash for Amiens, cutting the communications of the German forces facing the Canadian Army.{{sfn|Ellis|2004|p=465}}

It is a measure of the German disintegration that the [[1st Polish Armoured Division]] was in [[Ypres]] on 6 September and Canadian units were at Dunkirk on 7 September, just fifteen days after Falaise, despite their losses in the Normandy battles. There was significant resistance in the Canadian sector. [[Adolf Hitler]] had ordered that most of the Channel ports be established as fortresses and prepared to withstand a siege. Since the Allies needed the port facilities to supply their advance, they could not be sealed off and left to wither on the vine. The Germans had established artillery positions capable of shelling [[Dover]], threatening allied shipping and there were launch sites for the [[V-1 flying bomb]]s bombarding London.

==Prelude==
===Allied armies===
The composition of the First Canadian Army varied to meet changing demands but in general terms it was composed of the [[II Canadian Corps]] and the I British Corps. Within these formations, at various times, were Czech, Polish, French, Dutch and Belgian units. After Normandy, the Polish and Czech formations were augmented by countrymen who had been [[Conscription|conscripted]] into the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German Army]] and changed sides.

The First Canadian Army had fought several battles in Normandy, resulting in depleted commanders and manpower at all levels. This was particularly serious in the infantry [[Company (military unit)|rifle companies]]. The I British Corps (commanded by [[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[John Crocker]]), attached to the First Canadian Army, had the [[7th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|7th Armoured Division]] and the [[49th (West Riding) Infantry Division]], [[51st (Highland) Division]] and the [[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|British 6th Airborne Division]]. The infantry divisions had not performed satisfactorily in Normandy and had been relegated to defensive positions on the eastern flank of the bridgehead. The 6th Airborne Division had landed in [[Operation Tonga]] on [[Normandy landings|D-Day]] and despite its lack of heavy weapons, remained defending the area. It had suffered many casualties and [[Major-general (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[Richard Gale (British Army officer)|Richard Gale]], had been ordered to harry the German retreat yet conserve its manpower for the rebuilding that was due. The 6th Airborne Division was reinforced by the [[1st Belgian Infantry Brigade]] and the [[Royal Netherlands Motorized Infantry Brigade|Royal Netherlands Brigade (Prinses Irene)]], which were to gain "operational experience in quieter sections of the line in the hope that ultimately they would return to their own countries and form nuclei around which larger national forces might be organized".&lt;ref name=rep183-39&gt;Report 183, p.39&lt;/ref&gt;

The I British Corps advanced along the Channel coast, with the II Canadian Corps on the right.

===German===

Much of [[Army Group B]] (''Heeresgruppe'' B) had been destroyed or shattered in Normandy and the [[Falaise Pocket]] but divisions deployed east of the Allied bridgehead were largely intact. German troops within the "fortress cities" were generally second-rate and included some Austrian and other nationalities, that were not trusted enough to carry arms.{{Citation needed|date=December 2009}}

===Advance to the Seine===
[[File:The British Army in North-west Europe 1944-45 BU185.jpg|thumb|British troops cross the River Seine over a Bailey bridge at Vernon, 27 August 1944.]]
The First Canadian Army advance to the Seine was called [[Operation Paddle article|Operation Paddle]]&lt;!-- When the [[Operation Paddle]] redirect (which directs back here) is turned into an article, please remove this piping - it's only here to provide a redlink --&gt;. It had been hoped by the Allied commanders that a defeat comparable with the Falaise Pocket could be inflicted on the Germans by trapping them against the Seine and the sea. The American [[United States Army Central|Third Army]] advanced northwards to [[Elbeuf]], across the Second Army line of advance, to cut off the route towards Paris and was a partial success. Although much of its remaining transport and the bulk of its armour was lost west of the Seine, Army Group B held up the Canadians, protecting improvised river crossings and significant quantities of men and [[materiel]] were saved.&lt;ref name=XII&gt;Chapter XII, p.320&lt;/ref&gt;

The towns along the [[Touques (river)|River Touques]] were evacuated by the Germans around 24 August and the capture of [[Lisieux]], about {{convert|45|km|mi|abbr=on}} east of [[Caen]], opened an important route eastwards.&lt;ref&gt;Report 183, p.52&lt;/ref&gt; Next day, the next natural barrier, the [[Risle|River Risle]] was crossed just north of [[Brionne]] by the [[11th Hussars]], with other units close behind. The [[6th Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|6th Airlanding Brigade]] of the 6th Airborne Division took [[Honfleur]] on the Seine estuary but progress along the coast was slower than inland, rivers being wider and more difficult to cross. The 6th Airborne Division occupied the west bank of the Risle from [[Pont Audemer]] downstream to the Seine on 26 August, completing its tasks in France and the division returned to Britain on 3 September. Clearance of the last German units west of the Seine was completed on 30 August.&lt;ref&gt;Report 183, pp.53-55&lt;/ref&gt;

===Crossing the Seine===
I British Corps put patrols across the Seine on 31 August. The advance to the Seine had outstripped the preparations of the [[Royal Canadian Engineers]] for bridging equipment and assault boats but newly assembled assault boats carried the [[3rd Canadian Infantry Division]] across the Seine at Elbeuf on 27 August. Ferries for wheeled and armoured vehicles were in operation in the afternoon.&lt;ref&gt;Report 183, pp.65-67&lt;/ref&gt;

==Liberations==

===Dieppe===

{{Main|Operation Fusilade}}

Dieppe had been abandoned by the Germans before the order Hitler sent for it to be defended as a "fortress" had been received and it was captured by the [[2nd Canadian Infantry Division]] on 1 September, which had last been in the port during the [[Dieppe Raid]] in 1942. A ceremonial parade was held on 5 September and despite demolitions, the port was cleared and in use on 7 September, a delivery of oil and petrol being shipped to Brussels on 9 September.&lt;ref&gt;Report 183, pp.133-135&lt;/ref&gt;

===Le Havre===

{{Main|Operation Astonia}}

Le Havre was attacked by the I British Corps, supported by [[Hobart's Funnies]], specialized armoured vehicles of the 79th Armoured Division and bombardment from land, sea and air. It was taken on 12 September after 48 hours but the port needed lengthy clearance and repair.

===Boulogne===

{{Main|Operation Wellhit}}

Boulogne was reached on 5 September but the garrison had received the Hitler "fortress" order. The city was protected by high ground and was attacked by the [[3rd Canadian Division]] with extensive air and artillery support from 17–22 September.

===Rocket sites===
On 1 September, the last V-1 was launched against London as the Canadians were moving through the launch areas.&lt;ref name=XIV355&gt;Chapter XIV, p.355&lt;/ref&gt;

===Calais and Cap Gris Nez===

{{Main|Operation Undergo}}

Calais was sealed off in early September and [[Wissant]] was quickly captured, though an early attack on Cap Gris Nez failed.
The assault on Calais itself opened on 25 September and the town fell on 30 September. A second attack on the [[Cross-Channel guns in the Second World War#German guns|Cap Gris Nez batteries]] opened on 29 September and the positions secured by the afternoon of the same day. Despite the strong defences and although the city had been declared a [[German World War II strongholds|Fortress]], the garrison needed little persuasion to surrender and their reluctance to fight to the end was repeated at Cap Gris Nez.

===Dunkirk===

{{Main|Siege of Dunkirk (1944)}}

[[File:Dunkirk.png|thumb|{{centre|Diagram showing the investment of Dunkirk}}]]
Although Dunkirk had been reached by 7 September, it soon became clear that the garrison would fight to hold a port that was largely destroyed. It was then judged to be a better use of men and materiel to clear the Germans from the Scheldt estuary and open the port of Antwerp, which had been captured intact. A brigade sized force was left to isolate Dunkirk, which eventually surrendered on 9 May 1945, after the general German surrender. The investment was conducted by the [[1st Czechoslovak Armoured Brigade]], in which [[Belgian Resistance]] members assisted with information and [[French Resistance]] members were converted to regular units.&lt;ref name=nn&gt;{{cite web |last=Hyrman |first=Jan |title=The port of Dunkirk in WWII |work=Naše Noviny |url=http://www.nasenoviny.com/DunkirkEN1944_45.html |accessdate=4 December 2010 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110714154719/http://www.nasenoviny.com/DunkirkEN1944_45.html |archivedate=14 July 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Belgium===
Ostend had been omitted from Hitler's  list of "fortresses" and so was evacuated, despite its strong defences. The port had been demolished. The 1st Polish Armoured Division crossed the Belgian border and captured Ypres on 6 September, reaching the [[List of canals in Belgium|Ghent-Bruges Canal]] on 9 September.&lt;ref&gt;Report 183, p.157&lt;/ref&gt;

===Scheldt===

{{Main|Battle of the Scheldt}}

A long and costly operation was required to clear the Germans from both banks of the Scheldt, so that the Port of Antwerp could be opened.

==Aftermath==

Although Dieppe came rapidly into use, it could supply only a quarter of the needs of the 21st Army Group. The capture of Le Havre, Boulogne, Calais and Ostend only eased Allied supply problems after extensive clearance of debris and mines. Ostend was restricted to personnel only but the Boulogne terminal for a [[Operation Pluto|Pluto]] oil pipeline (Dumbo) was of great benefit, becoming the "... main supplies of fuel during the winter and spring campaigns" of the Allies.&lt;ref name=XIV356&gt;Chapter XIV, p.356&lt;/ref&gt; It has been questioned whether the capture of the defended ports was worthwhile, given the need for much effort to bring them into use and the greater potential benefit of Antwerp.&lt;ref name=XIV356 /&gt;

After the failure of [[Operation Market Garden]], Eisenhower "turned to Antwerp, which despite the long-delayed capture of Le Havre on 12 September, of Brest on the 18th and of Calais on the 30th, remained, as the closest, largest and best-preserved of the ports, the necessary solution to the difficulties of supply." Antwerp was opened in November 1944 after the delayed [[Battle of the Scheldt]], and this largely solved Allied supply problems.{{sfn|Ehrman|1956|p=528}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Ehrman|1956}}
|last=Ehrman |first=John |authorlink=John Ehrman |title=Grand Strategy: August 1943 – September 1944 |volume=V |year=1956 |publisher=[[HMSO]] |location=London |oclc=809657212}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Ellis|2004}}
|last1=Ellis |first1=Major L. F. |author1-link=Lionel Ellis |last2=Allen |first2=Captain G. R. G. |last3=Warhurst |first3=Lieutenant-Colonel A. E. |last4=Robb |first4=Air Chief-Marshal Sir J. |editor-first=J. R. M. |editor-last=Butler |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |series=[[History of the Second World War]] United Kingdom Military Series |title=Victory in the West: The Battle of Normandy |volume=I |publisher=[[HMSO]] |location=London |edition=repr. Naval &amp; Military Press, Uckfield |year=2004 |orig-year=1962 |isbn=978-1-84574-058-0 |display-authors=1}}
* {{cite book |ref=
|last1=Ellis |first1=Major L. F. |author1-link=Lionel Ellis |last2=Allen |first2=Captain G. R. G. |last3=Warhurst |first3=Lieutenant-Colonel A. E. |last4=Robb |first4=Air Chief-Marshal Sir J. |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=Sir James |series=History of the Second World War, United Kingdom Military Series |title=Victory in the West: The Defeat of Germany |volume=II |publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |location=Uckfield, UK |year=2004a |orig-year=1st. pub. [[HMSO]]:1968 |isbn=978-1-84574-059-7 |display-authors=1}}
* {{cite web |last=Stacey |first=C. P. |authorlink=C. P. Stacey |title=Part IV: First Canadian Army in the Pursuit (23 Aug – 30 Sep) (Report 183) |work=Canadian Participation in the Operations in North West Europe, 1944 |publisher=Historical section, Canadian Military Headquarters |date=|url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/his/rep-rap/doc/cmhq/cmhq183.pdf |accessdate = 17 Dec 2009}}
* {{cite book |first1=Colonel Charles Perry |last1=Stacey |authorlink= |last2=Bond |first2=Major C. C. J. |series=Official History of the Canadian Army in the Second World War |volume=III |title=The Victory Campaign: The Operations in North-West Europe 1944–1945 |chapter=XIV; Clearing the Coastal Belt and the Ports, September 1944 |chapterurl=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/Canada/CA/Victory/Victory-14.html#cn31 |accessdate=11 October 2016 |publisher=The Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery Ottawa |year=1960 |edition=online |url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/his/docs/Victory_e.pdf |oclc=256471407}}
* {{cite web |last=Stacey |first=C. P. |authorlink=C. P. Stacey |title=Chapter XII: The Campaign in North-West Europe: The Battle of Normandy, June–August 1944 |work=Official History of the Canadian Army |publisher=[[Department of National Defence (Canada)|Department of National Defence]] |year=1966 |url=http://ibiblio.net/hyperwar/UN/Canada/CA/OpSumm/OpSumm-12.html |accessdate=12 January 2010 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100706083407/http://ibiblio.net/hyperwar/UN/Canada/CA/OpSumm/OpSumm-12.html |archive-date=6 July 2010 |url-status=dead }}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
'''Books'''
* {{cite book |last=Brown |first=David |title=Warship Losses of World War Two |publisher=Arms and Armour |location=London |year=1990 |isbn=978-0-85368-802-0}}
* {{cite book |title=Monty's Men: The British Army and the Liberation of Europe |last=Buckley |first=J. |authorlink=John Buckley (historian) |year=2014 |orig-year=2013 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=London |edition=pbk. |isbn=978-0-300-20534-3}}
* {{cite book |first=Terry |last=Copp |title=Cinderella Army: The Canadians in Northwest Europe, 1944–1945 |year=2006 |publisher=University of Toronto Press |location= |isbn=978-0-8020-3925-5}}
* {{cite book |last=Doherty |first=R. |title=Normandy 1944: The Road to Victory |year=2004 |publisher=Spellmount |location=Staplehurst |isbn=978-1-86227-224-8}}
* {{cite book |last=Hinsley |first=F. H. |series=History of the Second World War |title=British Intelligence in the Second World War. Its influence on Strategy and Operations (abridged) |location=London |publisher=[[HMSO]] |year=1994 |orig-year=1993 |edition=2nd rev. |isbn=978-0-11-630961-7}}
* {{cite report |last=LeBlanc |first=S. S. G. |date=23 November 2016 |title=Breaching the Ramparts: The 3rd Canadian Infantry Division's Capture of Boulogne in World War Two |url=http://www.dtic.mil/dtic/tr/fulltext/u2/1022084.pdf |accessdate=30 November 2017 |publisher=School of Advanced Military Studies United States Army Command and General Staff College |location=Fort Leavenworth, KS |type=pdf |oclc=965801279}}
* {{cite book |title=Infantry Tank Warfare |last=Plant |first=J. |authorlink= |year=2014 |publisher=New Generation |location=London |edition=rev. enl. |isbn=978-1-78507-158-4}}
* {{cite book |title=Royal Air Force 1939–45: The Fight is Won |volume=III |last1=St George Saunders |first1=H. |last2=Richards |first2=D. |authorlink= |year=1975 |orig-year=1954 |publisher=HMSO |location=London |edition=pbk. |isbn=978-0-11-771594-3}}
* {{cite book |first=Milton |last=Shulman |title=Defeat in the West |publisher=Martin Secker &amp; Warburg |location=London |year=2003 |orig-year=1947 |edition=repr. Cassell Military Paperbacks |isbn=978-0-304-36603-3}}
* {{cite book |last=Stacey |authorlink= |author2=Bond, Major C. C. J. |series=Official History of the Canadian Army in the Second World War |volume=III |title=The Victory Campaign: The operations in North-West Europe 1944–1945 |publisher=The Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery Ottawa |year=1960 |url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/his/docs/Victory_e.pdf |first=Colonel C. P. |accessdate=26 November 2017 |format=pdf |oclc=606015967}}
* {{cite book |series=History of the Second World War United Kingdom Military series |title=The Strategic Air Offensive against Germany 1939–1945 |volume=III |others=Part 5 |last1=Webster |first1=C. |authorlink1=Charles Webster (historian) |last2=Frankland |first2=N. |authorlink2=Noble Frankland |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=J. R. M. |year=1994 |orig-year=1961 |publisher=HMSO |location=London |edition=Imperial War Museum and Battery Press |isbn=978-0-89839-205-0}}

'''Reports'''
* {{cite report |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |year=2008 |orig-year=1944 |title=Clearing of the Scheldt Estuary, October–November 1944 |url=http://cgsc.cdmhost.com/cdm/singleitem/collection/p4013coll8/id/2615/rec/4 |type=pdf |publisher=21st Army Group |edition=Combined Arms Research Library Digital Library online |id=N10209 |accessdate=9 December 2017}}
* {{cite report |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |year=2004 |orig-year=1945 |title=Notes on the Operations of 21 Army Group, 6 June 1944 – 5 May 1945 |url=http://cgsc.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/singleitem/collection/p4013coll8/id/357/rec/42 |type=pdf |publisher=British Army of the Rhine |edition=Combined Arms Research Library Digital Library online |id=N13331 |accessdate=2 December 2017}}
* {{cite report |last=Williams |first=M. P. |date=22 May 2014 |series=Command and General Staff College (CGSC), School of Advanced Military Studies (SAMS) Monograph |title=Rough Road to Antwerp: The First Canadian Army's Operations Along the Channel Coast |url=http://cgsc.cdmhost.com/cdm/singleitem/collection/p4013coll3/id/3155/rec/1 |publisher=US Army Command and General Staff College |type=pdf |oclc=913594548 |accessdate=9 December 2017}}

{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Channel}}
[[Category:Western European Campaign (1944–1945)]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]</text><sha1>a36nqqh7olt4wd89qwoht9zu259a7rm</sha1></revision></page>