<page><title>Battle of the Scheldt</title><ns>0</ns><id>1853296</id><revision><id>966876638</id><parentid>963986894</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-09T18:46:19Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Eik Corell</username><id>6136027</id></contributor><comment>Fixed misspelling --- Changing Eberling to Eberding</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="103349" xml:space="preserve">{{For|the 1574 battle|Battle of the Scheldt (1574)}}
{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Battle of the Scheldt
| partof = the [[Allied advance from Paris to the Rhine]] in the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]] of [[World War II]]
| image = File:acrossthescheldt.jpg
|image_size = 300px
| caption = [[Landing Vehicle Tracked|Buffalo amphibious vehicles]] taking Canadians&lt;br /&gt;across the [[Scheldt]] in Zeeland, 1944
| date = October 2 – November 8, 1944
| place = Dutch [[Zeeland]] and northern Belgium
| coordinates = {{coord|51|25|N|4|10|E|region:NL_type:event_scale:50000|display=inline}}
| result = Allied victory
| territory = [[Antwerp]] opened to Allied shipping
| combatant1 = {{flag|Canada|1921}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Poland|1928}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Belgium}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Netherlands}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|France|1830}} [[Provisional Government of the French Republic|France]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Norway}}
| combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1 = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Bernard Montgomery]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[Guy Simonds]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[Harry Crerar]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Bertram Ramsay]]
| commander2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Gustav-Adolf von Zangen]]
| units1 = {{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[First Canadian Army|1st Army]]
| units2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[15th Army (Wehrmacht)|15th Army]]
| strength1 = 135,000
| strength2 = 90,000
| casualties1 = Canadian: 6,367&lt;br /&gt;Total: 12,873
| casualties2 = Roughly 10-12,000&lt;br /&gt;41,043 captured
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Western Front (World War II)}}
{{Canadian military actions in World War II}}
{{Campaignbox Liberation of the Netherlands}}}}

The '''Battle of the Scheldt''' in World War II was a series of [[military operation]]s led by the [[First Canadian Army]], with Canadian, [[Polish Armed Forces in the West|Polish]] and [[British Army|British]] units attached, to open up the shipping route to [[Antwerp]] so that its port could be used to supply the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] in north-west Europe. Under acting command of the First Canadian's [[Lieutenant-General (Canada)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Guy Simonds]], the battle took place in northern [[Belgium]] and southwestern [[Netherlands]] from October 2 to November 8, 1944.&lt;ref name=VetAff&gt;{{citation |url=http://www.veterans.gc.ca/eng/remembrance/history/second-world-war/scheldt#scheldt03 |publisher=Veterans Affairs Canada. |title=The Battle of the Scheldt |accessdate=10 August 2014 |date=14 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The well-established [[Wehrmacht]] defenders staged an effective delaying action, during which the Germans flooded land areas in the [[Scheldt|Scheldt estuary]], slowing the Allied advance. After five weeks of difficult fighting, the Canadian First Army, at a cost of 12,873 Allied casualties (half of them Canadian), was successful in clearing the Scheldt after numerous [[amphibious assault]]s, obstacle crossings, and costly assaults over open ground.

Once the German defenders were no longer a threat, it was a further three weeks{{snd}}November 29, 1944{{snd}}before the first convoy carrying Allied supplies was able to unload in Antwerp due to the necessity of [[de-mining]] the harbours.

==Background==
{{Further|Battle of the Scheldt order of battle}}

Following the Allied breakout after success in the [[Operation Overlord|battle of Normandy]], they began a series of rapid advances deeper into France, away from their initial avenues of supply along the west coast of France.

Lack of a sufficiently robust supply line – including enough port capacity – was the main factor holding back further Allied advance. [[Brest, France|Brest]], when finally taken, was too wrecked to use, and other ports were held as fortresses by the Germans. The Allies needed the large port of Antwerp and had counted on it.&lt;ref&gt;Weinberg, Gerhard ''A World In Arms'', Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2005 page 761-762.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first plans for liberating Europe by the Anglo-American armies, code-named "[[Operation Roundup (1942)|Roundup]]", had been drawn up in December 1941. They had stressed that the port of Antwerp would be crucial for an invasion of Germany, as it was the largest deep-water port close to Germany that the Allies could hope to capture intact.&lt;ref name="Weinberg, Gerhard page 700"&gt;Weinberg, Gerhard ''A World In Arms'', Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2005 page 700.&lt;/ref&gt; Antwerp is a deep water inland port connected to the North Sea via the river [[Scheldt]]. The Scheldt was wide enough and dredged deep enough to allow the passage of ocean-going ships, and was close to Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Antwerp'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1984 page 129.&lt;/ref&gt; [[File:The Commander of 21st Army Group, General Sir Bernard Montgomery, during his first press conference for Allied war correspondents after the Allied invasion of Normandy, 11 June 1944. B5337.jpg|thumb|200px|The Commander of [[21st Army Group]], General [[Bernard Montgomery]]]]

The ''[[Witte Brigade]]'' (White Brigade) of the Belgian resistance seized the port of Antwerp before the Germans could blow up the port as they were planning. On September 4, Antwerp was taken by the [[11th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|11th Armoured Division]] with its harbour 90% intact.&lt;ref name="Weinberg, Gerhard page 700" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry ""No Lack of Rational Speed": First Canadian Army Operations, September 1944". from ''The Journal of Canadian Studies'' Volume 16, Fall 1981 page 149.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Germans had heavily fortified [[Walcheren]] island at the mouth of the [[Western Scheldt]], establishing well dug-in artillery impervious to air attack and controlling access to the river. This made it impossible for Allied minesweepers to clear the heavily mined river.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 120"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 120.&lt;/ref&gt; [[Adolf Hitler]] ordered the 15th German Army, which had been stationed in the [[Pas-de-Calais|Pas de Calais]] region and was now marching north into the Low Countries, to hold the mouth of the river Scheldt, depriving the Allies of the use of the Antwerp port. Montgomery became aware of this on September 5, thanks to [[Ultra]] intelligence.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry ""No Lack of Rational Speed": First Canadian Army Operations, September 1944". from ''The Journal of Canadian Studies'' Volume 16, Fall 1981 page 148.&lt;/ref&gt; Hitler had personally designated the island "Fortress Walcheren", which he ordered to be defended to the last man.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 120" /&gt; Walcheren island was held by mixture of [[Kriegsmarine]] and [[Wehrmacht]], with its garrison consisting of the 202nd Naval Coastal Artillery Battalion, the 810th Naval Anti-Aircraft Battalion, the 89th Fortress Regiment and the 70th Infantry Division commanded by General [[Wilhelm Daser]].&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 120-122&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 5, SHAEF's naval commander, Admiral Sir [[Bertram Ramsay]] advised Montgomery to make taking the mouth of the Scheldt his main priority, stating that as long as the mouth of the Scheldt was in German hands, it was impossible for the [[Royal Navy]] [[minesweeper]]s to clear the numerous mines in the river, rendering the port of Antwerp useless.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 16 &amp; 42–43&lt;/ref&gt; Among the Allied senior leaders, only Ramsay saw opening Antwerp as crucial to sustaining the advance into Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page16&lt;/ref&gt; On 6 September 1944, Montgomery told Canadian General [[Harry Crerar]] that "I want Boulogne badly" and that city should be taken at once with no regard to losses.&lt;ref name="Copp page 150"&gt;Copp, Terry ""No Lack of Rational Speed": First Canadian Army Operations, September 1944". from ''The Journal of Canadian Studies'' Volume 16, Fall 1981 page 150.&lt;/ref&gt; By this point, ports like [[Cherbourg Harbour|Cherbourg]], which the Americans had taken in June, were too far away from the front line, causing the Allies great logistical problems.

From September on, Admiral Ramsay was deeply involved in planning the assault on "Fortress Walcheren". He appointed Captain Pugsley of the Royal Navy, who landed the 7th Brigade of the 3rd Canadian Division on D-Day, to the [[First Canadian Army]] headquarters to start preparations.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 120&lt;/ref&gt; Had Montgomery secured the Scheldt estuary in early September 1944 as Admiral Ramsay had strongly advised him to do, Antwerp would have been opened to Allied shipping far earlier than it was, and the escape of the German [[15th Army (Wehrmacht)|15th Army]] from France would have been stopped.&lt;ref name="Weinberg, Gerhard page 700" /&gt; As a part of [[Operation Fortitude]], the deception plan for [[Operation Overlord]], the Allies had tricked the Germans into believing they would land in the Pas-de-Calais region of France instead of in [[Normandy]], and as such, the Wehrmacht had reinforced the 15th Army in the Pas-de-Calais.

On 9 September, Montgomery wrote to Field Marshal Sir [[Alan Brooke]] of the [[Chief of the General Staff (United Kingdom)|Imperial General Staff]] that "one good Pas de Calais port" would be able to meet the logistical needs of the 21st Army Group only.&lt;ref name="Copp page 150" /&gt; Montgomery further noted that "one good Pas de Calais port" would be insufficient for the American armies in France, which thus forced Eisenhower, if for no other reasons than logistics, to favour Montgomery's plans for an invasion of northern Germany by the 21st Army Group, whereas if Antwerp were opened up, all of the Allied armies could be supplied.&lt;ref name="Copp page 150" /&gt; Montgomery had his eye on taking [[Berlin]] before either the Americans or the Soviets took the capital of the ''[[Nazi Germany|Reich]]''. Montgomery ordered that the First Canadian Army take Calais, Boulogne and Dunkirk and clear the Scheldt, a task that General Crerar stated was impossible because he did not have sufficient troops to perform both operations at once.&lt;ref name="Copp page 150" /&gt; Montgomery refused Crerar's request to have British XII Corps under General [[Neil Ritchie]] assigned to help clear the Scheldt because he needed XII Corps for [[Operation Market Garden]].&lt;ref name="Copp page 150" /&gt;
[[File:Guy Simonds e010786106-v8.jpg|left |thumb|200px|The Commander of [[First Canadian Army]], [[Lieutenant-general (Canada)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Guy Simonds]]]]

The importance of taking ports closer to Germany was highlighted with the liberation of the city of [[Le Havre]], which was assigned to General [[John Crocker]]'s I Corps. To take Le Havre, the British assigned two infantry divisions, two tank brigades, most of the artillery of the Second British Army, the specialized armoured "gadgets" of General [[Percy Hobart]]'s 79th Armoured Division, the battleship [[HMS Warspite (03)|HMS ''Warspite'']] and the monitor [[HMS Erebus (I02)|HMS ''Erebus'']].&lt;ref name="Copp page 150" /&gt; On 10 September 1944, [[Operation Astonia]] began when [[RAF Bomber Command]] dropped 4,719 tons of bombs on Le Havre, which was then assaulted by Crocker's men, who took the city two days later.&lt;ref name="Copp page 150" /&gt; The Canadian historian [[Terry Copp]] wrote that the commitment of this much firepower and men to take only one French city might "seem excessive", but by this point, the Allies desperately needed ports closer to the front line to sustain their advance.&lt;ref name="Copp page 150" /&gt;

Little was done about the blocked port of Antwerp during September because Montgomery chose to make the ill-fated Operation Market Garden his key priority, rather than clearing the Scheldt.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 12.&lt;/ref&gt; With Market Garden, Montgomery intended to by-pass the [[Siegfried Line|West Wall]] and break into the [[North German Plain|north German plain]] in order to take Berlin, but the British defeat at the [[Battle of Arnhem]], which proved to be the proverbial "bridge too far", left the British forming an exposed [[Salient (military)|salient]] reaching deep into the Netherlands.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 7 &amp; 12.&lt;/ref&gt; In the meantime, German forces in the Scheldt estuary were able to deploy defensively and prepare for the expected advance. The first attacks occurred on September 13.&lt;ref name="VetAff" /&gt; After an attempt by the 4th Canadian Armoured Division to storm the [[Leopold Canal (Belgium)|Leopold Canal]] on its own had ended in bloody repulse, General Guy Simonds, commanding the II Canadian Corps, ordered a halt to operations in the Scheldt until the French channel ports had been taken, reporting the Scheldt would need more than one division to clear.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 124"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Antwerp'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1984 page 124.&lt;/ref&gt; The halt allowed the German [[15th Army (Wehrmacht)|15th Army]] ample time to dig in to its new home by the banks of the Scheldt.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 124" /&gt;

On the German side, holding the Scheldt was regarded as crucial. Hitler ordered planning for what became the [[Battle of the Bulge|Ardennes Offensive]] in September 1944, the objective of which was retaking Antwerp. The 15th Army, which was holding the Scheldt on the far right on the German line, was deprived of supplies as the Wehrmacht focused on building up its strength for the planned Ardennes offensive in December, while a number of newly raised ''[[Volksgrenadier]]'' divisions were sent to replace the divisions lost in Normandy and in [[Operation Bagration]] on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]. However, the flat [[polder]] ground of the Dutch countryside favoured the defensive, and was felt to compensate for the 15th Army's reduced numbers. It was assigned only two of the ''Volksgrenadier'' divisions.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 10"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 10.&lt;/ref&gt; Field Marshal [[Gerd von Rundstedt]] told General [[Gustav-Adolf von Zangen]]: "Enemy supplies, and therefore, his ability to fight, is limited by the stubborn defense of the Harbour, as intelligence report prove. The attempt of the enemy to occupy the Western Scheldt in order to obtain the free use of the harbour of Antwerp must be resisted ''to the utmost"'' (emphasis in the original).&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 11.&lt;/ref&gt; In his orders to his men, Von Zangen declared:

{{quote|Therefore, I order all commanders as well as the National Socialist indoctrination officers to instruct the troops in the clearest and most factual manner in the following points: Next to HAMBURG, ANTWERP is the largest port in Europe. Even in the First World War, Churchill, in person, traveled to ANTWERP in order to organise the defense of the harbor because he appreciated it as of vital importance to the struggle on the continent. At that time, Churchill's plan was completely shattered; the same must happen again. After overrunning the SCHELDT fortifications, the English would finally be in a position to land great masses of material in a large and completely protected harbor. With this material they might deliver a death blow at the NORTH GERMAN plain and at BERLIN before the onset of winter...The enemy knows that he must assault the European fortress as speedily as possible before its inner lines of resistance are fully built up and occupied by new divisions. For this, he needs the ANTWERP harbor. And for this reason, we must hold the SCHELDT fortifications to the end. The German people are watching us. In this hour, the fortifications along the SCHELDT occupy a role which is decisive for the future of our people. Each additional day will be vital that you deny the port of ANTWERP to the enemy and the resources he has at his disposal.

(signed) v. ZANGEN General der Infanterie.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 27.&lt;/ref&gt;}}

In early October, after Operation Market Garden, Allied forces led by the Canadian First Army finally set out to open the port of Antwerp to the Allies by giving it access to the sea. As the [[Arnhem]] salient was his major concern, Montgomery pulled away from the First Canadian Army (which was under the temporary command of Simonds as Crerar was ill), the [[51st (Highland) Division|British 51st Highland Division]], 1st Polish Division, [[49th (West Riding) Infantry Division|British 49th (West Riding) Division]] and [[2nd Canadian Armoured Brigade]], and sent all of these formations to help the [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|2nd British Army]] hold the Arnhem salient.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 18.&lt;/ref&gt; Simonds saw the Scheldt campaign as a test of his ability, a challenge to be overcome, and he felt he could clear the Scheldt with only three divisions of the 2nd Corps despite having to take on the entire 15th Army, which held strongly fortified positions in a landscape that favoured the defence.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry pages 19-20"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 19-20.&lt;/ref&gt; Simonds not once registered complaints about his lack of manpower, the fact that ammunition was being rationed as supplying the Arnhem salient was Montgomery's chief concern, and the lack of air support, which was made worse by the cloudy October weather.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry pages 19-20"/&gt;

===Plan===
On September 12 and 13, 1944, the Canadian First Army, under temporary command of Lieutenant-General [[Guy Simonds]], was given the task of clearing the Scheldt once it had completed the clearing of the Channel ports, particularly Boulogne, Calais and Dunkirk. Montgomery then decided that the importance of Antwerp was such that the capture of Dunkirk could be delayed.&lt;ref&gt;Official History p331, 336&lt;/ref&gt; Under his command at that time were [[II Canadian Corps|Canadian II Corps]], with the [[1st Armoured Division (Poland)|Polish 1st Armoured Division]], [[49th (West Riding) Infantry Division|49th]] and [[52nd (Lowland) Infantry Division|52nd Divisions]] attached, and the [[I Corps (United Kingdom)|British I Corps]]. Montgomery promised the support of [[RAF Bomber Command]] in attacking the German fortifications and that of the [[USAAF]] [[8th Air Force]] "[o]n the day concerned".&lt;ref&gt;Official History p358&lt;/ref&gt; The [[51st (Highland) Division|51st (Highland) Infantry Division]] was to give up its transport to enable the movement of forces into battle positions. Abandoning the capture of Dunkirk freed the [[2nd Canadian Infantry Division]].
[[File:Mapnorthernfront.gif|thumb|The Northern Front. The salient buffer of Market Garden up to Nijmegen can be seen.]]

The plan for opening the Scheldt estuary involved four main operations, conducted over daunting geography:
* Clearing the area north of Antwerp and securing access to the [[South Beveland]] peninsula.
* Operation Switchback, clearing the [[Breskens pocket|Breskens Pocket]] north of the Leopold canal and south of the Western Scheldt.
* Operation Vitality, the capture of the [[Zuid-Beveland|South Beveland]] peninsula, north of the Western Scheldt.
* Operation Infatuate, the capture of [[Walcheren]] island, which had been fortified into a powerful German stronghold. As part of the [[Atlantic Wall]], Walcheren island, with its strategic position just north of the Scheldt river mouth, was considered to be the "strongest concentration of defences the [[Nazis]] had ever constructed."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Williams|first=Jeffery|title=The Long Left Flank|publisher=Leo Cooper|location=London|year=1988|isbn=0-85052-880-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On September 21, the [[4th Canadian (Armoured) Division]] moved north roughly along the line of the [[Ghent–Terneuzen Canal]], given the task of clearing an area on the south shore of the Scheldt around the Dutch town of [[Breskens]], called the "Breskens Pocket". The Polish 1st Armoured Division headed for the Dutch-Belgian border further east and the crucial area north of Antwerp.

The [[4th Canadian Division|Canadian 4th Armoured Division]] advanced from a hard-won [[bridgehead]] over the Ghent-Brugge Canal at [[Moerbrugge]] to find themselves the first Allied troops facing the formidable obstacle of the double line of the Leopold and [[Lys River|Schipdonk]] Canals. An attack was mounted in the vicinity of [[Moerkerke]], crossing the canals and establishing a bridgehead before counter-attacks forced a withdrawal with heavy casualties.

The 1st Polish Armoured Division enjoyed greater success to the east as it advanced northeast from [[Ghent]]. In country unsuitable for armour, and against stiffening resistance, the division advanced to the coast by September 20, occupying [[Terneuzen]] and clearing the south bank of the Scheldt east toward Antwerp.

It became apparent to Simonds that any further gains in the Scheldt would come at heavy cost, as the [[Breskens pocket|Breskens Pocket]], extending from [[Zeebrugge]] to the [[Braakman|Braakman Inlet]] and inland to the Leopold Canal, was strongly held by the enemy.

==Battle==

=== Securing access to South Beveland ===
On October 2, the Canadian 2nd Division began its advance north from Antwerp. Stiff fighting ensued on October 6 at [[Woensdrecht (village)|Woensdrecht]], the objective of the first phase. The Germans, reinforced by [[85th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|Battle Group Chill]], saw the priority in holding there, controlling direct access to South Beveland and Walcheren island.
[[File:Alligators passing Terrepin amphibious vehicles.jpg|right|thumb|Column of [[Landing Vehicle Tracked|Alligator amphibious vehicles]] passing [[Terrapin (amphibious vehicle)|Terrapin]] amphibious vehicles on the Scheldt river, October 1944.]]

There were heavy casualties as the Canadians attacked over open, flooded land. Canadian historians [[Terry Copp]] and Robert Vogel wrote: "the very name Woensdrecht sends shivers down the spines of veterans of the 2nd Canadian Infantry Division".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 30"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 30.&lt;/ref&gt; Driving rain, booby traps and land mines made advance very difficult. Attacking on 7 October in heavy mist, the [[Calgary Highlanders]] came under heavy fire from German positions. As described in its war diary, "the battle thickened...the Germans forces...hit back with a pugnacity which had not been encountered in the enemy for a long time".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 30"/&gt; The [[Le Régiment de Maisonneuve|Régiment de Maisoneuve]] was halted 1,000 yards from their target while the next day, [[The Black Watch (Royal Highland Regiment) of Canada|The Black Watch of Canada]] was stopped in its attempt.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 30"/&gt; On October 9, the Germans counter-attacked and pushed the Canadians back.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 30"/&gt; The war diary of the [[85th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|85th Infantry Division]] reported that they were "making very slow progress" in face of tenacious Canadian resistance.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 31&lt;/ref&gt;

Back at [[Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force|SHAEF]] headquarters, Admiral Ramsay, who was more concerned about the problems facing the Canadians than their own generals, complained to [[Supreme Allied Commander]] General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower|Dwight Eisenhower]] that the Canadians were having to ration ammunition as Montgomery made holding the Arnhem salient his main priority.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry pages 42"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 42.&lt;/ref&gt; After Ramsay raised the issue with Eisenhower, the latter informed Montgomery on October 9 about "the supreme importance of Antwerp. It is reported to me this morning by the Navy that the Canadian Army will not repeat not be able to attack until November 1 unless immediately supplied with ammunition."&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry pages 42"/&gt; Montgomery replied by writing: "Request you will ask Ramsay from me by what authority he makes wild statements to you concerning my operations about which he can know nothing repeat nothing...there is no repeat no shortage of ammunition...The operations are receiving my personal attention".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry pages 42"/&gt;

Field Marshal [[Walter Model]], who was commanding [[Army Group B]], ordered: "The corridor to Walcheren will be kept open at any price; if necessary, it will be regained by forces ruthlessly detached from other sectors".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 31"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 31.&lt;/ref&gt; Model, a tough and ruthless [[Nazism|National Socialist]] fanatic known for his devotion to Hitler, was called "the [[Führer]]'s Fireman" because Hitler always gave him the toughest jobs. Model sent the 256th ''Volksgrenadier'' division and assault gun companies to allow the release of Battle Group Chill, the "fire brigade" consisting of 6th Paratroop Regiment and assault gun companies.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 31"/&gt; On October 10, the [[Royal Regiment of Canada]] launched a surprise attack against the German lines at Woensdrecht, but for the next days was engaged in heavy fighting against counterattacks from Battle Group Chill.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 31"/&gt; Major-General [[Charles Foulkes (Canadian Army general)|Charles Foulkes]] of the 2nd Division sent the Black Watch to support the Royal Regiment.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 34"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 34.&lt;/ref&gt; The German forces at Woensdrecht greatly outnumbered the Canadians and had Model known of this, he might have launched a counter-offensive. Instead he used [[Attrition warfare|attrition tactics]] by making piecemeal counterattacks.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 34-35.&lt;/ref&gt; During this time, war diaries of the Royal Hamilton Light Infantry noted "many snipers in the houses and hedges" had been encountered while the weather was "cold and wet with high winds. Floods rising again".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 40"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 40&lt;/ref&gt;

Simonds had planned to commit the 4th Division to assist the 3rd Division with clearing the Breskens Pocket, but problems faced by the 2nd Division forced Simonds to start peeling off units from the 4th Division.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 46.&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 October 1944, the [[South Alberta Regiment]] was ordered to "protect the right flank of 2 Division and present infiltration between 2 Div and 1 Polish Armd. Div".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 46"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 46&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, Simonds ordered General Harry Foster of the 4th Division "to send 4 Cnd Armd Bde to the Antwerp area at the rate of one get a day, beginning 11 Oct".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 40"/&gt;
[[File:Map - Battle of the Scheldt (Oct-Nov 44).jpg|thumb|Map of the Battle of the Scheldt]]

On October 13, on what would come to be known as "Black Friday", the [[Canadian 5th Infantry Brigade]]'s [[The Black Watch (Royal Highland Regiment) of Canada|Black Watch]] was virtually wiped out in an unsuccessful attack. The Black Watch attacked German positions, already known to be well defended, while the rest of the 2nd Division was not engaged, suggesting that neither Foulkes nor Simonds had taken seriously the problem of fighting by the river Scheldt.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 34"/&gt; The Black Watch, whose officers had come from Montreal's Scottish elite, had billed itself as the most exclusive regiment in the Canadian Army. Despite this reputation, the Black Watch was considered to be a "jinxed" regiment which had had more than its fair share of misfortune.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 34"/&gt; One officer of the Black Watch reported that the soldiers sent to replace the Black Watch men killed and wounded in France "had little or no infantry training, and exhibited poor morale" and that the men of C Company had "all been killed or taken prisoner" during "Black Friday".&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 38&lt;/ref&gt; The Black Watch had already taken very heavy losses at the [[Battle of Verrières Ridge]] in July 1944 and its heavy losses on "Black Friday" almost finished the regiment. The [[Stormont, Dundas and Glengarry Highlanders|Calgary Highlanders]] were to follow up with a more successful action, and their Carrier Platoon succeeded in taking the railroad station at Korteven, north of Woensdrecht.&lt;ref&gt;two kilometers northeast of Woensdrecht&lt;/ref&gt; Fighting at [[Hoogerheide]]&lt;ref&gt;two kilometers southeast of Woensdrecht&lt;/ref&gt; also ensued. On October 16, [[The Royal Hamilton Light Infantry (Wentworth Regiment)|The Royal Hamilton Light Infantry]], known as the "Rileys", under the command of Lieutenant Colonel [[Denis Whitaker]], attacked Woensdrecht at night, taking much of the village. However, they were unable to pass beyond the ridge to the west of Woensdrecht.&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 34&lt;/ref&gt; The "Rileys" took losses equal to those suffered by the Black Watch on "Black Friday", but as they had taken Woensdrecht while the Black Watch had been thrown back, the fighting on October 16 is not remembered as "Black Monday".&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt; By October 16, Woensdrecht was secured, cutting the land link to South Beveland and Walcheren. The Canadians achieved their first objective, but had suffered heavy casualties.

On 14 October Field Marshal Montgomery issued "Notes on Command" that were highly critical of Eisenhower's leadership and asked he be made Land Forces commander again.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 43"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 43.&lt;/ref&gt; On the next day, Eisenhower replied that the issue was not the command arrangement, but rather the ability and willingness of Montgomery to obey orders, saying he had ordered him to clear the Scheldt and warned if he was unable to obey orders, he would be fired.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 43"/&gt; Stung by Eisenhower's message, a chastised Montgomery promised: "You will hear no more from me on the subject of command...Antwerp top priority in all operations of 21 Army Group".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 43"/&gt; On October 16, Montgomery issued a directive along that line.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 43"/&gt; To the east, the British Second Army attacked westward to clear the Netherlands south of the [[Maas River]] during [[Operation Pheasant]], securing the Scheldt region from counter-attacks.

As part of his newly focused efforts to assist Simonds, Montgomery assigned the [[52nd (Lowland) Infantry Division|52nd Lowland Division]] of the British Army to the First Canadian Army.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 56"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 56.&lt;/ref&gt; The 52nd division, recruited in the Lowlands of Scotland, was a mountain division, requiring men with unusual strength and stamina in order to fight in the mountains, making it into something of an elite division within the British Army.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 56"/&gt; Simonds greatly appreciated having the Lowlanders under his command and told Major-General [[Edmund Hakewill-Smith]] that the 52nd was to play the decisive role in taking Walcheren island.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 56"/&gt; As such, Simonds ordered Hakewill-Smith to start preparing an amphibious operation as Simonds planned to land the 52nd division on Walcheren at the same time the Canadians attacked the island.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 56"/&gt;

Between October 23 and November 5, 1944, the U.S. [[104th Infantry Division]] experienced its first battle while attached to the [[British I Corps]]. The division succeeded in pushing through the central portion of [[North Brabant]] against resistance from German snipers and artillery.

Meanwhile, Simonds concentrated forces at the neck of the South Beveland peninsula. On 17 October, Major-General Harry Forster announced 4th Division would attack on 20 October to take [[Bergen op Zoom]].&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 46"/&gt; The offensive began in the early morning of October 20 and was led by the Argyll and Lake Superior regiments.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 46"/&gt; On October 22, the [[The Lincoln and Welland Regiment|Lincoln and Welland Regiment]], known as the "Lincs" in the Canadian Army, and [[The Algonquin Regiment]] took Esschen in a surprise attack.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 46"/&gt; On October 23, the German 85th Division launched a counterattack led by some [[Self-propelled gun|self-propelled (SP) guns]].&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 47"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 47&lt;/ref&gt; The [[M4 Sherman|Sherman tanks]] of the [[Governor General's Foot Guards|Governor-General's Foot Guards]] and the [[The Lake Superior Scottish Regiment|Lake Superior Regiments]] were decimated by the German SP guns.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 47"/&gt; For the next days, there occurred what the 85th Division's war diary called "extremely violent fighting".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 47"/&gt; The war diary of the Canadian [[The Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders of Canada (Princess Louise's)|Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders]] spoke of "nightmarish fighting" at [[Wouwsche Plantage]].&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 52&lt;/ref&gt; The fighting at Wouwsche Plantage was considered so important that Field Marshal Montgomery arrived at the headquarters of the 4th Canadian Division to press Forster for speed, but Forster protested that the flat ''polder'' country made speed impossible.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 49050&lt;/ref&gt; One company of the [[The Lincoln and Welland Regiment|Lincoln and Welland Regiment]] lost 50% of its men in a single day's fighting, while an advance company of the [[The Algonquin Regiment|Algonquin Regiment]] was cut off and surrounded by the Wehrmacht, requiring desperate fighting to break out.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 49-50&lt;/ref&gt; The Canadian advance towards Bergen op Zoom forced Rundstedt to redeploy the elite [[6th Parachute Division (Germany)|6th Parachute Regiment]], which until then had been blocking the 2nd Canadian Division on the Beveland isthmus to the defense of Bergen op Zoom.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 56"/&gt;

By October 24, Allied lines were pushed out further from the neck of the peninsula, ensuring German counterattacks would not cut off the 2nd Canadian Division, by then moving west along it towards Walcheren island. On October 26, 1944, Field Marshal von Rundstedt ordered to "forestall an enemy breakthrough and economize with our strength, I hereby authorize Fifteenth Army to withdraw to the general line Bergen op Zoom/[[Roosendaal]]/[[Breda]]/[[Dongen]]/west of [['s-Hertogenbosch]]".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 50"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 50&lt;/ref&gt; The [[4th Canadian Armoured Division]] moved north from the Leopold Canal and took Bergen op Zoom. The [[South Alberta Regiment]] and [[The Lincoln and Welland Regiment]], which liberated Bergen op Zoom, reported "the reception of the people of Bergen Op Zoom was as enthusiastic and wild as any yet seen".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 50" /&gt;

Dempsey had been ordered by Montgomery to use the 12th Corps to cut off the retreat of the German 15th Army.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 130.&lt;/ref&gt; The 1st Polish Division had been assigned a defensive role and was joined on 23 October by the U.S. [[Timberwolf Division|104th "Timberwolf" Division]] commanded by [[Terry de la Mesa Allen Sr.|General Terry Allen]].&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 131.&lt;/ref&gt;  Model argued that recently arrived 47th Panzer corps of two divisions making up 24,000 men and 40 tanks go on the offensive to distract the Allies, a request Rundstedt approved.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 130" /&gt; On 27 October, the Germans attacked the U.S. 7th Armored Division, which was holding the flanks for the Canadians with much success, advancing 6 miles.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 130" /&gt; Through Rundstedt believed that Model's offensive had achieved nothing and ordered his men back, in fact Model's "spoiling attack" had caused the British 15th Infantry Division to be pulled out of Tilburg to reinforce the 7th Division, slowing Dempsey's advance.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 130" /&gt; As the Germans had attacked, the American Timberwolf Division went on the offensive on 27 October with the aim of taking Zundert.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 131" /&gt; The disjointed attacks which Montgomery ordered with the 1st Polish Division and 104th heading towards Breda allowed the German 15th Army to escape once again.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 131" /&gt;

On 29 October, the 4th Canadian Armored Division went on the offensive, with the Algonquin Regiment trying to encircle German position at Steenbergen just north of Bergen Op Zoom while the Governor-General's Foot Guards heading towards Steenbergen.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 131" /&gt; The elite German 6th Parachute Regiment put stiff resistance, using ''panzerfausts'' (bazookas) and SP guns to knock out the Canadian tanks, but withdrew into Steenbergen when the Foot Guards threatened to cut off their line of retreat.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 131" /&gt; The war diary of the Canadian 4th Armored Division sarcastically described the 6th Parachute Regiment as "...under the command of Lt. Col von der Heydt and are of a better quality than most of the master race we have so far encountered. They worship their leader who is reported to have knocked out four of our tanks with a German bazooka...".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 131" /&gt; On 31 October, the Algonquin Regiment and the Grenadier Guards attacked the village of Welberg just outside of Steenbergen, which was so fiercely defended by the 6th Parachute Regiment that ultimately the almost entire 4th Division had to be committed to take Welberg over three days of fighting.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 131" /&gt; On 7 November, Rundstedt, having pulled out most of the 15th Army, ordered German forces to move north of the Maas River in order to form a stronger defensive line.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 131" /&gt;

===Operation Switchback===
The second main operation, Operation Switchback, opened with fierce fighting to reduce the [[Breskens Pocket]]. Here, the [[3rd Canadian Infantry Division|Canadian 3rd Infantry Division]] encountered tenacious German resistance as it fought to cross the Leopold Canal.&lt;ref&gt;''In the Shadow of Arnhem'' - Ken Tout - 2003 (Paperback 2009, {{ISBN|9780752451947}})&lt;/ref&gt; An earlier failed attempt by the Canadian 4th Armoured Division at [[Battle of Moerbrugge|Moerbrugge]] had demonstrated the challenge they faced. In addition to the formidable German defences on both the Leopold Canal and the Schipdonk Canal, much of the approach area was flooded.

The Breskens pocket was held by the 64th Division commanded by General Knut Eberding, an infantryman with extensive experience on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] who was regarded as an expert in defensive warfare.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 78"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 78.&lt;/ref&gt; When the 15th Army had retreated from the Pas de Calais region of France across the Low Countries in September 1944, an enormous number of guns and ammunition ended up in the Breskens Pocket, including one hundred [[2 cm Flak 30/38/Flakvierling|20 mm anti-aircraft guns]]. They were used by the Wehrmacht as a sort of "super-heavy [[machine gun]]" and were much dreaded by the Canadian infantry. 20-mm guns could shred a man to pieces within seconds.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 78" /&gt; Besides the 20-mm guns, the 64th Division had 23 of the famous [[8.8 cm Flak 18/36/37/41|88 mm flak guns]], known for their power to destroy an Allied [[tank]] with a single direct hit, together with 455 light machine guns and 97 mortars.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 78" /&gt;

While Montgomery focused on Operation Market Garden in September 1944, Eberding used three weeks of quiet to have his men dig in. He later expressed amazement about the Allied air forces hardly ever bombing the Breskens Pocket in September, allowing his men to build defensive works with barely an effort to stop them.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 78" /&gt; The flat, swampy ''polder'' country made the Breskens Pocket into an "island", as much of the ground was impassable with only a few "land bridges" connecting the area to the mainland. The Wehrmacht had blown up [[Levee|dykes]] to flood much of the ground so that the Canadians could only advance along the raised country roads.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 78" /&gt; Eberding reported that the ''polder'' country was "a maze of ditches, [[River engineering|canalized rivers]] and commercial canals, often above the level of the surrounding countryside...which made military maneuver almost impossible except on the narrow roads built on top of the [[Levee|dykes]]. Each of these roadways were carefully registered for both artillery and mortar fire".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 78" /&gt;

It was decided that the best place for an assault would be immediately east of where the two canals divided: a narrow strip of dry ground, only a few hundred metres wide at its base beyond the Leopold Canal (described as a long triangle with its base on the [[Maldegem]]-[[Aardenburg]] road and its apex near the village of Moershoofd some {{convert|5|km|mi|abbr=on}} east). Despite the fact that the Ultra intelligence provided by [[Bletchley Park]] had revealed that the 64th Division was digging in for a hard fight and that Eberding had ordered a fight to the death, Canadian military intelligence underestimated the size of the German forces by 100%. They expected Eberding to retreat to Walcheren island once the 3rd Canadian division started to advance.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 79"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 79.&lt;/ref&gt; However, Simonds appreciated the problems imposed by the polder country and the Germans concentrating their forces at the few "land bridges". He planned to use [[amphibious vehicle]]s known as "[[Landing Vehicle Tracked|Buffalos]]" to travel across the flooded countryside to outflank the German forces.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 79" /&gt; Simonds planned to strike both at the Leopold canal and at the rear of the Breskens Pocket via an amphibious landing at the [[Braakman]] inlet.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 79" /&gt;

A two-pronged assault commenced. The Canadian 3rd Division's [[7th Canadian Infantry Brigade|7th Brigade]] made the initial assault across the Leopold Canal, while the [[9th Canadian Infantry Brigade|9th Brigade]] mounted the amphibious attack from the northern (coastal) side of the pocket. The 7th Brigade was known as the "Western Brigade" in the Canadian Army as its three regiments were all from western Canada with the [[Canadian-Scottish regiment|Canadian Scottish Regiment]] coming from [[Victoria, British Columbia|Victoria]] area, the [[Regina Rifles]] from the [[Regina, Saskatchewan|Regina]] area, and the [[Royal Winnipeg Rifles]] from the [[Winnipeg]] area, while the 9th Brigade was known as the "Highland brigade" as its three regiments were all [[Scottish regiment|Highland regiments]] with two coming from [[Ontario]] and another from [[Nova Scotia]]. The [[The North Shore (New Brunswick) Regiment|North Shore Regiment]] made a diversionary attack across the Leopold Canal, while the Regina Rifles regiment and the Canadian Scottish Regiment made the main assault.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 79" /&gt; The [[The Royal Montreal Regiment|Royal Montreal Regiment]], which had never seen action yet, were pressing to get into the fight, and as such, the B company of the Regina Rifles, nicknamed the "Johns", agreed to step aside so one company of the Royal Montreal Regiment could take their place.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 82-83.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Field hospital, Walcheren Dyke (11874872204).jpg|thumb|A Canadian field hospital on a Walcheran Dyke]]

The 9th Highland Brigade, however, was unable to land at the same time as expected, owing to their unfamiliarity with amphibious vehicles.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 80.&lt;/ref&gt; The assault began on October 6, supported by extensive artillery and Canadian-built Wasp [[Universal Carrier]]s, equipped with [[flamethrower]]s. The 7th Brigade was supposed to be on their own for 40 hours, but instead faced 68 hours of the Germans using everything they had to try the stop the Canadians from crossing the Leopold canal.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 82"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 82.&lt;/ref&gt;

Simonds had planned to take the Wehrmacht by surprise by avoiding a preliminary bombardment and instead having the Wasps incinerate the German defenders with a "barrage of flame".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 82" /&gt; The Wasps launched their barrage of flames across the Leopold Canal, allowing the 7th Brigade troops to scramble up over the steep banks and launch their assault boats. However, the Germans had dug in well and many escaped the flamethrowers. One company of the Royal Montreal Regiment was almost destroyed on the edge of the Leopold canal. The Germans brought down heavy machine gun and mortar fire and only a few of the Montrealers made it to the other side.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 83&lt;/ref&gt; The A company of the Regina Rifles did not attempt to cross the canal because the volume of machine gun fire convinced the experienced "Johns" that it was too dangerous to try to cross the canal in daylight.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 83"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 83.&lt;/ref&gt; The Royal Montreal Regiment company held their precious "bridgehead" for several hours before being joined by the "Johns" three hours later when D company of the Regina Rifles crossed the canal. They were joined by C and A companies in the evening.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 83"/&gt; By that time, most of the men of B company of the Royal Montreal Regiment, who had been anxious to get into action, were dead.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 83"/&gt; By contrast, the "barrage of flame" worked as expected for the Canadian Scottish Regiment, who were able to cross the Leopold canal without much opposition and put up a [[Kapok tree|kapok]] footbridge&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |chapterurl=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=QSjfrnESw7kC&amp;pg=PA167&amp;lpg=PA167&amp;dq=kapok+footbridge&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=LJWrJ7_Tvt&amp;sig=ACfU3U1lRgm94sutdUx9xk1xDkluJo1GGg&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiupIDHg4vpAhVHe8AKHV-XClgQ6AEwC3oECAwQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=kapok%20footbridge&amp;f=false |chapter=Kapok footbridge |page=167 |title=Engineer Field Manual |volume=II:I |editor=[[Chief of Engineers]] |date=1932 |publisher=[[United States Government Printing Office]]}}&lt;/ref&gt; within the first hour of crossing the canal.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 83"/&gt;

Two precarious, separate footholds were established, but the enemy recovered from the shock of the flamethrowers and counter-attacked, though the Germans were unable to move the Canadians from their vulnerable bridgeheads. Brigadier J.C. Spraggree became worried that the Regina Rifles might be destroyed by the Germans' ferocious defense, leading him to order his reserve, the [[Royal Winnipeg Rifles]], to cross over the Canadian Scottish Regiment's bridgehead and link up with the Regina Rifles.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 83"/&gt; The polderland, which limited avenues of advance, proved to be a major difficulty as the Germans concentrated their fire along the few raised roads.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 83"/&gt; At the same time, the Regina Rifles came under heavy counterattacks and were barely hanging on.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 83"/&gt; Canadian losses were so heavy that a squadron of tankmen from the 17th Hussars Regiment were given rifles and sent to fight as infantrymen.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 83"/&gt; The Canadian historians' Terry Copp and Robert Vogel wrote the fighting "...{{nbsp}}was at close quarter and of such ferocity that veterans insist that it was worse than the blackest days of Normandy".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 83"/&gt; The war diary of the Royal Winnipeg Rifles reported: "Heavy casualties were suffered by both sides and the ground was littered with both German and Royal Winnipeg Rifle dead".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 83"/&gt; The war diary of the Canadian Scottish regiment sardonically noted: "The grim fighting was such that Piats and Bazookas were used to blow down walls of houses where resistance was worst. These anti-tank weapons are quite handy little house-breakers!"&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 90.&lt;/ref&gt; By October 9, the gap between the bridgeheads was closed, and by early morning on October 12 a position had been gained across the Aardenburg road.

October 10, 11, and 12 were days of intense struggle while the men of the 7th Brigade with the Royal Winnipeg Rifles took, lost and then retook a group of houses known as Graaf Jan and the Regina Rifles found themselves pinned down by a group of well dug-in pillboxes that seemed to be resilient to artillery.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 88.&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans had ample artillery, together with an immense number of artillery shells, and brought down heavy fire on any Canadian advance.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 84"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 84.&lt;/ref&gt; Making the fighting even more difficult was the heavy rain that started the day after the crossing of the Leopold canal, with a post-operation report on Operation Switchback stating: "In places the bridgehead was little bigger than the northern canal bank. Even protection was slight: slit trenches rapidly filled with water and had to be dug out many times a day".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 84"/&gt; The Canadians could not advance beyond their bridgehead on the Leopold canal, but Eberding, not content with stopping the Canadians, decided to "annihilate" the 7th Brigade by launching a series of counter-attacks that cost the German 64th Division dearly, as Canadian artillerymen were killing German infantrymen as proficiently as German artillerymen were killing Canadians.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 84"/&gt; Simonds' plan failed when the 9th Brigade did not land at the same time as the 7th Brigade crossed the Leopold Canal and the 64th Division decisively stopped the advance of the 7th Brigade. In the end, only Eberding's determination to wipe out the 7th Brigade allowed Simonds' plan to work.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 84"/&gt; In terms of numbers lost as a percentage of those engaged, the battle of the Leopold Canal was one of the bloodiest battles for Canada in World War II, with 533 killed and another 70 men breaking down due to battle exhaustion.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 84"/&gt; Copp and Vogel wrote: "One in every two men who crossed the Leopold became a casualty!"&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 84"/&gt; The men who broke down under battle curled up in a fetal position and refused to move, speak, eat or drink as their spirits had been broken by the stress of the fighting. On 14 October 1944, Eberding, a man deeply committed to National Socialism, ordered that German soldiers who retreated without orders were to be regarded as [[Desertion|deserters]] and [[Summary execution|summarily executed]], and "...{{nbsp}}where the names of deserters are ascertained their names will be made known to the civilian population at home and their next of kin will be looked upon as enemies of the German people".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 102"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 102.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Canadian 9th Brigade conducted an amphibious operation with the aid of [[Terrapin (amphibious vehicle)|Terrapin]] (the first use of the vehicle in Europe) and Buffalo amphibious vehicles, crewed by the British 5th Assault Regiment of the [[Royal Engineers]].&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 92"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 92.&lt;/ref&gt; The brigade planned to cross the mouth of the Braakman Inlet in these vehicles and to land in the vicinity of [[Hoofdplaat]], a tiny hamlet in the rear or coastal side of the pocket, thus exerting pressure from two directions at once. An "after action" report described the scene on the Terneuzen Canal: "As darkness fell only tail lights showed. The locks at Sas Van Gent proved difficult to negotiate, for the Buffaloes were not easily steered when moving slowly. Their aeroplane engines created a sound so like the roar of aircraft that over Flushing the anti-aircraft guns fired sporadically...Because of the damage to the locks near the ferry (at [[Terneuzen|Neuzen]]) it was necessary to cut ramps in the bank and by-pass the obstacle. Not only was this a slow progress, but many craft were damaged. The decision was therefore taken to postpone the operation for 24 hours".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 92"/&gt; The delay allowed for Admiral Ramsay to volunteer the services of Lieutenant-Commander R.D. Franks of the Royal Navy to serve as a pilot, guiding the Buffaloes expertly down the river Scheldt without the Germans noticing.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 92"/&gt; Franks reported: "It was nearly ideal night, calm and quiet with a half moon behind a light cloud, but a bit of haze which restricted visibility to a mile at most. We were quite invisible from the north shore of the Scheldt, where all was quiet...Our touchdown was planned to be on either side of a [[groyne]]...we were able to identify it and then lie off flicking our lamps to guide the [[Landing Vehicle Tracked|LVT]]'s in. They deployed and thundered past us...I could see through my binoculars the infantry disembark on dry land and move off".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 92"/&gt;

In spite of difficulties in maneuvering vehicles through the canals and the resulting 24-hour delay, the Germans were taken by surprise and a bridgehead was established. The [[The Nova Scotia Highlanders (North)|North Nova Scotia Highland regiment]] landed with no resistance and woke nine sleeping German soldiers at their dug-out, taking them prisoner.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 92"/&gt; The [[Highland Light Infantry of Canada|Highland Light Infantry]] regiment's major problem at the landing site was not the Wehrmacht, but mud.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 92"/&gt; After the initial landing, the [[Queen's Own Cameron Highlanders|Cameron Highlanders]] and the [[Stormont, Dundas and Glengarry Highlanders|Stormont, Dundas and Glengary Highlanders]] were landed by Franks.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 92"/&gt; Once again, the Germans recovered quickly and counter-attacked with ferocity; however, they were slowly forced back. Upon hearing of the landing at the Braakman Inlet, Field Marshal Model reacted promptly, telling Hitler: "Today, the enemy launched a decision-seeking attack on the Breskens bridgehead".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 94"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 94.&lt;/ref&gt; Living up to his reputation as the "Führer's Fireman", Model ordered Eberding to immediately "annihilate" the Highland Brigade.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 94"/&gt;

Starting on daybreak on October 10, the Highland Brigade came under counter-attack, with the Stormont, Dundas and Glengary Highland regiment, known as the "Glens" in the Canadian Army, spending two days fighting for the village of [[Hoofdplaat]] with a loss of 17 dead and 44 wounded.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 92"/&gt; The North Nova Scotia Highlanders took three days to take the village of [[Driewegen, Terneuzen|Driewegen]], with the regimental war diary reporting: "The artillery is kept busy and this dyke to dyke fighting is very different to what we have been doing. It appears the enemy are a much better type than we have been running into lately".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 92"/&gt; The Canadian Army was known for the quality of its artillery, which took a heavy toll on the German counter-attacks by day, with the war diary of [[15th Field Artillery Regiment (Canada)|15th Field Regiment]] for 12 October reading: "Today we were the busiest we have been since Cormelles and Falaise pocket days".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 94"/&gt; The Germans' nightly attacks enjoyed more success, with the Highland Light Infantry losing and then retaking the village of [[Biervliet]] during a confusing night battle.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 94"/&gt; Canadian Major-General [[Daniel Spry]] of the 3rd Division changed the original plan to commit the 8th Brigade in support of the 7th Brigade, and instead sent the 8th Brigade to link up with the 4th Division and then come to the support of the 9th Brigade.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 94-96.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Map - Battle of the Scheldt (Breskens pocket).jpg|thumb|Map of the Breskens Pocket]]

The [[10th Canadian Infantry Brigade|Canadian 10th Brigade]] of the 4th Armoured Division crossed the Leopold Canal and advanced at Isabella Polder. Then the 3rd Division's [[8th Canadian Infantry Brigade|8th Brigade]] was called to move south from the coastal side of the pocket. This opened up a land-based supply route into the pocket. Eberding used his reserves in his counter-attacks and reported to the [[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]] that some units of the 64th Division had "been reduced to one third".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 102"/&gt; Between October 10 and 15, the 64th Division staged a "fighting retreat", as Eberding called it, to new pocket designed to shorten his lines, since so many of his units were now under-strength.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 102"/&gt; The Canadian Scottish Regiment found the village of [[Eede]] empty and abandoned, entered the village and promptly came under heavy artillery bombardment.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 102"/&gt; The Queen's Own Rifles regiment, leading the advance of the 8th Brigade, found the village of [[Ijzendijke|IJzendijke]] "well defended" on October 15, but abandoned the next day.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 102"/&gt; The Highland Light Infantry and the "Glens" broke through the main German line, but General Spry, unaware of this, ordered a withdrawal, in order to concentrate greater forces.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 102=1-3.&lt;/ref&gt;

The German officers explained away their retreat by claiming they were being overwhelmed by tanks, but in fact there were only four, belonging to the [[The British Columbia Regiment (Duke of Connaught's Own)|British Columbia Regiment]], operating north of the Leopold canal.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 104"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 104&lt;/ref&gt; The presumed tanks were actually the [[M10 tank destroyer|M10 self-propelled anti-tank guns]] of the 3rd Canadian Anti-Tank Regiment which provided fire support to the Canadian infantry.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 104"/&gt; Joining the Canadians on October 20 were the [[157th (Highland Light Infantry) Brigade|157th Highland Light Infantry Brigade]] of the 52nd Division, which allowed Spry to group the three brigades of the 3rd Division for the final push.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 104.&lt;/ref&gt;

From the summer of 1944 the Canadian Army experienced a major shortage of infantrymen, owing to policies of Prime Minister [[William Lyon Mackenzie King|William Lyon Mackenzie-King]]. In order to defeat [[Maurice Duplessis]], the ''Union Nationale'' premier of Quebec who called a snap election in 1939 to seek a mandate to oppose the war, Mackenzie-King had promised that only volunteers would be sent to fight overseas and that there would be no overseas conscription. With only so many Canadians willing to volunteer, especially as infantry, the Canadian Army ran seriously short of infantrymen, as their losses were not compensated by replacements.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 106"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 106.&lt;/ref&gt; In planning the final push, Spry favored a cautious, methodical approach, emphasizing firepower that was designed to save as many of the lives of his men as possible.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 104=106.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 3rd Division fought additional actions to clear German troops from the towns of [[Breskens]], [[Oostburg]], [[Zuidzande]], and [[Cadzand]], as well as the coastal fortress Fort Frederik Hendrik. When advancing, the Canadians proceeded very slowly and used massive firepower via air strikes and artillery bombardments when faced with opposition.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 106" /&gt; The shortage of infantry replacements meant that Canadian officers were loath to engage in operations that might lead to heavy losses.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 106" /&gt; On October 24, Field Marshal Montgomery arrived at the headquarters of the 3rd Division. Despite the fact that Montgomery had chosen to fight the Battle of Arnhem instead of clearing the Scheldt in September 1944, thus having allowed the Germans to dig in, he criticized the 3rd Canadian Division for its slow advance, saying the Breskens Pocket should have been cleared weeks ago and calling the Canadian officers cowards for their unwillingness to take heavy losses.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 106" /&gt; As a result, the 157th Brigade was withdrawn as a punishment and the 3rd Division was ordered to press on with "all speed".&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 106-108.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the fact that the Canadians could not afford heavy losses, the 3rd Division began a period of "intense combat" to clear out the Breskens Pocket.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 108"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 108.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Régiment de la Chaudière]] attacked the town of Oostburg on October 24, losing an entire company, but since they had been ordered to take Oostburg at "any price", the "Chads" dug in to hold their ground while the Queen's Own Rifles came to their aid.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 108" /&gt; On October 25, the Queen's Own Rifles took Oostburg after what its war diary called "a wild bayonet charge" amid "fairly heavy" casualties.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 108" /&gt; Lieutenant Boos of the A company of the Queen's Own Rifles was awarded the Military Cross for leading what should have been a suicidal bayonet charge on the Oostburg town gates but ended with him and his men taking the gates.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 108" /&gt; Despite tenacious German opposition, inspired at least in part by Eberding's policy of executing soldiers who retreated without orders, the Canadians pushed the Germans back steadily.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 110"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 110.&lt;/ref&gt; In the last days of the battle, German morale declined and the number of executions of "deserters" increased as many German soldiers wished to surrender rather than die in what was clearly a lost battle.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 110" /&gt; The Régiment de la Chaudière, which could ill-afford the losses, seized a bridgehead on the ''Afleidingskanaal van de Lije'' (Derivation Canal of the Lys), over which the engineers built a bridge.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 110" /&gt;

On November 1, the North Nova Scotia Highlanders stormed a pillbox and captured Eberding, who, despite his own orders to fight to the death for the Führer, surrendered without firing a shot.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 111.&lt;/ref&gt; After being taken prisoner, Eberding met Spry and accused him of not being aggressive enough in taking advantage of "opportunities", saying any German general would have moved far more swiftly. Spry responded that having lost about 700 men killed in two "aggressive" operations within five days, he preferred a methodical advance that preserved the lives of his men.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 96.&lt;/ref&gt; Eberding replied that this showed "weakness" on the side of the Canadians, noting that Wehrmacht generals were only concerned with winning and never let concern with casualties interfere with the pursuit of victory.

Operation Switchback ended on November 3, when the Canadian 1st Army liberated the Belgian towns of [[Knokke]] and [[Zeebrugge]], officially closing the Breskens Pocket and eliminating all German forces south of the Scheldt.&lt;ref group="note"&gt;Montgomery also bestowed the nickname "Water Rats" on the [[3rd Canadian Infantry Division]], a play on the [[Desert Rats]] title the 7th Armoured Division had earned in the Western Desert. General [[Harry Crerar]] reportedly hated the term, though it was meant as a tribute to their success in [[amphibious operation]]s in Normandy and the Scheldt. (Granatstein, Jack. ''The Generals: Canadian Senior Commanders in the Second World War''.)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Operation Vitality===
[[File:2ndcanadianinscheldt.jpg|thumb|Troops of the Royal Hamilton Light Infantry, (2nd Canadian Infantry Division), in [[C15TA Armoured Truck|C15TA trucks]] move towards South Beveland during the Battle of the Scheldt]]
On the afternoon of October 22, Major-General Foulkes, as acting commander of the 2nd Canadian Corps told the 2nd Canadian Division that the start of Operation Vitality, the operation to take the South Beveland peninsula, had been pushed forward by two days by the "express orders from Field Marshal Montgomery who had placed this operation at first priority for the British and Canadian forces in this area".&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 57-58.&lt;/ref&gt; Major Ross Ellis of [[The Calgary Highlanders]] told Foulkes that the men were tired after the hard fighting earlier in October, only to be informed that the operation would go through.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 58"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 58.&lt;/ref&gt; Morale in the 2nd Division was poor, with only the Royal Regiment of Canada, the [[The Essex Scottish Regiment|Essex Scottish Regiment]], the Cameron Highland Regiment and the Calgary Highlanders being anything close to assembling four rifle companies.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 58"/&gt; The attack was to be led by the 6th Brigade consisting of the Cameron Highlanders, the battered [[The South Saskatchewan Regiment|South Saskatchewan Regiment]] and the even more battered [[Fusiliers Mont-Royal]], who despite being very under-strength were assigned to lead the attack on the centre.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 58"/&gt; This third major operation opened on October 24, when the [[2nd Canadian Infantry Division]] began its advance down the South Beveland peninsula. The Canadians hoped to advance rapidly, bypassing opposition and seizing bridgeheads over the ''Kanaal door Zuid-Beveland'' [[Canal through Zuid-Beveland|(Canal through South Beveland)]], but they too were slowed by mines, mud and strong enemy defenses.

The war diary of the Fusiliers Mont-Royal reports simply that the regiment had taken "heavy casualties", the Cameron Highlanders reported "stiff opposition" from the 6th Parachute Regiment of the [[Luftwaffe]], while the South Saskatchewan Regiment reported: "The county over which we had come was not the kind you dream about to make an attack in as it was partly wooded, partly open, and it had many buildings, ditches, etc".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 58"/&gt; Joining the 6th Brigade later that day were the 5th Brigade, with the Calgary Highlanders leading the assault and reporting the "remnants" of two platoons that had advanced beyond the dyke to be joined by the Black Watch when night fell.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 58"/&gt; The Royal Regiment had seized its start-line during the night and in the early morning was joined by the Essex Scottish Regiment and the Fort Garry Horse Regiment to make a slow advance supported by heavy artillery fire.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 58-59.&lt;/ref&gt; On October 25, the Essex Scottish Regiment reported that 120 Germans had surrendered and that the "tough shell of defences at the narrowest point of the peninsula was broken".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 59"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 59.&lt;/ref&gt; On October 26, the [[70th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|70th Infantry Division]]'s commander General Wilhelm Daser reported to Rundstedt that the situation was untenable, and that retreat was unavoidable.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 58"/&gt;

An [[Amphibious warfare|amphibious attack]] was made across the Western Scheldt by the [[British 52nd (Lowland) Division]] to get in behind the German's Canal through South Beveland defensive positions. The 156th West Scottish Brigade described the Dutch countryside as "extremely difficult", but also noted that German morale was poor, stating that they had expected the Wehrmacht to fight harder and that most of their casualties were coming from mines and booby-traps.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 59"/&gt; With the formidable German defence outflanked, the [[6th Canadian Infantry Brigade|Canadian 6th Infantry Brigade]] began a frontal attack in assault boats. The engineers were able to bridge the canal on the main road.

With the canal line gone, the German defense crumbled and South Beveland was cleared. The third phase of the Battle of the Scheldt was now complete. Daser ordered his men to retreat and make a stand on "Fortress Walcheren".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 59"/&gt;

===Operation Infatuate===&lt;!-- This section is linked from [[Walcheren]] --&gt;
{{Main|Operation Infatuate}}
[[File:Walcheren2.gif|thumb|Map of troops at Walcheren Island]]
As the fourth phase of the battle opened, only the island of [[Walcheren]] at the mouth of the Scheldt remained in German hands. The island's defenses were extremely strong: heavy coastal [[Artillery battery|batteries]] on the western and southern coasts defended both the island and the western Scheldt estuary, and the coastline had been strongly [[Fortification|fortified]] against amphibious assaults. Furthermore, a landward-facing defensive perimeter had been built around the town of [[Vlissingen|Flushing]] (Dutch: ''Vlissingen)'' to defend its port facilities, should an Allied landing on Walcheren succeed. The only land approach was the [[Sloedam]], a long, narrow causeway from South Beveland, little more than a raised two-lane road. To complicate matters, the flats that surrounded this causeway were too saturated with sea water for movement on foot, but had too little water for an assault in storm boats.

==== Inundation of Walcheren ====
{{Main|Inundation of Walcheren}}
To hamper German defense, Walcheren island's dykes were breached by attacks from [[RAF Bomber Command]]. Due to the high risks for the local population, the bombings were sanctioned at the highest level and preceded by [[Leaflet (information)|leafleting]] to warn the island's inhabitants. The first bombing was on October 3 at [[Westkapelle (Netherlands)|Westkapelle]], on the western shore of the island. The Westkapelle dyke was attacked by 240 heavy bombers, resulting in a large gap that allowed the seawater to enter. This flooded the central part of the island, allowing the use of amphibious vehicles and forcing the German defenders onto the high ground surrounding the island and in the towns. The bombing at Westkapelle came with severe loss of life, with 180 civilian deaths resulting from the bombardment and the resulting flooding. Attacks on other dykes had to ensure that the flooding could not be contained. On October 7, dykes in the south were bombed, west and east of Flushing. Finally, on October 11, northern dykes at [[Veere]] became a target. Bombing against the island defenses was hampered by bad weather and requirements for attacks on Germany. {{sfn|Stacey|1960|pp=376–377}}

The island was then attacked from three directions: across the Sloedam causeway from the east, across the Scheldt from the south, and by sea from the west.

==== Battle of Walcheren Causeway ====
{{Main|Battle of Walcheren Causeway}}
[[File:Commandos landing near Flushing.jpg|thumb|Royal Marines wade ashore near Vlissingen to complete the occupation of Walcheren on November 1, 1944.]]
The 2nd Canadian Infantry Division attacked the Sloedam causeway on October 31. Post-war controversy exists around the claim that there was a "race" within the 2nd Division for the first regiment to take the causeway to Walcheren island, implying that the failure to take the causeway on October 31 was due to reckless determination to win the "race".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 68"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 68.&lt;/ref&gt; Colonel [[Charles Perry Stacey|C.P. Stacey]] wrote about the "race" in the official history of the Canadian Army, a charge that was vehemently disputed by Copp and Vogel in the ''Maple Leaf Route''.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 68"/&gt;

The 4th Brigade of the 2nd Division had advanced rapidly up to the causeway, which led to Brigadier Keefler giving orders to take the causeway while the task of taking the Beveland end of the causeway had been given to the 52nd Division.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 68-69.&lt;/ref&gt; The Royal Regiment took the eastern end of the causeway in a night attack.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 70"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 70.&lt;/ref&gt; As there seemed an actual chance of taking the entire causeway, orders were sent to the 5th Brigade of the 2nd Division to launch an attack, to be led by the "jinxed" Black Watch who were to advance down the causeway while the Calgary Highlanders and Le Régiment de Maisonneuve were to advance by boat.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 70"/&gt; An initial attack by the Black Watch was rebuffed while it discovered the waters in the channel were too shallow for the 2nd Division to cross it, leaving a company of the Black Watch stranded on the causeway under heavy German attack.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 70"/&gt; The Calgary Highlanders then sent a company over which was also stopped halfway across the causeway.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 70"/&gt; During a second attack on the morning of November 1, the Highlanders managed to gain a precarious foothold. A day of fighting followed and then the Highlanders were relieved by the Régiment de Maisonneuve, who struggled to maintain the bridgehead.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 70"/&gt; The Régiment de Maisonneuve finally did secure the bridgehead, only to find that it was useless for an advance, since the German defenses in the ''polderland'' were too entrenched for an advance to be made.&lt;ref&gt;Morton, Desmond ''A Military History of Canada'', Toronto: McClelland &amp; Stewart, 1999 page 221.&lt;/ref&gt;

General Foulkes ordered Major-General Hakewill-Smith to launch the 52nd Division into a frontal attack on Walcheren, which Hakewill-Smith protested strongly.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 70-72.&lt;/ref&gt; The "Maisies" withdrew onto the Causeway on November 2, to be relieved by the 1st Battalion, [[Glasgow Highlanders]] of the 52nd Division. Instead of launching a frontal attack as ordered by Foulkes, Hakewill-Smith outflanked the Germans by landing the Cameronian regiment at the village of [[Nieuwdorp]], two miles south of the causeway, and linked up with the Glasgow Highlanders the next day.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 72"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 72.&lt;/ref&gt; In conjunction with the waterborne attacks, the 52nd continued the advance.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry. ''The Brigade: The 5th Canadian Infantry Brigade in the Second World War'' {{page needed|date=August 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The battle for the causeway had caused the 2nd Division 135 dead in what has become of the most controversial operations of the 2nd Division, with much criticism centering on the decisions of Foulkes.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 72"/&gt; Despite the fact that Lieutenant-General Simonds and Foulkes were both British immigrants to Canada, the two detested one another and Simonds often spoke of his wish to sack Foulkes, believing him to be incompetent.

Because of port shortage, Captain Pugsley of the Royal Navy had to improvise heavily to provide the necessary shipping for the landings on Walcheren island.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 124.&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the refusal of Bomber Command to strike various German fortifications on Walcheren, opening up the Scheldt was regarded as so important that during a meeting on October 31 between Simonds, Foulkes, and Admiral Ramsay, it was decided that the landings on Walcheren were to go ahead.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; Captain Pugsley, aboard the command ship [[HMS Kingsmill (K484)|HMS ''Kingsmill'']], was given the final decision, with orders to cancel the operation if he thought it was too risky.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; At the same time, Simonds ordered two Canadian artillery regiments to concentrate 300 guns on the mainland, to provide fire support for the landings.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB"/&gt; The amphibious landings were conducted in two parts on November 1.

==== Operation Infatuate I ====
Operation Infatuate I consisted mainly of infantry of the [[155th (South Scottish) Brigade|155th Infantry Brigade]] (4th and 5th battalions [[King's Own Scottish Borderers]], 7th/9th battalion, [[Royal Scots]]) and [[No. 4 Commando]], who were ferried across from [[Breskens]] in small landing craft to an assault beach in the south-eastern area of Flushing, codenamed "Uncle" Beach. With the Canadian artillery opening fire, the 4th Commando were carried ashore in twenty [[Landing Craft Assault]]s, to be followed by the King's Own Scottish Borderers regiment who attacked Flushing.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB" /&gt; During the next few days, they engaged in heavy street fighting against the German defenders, destroying much of Flushing.&lt;ref name="ReferenceB" /&gt; The Hotel Britannia, which before the war had catered to British tourists, was the headquarters of the German 1019th Regiment holding Flushing and became the scene of "spectacular fighting" described as "worthy of an action film" when the Royal Scots regiment engaged to take the hotel, which finally fell after three days.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 124-126.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:German Prisoners on Walcheren CL1513.jpg|thumb|German prisoners being marched off on Walcheren]]

==== Operation Infatuate II ====
Operation Infatuate II was the amphibious landing at Westkapelle, also conducted on the morning of November 1. To cross the shallow water required a daylight assault with fire support provided by the Support Squadron Eastern Flank (SSEF) commanded by Commander K.A Sellar, with additional support from the [[battleship]] [[HMS Warspite (03)|HMS ''Warspite'']] and two [[Monitor (warship)|monitors]], [[HMS Erebus (I02)|HMS ''Erebus'']] and [[HMS Roberts (F40)|HMS ''Roberts'']].&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 126"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 126.&lt;/ref&gt; Air support was limited due to weather conditions. With no air support, no spotter aircraft to guide the guns of his ships, and the Germans fully alerted with their coastal artillery already firing at the British ships, Captain Pugsley was faced with the difficult decision to cancel or proceed, and after some deliberation, sent out the message reading "Nelson", which was the code name to land.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 126" /&gt; The radar-guided guns of the German coastal artillery took a heavy toll on the SSEF, which lost 9 ships sunk and another 11 that were so badly damaged that they had to be broken up for scrap as they were beyond repair.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 126" /&gt; After a heavy bombardment by the Royal Navy (a battleship and two monitors, plus a support squadron of landing craft carrying guns), troops of [[4th Special Service Brigade]] (Nos. [[41 Commando|41]], [[47 Commando|47]], and [[48 Commando|48]] [[Royal Marines]] [[Commando]] and [[No. 10 Inter Allied Commando]], consisting mainly of Belgian and Norwegian troops) supported by the [[Hobart's Funnies|specialized armoured vehicles]] (amphibious transports, mine-clearing tanks, bulldozers, etc.) of the [[79th Armoured Division]] were landed on both sides of the gap in the sea dyke, using large landing craft as well as amphibious vehicles to bring men and tanks ashore. The Royal Marines took Westkapelle and [[Domburg]] the next day.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 126-127.&lt;/ref&gt; Anticipating the fall of "Fortress Walcheren", on November 4, Admiral Ramsay ordered that mine-sweepers start the work of removing the German mines from the river Scheldt, a task that was not completed until 28 November.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry pages 127"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 127.&lt;/ref&gt;

Heavy fighting ensued in Domburg &lt;!--Unfortunately, Copp &amp; Vogel, pp-126-127, the source given, is not accessible online, but from the context this can only be Domburg--&gt; as well before the ruins of the town were captured.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 127.&lt;/ref&gt; On 3 November, the Royal Marines had linked with the 52nd Division.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry pages 127" /&gt; Part of the troops moved south-east toward Flushing, while the main force went north-east to clear the northern half of Walcheren (in both cases along the high-lying dune areas, as the center of the island was flooded) and link up with the Canadian troops who had established a bridgehead on the eastern part of the island. Fierce resistance was again offered by some of the German troops defending this area, so that fighting continued until November 7.

On November 6, the island capital [[Middelburg]] fell after a calculated gamble on the Allies' part when the Royal Scots attacked Middelburg with a force of Buffaloes from the rear.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry pages 127" /&gt; Since Middelburg was impossible to reach with tanks, due to the inundations, a force of amphibious [[Landing Vehicle Tracked]] ("Buffaloes") were driven into the town, forcing an end to all German resistance on November 8. General Daser portrayed the Buffaloes as tanks, giving him an excuse to surrender as he was faced with an overwhelming force.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry pages 127" /&gt;

Meanwhile, the Canadian 4th Armoured Division had pushed eastward past [[Bergen-op-Zoom]] to [[Sint Philipsland (island)|Sint Philipsland]] where it sank several German vessels in [[Zijpe]] harbor.

With the approach to [[Antwerp]] clear, the fourth phase of the Battle of the Scheldt was complete. Between 20 and 28 November, Royal Navy minesweepers were brought in to clear the Scheldt estuary of [[naval mine]]s and other underwater obstacles left by the Germans. On November 28, after much-needed repairs of the port facilities, the first convoy entered Antwerp, led by the Canadian-built [[Cargo ship|freighter]] ''[[Fort Cataraqui (ship)|Fort Cataraqui]]''.

==Aftermath==
[[File:The British Army in North-west Europe 1944-45 B12260.jpg|thumb|Canadian vessel [[SS Fort Cataraqui|Fort Cataraqui]] unloads oil at the harbour of Antwerp]]
At the end of the five-week offensive, the Canadian First Army had taken 41,043 German prisoners. Complicated by the waterlogged terrain, the Battle of the Scheldt proved to be a challenging campaign in which significant losses were suffered by the Canadians.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.veterans.gc.ca/eng/remembrance/history/second-world-war/scheldt ''At the end of the five-week offensive, the victorious First Canadian Army had taken 41,043 prisoners, but suffered 12,873 casualties (killed, wounded, or missing), 6,367 of whom were Canadians.'']&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout the Battle of the Scheldt, battle exhaustion was a major problem for the Canadians.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 116"&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 116.&lt;/ref&gt; The 3rd Canadian Division had landed on D-Day on 6 June 1944 and had been fighting more or less continuously since. During the Normandy campaign, the 3rd Canadian Division had taken the heaviest losses of all the divisions in the 21st Army Group, with the 2nd Canadian Division taking the second-heaviest losses.&lt;ref&gt;Morton, Desmond ''A Military History of Canada'', Toronto: McClelland &amp; Stewart, 1999 page 216.&lt;/ref&gt; A psychiatric report from October 1944 stated that 90% of battle exhaustion cases were men who been in action for three months or longer.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 116"/&gt; Men suffering from battle exhaustion would go catatonic and curl up in fetal position, but the report found that after a week of rest, most men would recover enough to speak and move about.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 116"/&gt; According to the report, the principal cause of battle exhaustion "seemed to be futility. The men claimed there was nothing to which to look forward to – no rest, no leave, no enjoyment, no normal life and no escape....The second most prominent cause...seemed to be the insecurity in battle because the condition of the battlefield did not allow for average cover. The third was the fact that they were seeing too much continual death and destruction, loss of friends, etc".&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 116"/&gt; The Canadian government policy of sending only volunteers overseas had caused major shortages of men, especially in the infantry regiments. Canadian units were too under-strength to allow leave, where U.S. and British units could. This stretched the soldiers tremendously.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 pages 116-117.&lt;/ref&gt; A common complaint of soldiers suffering from battle exhaustion was that the Army was to trying to "get blood from a stone", with the under-strength units being pushed relentlessly to keep fighting, without replacements for their losses and no chance to rest.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 116"/&gt;

After the battle, the II Canadian Corps moved to the Nijmegen sector to take over from the 30 British Corps.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 134.&lt;/ref&gt; Although Antwerp was opened to Allied shipping on 28 November, the German 15th Army had delayed the use of Antwerp to the Allies from 4 September to 28 November 1944, which was longer than what Hitler had hoped for, justifying the German decision to hold the river Scheldt.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 134"/&gt; Even before the Battle of the Scheldt, the Canadian Army was aware that it lacked reinforcements to replace its losses, and the losses endured during the fighting help provoke the Conscription Crisis.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 138-139.&lt;/ref&gt; The Canadian Defense Minister, Colonel John Ralston, was forced to report to the prime minister, William Lyon Mackenzie King, that the current policy of only sending volunteers overseas was not sustainable as the losses in the Battle of the Scheldt vastly exceeded the number of volunteers, and conscripts would have to be sent overseas.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 139.&lt;/ref&gt; Copp and Vogel strongly praised Simonds's leadership of the 1st Canadian Army, writing how his operations "were brilliantly planned and sometimes brilliantly executed".&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 137&lt;/ref&gt; Copp and Vogel also defended the Canadians from charges of incompetence and cowardice made by American and British historians stating: "The Canadian Army had, through October, the most difficult and important task of all the Allied armies, it had carried through a series of complex operations to a successful conclusion and it had done this with verve and skill despite the growing manpower shortage now apparent on all the Allied fronts."&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 134&lt;/ref&gt;

After the first ship reached Antwerp on November 28, [[convoy]]s started bringing a steady stream of supplies to the continent, but this actually changed very little. [[Operation Queen]] continued to flounder while the Americans then suffered a major reverse in the [[Battle of the Hurtgen Forest|Hurtgen forest offensive]] by December. The dismal fall weather hindered not only the Canadians in the Battle of Scheldt, but also the operations of 1st U.S Army in the Hurtgen forest, the 3rd U.S Army in Lorraine, and the 9th U.S. Army, the 7th U.S Army and 1st French Army further south.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 136.&lt;/ref&gt; On 5 November 1944, Eisenhower calculated that for the offensives into the western borderlands of Germany to be successful, over the following month, it would require 6 million artillery shells, two million mortar shells, 400 more tanks, 1,500 jeeps, and 150,000 spare tires to replace worn-out ones, none of which was readily available until the Scheldt was cleared.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 136"/&gt; By 15 December, only the 7th U.S. Army had reached the Rhine by taking Strasbourg while the U.S. Third Army had advanced into Germany to run up against one of the strongest sections of the West Wall.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 136"/&gt; At least part of the reason for the failure for the Allied offensives was the shortage of infantry replacements with the Americans coming close to running out of infantry replacements while the British were forced to break up divisions to provide reinforcements.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 136"/&gt; Germany recognized the danger of the Allies having a deep water port and in an attempt to destroy it – or at least disrupt the flow of supplies – the German military fired more [[V-2 rocket]]s at Antwerp than at any other city. Nearly half of the V-2s launched during the war were aimed at Antwerp.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 127.&lt;/ref&gt; The port of Antwerp was so strategically vital that during the [[Battle of the Bulge]], the last major German [[Offensive (military)|offensive]] [[Military campaign|campaign]] on the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]], launched on 16 December 1944, the primary German objective was to retake the city and its port.&lt;ref&gt;Copp, Terry &amp; Vogel, Robert, ''Maple Leaf Route: Scheldt'', Alma: Maple Leaf Route, 1985 page 137.&lt;/ref&gt; Without Antwerp being opened, which allowed 2.5 million tons of supplies to arrive at that port between November 1944 and April 1945, the Allied advance into Germany in 1945 with the American, British, and French armies heading into the ''Reich'' would have been impossible.&lt;ref name="Copp, Terry page 127"/&gt;

===Controversy===
The Battle of the Scheldt has been described by historians as unnecessarily difficult, as it could have been cleared earlier and more easily had the Allies given it a higher priority than Operation Market Garden. American historian [[Charles B. MacDonald]] called the failure to immediately take the Scheldt "[o]ne of the greatest tactical mistakes of the war."&lt;ref&gt;Charles B. MacDonald, ''The Mighty Endeavor; American Armed Forces in the European Theater in World War II,'' (New York, 1969)&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;!--- page number ? ---&gt; Because of the flawed strategic choices made by the Allies in early September 1944, the battle became one of the longest and bloodiest that the Canadian army faced over the course of the Second World War.

The French Channel ports were "resolutely defended" like "fortresses" and Antwerp was the only viable alternative. However, Field Marshal Montgomery ignored [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Admiral Cunningham]], who said that Antwerp would be "as much use as Timbuctoo" unless the approaches were cleared, and Admiral Ramsay, who warned SHAEF and Montgomery that the Germans could block the Scheldt estuary with ease.

The Antwerp city and port fell in early September and were secured by [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX&amp;nbsp;Corps]] under the command of Lieutenant General [[Brian Horrocks]]. Montgomery halted XXX Corps for resupply short of the wide [[Albert Canal]] to the north of the city, which consequently remained in enemy hands.&lt;ref&gt;Neillands. ''The Battle for the Rhine'', p.&amp;nbsp;53.&lt;/ref&gt; Horrocks regretted this after the war, believing that his corps might have advanced another {{convert|100|mi|km}} with the fuel available.&lt;ref&gt;Horrocks. ''A Full Life'', p.&amp;nbsp;205.&lt;/ref&gt; Unknown to the Allies, at that time XXX&amp;nbsp;Corps was opposed by only a single German division.&lt;ref&gt;Warner. ''Horrocks'', p.&amp;nbsp;111.&lt;/ref&gt;

The pause allowed the Germans to regroup around the Scheldt River, and by the time the Allies resumed their advance, General [[Kurt Student]]'s [[1st Parachute Army (Germany)|1st Parachute Army]] had arrived and set up strong defensive positions along the opposite side of the Albert Canal and Scheldt river.&lt;ref&gt;Neillands. ''The Battle for the Rhine'', p.&amp;nbsp;58.&lt;/ref&gt; The task of breaking the strengthened German line, which stretched from Antwerp to the North Sea along the Scheldt River, would fall to the First Canadian Army in the month-long, costly Battle of the Scheldt.&lt;ref&gt;Neillands. ''The Battle for the Rhine'', pp.&amp;nbsp;157–161.&lt;/ref&gt; The Canadians "sustained 12,873 casualties in an operation which could have been achieved at little cost if tackled immediately after the capture of Antwerp. .... This delay was a grave blow to the Allied build-up before winter approached." {{sfn|Beevor|2012|p=634}}

The British historian [[Antony Beevor]] was of opinion that Montgomery, not [[Brian Horrocks|Horrocks]] was to blame for not clearing the approaches, as Montgomery "was not interested in the estuary and thought that the Canadians could clear it later". Allied commanders were looking ahead to "leaping the Rhine...in virtually one bound."{{sfn|Beevor|2015|pp=14–15}} Despite Eisenhower wanting the capture of one major port with its dock facilities intact, Montgomery insisted that the First Canadian Army should clear the German garrisons in Boulogne, Calais and Dunkirk first, although these ports had all suffered demolitions and would not be navigable for some time.{{sfn|Beevor|2015|p=20}} Boulogne ([[Operation Wellhit]]) and Calais ([[Operation Undergo]]) were captured on 22 and 29 September 1944; but Dunkirk was not captured until the end of the war on 9 May 1945 (see [[Siege of Dunkirk (1944–45)|Siege of Dunkirk]]). When the Canadians eventually stopped their assaults on the northern French ports and started on the Scheldt approaches on 2 October, they found that German resistance was far stronger than they had imagined, as the remnants of the Fifteenth Army had had time to escape and reinforce the island of Walcheren and the South Beveland peninsula {{sfn|Beevor|2015|pp=22–23}}

[[Winston Churchill]] claimed in a telegram to [[Jan Smuts]] on October 9 that "As regards Arnhem, I think you have got the position a little out of focus. The battle was a decided victory, but the leading division, asking, quite rightly, for more, was given a chop. I have not been afflicted with any feeling of disappointment over this and am glad our commanders are capable of running this kind of risk." He said that the risks "...{{nbsp}}were justified by the great prize so nearly in our grasp" but acknowledged that "[c]learing the Scheldt Estuary and opening the port of Antwerp had been delayed for the sake of the Arnhem thrust. Thereafter it was given first priority." &lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Churchill | first = Winston | authorlink = Winston Churchill  | title = The Second World War: Triumph and Tragedy |volume=VI | publisher = Cassell |year=1954 | location=London |pages=174–175 |isbn = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist |group=note}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Beevor|2012}}
|last=Beevor |first=Antony |authorlink=Antony Beevor |title=The Second World War |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |year=2012 |location=London |isbn=978-0-297-84497-6 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Beevor|2015}}
|last=Beevor |first=Antony |title=Ardennes 1944: Hitler’s Last Gamble |publisher=Viking |year=2015 |location=New York |isbn=978-0-670-02531-2 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Stacey|1960}}
|first=Colonel C. P. |last=Stacey |authorlink= |author2=Bond, Major C. C. J. |series=Official History of the Canadian Army in the Second World War |volume=III |title=The Victory Campaign: The operations in North-West Europe 1944–1945 |publisher=The Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery Ottawa |year=1960 |url=http://www.cmp-cpm.forces.gc.ca/dhh-dhp/his/docs/Victory_e.pdf |accessdate=2 December 2017 |format=pdf |oclc=606015967}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book| last=Copp| first=Terry| title=Cinderella Army - The Canadians in North-West Europe 1944–1945| publisher=University of Toronto Press| year=2006| isbn=978-0-8020-9522-0}}
* {{cite thesis|degree=M.A.|first=Dirk Marc |last=DeWaard|url=http://scholars.wlu.ca/etd/8/ |title=Luctor et Emergo: The impact of the Second World War on Zeeland|publisher=Wilfrid Laurier University|year=1983}}
* {{cite book| last=Moulton| first=James L.| title=Battle for Antwerp| publisher=Ian Allan| location=London| year=1978| isbn=0711007691}}
* {{cite book| last1=Whitaker| first1=Denis| first2=Shelagh| last2=Whitaker| title=Tug of War: Allied Command &amp; the Story Behind the Battle of the Scheldt| publisher=Beaufort Books| location=New York| year=1984| isbn=0-8253-0257-9| url-access=registration| url=https://archive.org/details/tugofwaralliedco0000whit}}
* {{cite book| last=Zuelhlke| first=Mark| title=Terrible Victory: First Canadian Army and the Scheldt Estuary Campaign, September 13 – November 6, 1944| location=Vancouver| publisher=Douglas &amp; McIntyre| year=2007| isbn=1-55365-227-4}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Battle of the Scheldt}}
* [http://www.wwii.ca/page47.html ''Canadians on the Scheldt''] Photos, battle information, video and more on the Canadian role in the battle.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20041128062538/http://collections.ic.gc.ca/TOHarchive/pages/Scheldt.html ''Testaments of Honor, The Scheldt''] Official digital collection of experiences from World War II.
* [https://www.bbc.co.uk/dna/ww2/A1143442 BBC, ''The Peoples War''].
* [http://www.waramps.ca/video/aaod.html War Amps of Canada] ''Against All Odds'', a documentary by [[Cliff Chadderton]]
* [http://www.civilization.ca/cwm/newspapers/operations/netherlands_e.html Liberation of the Netherlands] at the online Canadian War Museum
* [http://www.calgaryhighlanders.com ''The Calgary Highlanders''] Includes detailed history section with maps and descriptions of key battles such as Hoogerheide, The Coffin, and the storming of Walcheren Causeway.
* [http://www.canadiansoldiers.com/history/campaigns/northwesteurope/scheldt.htm ''Canadiansoldiers.com''] article on the battle, including maps and detailed information on German formations.
* [http://www.naval-history.net/WW2Memoir-Walcheren.htm, Petty Officer Basil Woolf Royal Navy and his account of LCH.269 and the Battle for Walcheren]{{dead link|date=October 2016 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}
* [http://www.soldatenvanoranje.com The contribution of the Nr 2 Dutch Troop, Nr 10 Inter Allied Commando to Infatuate I and Infatuate II.]
* [http://www.lawlerbrown.com Memoirs of Joe Brown of Peebles (Battles at Flushing and Middelburg).]

{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Scheldt, Battle Of The}}
[[Category:Military history of Canada during World War II]]
[[Category:Allied advance from Paris to the Rhine]]
[[Category:History of Antwerp|Battle of the Scheldt]]
[[Category:History of Zeeland|Battle of the Scheldt]]
[[Category:Military history of the Netherlands during World War II]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Belgium]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Norway]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Poland]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944|Battle of the Scheldt]]
[[Category:1944 in Belgium|Battle of the Scheldt]]
[[Category:1944 in the Netherlands|Battle of the Scheldt]]
[[Category:October 1944 events]]
[[Category:November 1944 events]]</text><sha1>n6g3vy9zpv210vqk7bx4mkwpkih1h4n</sha1></revision></page>