<page><title>Battle of Metz</title><ns>0</ns><id>20498318</id><revision><id>944031252</id><parentid>937749577</parentid><timestamp>2020-03-05T09:10:36Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>2A00:23C7:6889:7700:F437:FCFC:A2E9:CCF7</ip></contributor><comment>/* Background */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="13638" xml:space="preserve">{{about|the 1944 battle|Sieges of Metz|Siege of Metz (disambiguation){{!}}Siege of Metz}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Metz
| partof      = the [[Lorraine Campaign]], [[World War II]]
| image       = Metz1944-1.jpg
| image_size  = 300
| caption     = Troops of the [[5th Infantry Division (United States)|U.S. 5th Infantry Division]] entering Metz on 18 November 1944.
| date        = 27 September – 13 December 1944
| place       = [[Metz]], France
| coordinates = {{coord|49|07|13|N|6|10|40|E|display=inline,title}}
| territory   = The US occupy the German city of Metz
| result      = American tactical victory&lt;br&gt;German strategic victory
| status      =
| combatant1  = {{flag|United States|1912}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = [[George S. Patton]]
| commander2  = [[Otto von Knobelsdorff]]
| strength1   =
| strength2   =
| casualties1 =
| casualties2 =
| notes       =
}}
{{Campaignbox Siegfried Line}}
The '''Battle of Metz''' was a battle fought during [[World War II]] at the city of [[Metz]], France, from late September 1944 through mid-December between the [[United States Army Central|U.S. Third Army]] commanded by [[Lieutenant general (United States)|Lieutenant General]] [[George S. Patton|George Patton]] and the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German Army]] commanded by General [[Otto von Knobelsdorff]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite video
 | year =1944
 | title =Video: Third Army blasts Nazi Strongholds, 1944/11/02 (1944)
 | url =https://archive.org/details/1944-11-02_3rd_Army_blasts_Nazi_Strongholds
 | publisher =[[Universal Newsreel]]
 | accessdate =February 21, 2012
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Strong German resistance resulted in heavy casualties for both sides.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.worldwartwobooks.com/product.php/5665/metz--1944-one-more-river- |title=Metz, 1944 One More River |accessdate=1 December 2008 |publisher=World War Two Books |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081206030953/http://www.worldwartwobooks.com/product.php/5665/metz--1944-one-more-river- |archivedate=2008-12-06 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The city was captured by U.S. forces and hostilities formally ceased on 22 November; the last of the forts defending Metz surrendered on 13 December.

==Background==
Metz is located between the rivers [[Moselle river|Moselle]] and [[Seille (Moselle)|Seille]]. The [[fortifications of Metz]] consisted of several forts and observation posts with connecting entrenchments and tunnels. The city had fallen to the German forces when France was defeated in 1940.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.eyewitnesstohistory.com/patton.htm |title=General George Patton Interrogates a SS General, 1944 |accessdate=1 December 2008 |publisher=Eyewitness to History | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20081220041617/http://www.eyewitnesstohistory.com/patton.htm| archivedate= 20 December 2008 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following the fall of France, the city was immediately annexed to the [[Third Reich]], as were most districts previously annexed to the Reich that had been lost in 1918. Most of the Nazi dignitaries assumed it was obvious that Metz, where so many German army officers were born,&lt;ref group=note&gt;Admiral [[Hans Benda]] (1877–1951), General [[Arthur Kobus]] (1879†1945), General [[Günther Rüdel]] (1883†1950), General [[Joachim Degener]] (1883†1953), General [[Wilhelm Baur]] (1883†1964), General [[Hermann Schaefer]] (1885†1962), General [[Bodo Zimmermann]] (1886†1963), General [[Walther Kittel]] (1887†1971), General [[Hans von Salmuth]] (1888†1962), General [[Karl Kriebel]] (1888†1961), General [[Arthur von Briesen]] (1891†1981), General [[Eugen Müller]] (1891†1951), General [[Ernst Schreder]] (1892†1941), General [[Ludwig Bieringer]] (1892†1975), General [[Edgar Feuchtinger]] (1894†1960), General [[Kurt Haseloff]] (1894†1978), General [[Hans-Albrecht Lehmann]] (1894†1976), General [[Theodor Berkelmann]] (1894†1943), General [[Hans Leistikow]] (1895†1967), General [[Rudolf Schmundt]] (1896†1944), General [[Wilhelm Falley]] (1897†1944), General [[Julius von Bernuth]] (1897†1942), General [[Johannes Hintz]] ( 1898 - 1944 ), General [[Herbert Gundelach]] (1899†1971), General [[Joachim-Friedrich Lang]] (1899†1945), General [[Heinz Harmel]] (1906†2000), [[Erich von Brückner]] (1896†1949), [[Helmuth Bode]] (1907†1985), [[Johannes Mühlenkamp]] (1910†1986),  [[Peter-Erich Cremer]] (1911†1992), [[Joachim Pötter]] (1913†1992), [[Ludwig Weißmüller]] (1915†1943), [[Walter Bordellé]] (1918†1984) among others.&lt;/ref&gt; was a German city. At that time, the [[Wehrmacht]] did not consider it an important location and the city's defenses were reduced with many guns and equipment removed, although the fortifications were still heavily defended and well armed.&lt;ref name="award" &gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.wehrmacht-awards.com/campaign_awards/cufftitles/metz.htm |title=Metz 1944 |accessdate=1 December 2008 |author=Col. Scott Pritchett |publisher=Campaign Awards of the Wehrmacht |date= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

However, after the Allied "break out" from the lodgement established by the [[Normandy landings]], the [[U.S. Third Army]] raced 400 miles across France, with the German forces retreating in disorder. As Third Army supply lines became stretched, material (especially gasoline) became scarce, and Supreme Commander General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] called a halt to the Third Army advance so that supplies could be stockpiled for [[Operation Market Garden]], an attempt to break into the vital (and heavily industrialized) German Ruhr Valley in the north. This pause by Third Army gave the Germans time to reorganize and fortify Metz, in an attempt to contain the Allied advance.&lt;ref name="award" /&gt; 

By the end of August 1944, German forces in [[Lorraine (region)|Lorraine]] had managed to reestablish a defensive line around Metz and [[Nancy, France|Nancy]]. According to an order issued by [[Hitler]] in March 1944, fortress commanders were to hold their positions at all costs, surrendering only with Hitler's approval, which he would never give. Metz was surrounded by forts built by the Germans between 1870 and 1919, then allowed to decay by the French, who possessed the Lorraine region until it was retaken by Germany in 1940. The German commanders of the Metz forts were  required to follow Hitler's "hold at all costs" order when  attacked, in September 1944, by the [[U.S. Third Army]] led by General [[George S. Patton]], who had reached [[Verdun]] before Eisenhower's order to halt the advance and conserve supplies. Hitler understood the pause was due to a supply shortage, and would not last, and he recognized that the Third Army posed a threat to the [[Saarland|Saar]] region of Germany.&lt;ref name="award" /&gt; Hitler ordered his commanders to hold the Allies "as far west as possible," to give time for the strengthening of the [[Siegfried Line|West Wall]], which had been depleted to build up the Atlantic Wall. 

The defense of Metz was undertaken by the [[1st Army (Wehrmacht)|German First Army]], commanded by [[General]] Otto von Knobelsdorff. The number of German troops positioned in the vicinity of Metz was equivalent to four and a half [[Military division|divisions]].&lt;ref name="award" /&gt;

==Battle==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-J28180, Westfront, bei Metz, Grenadier mit Panzerschreck.jpg|thumb|German Grenadier with ''[[Panzerschreck]]'', on 27 October 1944, near [[Metz]]]]
[[File:EnteringMetz.jpg|thumb|Men of the 378th Infantry, 95th Division enter Metz (17 November 1944).]]

[[Armoured cavalry|Armored]] elements of the United States [[XX Corps (United States)|XX Corps]], while on a reconnaissance operation in the direction of the Moselle, made contact with elements from the [[17th SS Panzergrenadier Division]] on 6 September 1944. On 18 September, U.S. reconnaissance units encountered Wehrmacht Panzergrenadiers again. The U.S. forces had not expected the German forces to be in the area, and had to bring together their units that were spread out.&lt;ref name="award" /&gt; Several small scale attacks were made by the U.S. forces after this encounter.

The first U.S. attack was launched by the [[95th Infantry Division (United States)|95th Infantry Division]], in which they attempted to capture a bridgehead to the north of Metz. This attack was repelled by the German forces, as was another attack on the city that followed. In another attack, the US forces captured a small bridgehead across the Moselle to the south of Metz.&lt;ref name="award" /&gt;
[[File:Metz1944-2.jpg|thumb|left|Troops of 95th Infantry Division conducting a house-to-house search in Metz on 19 November 1944]]
By the end of September, German forces positioned to the north had moved to the southern area of Metz. Some troops were also withdrawn from Metz. After this development, the [[XII Corps (United States)|XII Corps]] launched another attack but was countered by the German defenders. In the following two weeks, the U.S. forces limited themselves to small scale attacks and patrolling in the Metz area. During this time, the XX Corps underwent a training program, experimenting with methods of reducing the defenses of the fortress. By this time, the U.S. command had decided to attack Metz from its rear, coming from the east.&lt;ref name="award" /&gt;

On 3 November a new attack was launched by the U.S. forces, which resulted in the capture of the outer defenses with the aid of the tactics developed during the training process. On 14 November [[Generalleutnant]] [[Heinrich Kittel]] was appointed as the new commander of the German forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Lorraine Campaign |last=Cole |first=Hugh M. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1950 |publisher=Historical Division, United States Army |location= |isbn= |pages=429 |url=https://history.army.mil/html/books/007/7-6-1/CMH_Pub_7-6-1.pdf }}&lt;/ref&gt; By 17 November, U.S. forces had managed to isolate most of the forts, and were attacking the city. German forces had been retreating since 17 November, and U.S. forces pursued them for the following two days.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Lorraine Campaign |last=Cole |first=Hugh M. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1950 |publisher=Historical Division, United States Army |location= |isbn= |pages=413 |url=https://history.army.mil/html/books/007/7-6-1/CMH_Pub_7-6-1.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;  U.S. forces entered Metz on 18 November, and on 21 November Kittel was wounded and subsequently captured. Although the city itself was captured by U.S. forces and hostilities formally ceased on 22 November, the remaining isolated forts continued to hold out.&lt;ref name="award" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Lorraine Campaign |last=Cole |first=Hugh M. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1950 |publisher=Historical Division, United States Army |location= |isbn= |pages=446 |url=https://history.army.mil/html/books/007/7-6-1/CMH_Pub_7-6-1.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Direct assault was forbidden against the holdout forts in order to preserve artillery ammunition for the XX Corps' advance to the [[Saar River|Sarre River]] and the isolated forts subsequently surrendered one by one following the surrender of Fort Verdun on 26 November. By the end of November, several forts were still holding out. The last of the forts at Metz to surrender was [[Fort Jeanne d'Arc]], which capitulated to the [[III Corps (United States)|U.S. III Corps]] on 13 December.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Lorraine Campaign |last=Cole |first=Hugh M. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1950 |publisher=Historical Division, United States Army |location= |isbn= |pages=447 |url=https://history.army.mil/html/books/007/7-6-1/CMH_Pub_7-6-1.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
Although the battle resulted in defeat for the German forces, it served the intended purpose of the German command of halting the advance of the U.S. Third Army for three months, enabling retreating German forces to make an organized withdrawal to the Sarre river and to organize their defenses. The level of casualties for both sides are unknown but high.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=The Lorraine Campaign |last=Cole |first=Hugh M. |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1950 |publisher=Historical Division, United States Army |location= |isbn= |pages=448 |url=https://history.army.mil/html/books/007/7-6-1/CMH_Pub_7-6-1.pdf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Germans were surprised at the American approach on the battlefield. Generaloberst [[Johannes Blaskowitz]], C.O of Armeegruppe G, reviewed Patton's decision to launch a headlong attack straight into the fortifications of Metz by saying:

&lt;small&gt;"A direct attack on Metz was unnecessary....in contrast a swerve northward in the direction of Luxemburg and Bitburg would have met with greater success and caused our 1st Army's right flank collapsed followed by the breakdown of our 7th Army."&lt;/small&gt;

The military strategist and historian [[B. H. Liddell Hart|Liddel Hart]] remarked:

&lt;small&gt;"Patton's 3rd Army began to cross the Moselle as early as 5 September, yet was little farther forward 2 weeks later - or indeed two months later." &lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Christer Bergström, "The Ardennes - Hitler's Winter Offensive", p. 28&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
;Footnotes
{{reflist|group=note}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
{{commons category|Lorraine Campaign}}
*[http://content.library.ccsu.edu/u?/VHP,5599 Oral history interview with Frank Niedermayer, an infantryman during the Battle of Metz] from the Veterans History Project at Central Connecticut State University

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Metz}}
[[Category:Western European Campaign (1944–1945)]]
[[Category:History of Metz]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States|Metz]]</text><sha1>2vsn6pc901ctmhwfnu03h95kkk1en6n</sha1></revision></page>