<page><title>Battle of Arnhem</title><ns>0</ns><id>158267</id><revision><id>965020273</id><parentid>965019405</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-28T23:00:19Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Audaciter</username><id>5839510</id></contributor><minor /><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="96265" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Failed British airborne operation in Arnhem, Netherlands. Part of Operation Market Garden}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2019}}
{{Use British English|date=July 2011}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Arnhem
| partof      = [[Operation Market Garden]]
| image       = Aerial view of the bridge over the Neder Rijn, Arnhem.jpg
| image_size  = 300
| caption     = Aerial reconnaissance photo of the [[John Frost Bridge|Arnhem road bridge]] taken by the Royal Air Force on 19 September, showing signs of the British defence on the northern ramp and wrecked German vehicles from the previous day's fighting.
| coordinates = {{coord|51|58|49|N|5|54|01|E|type:event_scale:10000_region:NL|display=inline,title}}
| date        = 17–26 September 1944
&lt;br /&gt;({{Age in years, months, weeks and days|month1=9 |day1=17|year1=1944|month2=09|day2=26|year2=1944}})
| place       = [[Gelderland]], Netherlands
| result      = German victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagdeco|Poland|1928}} Poland
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Roy Urquhart]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Poland|1928}} [[Stanisław Sosabowski]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[John Frost (British Army officer)|John Frost]] &lt;sup&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[&lt;/nowiki&gt;POW&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Walter Model]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Wilhelm Bittrich]]
| strength1  =  1 reinforced airborne division&lt;br /&gt;1 parachute infantry brigade&lt;br /&gt;[[Royal Air Force|RAF]] Resupply flights&lt;br /&gt; Limited support from XXX Corps in later stages
| strength2  =  &lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;Initially equivalent to:&lt;br /&gt;1 ''[[Kampfgruppe]]''&lt;br /&gt;1 armoured division
| casualties1 = &lt;sup&gt;#&lt;/sup&gt;Approx 1,984 killed&lt;br /&gt;6,854 captured
| casualties2 = &lt;sup&gt;#&lt;/sup&gt;Approx 1,300 killed&lt;br /&gt;2,000 wounded
| notes       = &lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;More details of the German strength can be found in the German forces section &lt;br /&gt;&lt;sup&gt;#&lt;/sup&gt;More detailed information is available in the losses sections
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Operation Market Garden}}
{{Campaignbox Liberation of the Netherlands}}
{{Campaignbox British airborne forces operations}}
}}
The '''Battle of Arnhem''' was a major battle of the Second World War at the vanguard of the Allied [[Operation Market Garden]]. It was fought in and around the Dutch towns of [[Arnhem]], [[Oosterbeek]], [[Wolfheze]] and [[Driel]] and the surrounding countryside from 17–26 September 1944.

The Allies were poised to enter the Netherlands after sweeping through France and Belgium in the summer of 1944, after the [[Operation Overlord|Battle of Normandy]]. Market Garden was proposed by Field Marshal Sir [[Bernard Montgomery]], who favoured a single thrust north over the branches of the [[Lower Rhine]] River, allowing the British Second Army to bypass the [[Siegfried Line]] and attack the [[Ruhr]]. Allied Airborne troops were dropped in the Netherlands to secure key bridges and towns along the Allied axis of advance. Farthest north, the British [[1st Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|1st Airborne Division]] landed at Arnhem to secure bridges across the [[Nederrijn]], supported by men of the [[Glider Pilot Regiment]] and the [[1st Independent Parachute Brigade (Poland)|1st Polish Parachute Brigade]]. British [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]] were expected to reach the British airborne forces in two to three days.

The British airborne forces landed some distance from their objectives and were hampered by unexpected resistance, especially from elements of the 9th and 10th SS Panzer Divisions. Only a small force was able to reach the [[Arnhem road bridge]] while the main body of the division was halted on the outskirts of the town. Meanwhile, XXX Corps was unable to advance north as quickly as anticipated and they failed to relieve the airborne troops according to schedule. After four days, the small British force at the bridge was overwhelmed and the rest of the division became trapped in a small pocket north of the river, where they could not be sufficiently reinforced by the Poles or XXX Corps when they arrived on the southern bank, nor by the RAF's resupply flights. After nine days of fighting, the shattered remains of the division were withdrawn in [[Operation Berlin (Arnhem)|Operation Berlin]]. The Allies were unable to advance farther with no secure bridges over the Nederrijn, and the front line stabilised south of Arnhem. The British 1st Airborne Division lost nearly ¾ of its strength and did not see combat again.

==Background==
{{Main|Operation Market Garden}}

By September 1944, [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] forces had successfully [[Falaise pocket|broken out of their Normandy beachhead]] and pursued shattered [[Wehrmacht|German forces]] across [[Northern France]] and [[Belgium]]. Although Allied commanders generally favoured a broad front policy to continue the advance into Germany and the Netherlands, [[Field marshal (United Kingdom)|Field Marshal]] [[Bernard Montgomery, 1st Viscount Montgomery of Alamein|Bernard Montgomery]] proposed a bold plan to head north through the Dutch [[Gelderland]], bypassing the German [[Siegfried Line]] defences and opening a route into the German industrial heartland of the [[Ruhr]]. Initially proposed as a British and Polish operation codenamed Operation Comet, the plan was soon expanded to involve most of the [[First Allied Airborne Army]] and a set piece ground advance into the Netherlands, codenamed [[Operation Market Garden|Market Garden]].&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.9&lt;/ref&gt;

Montgomery's plan involved dropping the [[101st Airborne Division|US 101st Airborne Division]] to capture key bridges around [[Eindhoven]], the [[82nd Airborne Division|US 82nd Airborne Division]] to secure key crossings around [[Nijmegen]], and the [[1st Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|British 1st Airborne Division]], with the [[1st Independent Parachute Brigade (Poland)|Polish 1st Independent Parachute Brigade]] attached, to capture three bridges across the [[Nederrijn]] at Arnhem. Although [[Lieutenant general (United States)|Lieutenant General]] [[Lewis H. Brereton]] commanded the First Allied Airborne Army, his second in command [[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Frederick Browning]] took command of the airborne operation. The [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|British Second Army]], led by [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]] would advance up the "Airborne corridor", securing the airborne division's positions and crossing the Rhine within two days. If successful the plan would open the door to Germany and hopefully force an end to the war in Europe by the end of the year.&lt;ref name="Frost, p198"&gt;Frost, p.198&lt;/ref&gt;

===British plan===
[[File:Arnhem Map 1.jpg|thumb|400px|The planned British landings and defence at Arnhem]]
{{Further|Operation Market Garden order of battle}}

With the [[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|British 6th Airborne Division]] still refitting after [[Operation Tonga]] and the subsequent [[6th Airborne Division advance to the River Seine|fighting in Normandy]], the task of securing the Rhine bridgehead fell to the 1st Airborne Division under the command of [[Major-general (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[Roy Urquhart]]. The division was made up of three brigades of infantry (two [[Paratrooper|parachute]], one [[Glider infantry|glider borne]]), supporting [[1st Airlanding Light Regiment|artillery]] and anti-tank batteries and substantial [[Royal Engineers|Royal Engineer]] units, as well as supporting elements such as [[Royal Army Service Corps]] and [[Royal Army Medical Corps]] units.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.20–58&lt;/ref&gt; Most of the division had seen action in [[British airborne operations in North Africa|North Africa]] and [[Allied invasion of Sicily#Battle|Sicily]],&lt;ref name=Middlebrook20&gt;Middlebrook, p.20&lt;/ref&gt; particularly the [[1st Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Parachute Brigade]] and [[1st Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Airlanding Brigade]].&lt;ref name=Middlebrook20/&gt; However, this was the first time the division had fought together as a complete formation.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.39&lt;/ref&gt;

In addition, Urquhart also had the [[1st Independent Parachute Brigade (Poland)|1st Independent Polish Parachute Brigade]] under his command.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.42&lt;/ref&gt; His force was also substantially reinforced by some 1,200 men of the [[Glider Pilot Regiment]], who would fly the glider-borne infantry and vehicles into Arnhem, providing the equivalent of two battalions of infantry for the operation.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.41&lt;/ref&gt; Smaller additions included a Dutch commando team and American communications teams.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook68"/&gt;

The division was required to secure the road, rail and [[pontoon bridge|pontoon]] bridges over the Nederrijn at Arnhem and hold them for two to three days until relieved by XXX Corps.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.26&lt;/ref&gt; From the beginning, however, Urquhart was severely restricted in how he could prepare and deploy his troops for the upcoming battle. The [[IX Troop Carrier Command|U.S. IX Troop Carrier Command]] were limited in their availability; with two more major drops taking place at the same time, there were insufficient carrier aircraft available to fly the entire division to the Netherlands in one lift. Additionally, Major General Williams – commander of IX Troop Carrier Command – decided that it would only be possible to fly one air lift per day,&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.113&lt;/ref&gt; meaning it would take three days to deliver the entire Division and Polish Brigade to the area. A limited number of areas suitable for glider landings and a reluctance from troop command to fly too near to Arnhem, exposing them to [[flak]] from [[Deelen Air Base|Deelen airfield]] after the drop,&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.55&lt;/ref&gt; meant that Urquhart was forced to pick [[drop zone]]s (DZ) and [[landing zone]]s (LZ) up to {{convert|8|mi|km|abbr=on}} from Arnhem itself, on the north side of the river.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p42"&gt;Waddy, p.42&lt;/ref&gt; With the need to secure the bridges, towns and drop zones for subsequent supply drops, the 1st Airborne would need to defend a perimeter of some {{convert|18|mi|km|abbr=on}} whilst waiting for XXX Corps.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p42"/&gt;

[[File:Urquhart outside his headquarters.jpg|thumb|alt=Men standing in front of building next to a small flag pole|left|Major General [[Roy Urquhart]] shortly after returning to his Divisional HQ at the [[Hotel Hartenstein]], 19 September.]]

Urquhart decided to land [[Brigadier (United Kingdom)|Brigadier]] [[Gerald Lathbury]]'s 1st Parachute Brigade and Brigadier [[Philip Hugh Whitby Hicks|"Pip" Hicks']] [[1st Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Airlanding Brigade]] on the first day of the operation, along with Divisional HQ, 1st Airlanding Light Regiment, Royal Artillery, and attached Royal Engineer and medical units.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p42"/&gt; The Airlanding Brigade would land on LZs 'S' and 'Z' and move to secure the drop zones and landing zones for the following days' drops, whilst the three battalions of the parachute brigade would arrive at DZ 'X' and follow three separate routes into Arnhem to secure the bridges.&lt;ref name= Waddy47&gt;Waddy, p.47&lt;/ref&gt; The [[2nd Battalion, Parachute Regiment|2nd Battalion]] — under the command of [[Lieutenant colonel (United Kingdom)|Lt. Col.]] [[John Frost (British Army officer)|John Frost]] — would follow the riverside roads to the centre of Arnhem (codenamed the ''Lion'' route) and secure the main road and railway bridges, as well as a pontoon bridge situated between them. The [[3rd Battalion, Parachute Regiment|3rd Battalion]] of Lt. Col. Fitch would head through Oosterbeek to Arnhem (''Tiger'' route), assist in the capture of the road bridge and take up positions in the east of the town.&lt;ref name=Waddy47/&gt; Lt. Col. Dobie's [[1st Battalion, Parachute Regiment|1st Battalion]] would follow ''Leopard'' route north of the railway line to occupy high ground north and north west of Arnhem.&lt;ref name=Waddy47/&gt; The whole advance would be led by a troop of jeeps from the 1st Airborne Reconnaissance Squadron, under [[Major (United Kingdom)|Major]] [[Frederick Gough]] on ''Leopard'' route, who would attempt a ''[[coup de main]]'' on the road bridge.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, pp.46–47&lt;/ref&gt; On the second day, Brigadier [[John Hackett (British Army officer)|"Shan" Hackett's]] [[4th Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|4th Parachute Brigade]] would arrive at DZ 'Y', accompanied by extra artillery units and remaining elements of the Airlanding Brigade on LZ 'X'. Hackett's three battalions would then reinforce the positions north and north west of Arnhem.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p42" /&gt; On the third day, the 1st Independent Polish Parachute Brigade would be dropped south of the river at DZ 'K'.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p42"/&gt; Using the road bridge, they would reinforce the perimeter east of Arnhem, linking up with their own artillery who would be flown in by glider to LZ 'L'. 1st Airlanding Brigade would fall back to cover Oosterbeek on the western side of the perimeter and 1st Parachute Brigade would fall back to cover the southern side of the bridges.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p42"/&gt; The remaining units of the division would follow XXX Corps on land in what was known as the ''sea tail''.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p42"/&gt; Once XXX Corps had arrived and advanced beyond the bridgehead, the [[52nd (Lowland) Infantry Division]] would be flown into Deelen airfield to support the ground forces north of the Rhine.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.53–54&lt;/ref&gt; The whole operation would be re-supplied by daily flights by No's. 38 and 46 Group RAF&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.386&lt;/ref&gt; who would make the first drop on LZ 'L' on day 2, and subsequent drops on DZ 'V'.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p246"&gt;Middlebrook, p.246&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intelligence===
The division was told to expect only limited resistance from German [[Military reserve|reserve]] forces. A serious challenge to their operation was not expected and many men believed that their work would lead to the ending of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Frost, p.200&lt;/ref&gt; Some – anticipating a period of occupation in Germany – packed leisure equipment in their kit or in the sea tail.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.71&lt;/ref&gt; The optimistic mood prior to the operation would have tragic consequences however. Browning's intelligence officer – Major [[Brian Urquhart]] — obtained information from the [[21st Army Group]] in Belgium and [[Dutch resistance]] that German armour was present around Arnhem. This was backed up with [[aerial reconnaissance]] that he ordered to be flown.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p65"&gt;Middlebrook, p.65&lt;/ref&gt; Browning however was dismissive and ordered his chief medical officer to have Urquhart sent on sick leave.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.66&lt;/ref&gt; In fact, [[Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force|SHAEF]] was aware that there were almost certainly two [[Panzer division]]s at Arnhem but with the operation looming chose to ignore them.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p65"/&gt; Such information would have been gleaned from [[Ultra]] intercepts that the First Allied Airborne Army was not privy to and therefore could not act upon themselves.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p65"/&gt;

===German forces===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101II-M2KBK-771-34, Arnheim, Sturmgeschütze.jpg|thumb|alt=Two armoured vehicles one cowered in tree branches on a hedge lined road|German [[self-propelled gun]]s of the 9th SS Panzer Division during the battle. The presence of the [[II SS Panzer Corps]] would have a significant effect on the battle.]]

The Allied liberation of [[Antwerp]] on 4 September had caused a rout of German reserve troops in the Netherlands, nicknamed "[[Dolle Dinsdag|Mad Tuesday]]".&lt;ref name="Badsey, p22"&gt;Badsey, p.22&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Allied pause at the Dutch border gave the Germans time to regroup and reorganise,&lt;ref&gt;Ryan pp.53–54&lt;/ref&gt; although it would make subsequent attempts to clarify the exact German forces opposing the Allies extremely difficult.&lt;ref name="Badsey, p22"/&gt;

''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'' [[Walter Model]] — commander of [[Army Group B]] — had moved his headquarters to Arnhem and was re-establishing defences in the area and co-ordinating the reorganisation of the scattered units&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.98&lt;/ref&gt; so that by the time the Allies launched Market Garden there would be several units opposing them. To the west of Arnhem was ''[[Kampfgruppe]] Von Tettau'', a force equivalent to seven battalions made up of all manner of German units (including ''[[German Army (Wehrmacht)|Das Heer]]'', ''[[Luftwaffe]]'', ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'', rear echelon and ''[[Waffen-SS]]'' troops) under the command of [[General (Germany)|General]] [[Hans von Tettau]] at [[Battle of the Grebbeberg|Grebbeberg]].&lt;ref name="Kershaw, p108"&gt;Kershaw, p.108&lt;/ref&gt; This included the SS [[Non-commissioned officer]] school ''SS Unteroffizierschule Arnheim'' and the [[16th SS Panzergrenadier Division Reichsführer-SS|16th SS Training Battalion]] under the command of SS ''[[Sturmbannführer]]'' [[Sepp Krafft]], whose unit would play a crucial role in the opening phases of the battle. Within Arnhem itself, the town garrison was under the command of Major-General [[Friedrich Kussin]].&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.94&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-J27784, Arnheim, Walter Model, Heinz Harmel.jpg|thumb|alt=Portrait of two men|left|[[Walter Model]] and [[Heinz Harmel]]]]

Additionally, ''[[Obergruppenführer]]'' [[Wilhelm Bittrich]]'s [[II SS Panzer Corps]] — comprising the remains of [[Walter Harzer]]'s [[9th SS Panzer Division Hohenstaufen|9th SS]] and [[Heinz Harmel]]'s [[10th SS Panzer Division Frundsberg|10th SS Panzer Divisions]] — had moved into the area north of Arnhem to refit and reorganise.&lt;ref name= "Kershaw, p38"&gt;Kershaw, p.38&lt;/ref&gt; Although badly mauled after escaping the [[Falaise pocket]], the corps was made up of seasoned veterans and made available significantly more forces to the Germans than the Allies had been led to expect.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, pp.144–145&lt;/ref&gt; The divisions were also specially trained in anti-airborne operations; during their formation both divisions had undergone month-long anti-airborne exercises whilst waiting for their heavy equipment, and had also spent the last 15 months studying the best reactions to a parachute attack in classroom and field exercises.&lt;ref name=Kershaw41&gt;Kershaw, p.41&lt;/ref&gt; The 9th SS had a ''[[Panzergrenadier]]'' brigade, a reconnaissance battalion, an artillery battalion, two batteries of [[self-propelled gun]]s and a company of tanks.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p21"&gt;Waddy, p.21&lt;/ref&gt; Exactly how many men were available after the withdrawal from Normandy is unclear. Some sources suggest that the 9th had up to 6,000 men,&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.133&lt;/ref&gt; others suggest that the combined total of the 9th and 10th SS was only 6,000–7,000 men.&lt;ref name="Kershaw, p38"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Waddy, p21"/&gt;

There were also Dutch units allied to the Germans present at Arnhem. These formations recruited from Dutch nationals (mainly criminals, men wishing to avoid national service or men affiliated with the ''[[Nationaal-Socialistische Beweging]]'') and were incorporated into the German Army.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.36&lt;/ref&gt; At Arnhem, the partly Dutch SS Wachbattalion 3 was attached to ''Kampfgruppe Von Tettau''&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.110&lt;/ref&gt; and the 3rd Battalion of the [[34th SS Volunteer Grenadier Division Landstorm Nederland]] training at nearby [[Hoogeveen]] was quickly attached to Harzer's 9th SS Panzer Division when they arrived at the battle on 20 September.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.defendingarnhem.com/landstorm-nederland.htm |title=Defending Arnhem&amp;nbsp;– III./Gren. Rgt. 1 'Landstorm Nederland' |accessdate=21 June 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091128114236/http://www.defendingarnhem.com/landstorm-nederland.htm |archivedate=28 November 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the battle progressed, more and more forces would become available to the Germans. [[Adolf Hitler]], stunned by the attack, agreed that the defence of the Netherlands should receive absolute priority and over the course of the battle reinforcements would stream in; from [[Wehrkreis VI]], the [[Wesel]] area and General [[Friedrich Christiansen]]'s Armed Forces Command Netherlands.&lt;ref name="Badsey, p43"&gt;Badsey, p.43&lt;/ref&gt; Model arranged for units to be sent straight to the units in action in order to avoid long-winded logistics, and rushed in specialist [[urban warfare]] and machine gun battalions.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.123&lt;/ref&gt; Each day of the battle, the German military strength increased whilst the British supplies diminished. By 21 September, the fifth day of the battle, German forces outnumbered the British by 3:1 and continued to increase.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p124"&gt;Waddy, p.124&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==
===Day 1&amp;nbsp;– Sunday 17 September===
[[File:Arnhem Map 2.jpg|thumb|right|First infantry movements, 17 September.]]

The first lift was preceded by intense bombing and strafing raids made by the British [[RAF Second Tactical Air Force|Second Tactical Air Force]] and the American [[8th Air Force|8th]] and [[9th Air Force|9th]] Air Forces. These targeted the known [[flak gun]]s and German garrisons and barracks across the area. Meanwhile, the first lift suffered only light losses as the aircraft and gliders flew from British bases to the target area. The first arrivals were the 21st Independent Parachute Company, who landed at 12:40 in order to mark the landing zones for the gliders and parachutists of the main force.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.48&lt;/ref&gt; The landings were largely unopposed and the battalions were formed up in good order and ready to carry out their tasks by 14:45.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.53&lt;/ref&gt;

The Airlanding Brigade moved quickly to secure the landing zones. The 2nd Battalion, [[South Staffordshire Regiment]] moved into [[Wolfheze]], the 1st Battalion, [[Border Regiment]] secured DZ 'X', deploying its companies around the DZ and in [[Renkum]], and the 7th Battalion, [[King's Own Scottish Borderers]] moved to secure DZ 'Y'.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.163&lt;/ref&gt; Here, they ambushed the Dutch SS Wach Battalion as it headed toward Arnhem from [[Ede, Netherlands|Ede]].&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.163–164&lt;/ref&gt; Units of the Airlanding Artillery and Divisional HQ headed into Wolfheze and Oosterbeek where medical officers set up a Regimental Aid Post at the home of [[Kate ter Horst]].&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.219&lt;/ref&gt;

While the 1st Airlanding Brigade moved off from the landing zones, the 1st Parachute Brigade prepared to head east toward the bridges, with Lathbury and his HQ Company following Frost on ''Lion'' route. Although some jeeps of the reconnaissance squadron were lost on the flight over, the company formed up in good strength and moved off along ''Leopard'' route.&lt;ref name="Badsey, p43"/&gt;

The Germans were unprepared for the landings and initially thrown into confusion. Model – erroneously assuming that the paratroopers had come to capture him – fled his headquarters at the Tafelberg Hotel in Oosterbeek and went to Bittrich's headquarters east of Arnhem at [[Doetinchem]], where he took personal control of the battle.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.199&lt;/ref&gt; The 10th SS Division was sent south to respond to the American landings at Nijmegen and to defend the "island" (the [[polder]] between the Nederrijn and [[Waal (river)|Waal]] rivers), while the 9th would defend Arnhem. The 9th SS was in the midst of preparing to return to Germany and Harmel was in Berlin trying to secure more men and supplies for his unit. He was instantly ordered to return to Arnhem whilst his division began to prepare its forces for battle. ''[[Obersturmbannführer]]'' [[Ludwig Spindler]] — commander of the 9th SS Armoured Artillery Regiment – quickly organised a small [[Kampfgruppe|battlegroup]] (''Kampfgruppe Spindler'' was initially only 120 men, but would incorporate 16 separate units over the course of the battle). In the late afternoon, he was ordered to advance west to Oosterbeek and establish a blocking line to prevent the British from reaching Arnhem centre.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.103&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, the Division's reconnaissance battalion under the command of ''[[Hauptsturmführer]]'' [[Viktor Gräbner]] was ordered south to Nijmegen, crossing the Arnhem bridge at dusk. Initially, however, no units were ordered to secure the bridge itself. Arnhem Garrison commander Major-General [[Friedrich Kussin]] was killed by men of the 3rd Parachute Battalion as he sped towards his headquarters, and his death led to a breakdown in command and responsibilities.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.309&lt;/ref&gt; It was not until late in the afternoon that the Reconnaissance Battalion of 10th SS Division were ordered to secure the bridge. At the time of the landings, only one organised unit was in place to oppose the Allied advance toward the bridges (the 16th SS Training Battalion camped in Wolfheze) and their commander – Sepp Krafft – acted quickly to establish a blocking screen west of Oosterbeek.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, pp.72–73&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Operation Market I - 04.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Aerial view of fields covered in abandoned gliders|[[Airspeed Horsa|Horsa]] and [[General Aircraft Hamilcar|Hamilcar]] gliders of the [[1st Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Airlanding Brigade]] litter landing zone 'Z' west of Wolfheze, 17 September.]]

The Allied advance quickly ran into trouble. The reconnaissance squadron was [[ambush]]ed by the northern flank of Krafft's blocking line and withdrew.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.123–126&lt;/ref&gt; The 1st and 3rd Parachute Battalions were also stalled by Krafft's defences and spent the rest of the day skirting his line. The 3rd Parachute Battalion went south and halted in Oosterbeek for most of the night&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.135–136&lt;/ref&gt; while 1st Parachute Battalion went further north but hit Spindler's forces and was unable to reach the Arnhem-Ede road of ''Leopard'' route. Instead Dobie decided to abandon his original plan, and head towards the bridge to assist Frost instead. The battalion headed south into Oosterbeek overnight.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.142&lt;/ref&gt; Only the 2nd Parachute Battalion was largely unopposed, bypassing the defences that did not as yet reach down as far as the river. They were slowed by cheering Dutch civilians and did not reach the bridges until late in the day.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.142–162&lt;/ref&gt; The railway bridge was blown by German engineers as the Allies approached it&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.61&lt;/ref&gt; and the pontoon bridge was missing its central section.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.249&lt;/ref&gt; At dusk, the men of A Company under Major [[Allison Digby Tatham-Warter|Digby Tatham-Warter]] observed Gräbner's force cross the bridge, on their way to Nijmegen. Most of the battalion and various other supporting units—including two jeeps of Gough's squadron, four [[Ordnance QF 6 pounder|6-pounder anti-tank guns]], Brigade HQ (but without Lathbury), and Royal Engineers (in total numbering about 740 men)—&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.67&lt;/ref&gt; moved into Arnhem centre as night fell and, owing to the oversight in German orders, were able to secure the undefended northern end of the road bridge.&lt;ref&gt;Steer, p.99&lt;/ref&gt; Brigade HQ was being led by [[Brigade major|Brigade Major]] [[Tony Hibbert (British Army officer)|Tony Hibbert]].&lt;ref name=ParaData&gt;[http://www.paradata.org.uk/people/tony-hibbert-1 Roll Call: Major Tony Hibbert, MBE MC] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141019094205/http://www.paradata.org.uk/people/tony-hibbert-1 |date=19 October 2014 }} ParaData, Airborne Assault (Registered Charity)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=PegasusArchive&gt;[http://www.pegasusarchive.org/arnhem/tony_hibbert.htm Major James Anthony Hibbert], The Pegasus Archive—The Battle of Arnhem Archive&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ArnhemAccount&gt;[http://www.paradata.org.uk/article/857/related/13389 Personal account of Major Tony Hibbert's experiences of the Battle of Arnhem] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141022034811/http://www.paradata.org.uk/article/857/related/13389 |date=22 October 2014 }} ParaData, Airborne Assault (Registered Charity)&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Lieutenant (British Army and Royal Marines)|Lieutenant]] [[John Hollington Grayburn|Jack Grayburn]] led an attempt to secure the southern end of the bridge but was unsuccessful, and a later attempt using a [[flame thrower]] only succeeded in setting the freshly painted girders of the bridge alight.&lt;ref&gt;Frost, pp.217–218&lt;/ref&gt; However, the British were able to make good their position and quickly repulsed the 10th SS Reconnaissance Battalion and other German units when they arrived to secure the bridge.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, pp.97, 310&lt;/ref&gt;

The Allied advance was severely hampered by poor communications in these crucial initial phases.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, pp.213–214&lt;/ref&gt; The paratroopers' [[Two-way radio|radio sets]] range was instantly limited by the wooded terrain and as the battalions advanced they lost contact with Divisional HQ at the landing zones.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.128&lt;/ref&gt; Over the coming nine days, radio communication within the division, with Browning's HQ at Nijmegen, with XXX Corps and with the United Kingdom would be intermittent and unreliable, severely hampering the British units.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.pegasusarchive.org/arnhem/depth_reason2.htm|title=Reasons for the failure |work=The Pegasus Archive |accessdate=9 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Carrier pigeons were even used to [[William of Orange (Pigeon)|make contact]] with Britain.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.pdsa.org.uk/about-us/animal-bravery-awards/dickin-medal-pigeons#awards-made-between-1943--1945 |title=Awards made between 1943 – 1945 |accessdate=1 October 2011 |publisher=PDSA |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110929194956/http://www.pdsa.org.uk/about-us/animal-bravery-awards/dickin-medal-pigeons/ |archivedate=29 September 2011  }}&lt;/ref&gt; Partly as a consequence of this limitation, Urquhart decided to follow the 1st Parachute Brigade and make contact with Lathbury. When he found the Brigade HQ on ''Lion'' route, he was informed by Major Hibbert, who, at that time, was still en route to the bridge, that Lathbury himself was visiting the 3rd Battalion.&lt;ref name=ParaData /&gt; Urquhart followed Lathbury there but subsequently would not be able to return to Divisional HQ for two days.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.129&lt;/ref&gt;

===Day 2&amp;nbsp;– Monday 18 September===
[[File:Arnhem Map 3.jpg|thumb|The 2nd lift advances into Arnhem where it encounters the German blocking line, 18 September.]]

As the second day dawned, the 9th SS Panzer Division continued to reinforce the German blocking line. Krafft's unit withdrew overnight and joined Spindler's line, coming under his command.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.107&lt;/ref&gt; Spindler's force was now becoming so large as more men and units arrived at the new front, that he was forced to split it into two battle groups: ''Kampfgruppen'' Allworden and Harder. The defensive line now blocked the entire western side of Arnhem and had closed the gap exploited by Frost alongside the river the previous evening.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, pp.104–108&lt;/ref&gt;

Overnight, the 1st and 3rd Parachute battalions had skirted as far south as 2nd Parachute Battalion's original ''Lion'' route, hoping to follow them into Arnhem centre.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.167&lt;/ref&gt; They approached the German line on the outskirts of the town before light and for several hours attempted to fight through the German positions. Spindler's force—being continually reinforced—was too strong to penetrate, and by 10:00 the British advance was stopped.&lt;ref name="Kershaw, p108"/&gt; A more coordinated attack followed in the afternoon, but it too was repulsed.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.81&lt;/ref&gt; Urquhart attempted to return to his Divisional Headquarters at Oosterbeek but became cut off and was forced to take shelter in a Dutch family's [[loft]] with two fellow officers.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.84&lt;/ref&gt; Lathbury was injured and also forced into hiding.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.174&lt;/ref&gt;

At the road bridge, German forces of the 9th SS had quickly surrounded Frost's battalion, cutting them off from the rest of the division.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.82&lt;/ref&gt; At around 09:00, the 9th SS Reconnaissance Battalion headed back toward Arnhem from south of the river, having concluded that it was not needed at Nijmegen. Though aware of the British troops at the bridge, it attempted to cross by force. In the resultant two-hour battle, it was beaten back with heavy losses; half of its armored vehicles were destroyed or knocked out and its commanding officer, [[Viktor Eberhard Gräbner|Viktor Gräbner]], was killed in action during the assault.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.131&lt;/ref&gt; German attacks carried on around the British perimeter at the Arnhem bridge for the rest of the day, but the British continued to hold.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, p.6&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:The British Airborne Division at Arnhem and Oosterbeek in Holland BU1091.jpg|thumb|alt=Men on foot and jeeps towing guns on a tree lined road|left|Men of the 2nd Battalion, [[South Staffordshire Regiment]], of the 1st Airlanding Brigade, advance toward Arnhem, towing a [[Ordnance QF 6 pounder|6-pounder anti-tank gun]] with them, 18 September.]]

At the landing zones, Urquhart's Chief of Staff Lt. Col [[Charles Mackenzie (British Army officer)|Charles Mackenzie]] informed Brigadier Hicks that, in Urquhart's and Lathbury's absence, he was acting divisional commander. Mackenzie also advised him to send one of his units – the South Staffords (which was not complete and was awaiting its full complement of men in the second lift) — to Arnhem to help with the advance to the bridge.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.187&lt;/ref&gt; The South Staffords departed in the morning and linked up with the 1st Parachute Battalion in the late afternoon.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.188&lt;/ref&gt;

German forces began to probe the 1st Airlanding Brigade defences throughout the morning. Units of Kampfgruppe Von Tettau attacked the Border's positions; men of the SS NCO school overran Renkum and ''Kriegsmarine'' troops engaged the British all day as they withdrew. Minor fighting broke out around LZ 'X' but not enough to seriously hamper the glider landing there.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.97&lt;/ref&gt; At DZ 'Y', the Dutch SS Wach Battalion became heavily engaged with the King's Own Scottish Borderers, threatening to hamper the arrival of the second lift.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.94&lt;/ref&gt; The communications breakdown meant that it was impossible to warn the aircraft. Equally, there was no way for the division to know that the 2nd lift had been delayed by ground [[fog]] in England.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.225&lt;/ref&gt; Thus, the arrival of the 4th Parachute Brigade under Brigadier Hackett and several more troops of artillery at the drop zones was several hours overdue. When the parachutists did arrive after 15:00, they dropped under fire.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.234&lt;/ref&gt; Several were killed as aircraft and parachutists were shot down and the [[heath (habitat)|heath-land]] they were landing on burned.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.316&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the arrival of a full brigade overwhelmed the Dutch who were routed and surrendered in droves.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.162&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the setbacks the units assembled with only slight casualties, but the changing circumstances at Arnhem meant that their roles were quickly changed. The [[11th Parachute Battalion (United Kingdom)|11th Parachute Battalion]] and the rest of the South Staffords were immediately despatched to Arnhem to assist in the attempt to break through to the bridge, where they linked up with the 1st and 3rd Parachute Battalions after dark. Hicks' decision to send the 11th Parachute Battalion to Arnhem (thus weakening the 4th Parachute Brigade), dismayed Hackett, who remonstrated with Hicks to no avail.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.250&lt;/ref&gt; However, he was given command of the King's Own Scottish Borderers who were moving toward LZ 'L' to secure it for Tuesday's landing.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.251&lt;/ref&gt; The [[10th Parachute Battalion (United Kingdom)|10th]] and [[156th Parachute Battalion (United Kingdom)|156th Parachute]] Battalions moved north of the railway line to take up their planned defensive positions north west of Arnhem, but the leading elements of 156th Parachute Battalion made contact with the main 9th SS blocking line after dark and withdrew for the night.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.252&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly after the second lift arrived, the first supply drop was made onto LZ 'L'. Although most supplies arrived, only a small amount could be collected as the area was not under full British control.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p246"/&gt; The poor radio communication meant that it was not possible to alert the RAF and unsecured drop zones would be a major problem in the days to come.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.400&lt;/ref&gt;

===Day 3&amp;nbsp;– Tuesday 19 September===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-2005-0077, Arnheim, britische Gefangene.jpg|thumb|alt=Eight men walking towards the camera with the hands on their heads|British [[prisoners-of-war]]. The Germans took scores of prisoners after the morning's fighting on 19 September.]]

When the South Staffords and 11th Parachute Battalion arrived at the 1st and 3rd Parachute Battalion's positions on the western outskirts of Arnhem, the British hoped to have sufficient troops to break through to Frost's position at the bridge.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.86&lt;/ref&gt; Lieutenant Colonel Dobie of 1st Parachute Battalion planned to attack before first light but an erroneous report suggesting that the bridge had fallen led to the attack being cancelled.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.190&lt;/ref&gt; By the time the report was corrected first light was not long away, but, with reinforcement at the bridge the priority, the attack had to proceed. The advance began on a narrow front between the railway line to the north and the river to the south. The 1st Parachute Battalion would lead, supported by remnants of the 3rd Parachute Battalion, with the 2nd South Staffordshires on the left flank and the 11th Parachute Battalion following behind.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.87&lt;/ref&gt; As soon as it became light, the 1st Parachute Battalion was spotted and halted by fire from the main German defensive line. Trapped in open ground and under heavy fire from three sides, the 1st Parachute Battalion disintegrated and what remained of the 3rd Parachute Battalion fell back.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.195–196&lt;/ref&gt; The 2nd South Staffordshires were similarly cut off and save for about 150 men, overcome by midday.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.200–205&lt;/ref&gt; The 11th Parachute Battalion – which had thus far not been heavily involved – was now overwhelmed in exposed positions while attempting to capture high ground to the north.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.206–209&lt;/ref&gt; The South Staffords similarly attempted to secure high ground but were driven off. With no hope of breaking through, the 500 remaining men of these four battalions retreated westwards in the direction of the main force, {{convert|5|km|mi|abbr=on}} away in Oosterbeek.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.209,216&lt;/ref&gt; As they approached Oosterbeek they were met by Lieutenant Colonel [[Sheriff Thompson]], of the 1st Airlanding Light Artillery Regiment, who formed most of the men into a defensive screen under Major [[Robert Henry Cain|Robert Cain]] {{convert|0.5|mi|km|abbr=on}} forward of his artillery positions.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook326&gt;Middlebrook, p.326&lt;/ref&gt; The battle gave Urquhart the opportunity to escape from his hiding place and he was able to return to Division HQ at the [[Hotel Hartenstein]] in Oosterbeek, where for the first time he was able to learn the extent of the German forces facing them.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.194,210&lt;/ref&gt;

In Britain, ground fog again frustrated reinforcement. Thirty-five gliders of the 3rd lift carrying the Polish glider borne elements were delayed in taking off and the whole parachute brigade failed to take off at all.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.269–270&lt;/ref&gt; This would have serious consequences on the ground when the delayed gliders arrived.
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101II-M2KBK-772-24, Arnheim, deutsches 2 cm Flakgeschütz.jpg|thumb|alt=Four men at side of wooded area looking up to the sky|left|A German [[2 cm Flak 30|20 mm ''Flak'' gun]] awaits the arrival of supply aircraft during the battle.]]

North of the railway line, the 156th and 10th Parachute Battalions became engaged with the German defensive line as they attempted to seize the high ground in the woods north of Oosterbeek. Both battalions' advances were blunted against the well-defended German positions and by early afternoon they had not advanced any further than their original positions.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.254–260&lt;/ref&gt; Urquhart—realising the need to assume a more defensive stance and prevent the two battalions being cut off north of the railway—ordered them to fall back to Wolfheze and Oosterbeek.&lt;ref name="Evans, p8"&gt;Evans, p.8&lt;/ref&gt; Making a fighting withdrawal with the Germans of ''Kampfgruppe'' Krafft closely pursuing them, the units fell back across LZ 'L', defended by the King's Own Scottish Borderers who were awaiting the arrival of the glider borne elements of the Polish Parachute Brigade.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.271&lt;/ref&gt; Heavy fighting ensued as the gliders arrived in the middle of the retreat and Polish losses were heavy.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, pp.111–113&lt;/ref&gt; All four Allied units streamed south and west toward the road crossings over the steep railway [[cutting (transportation)|cutting]] at Oosterbeek and Wolfheze and gathered in ''ad hoc'' units in the woods on the south side, where most of them spent the night.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.115&lt;/ref&gt; Some German units followed them across the railway and an SS battalion reached Wolfheze, but was stopped when it was strafed by its own air force.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.206&lt;/ref&gt;

In the afternoon, the RAF flew its first major resupply mission, using 164 aircraft&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.387&lt;/ref&gt; to fly in {{convert|390|ST|t|lk=on|abbr=on}} of supplies to the British.&lt;ref name="Evans, p8"/&gt; The Germans – who had been expecting resupply efforts – had moved five flak batteries into the area specifically to attack these flights and, as the RAF came into view, they succeeded in shooting down 10 aircraft. Despite the bravery of the pilots ([[Flight Lieutenant]] [[David Lord]] received the [[Victoria Cross]] posthumously), the Airborne forces only recovered {{convert|31|ST|t|abbr=on}} of supplies.&lt;ref name="Evans, p8"/&gt; The dropzone – Supply DZ 'V' — was still in German hands (the British would never reach this SDZ during the battle) and no message had reached Britain to explain this.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.388&lt;/ref&gt;

At the bridge, Frost's forces continued to hold but without supply or reinforcement their position was becoming weaker. The Germans – realising that infantry attacks were unlikely to remove the stubborn defenders – began to systematically destroy the houses the British were in using tanks, artillery, and [[Mortar (weapon)|mortars]].&lt;ref&gt;Steer, p.100&lt;/ref&gt; In the absence of any Allied air cover, the ''Luftwaffe'' were able to make strafing runs on the British occupied houses as well.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.73&lt;/ref&gt;

===Day 4&amp;nbsp;– Wednesday 20 September===
[[File:Arnhem Map 4.jpg|thumb|The British battalions break off their engagements and withdraw into the Oosterbeek perimeter, 19–21 September.]]

By now, the division was too weak to attempt to reach Frost at the bridge. Eight of the nine infantry battalions were badly mauled or scattered and only one – 1st Battalion, The Border Regiment – still existed as a unit.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.325&lt;/ref&gt; Urquhart made the difficult decision to abandon the 2nd Parachute Battalion.&lt;ref name= Waddy121&gt;Waddy, p.121&lt;/ref&gt; By forming a defensive perimeter around Oosterbeek and securing the Driel [[pontoon (boat)|ferry crossing]], Urquhart hoped to hold out until XXX Corps could reach them and establish a new bridgehead over the Rhine.&lt;ref name=Waddy121/&gt;

The eastern side of this new perimeter was fairly stable after the previous day's retreat from Arnhem, with numerous ''ad hoc'' units under company commanders defending the approaches to Oosterbeek. Major [[Richard Lonsdale]] had taken command of the outlying units and their positions weathered heavy German attacks before falling back to the main divisional perimeter.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.134&lt;/ref&gt; This sector was later designated Lonsdale Force and would remain the main line of defence on the south eastern perimeter.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy. p.135&lt;/ref&gt; The Border Regiment held most of the western edge of the town, with scattered units filling the gaps to the north. As more units fell back to the new defensive area, they were re-organised to establish a thumb-shaped perimeter using the Nederrijn as its southern base.&lt;ref name= "Middlebrook, p339"&gt;Middlebrook, p.339&lt;/ref&gt;

The mixed units at Wolfheze began to fall back in the morning but several were surrounded and captured, including one party of 130 men.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.282–286&lt;/ref&gt; 150 men of 156th Parachute Battalion – led by Hackett himself – became pinned down and took cover in a hollow some {{convert|400|m|yd|abbr=on}} west of the Oosterbeek perimeter.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.117&lt;/ref&gt; The men broke out of the hollow in the late afternoon and approximately 90 of them made it to the Border Regiment's positions.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, pp.117–118&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Dutch school being searched for German snipers.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Two men in doorway of bomb damaged building|Men of the [[Glider Pilot Regiment]] search for snipers, 20 September.]]

The afternoon's supply drop was little better than the previous day's. Although a message had reached Britain to arrange a new dropping zone near the Hotel Hartenstein, some aircraft flew to LZ 'Z' where their supplies fell into German hands.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p392"&gt;Middlebrook, p.392&lt;/ref&gt; At Oosterbeek, the Germans had used British marker panels and flares to attract the aircraft to their positions and the aircraft were unable to distinguish the exact dropping zones. Ten of the 164 aircraft involved were shot down around Arnhem&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p392"/&gt; for only 13% of supplies reaching British hands.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, p.12&lt;/ref&gt;

At the bridge, Frost was finally able to make radio contact with his divisional commander and was given the difficult news that reinforcement was doubtful.&lt;ref name="Frost, p229"&gt;Frost, p.229&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterwards, at about 13:30, Frost was injured in the legs by a mortar bomb and command passed to Major Gough.&lt;ref name="Frost, p229"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.311&lt;/ref&gt; Despite their stubborn defence of the few building they still held, by late afternoon the British position was becoming untenable.&lt;ref name=Waddy75&gt;Waddy, p.75&lt;/ref&gt; When fire took hold of many of the buildings in which the wounded were being treated, a two-hour truce was organised in the late afternoon and the wounded (including Frost) were taken into captivity.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.76&lt;/ref&gt; Overnight, a few units managed to hold out for a little longer and several groups tried to break out toward the Oosterbeek perimeter, although almost all of them, including Major Hibbert, were captured.&lt;ref name=ParaData /&gt;&lt;ref name=PegasusArchive /&gt;&lt;ref name=ArnhemAccount /&gt;

By 05:00 on Thursday morning all resistance at the bridge had ceased.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.321&lt;/ref&gt; In the final hours of the struggle, a radio message was sent from the bridge. It was not picked up by the British but was heard by the German forces, who recalled that it ended with the sentences: "Out of ammunition. God Save the King."&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.430&lt;/ref&gt;

===Day 5&amp;nbsp;– Thursday 21 September===
[[File:The vital bridge at Arnhem after the British paratroops had been driven back.jpg|thumb|alt=Litter strewn road looking towards bridge|The Arnhem Bridge after Frost's force had been overrun and the road cleared. Notice the destroyed buildings on the right.]]

Throughout the morning, the Germans mopped up British survivors and stragglers in hiding around Arnhem bridge. It took several hours to clear the bridge of debris allowing German armour to cross and reinforce Nijmegen. Crucially, the British had held the bridge long enough to allow Nijmegen bridge to be [[Operation Market Garden#Nijmegen 2|captured by the 82nd Airborne and Guards' Armoured Division working together]].&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.224&lt;/ref&gt; With the resistance at the bridge crushed, the Germans had more troops available to commit to the Oosterbeek engagement, although this changed suddenly in the afternoon.

Delayed by weather, the parachute infantry battalions of [[Stanisław Sosabowski]]'s 1st (Polish) Parachute Brigade were finally able to take off in England. 114 C-47s took off but 41 aircraft turned back after Troop Carrier Command decided it would be too dangerous to land if the aircraft were up too long. The remainder pressed on; they did not have the correct transmission codes and did not understand the messages.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.403&lt;/ref&gt; One of the few messages to get out of Arnhem warned the Poles that DZ 'K' was not secure and to land instead on the [[polder]] east of Driel where they should secure the Heveadorp ferry on the south bank of the Rhine.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.169&lt;/ref&gt; The Poles dropped under fire at 17:00 and sustained casualties but assembled in good order. Advancing to the river bank, they discovered that the ferry was gone; the ferryman had sunk it to deny its use to the Germans.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.340&lt;/ref&gt;

The arrival of the Poles relieved the pressure on the British as the Germans were forced to send more forces south of the Rhine.&lt;ref name="Evans, p16"&gt;Evans, p.16&lt;/ref&gt; Fearing an attack on the southern end of the road bridge or the Nijmegen road, a battalion of the 34th SS Volunteer Grenadier Division Landstorm Nederland, Machine Gun Battalion 47 and other ''Kampfgruppes'' headed across the river overnight.&lt;ref name="Kershaw, p244"&gt;Kershaw, p.244&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-S73820, Arnheim, britische Gefangene.jpg|thumb|alt=Soldiers surrendering some with their hands in the air other with them on their heads|left|British prisoners at Arnhem Bridge. They are unshaven after four days of fighting&amp;nbsp;– water was scarce during the battle.]]

At Oosterbeek, the defensive positions were consolidated and organised into two zones. Hicks would command the western and northern sides of the perimeter and Hackett, after some rest, the eastern front.&lt;ref&gt;Middelbrook, p.339&lt;/ref&gt; The perimeter was not a complete defensive line but a collection of defensive pockets in houses and foxholes surrounding the centre of Oosterbeek, with the divisional Headquarters at the Hotel Hartenstein at its centre. The perimeter was roughly {{convert|3|mi|km|abbr=on}} around and was defended by approximately 3,600 men.&lt;ref name= "Middlebrook, p339"/&gt; Despite the Germans' best efforts, the line would remain roughly unchanged for the next five days,&lt;ref&gt;Evans, p.15&lt;/ref&gt; although Germans of the Hermann Göring NCO School attacked the Border positions on the west side near the Rhine, forcing them to abandon strategically important high ground overlooking Oosterbeek.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, p.14&lt;/ref&gt; The biggest boost to the besieged British was being able to make contact with forward artillery units of XXX Corps. Radio contact was made with [[64th Regiment Royal Artillery|64th Medium Regiment, Royal Artillery]] who were able to drop heavy and accurate shellfire on German positions around the perimeter.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p124"/&gt; The radio link to the battery's Headquarters was also used as the main line of communication to XXX Corps.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook377&gt;Middlebrook, p.377&lt;/ref&gt; So important was the shellfire provided by 64 Medium Regiment that afterward Urquhart lobbied (unsuccessfully) for the Regiment to be able to wear the airborne Pegasus badge on their uniforms.&lt;ref name= Middlebrook377/&gt;

The British had witnessed the Polish drop but were unable to make contact by radio so a swimmer (Private Ernest Henry Archer) was sent south of the Rhine. The British planned to supply rafts for a river crossing that night as the Poles were desperately needed on the northern bank.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p170"&gt;Waddy, p.170&lt;/ref&gt; The Poles waited on the southern bank, but by 03:00 no rafts were evident and they withdrew to Driel to take up defensive positions.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p170"/&gt;

===Day 6&amp;nbsp;– Friday 22 September===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-590-2333-30, Arnheim - Osterbeek, Soldaten zwischen Häuserfronten.jpg|thumb|alt=One man running across open space while a second peeps around a doorway|German forces in [[Oosterbeek]]. There was bitter house to house fighting around the perimeter.]]

Overnight, the Germans south of the river formed a blocking line along the railway, linking up with 10th SS to the south and screening the road bridge from the Poles.&lt;ref name="Kershaw, p244"/&gt; The Polish were well dug in at Driel, however, and German armour was unable to manoeuvre off of the main roads to attack them. Hopes were raised when three armoured cars of XXX Corps' [[Household Cavalry]] managed to skirt the German defences on the island and link up with Sosabowski's force. These were followed after dark by tanks of the [[4th/7th Royal Dragoon Guards]] and infantry of the 5th Battalion [[Duke of Cornwall's Light Infantry]].&lt;ref name="Evans, p16"/&gt; Behind them, the rest of the [[43rd Wessex Division]] was making its way up a narrow corridor.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.409&lt;/ref&gt;

In Oosterbeek, heavy fighting continued around the perimeter. Intense shelling and snipers increased the number of casualties at the aid posts in the hotels and houses of the town.&lt;ref name="Evans, p16"/&gt; Bittrich ordered that the attacks be stepped up and the British bridgehead north of the Rhine destroyed, and at 09:00 the major attacks began with the various ''Kampfgruppen'' of 9th SS attacking from the east and ''Kampfgruppe von Tettau''{{'}}s units from the west.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p137"&gt;Waddy, p.137&lt;/ref&gt; There were only small gains but these attacks were followed by simultaneous attacks in the afternoon when the Germans made determined moves on the northern and eastern ends.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.147&lt;/ref&gt; To the north, they succeeded in briefly forcing back the King's Own Scottish Borderers before the latter counterattacked and retook their positions.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.148&lt;/ref&gt; Urquhart realised the futility of holding the tactically unimportant tip however and ordered the units in the north to fall back and defend a shorter line.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.349&lt;/ref&gt; To the east, the remains of 10th Parachute Battalion were nearly annihilated in their small position on the main Arnhem road, but the Germans failed to gain any significant ground.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.346&lt;/ref&gt;

Two of Urquhart's staff officers swam the Rhine during the day and made contact with Sosabowski's HQ. It was arranged that six rubber boats should be supplied on the northern bank to enable the Poles to cross the river and come into the Oosterbeek perimeter.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p173"&gt;Waddy, p.173&lt;/ref&gt; That night, the plan was put into operation, but the cable designed to run the boats across broke and the small oars weren't enough to paddle across the fast flowing river.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.410&lt;/ref&gt; Only 55 Poles made it over before light and only 35 of these made it into the perimeter.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p173"/&gt;

===Day 7&amp;nbsp;– Saturday 23 September===
[[File:British paratroopers in Oosterbeek.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Four men in bombed building walking over rubble|British forces move through a ruined building in Oosterbeek.]]

Spindler was ordered to switch his attacks further south to try to force the British away from the river, isolating the British from any hope of reinforcement and allowing them to be destroyed.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p137"/&gt; Despite their best efforts, however, they were unsuccessful, although the constant artillery and assaults continued to wear the British defences down further.&lt;ref name= "Evans, p18"/&gt;

A break in the weather allowed the RAF to finally fly combat missions against the German forces surrounding Urquhart's men.&lt;ref name=Kershaw266&gt;Kershaw, p.266&lt;/ref&gt; [[Hawker Typhoon]]s and [[Republic P-47 Thunderbolt]]s strafed German positions throughout the day and occasionally dueled with the ''Luftwaffe'' over the battlefield.&lt;ref name=Kershaw266/&gt; The RAF attempted their final resupply flight from Britain on the Saturday afternoon, but lost eight planes for little gain to the Airborne troops.&lt;ref name="Evans, p18"&gt;Evans, p,18&lt;/ref&gt; Some small resupply efforts would be made from Allied airfields in Europe over the next two days but to little effect.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.398&lt;/ref&gt;

South of the river, the Poles prepared for another crossing. That night, they awaited the arrival of assault boats from XXX Corps, but these did not arrive until after midnight, and many were without oars. The crossings started at 03:00, with fire support from the 43rd Wessex Division.&lt;ref name= "Waddy, p174"&gt;Waddy, p.174&lt;/ref&gt; Through the remaining hours of darkness, only 153 men were able to cross&amp;nbsp;– less than ¼ of the hoped for reinforcement.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.411&lt;/ref&gt;

===Day 8&amp;nbsp;– Sunday 24 September===
[[File:Two British Airborne troops dug in.jpg|thumb|alt=Two men facing away from the camera armed with Sten guns|Two troopers dug in near Oosterbeek on 18 September, showing the woodland fought in on the western side of the British perimeter.]]

In the morning, Horrocks visited the Polish positions at Driel to see the front for himself.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p174"/&gt; Later, he hosted a conference attended by Browning, Major-General [[Gwilym Ivor Thomas|Ivor Thomas]] of the 43rd (Wessex) Division and Sosabowski at [[Valburg]].&lt;ref name= "Waddy, p174"/&gt; In a controversial meeting in which Sosabowski was politically outmanoeuvred,&lt;ref name="Waddy, p174"/&gt; it was decided that another crossing would be attempted that night.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.414–417&lt;/ref&gt; When the Germans cut the narrow supply road near Nijmegen later that day though, it seems Horrocks realised the futility of the situation and plans were drawn up to [[Withdrawal (military)|withdraw]] the 1st Airborne Division.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.417&lt;/ref&gt;

In Oosterbeek, the situation was becoming more desperate. Hackett was wounded in the morning&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.495&lt;/ref&gt; and had to give up the eastern command. The RAF attempted some close support around the perimeter&lt;ref name="Evans, p18"/&gt; which just held, but shelling and sniping increased casualties by the hour.&lt;ref name="Evans, p18"/&gt; The aid stations were home to some 2,000 men,&lt;ref name="Waddy, p155"&gt;Waddy, p.155&lt;/ref&gt; both British and German as well as Dutch civilian casualties.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p383"&gt;Middlebrook, p.383&lt;/ref&gt; Because many of them were actually in the front line in homes taken over earlier in the battle, the odd situation was created where casualties were evacuated forward rather than rearwards.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p380"&gt;Middlebrook, p.380&lt;/ref&gt; Without evacuation, the wounded were often injured again and some posts changed hands between the British and Germans several times as the perimeter was fought over.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p155"/&gt;
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101II-M2KBK-771-29, Arnheim, Schützenpanzer im Einsatz.jpg|thumb|alt=Man manning machine gune on top of a half track vehicle|left|A 9th SS [[Sd.Kfz. 250|Sd.Kfz. 250 half-track]] in action at Oosterbeek. Notice the supply parachute in the background.]]

Throughout the fighting around Oosterbeek, there had been short localised [[truce]]s around the aid posts to allow the wounded to reach them,&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p380"/&gt; but by Sunday the situation needed a more serious arrangement. Colonel Graeme Warrack—the senior medical officer—asked permission to arrange a truce; it was a request that Urquhart agreed to.&lt;ref name= "Middlebrook, p383"/&gt; Warrack was taken to see Bittrich who similarly agreed and offered Warrack as many supplies as he could carry.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p155" /&gt; Between 15:00 and 17:00, a general ceasefire went into effect around the perimeter and about 450 stretcher cases and [[walking wounded]] were evacuated from the perimeter,&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p383"/&gt; the Germans using jeeps and ambulances to take serious cases straight to Saint Elisabeth Hospital in Arnhem where British, German and Dutch medical staff worked side by side.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p155"/&gt;

That night, the Allies on the south side of the river attempted another crossing. The plan called for 4th Battalion [[The Dorset Regiment]] and the 1st Polish Parachute Battalion to cross at 22:00 using boats and [[DUKW]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.419–420&lt;/ref&gt; Sosabowski was furious at having to give up control of one of his battalions and thought the plan dangerous, but was silenced.&lt;ref name= "Evans, p18"/&gt; The boats failed to arrive until 1&amp;nbsp;am and several had been destroyed or lost ''en route'', so a last minute change of plan mean that only the Dorsets would cross.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.419&lt;/ref&gt; The small boats without skilled crews, the strong current and poor choice of landing site on the north bank meant that of the 315 men who embarked, only a handful reached the British lines on the other side. The DUKWs and most boats landed too far downstream and at least 200 men were captured.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p422"&gt;Middlebrook, p.422&lt;/ref&gt;

===Day 9&amp;nbsp;– Monday 25 September===
{{Further|Operation Berlin (Arnhem)}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-J27757, Arnheim, Sturmgeschütz in den Strassen der Stadt.jpg|thumb|alt=Assault gun parked at the side of the street with houses across the road|A German [[Sturmhaubitze 42|''Sturmhaubitze'' 42]] at Arnhem.]]

Overnight, a copy of the withdrawal plan was sent across the river for Urquhart's consideration.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.160&lt;/ref&gt; Despite the obviously frustrating content, Urquhart knew there was little other choice and radioed Thomas at 08:00 to agree to the plan on the condition it went ahead that night.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.515&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, the Airborne forces would need to endure another day in their perimeter. More men were evacuated from the aid posts throughout the day, but there was no official truce and this was sometimes done under fire.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.156&lt;/ref&gt;

At 10:00, the Germans began their most successful assault on the perimeter, attacking the southeastern end with infantry supported by newly arrived [[Tiger I|Tiger tanks]].&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.424&lt;/ref&gt; This assault pushed through the defenders' outer lines and threatened to isolate the bulk of the division from the river. Strong counterattacks from the mixed defenders and concentrated shellfire from south of the river eventually repelled the Germans.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, pp.140–141&lt;/ref&gt;

Urquhart formulated his withdrawal plan on the successful method used in the evacuation of [[Gallipoli Campaign|Gallipoli]] during the First World War.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.427&lt;/ref&gt; The northernmost units would fall back first, moving through the more southerly groups who would then follow behind.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p161"&gt;Waddy, p.161&lt;/ref&gt; The Glider Pilots would organise the routes to the river and the whole operation would be covered by an intense artillery barrage from XXX Corps.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.421&lt;/ref&gt; South of the river the evacuation was organised and staffed by men of the Royal Engineers of 43rd Division and [[Royal Canadian Engineers]], using rafts and storm boats.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.429&lt;/ref&gt; In order to prevent the Germans from learning about the operation, the plan was not announced until the afternoon and some men (mainly wounded) would remain to lay covering fire through the night.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p161"/&gt; Men were ordered to muffle their boots and weapons to help them bypass known German incursions into the perimeter.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.428&lt;/ref&gt; Some men took the opportunity to shave before withdrawing, providing quite a morale boost.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.519&lt;/ref&gt;

By 21:00, heavy rain was falling which helped disguise the withdrawal. The heavy bombardment commenced and the units began to fall back to the river. Half of the engineers' boats were too far west to be used (43rd Division mistakenly believing the crossing points used by the Dorsets the previous night were in British hands), slowing the evacuation process. The Germans shelled the withdrawal, believing it to be a resupply attempt.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.431&lt;/ref&gt; At 05:00, the operation was ceased lest the coming light enable the Germans to fire onto the boats more accurately.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.433&lt;/ref&gt;

2,163 Airborne men, 160 Poles, 75 Dorsets and several dozen mixed other men were evacuated&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.434&lt;/ref&gt; but about 300 were left on the northern bank when the operation was ceased and 95 men were killed overnight.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p166"&gt;Waddy, p.166&lt;/ref&gt;

Throughout the morning of 26 September, the Germans pressed home their attacks and finally linked up from both sides at the river.&lt;ref name=Kershaw301&gt;Kershaw, p.301&lt;/ref&gt; It was not until about noon that they realised the British had actually withdrawn.&lt;ref name=Kershaw301/&gt; Later in the day, they rounded up about 600 men, mostly the men in the aid stations and those left on the north bank, as well as some pockets of resistance that had been out of radio contact with division Headquarters and did not know about the withdrawal.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.432&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Airborne grave, Arnhem 1945.jpg|thumb|alt=Wooden cross on grave with a steel helmet on top of cross|The grave of an unknown soldier at Arnhem, photographed by a British Army sergeant [[Liberation of Arnhem|after the liberation of the city]] in 1945.]]

The Allies withdrew from the southern bank of the Rhine and the front stabilised on "the island" between the Rhine and Waal rivers. Although the Germans counterattacked in October they were repulsed&lt;ref name= Badsey86&gt;Badsey, p.86&lt;/ref&gt; and subsequently the front line in the Netherlands would not move until after the winter.&lt;ref name="Kershaw, p303"&gt;Kershaw, p.303&lt;/ref&gt; However, the bridgeheads across the Maas and Waal served as an important base for subsequent operations against the Germans on the Rhine&lt;ref name="Shulman, p. 210"/&gt; and the [[Operation Veritable|strike into Germany]].&lt;ref name="Kershaw, p303"/&gt;

The Polish brigade was moved to Nijmegen to defend the withdrawal of British troops in [[Operation Berlin (Arnhem)|Operation Berlin]] before returning to England in early October.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.436&lt;/ref&gt; Shortly afterward, the British began making Sosabowski and the Polish Brigade a [[scapegoat]] for the failure at Arnhem, perhaps to cover their own failings.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook448&gt;Middlebrook, p.448&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Pegasussosabowski&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.pegasusarchive.org/arnhem/stanislaw_sosabowski.htm|title=The Pegasus Archive&amp;nbsp;– Major-General Stanislaw F. Sosabowski|accessdate=22 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 October, Montgomery informed [[Alan Brooke, 1st Viscount Alanbrooke|Alan Brooke]]—[[Chief of the General Staff (United Kingdom)|Chief of the Imperial General Staff]]—that he felt the Polish forces had "fought very badly" at Arnhem and that he did not want them under his command.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook447/&gt;&lt;ref name=Bennett238&gt;Bennett p.238&lt;/ref&gt; Author David Bennett observes that Montgomery had almost certainly been fed gross misinformation that supported his own prejudices.&lt;ref name=Bennett238/&gt; A month later, Browning wrote a long and highly critical letter of Sosabowski to Brooke's deputy.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook447/&gt;&lt;ref name=Sosabowski&gt;{{cite web|url=http://sosabowski.com/mg4.html |title=Lieutenant- General "Boy" Browning’s letter |website=Sosabowski Family Website|date=20 November 1944| accessdate=22 September 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; In it, he accused Sosabowski of being difficult, unadaptable, argumentative and "loth to play his full part in the operation unless everything was done for him and his brigade".&lt;ref name=Middlebrook448/&gt;&lt;ref name=Sosabowski/&gt; It is possible that Browning himself wanted to make Sosabowski a scapegoat, although it may equally have been the work of officers of the 43rd Division.&lt;ref&gt;Bennett, p.237&lt;/ref&gt; Browning recommended that Sosabowski be replaced – suggesting Lieutenant Colonel Jachnik or Major Tonn – and in December the Polish government in exile duly dismissed him in a move almost certainly made under British pressure.&lt;ref name=Pegasussosabowski/&gt;&lt;ref name=Buckingham199&gt;Buckingham, p.199&lt;/ref&gt;

Retired U.S. Army lieutenant colonel [[Carlo D'Este]] wrote: "Sosabowski, an experienced and highly competent officer, was removed because he had become an embarrassment to Browning's own ineptitude. Had Sosabowski's counsel been heeded the battle might have been won, even at the eleventh hour."&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=g72pCgAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT858|title=Eisenhower: A Soldier's Life|first=Carlo|last=D'Este|date=24 November 2015|publisher=Henry Holt and Company|isbn=978-1-62779-961-4|page=858}}&lt;/ref&gt; Although it may be fair to say that Sosabowski was difficult to work with,&lt;ref name=Pegasussosabowski/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bennett, p.235&lt;/ref&gt; his scapegoating is judged as disgraceful by many historical commentators.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook448/&gt;&lt;ref name=Buckingham199/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bennett, p.239&lt;/ref&gt; Brian Urquhart—who had done so much to warn his superiors about the dangers of Arnhem —described the criticism of Sosabowski and the brigade as "grotesque" and that his dismissal was a "shameful act".&lt;ref name=Sosabowskimemorial&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.driel-polen.nl/downloads/folder_monument-sosabowski-uk.pdf |title=The Sosabowski memorial&amp;nbsp;– Extracts from a welcome speech by Sir Brian Urquhart, KCMG, MBE |date=16 September 2006 |accessdate=22 September 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091127213205/http://www.driel-polen.nl/downloads/folder_monument-sosabowski-uk.pdf |archivedate=27 November 2009  }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Arnhem was a victory for the Germans&lt;ref name="Kershaw301"/&gt; (albeit tempered by their losses further south&lt;ref name=Kershaw314&gt;Kershaw, p.314&lt;/ref&gt;) and a major defeat for the British army.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p1"&gt;Middlebrook, p1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Ryan541&gt;Ryan, p.541&lt;/ref&gt; Many military commentators and historians believe that the failure to secure Arnhem was not the fault of the airborne forces (who had held out for far longer than planned), but of the operation as a whole.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.442&lt;/ref&gt; John Frost noted that "by far the worst mistake was the lack of priority given to the capture of Nijmegen Bridge"&lt;ref&gt;Frost, preface p.13&lt;/ref&gt; and was unable to understand why Browning had ordered U.S. Army [[Brigadier general (United States)|Brigadier General]] [[James M. Gavin]] of the [[82nd Airborne Division]] to secure the [[Groesbeek]] Heights ''before'' Nijmegen Bridge.&lt;ref&gt;Frost, p.242&lt;/ref&gt; In his analysis of the battle, [[Martin Middlebrook]] believed the "failure of Browning to give the 82nd US Airborne Division a greater priority in capturing the bridge at Nijmegen" was only just behind the weakness of the air plan in importance.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.444&lt;/ref&gt;

Likewise, in his assessment of the German perspective at Arnhem, Robert Kershaw concluded that "the battle on the [[Waal (river)|Waal]] at Nijmegen proved to be the decisive event"&lt;ref name= Kershaw314/&gt; and that Arnhem became a simple matter of containment after the British had retreated into the Oosterbeek perimeter. After that, it was merely "a side-show to the crisis being enacted on the Waal".&lt;ref name=Kershaw314/&gt; Heinz Harmel asserted that "The Allies were stopped in the south just north of Nijmegen&amp;nbsp;– that is why Arnhem turned out as it did."&lt;ref name=Kershaw314/&gt; Gavin himself commented that "there was no failure at Arnhem. If, historically, there remains an implication of failure it was the failure of the ground forces to arrive in time to exploit the initial gains of the [1st] Airborne Division".&lt;ref&gt;Gavin, p.121&lt;/ref&gt;

The air plan was a major weakness in the events at Arnhem itself. Middlebrook believes that the refusal to consider night drops, two lifts on day 1, or a ''coup-de-main'' assault on Arnhem bridge were "cardinal fundamental errors"; and that the failure to land nearer the bridge threw away the airborne force's most valuable asset&amp;nbsp;– that of surprise.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook443&gt;Middlebrook, p.443&lt;/ref&gt; Similarly, Frost believed that the distance from the drop zones to the bridge and the long approach on foot was a "glaring snag"&lt;ref name="Frost, p198"/&gt; and was highly critical of the "unwillingness of the air forces to fly more than one sortie in the day [which] was one of the chief factors that mitigated against success."&lt;ref&gt;Frost, preface p.12&lt;/ref&gt;

The Allies' failure to secure a bridge over the Lower Rhine spelled the end of Market Garden. While all other objectives had been achieved, the failure to secure the Arnhem road bridge over the Rhine meant that the operation failed in its ultimate objective.&lt;ref name="Kershaw, p303" /&gt; Field Marshal Montgomery claimed that the operation was 90% successful&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.537&lt;/ref&gt; and the Allies did possess a deep [[salient (military)|salient]] into German occupied territory that was quickly reinforced.&lt;ref name="Kershaw, p303"/&gt; [[Milton Shulman]] observed that the operation had driven a wedge into the German positions, isolating the 15th Army north of Antwerp from the First Parachute Army on the eastern side of the bulge. This complicated the supply problem of the 15th Army and removed the chance of the Germans being able to assemble enough troops for a serious counterattack to retake Antwerp.&lt;ref name="Shulman, p. 210"&gt;Shulman, p.210&lt;/ref&gt; [[Chester Wilmot]] agreed with this, claiming that the salient was of immense tactical value for the purpose of driving the Germans from the area south of the Maas and removing the threat of an immediate counterattack against Antwerp.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmot, p.523&lt;/ref&gt; Kershaw views the situation differently, observing that the north flank of the west wall was not turned and the 15th Army was able to escape. Dr. John Warren of the American Historical Division of the [[United States Air Force]] believed that the Allies now controlled a salient leading nowhere.&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.532&lt;/ref&gt; [[John Waddy (British Army officer)|John Waddy]] is of the belief that the strategic and tactical debate of Market Garden will never be resolved.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.9&lt;/ref&gt;

Arnhem was described as "a tactical change of plan, designed to meet a favourable local situation within the main plan of campaign" but the result "dispelled the hope that the enemy would be beaten before the winter. [[First United States Army|First]] and [[Third United States Army|Third U.S. Armies]] had already been checked, the former at [[Battle of Aachen|Aachen]] and in the [[Battle of Hürtgen Forest|Ardennes]], the latter at [[Battle of Metz|Metz]] and south of [[Nancy, France|Nancy]]. The failure to outflank the Siegfried Line finally dictated the pause in the general advance which Montgomery had feared", and meant that General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] "turned to Antwerp, which despite the long-delayed capture of [[Le Havre]] on 12 September, of [[Battle for Brest|Brest]] on the 18th and of [[Operation Undergo|Calais]] on the 30th, remained, as the closest, largest and best-preserved of the ports, the necessary solution to the difficulties of supply.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last= Ehrman |first= John |title= Grand Strategy Volume V; August 1943 – September 1944 |year= 1956 |publisher= Her Majesty’s Office |location=   London |page= 528 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Allied losses===
The battle exacted a heavy toll on the 1st Airborne Division from which it would never recover. Three-quarters of the formation were missing when it returned to England, including two of the three brigade commanders, eight of the nine battalion commanders and 26 of the 30 infantry company commanders.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p445"&gt;Middlebrook, p.445&lt;/ref&gt; Some 500 men were still in hiding north of the Rhine, and over the coming months many of these were able to escape: initially in [[Operation Pegasus]].&lt;ref name="Waddy, p166"/&gt; New recruits, escapees and repatriated POWs joined the division over the coming months, but the division was still so much weakened that the 4th Parachute Brigade had to be merged into the 1st Parachute Brigade, and the division as a whole could barely produce two brigades of infantry.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p445"/&gt; Between May and August 1945, many of the men were sent to Denmark and Norway to oversee the [[Operation Doomsday|German surrenders there]]&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p446"&gt;Middlebrook, p.446&lt;/ref&gt; but on their return the division was disbanded.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook447&gt;Middlebrook, p.447&lt;/ref&gt;

The Glider Pilot Regiment suffered the highest proportion of fatal casualties during the battle (17.3% killed).&lt;ref name=Middlebrook439&gt;Middlebrook, p.439&lt;/ref&gt; The regiment was so badly depleted that during [[Operation Varsity]] RAF pilots were used to fly many of the gliders.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.assaultgliderproject.co.uk/GPR.html |title=The Assault Glider Trust&amp;nbsp;– RAF Glider Pilots |accessdate=9 June 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080619170132/http://www.assaultgliderproject.co.uk/gpr.html |archivedate=19 June 2008  }}&lt;/ref&gt; As glider operations were phased out after the war, the regiment shrank and was eventually disbanded in 1957.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook447/&gt;

{| align="left" class="wikitable"
|+Allied Airborne Units&lt;ref name=Middlebrook439/&gt;
|-
!
!Killed in action&lt;br /&gt;or died of wounds
!Captured or&lt;br /&gt; missing
!Safely&lt;br /&gt; withdrawn
!&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Total&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;
|-
|align="center"|[[1st Airborne Division|1st Airborne]]
|align="right"|1,174
|align="right"|5,903
|align="right"|1,892
|align="right"|8,969
|-
|align="center"|[[Glider Pilot Regiment]]
|align="right"| 219
|align="right"| 511
|align="right"| 532
|align="right"|1,262
|-
|align="center"|[[Polish 1st Independent Parachute Brigade|Polish Brigade]]
|align="right"| 92
|align="right"| 111
|align="right"|1,486
|align="right"|1,689
|-
|align="center"|Total
|align="right"|1,485
|align="right"|6,525
|align="right"|3,910
|align="right"|
|-
|}
{{clear}}
{| align="left" class="wikitable"
|+Other Allied losses&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, pp.462–464&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
!
!Killed in action&lt;br /&gt; or died of wounds
!Captured or missing
|-
|align="center"|[[RAF]]
|align="right"|368
|align="right"|79
|-
|align="center"|[[Royal Army Service Corps]]
|align="right"|79
|align="right"|44
|-
|align="center"|[[IX Troop Carrier Command]]
|align="right"|27
|align="right"|6
|-
|align="center"| [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]]
|align="right"|25
|align="right"|200
|-
|align="center"|Total
|align="right"|499
|align="right"|329
|-
|}

{{clear}}

===Axis losses===
[[File:Flickr - Erfgoed in Beeld - Arnhem, John Frostbrug (2).jpg|thumb|alt=Two men in bomd damaged town |upright|Arnhem after the battle.]]

German casualty figures are less complete than those of the Allies, and official figures have never been released.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.167&lt;/ref&gt; A signal possibly sent by II SS Panzer Corps on 27 September listed 3,300 casualties (1,300 killed and 2,000 injured) around Arnhem and Oosterbeek.&lt;ref name= "Middlebrook, p441"&gt;Middlebrook, p.441&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ryan, p.539&lt;/ref&gt; Robert Kershaw's assessment of the incomplete records identified ''at least'' 2,500 casualties.&lt;ref name="Kershaw, p339"&gt;Kershaw, p.339&lt;/ref&gt; In the ''Roll of Honour: Battle of Arnhem 17–26 September 1944'', J.A. Hey of the ''Society of Friends of the Airborne Museum, Oosterbeek'' identified 1,725 German dead from the Arnhem area relating to the time of the battle.&lt;ref&gt;Kershaw, p.311&lt;/ref&gt; All of these figures are significantly higher than Model's conservative estimate of 3,300 casualties for the entire Market Garden area of battle (which included Eindhoven and Nijmegen).&lt;ref name="Kershaw, p339"/&gt;

===Arnhem===
Dutch records suggest that at least 453 civilians died during the battle, either as a result of Allied bombing on the first day or during the subsequent fighting.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p441"/&gt; After the battle, the residents of Arnhem and its surrounding towns and villages were forcibly evicted from their homes, allowing the Germans to turn the north bank of the Rhine into a heavily defended line.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook449&gt;Middlebrook, p.449&lt;/ref&gt; Residents were not allowed to return home without a permit and most did not return until after the war.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook449/&gt; The Dutch homes were then systematically looted, with the spoils being sent to bombing victims in Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Evans, p.21&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans continued to fight Allied forces on the plains between Arnhem and Nijmegen, and the bridge that the 1st Airborne had fought so hard for was eventually destroyed by the Allies to deny German forces its use. On 7 October, it was bombed and destroyed by [[Martin B-26 Marauder]]s of [[344th Bombardment Squadron|344th Bomb Group]], [[USAAF]].&lt;ref name=Middlebrook449/&gt; The buildings of Arnhem were heavily shelled by the Allies over the next few months and suffered further when the city was eventually [[Liberation of Arnhem|liberated in April 1945]].&lt;ref name=Middlebrook449/&gt;

==Honours and memorials==
[[File:Airbornemonument op het Jacob Groenewoudplantsoen.jpg|thumb|alt=Colour picture of memorial with the bridge in the background|right|The [[John Frost Bridge]], seen from a nearby memorial.]]

Although a disaster for the British 1st Airborne Division,&lt;ref&gt;Ambrose, p.138&lt;/ref&gt; their fight north of the Rhine is considered an example of courage and endurance&lt;ref name="Waddy, p10"&gt;Waddy, p.10&lt;/ref&gt; and one of the greatest feats of arms in the Second World War.&lt;ref name=Ryan541/&gt; Despite being the last great failure of the British Army,&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p1"/&gt; Arnhem has become a byword for the fighting spirit of the British people and has set a standard for the Parachute Regiment.&lt;ref name="Waddy, p10"/&gt; Montgomery claimed that "in years to come it will be a great thing for a man to be able to say: 'I fought at Arnhem'",&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url= http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3663530.stm|title=BBC News: Arnhem veterans remember comrades|date=17 September 2004| accessdate=11 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; a prediction seemingly borne out by the pride of soldiers who took part, and the occasional desire of those who did not to claim that they were there.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.451&lt;/ref&gt;

Within days of Operation Berlin, the British returned to a heroes' welcome in England.&lt;ref name= Badsey86/&gt; A list of 59 decorations was quickly published for the 2,000 men who had returned and an investiture ceremony for the division was held at Buckingham Palace in December.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p446" /&gt; Decorations for the 6000 who had not returned were not published until September 1945 and numbered only 25.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p446"/&gt;

Five of the British participants in the battle were awarded Britain's highest award for gallantry, the [[Victoria Cross]]. Four were members of the Airborne forces and one was from the [[RAF]]. They were:
* [[Lance-Sergeant]] [[John Daniel Baskeyfield]], 2nd Battalion, [[South Staffordshire Regiment]]
* [[Major (United Kingdom)|Major]] [[Robert Henry Cain]], 2nd Battalion, [[South Staffordshire Regiment]]
* [[Flight Lieutenant]] [[David Lord|David Samuel Anthony Lord]] [[No. 271 Squadron RAF|271 Squadron]], [[Royal Air Force]]
* [[Captain (British Army and Royal Marines)|Captain]] [[Lionel Queripel|Lionel Ernest Queripel]], [[10th Parachute Battalion (United Kingdom)|10th Battalion, Parachute Regiment]]
* [[Lieutenant (British Army and Royal Marines)|Lieutenant]] [[John Hollington Grayburn]], [[2nd Battalion, Parachute Regiment]]

The British and Commonwealth system of [[battle honours]] recognised participation in fighting at Arnhem in 1956, 1957 and 1958 by the award of the battle honour '''Arnhem 1944''' to six units.&lt;ref&gt;Rodger, p.251&lt;/ref&gt;

After the liberation of the Netherlands, the Grave Registration units of 2nd Army began the task of identifying the British dead.&lt;ref&gt;Waddy, p.190&lt;/ref&gt; They were buried together in a field that is on permanent loan to the [[Commonwealth War Graves Commission]] just north of Oosterbeek. There are nearly 1,800 graves in what is now known as the [[Airborne Cemetery]], ¾ of which are for those killed during the 1944 battle.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.469&lt;/ref&gt; By 2003, there were still 138 men unaccounted for and human remains, equipment and weaponry continue to be dug up in the farmland around the city.&lt;ref&gt;Steer, p.141&lt;/ref&gt;

In Germany, the battle was treated as a great victory&lt;ref&gt;Frost, p.235&lt;/ref&gt; and afterward no fewer than eight men were awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.defendingarnhem.com/Awardwinners.htm|title=Defending Arnhem&amp;nbsp;– Award Winners| accessdate=22 September 2009| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20090913170014/http://www.defendingarnhem.com/Awardwinners.htm| archivedate= 13 September 2009 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The German dead were gathered together and buried in the ''SS Heroes Cemetery'' near Arnhem, but after the war they were reburied in [[Ysselsteyn]].&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.450&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Airborne Museum Hartenstein.jpg|thumb|alt=White building with law in front and flagpoles with flags flying|left|The [[Airborne Museum (Oosterbeek)|Airborne Museum]] at the Hotel Hartenstein.]]

The shattered Arnhem road bridge was briefly replaced by a succession of [[Bailey bridge]]s before being rebuilt in the same style as the original. It was [[John Frost Bridge|renamed John Frostbrug]] (literally John Frost Bridge) on 17 December 1977.&lt;ref&gt;Frost, preface p.16&lt;/ref&gt;

On 31 May 2006, HM [[Queen Beatrix]] of the Netherlands conferred two honours on the Polish forces who fought at the battle. The Polish 1st Independent Airborne Brigade was awarded the Dutch [[Military William Order]] for gallantry and Stanisław Sosabowski was posthumously awarded the [[Bronze Lion]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.lintjes.nl/_en/militaire_willemsorde/mwo_polen.html |title=Royal Honours&amp;nbsp;– Military williams Order for Poles |accessdate=16 September 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110716063500/http://www.lintjes.nl/_en/militaire_willemsorde/mwo_polen.html |archivedate=16 July 2011  }}&lt;/ref&gt; In February of that year, an appeal was launched to raise funds so that a memorial to General Sosabowski and the brigade could be erected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.driel-polen.nl/uk/index-uk.htm |title=Stichting Driel-Polen&amp;nbsp;– The Sosabowski Memorial |accessdate=22 September 2009 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120227062045/http://www.driel-polen.nl/uk/index-uk.htm |archivedate=27 February 2012  }}&lt;/ref&gt; The memorial was unveiled in September 2006 in a ceremony that sought to undo the injustice of 1944.&lt;ref name=Sosabowskimemorial/&gt;

The Hotel Hartenstein, used by Urquhart as his Headquarters, is now the home of the [[Airborne Museum (Oosterbeek)|Airborne Museum]]. Several other memorials were built in Arnhem and Oosterbeek, and an [[Airborne March|annual parade]] is held in the area. A memorial near the museum reads: "To the People of Gelderland; 50 years ago British and Polish Airborne soldiers fought here against overwhelming odds to open the way into Germany and bring the war to an early end. Instead we brought death and destruction for which you have never blamed us. This stone marks our admiration for your great courage remembering especially the women who tended our wounded. In the long winter that followed your families risked death by hiding Allied soldiers and Airmen while members of the resistance led many to safety."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldwar2.be/World_War_II,_analyzed!/Monuments_Arnhem.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20111007235259/http://www.worldwar2.be/World_War_II,_analyzed!/Monuments_Arnhem.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=7 October 2011 |title=Monuments in Arnhem|accessdate=7 July 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
[[File:War correspondent typing his despatch.jpg|thumb|alt=Two men in woods one with a type writer|Alan Wood, [[war correspondent]] for the ''[[Daily Express]]'', types a dispatch during the battle. Behind him is Sergeant Lewis of the [[Army Film and Photographic Unit]].]]

The progress of the battle was widely reported in the British press,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.hill107.net/?page_id=66|title=Hill 107&amp;nbsp;– Arnhem Newspapers|accessdate=23 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; thanks largely to the efforts of two [[BBC]] reporters ([[Stanley Maxted]] and [[Guy Byam]]) and three journalists (newspaper reporters Alan Wood of the ''[[Daily Express]]'' and Jack Smyth of [[Reuters]]) who accompanied the British forces.&lt;ref name=Middlebrook68&gt;Middlebrook, p.68&lt;/ref&gt; The journalists had their reports sent back almost daily&amp;nbsp;– ironically making communication with London at a time when Divisional Signals had not.&lt;ref&gt;Middlebrook, p.164&lt;/ref&gt; The division was also accompanied by a three-man team from the [[Army Film and Photographic Unit]] who recorded much of the battle&lt;ref name=Middlebrook68/&gt;&amp;nbsp;– including many of the images on this page.

In 1945, Louis Hagen, a Jewish refugee from Germany and a British army glider pilot present at the battle, wrote ''Arnhem Lift'', believed to be the first book published about the events at Arnhem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pegasusarchive.org/arnhem/louis_hagen.htm |title= Sergeant Louis Edmund Hagen|publisher=Pegasus Archive|accessdate=11 October 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; In the same year filming began for the [[war movie]] ''[[Theirs is the Glory]]'', which featured some original footage and used 120 Arnhem veterans as extras in most of the other scenes.&lt;ref name="Middlebrook, p446"/&gt; In 1974 [[Cornelius Ryan]]'s book ''[[A Bridge Too Far (book)|A Bridge Too Far]]'', brought the battle to a wider audience,&lt;ref&gt;Frost, p.251&lt;/ref&gt; as did [[Richard Attenborough]]'s adaptation of the book into the [[A Bridge Too Far (film)|film of the same name]] in 1977. Frost, Urquhart and Arnhem veteran [[John Waddy (British Army officer)|John Waddy]] were hired as military consultants.&lt;ref&gt;Goldman&lt;/ref&gt;

English author [[Richard Adams]], himself an officer in the sea tail of 250th (Airborne) Light Company, Royal Army Service Corps, based the struggle of the [[Anthropomorphism|anthropomorphised]] rabbits in his award-winning 1972 novel ''[[Watership Down]]'' (adapted into an [[Watership Down (film)|animated film]] in 1978) on the adventures of the officers of the 250 Company of the 1st Airborne Division at Arnhem.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.neatorama.com/2012/05/18/10-facts-you-might-not-know-about-watership-down/#!oMVxX|title=10 Facts You Might Not Know about Watership Down|last1=Farrier|first1=John|date=18 May 2012|accessdate=28 June 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Arnhem Oosterbeek War Cemetery]]
* [[Operation Fustian]], 1st Parachute Brigade's previous airborne operation during the [[Invasion of Sicily]].
* [[Operation Ladbroke]], 1st Airlanding Brigade's operation during the Invasion of Sicily.
* [[Operation Pegasus]], the escape of several Arnhem survivors a month after the battle.
* [[Liberation of Arnhem|Second Battle of Arnhem]], the April 1945 liberation of the city.
* [[William of Orange (pigeon)]]

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book|first=Stephen|last=Ambrose|authorlink=Stephen Ambrose|title=Band of Brothers| publisher=Pocket Books &amp; Design|year=1992|isbn=0-7434-2990-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Badsey|first=Stephen|title=Arnhem 1944, Operation Market Garden|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=1993|isbn=1-85532-302-8}}
* {{cite book|first=David|last=Bennett|title=A Magnificent Disaster|publisher=Casemate|year=2008|isbn=978-1-932033-85-4}}
* {{cite book|first=William|last=Buckingham|title=Arnhem 1944| publisher=Temps Publishing|year=2002|isbn=0-7524-1999-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Evans|first=Martin|title=The Battle for Arnhem|publisher=Pitkin|year= 1998|isbn=0-85372-888-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Frost|first=Major General John|title=A Drop Too Many|authorlink=John Dutton Frost |publisher=Cassell|year=1980|isbn=0-85052-927-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Gavin|first=Major General James|authorlink=James M. Gavin|title=Airborne Warfare| year=1947|publisher=Infantry Journal Press|isbn=0-89839-029-X}}
* {{cite book|last = Goldman| first = William | authorlink = William Goldman| title = William Goldman's Story of a Bridge Too Far| publisher=[[Coronet Books]]|year = 1977| isbn = 0-340-22340-5 }} [NB: Book has no page numbers]
* {{cite book|first=Robert|last=Kershaw|title=It Never Snows in September|publisher=Ian Allan Publishing|year=1990|isbn=0-7110-2167-8}}
* {{cite book|first=Martin|last=Middlebrook|authorlink=Martin Middlebrook|title=Arnhem 1944: The Airborne Battle|publisher=Viking|year=1994|isbn=0-670-83546-3}}
* {{cite book | last = Rodger | first = Alexander | year = 2003 | title = Battle Honours of the British Empire and Commonwealth Land Forces | publisher=The Crowood Press | location = Marlborough | isbn = 1-86126-637-5}}
* {{cite book|first=Cornelius|last=Ryan|title=[[A Bridge Too Far (book)|A Bridge Too Far]]| authorlink = Cornelius Ryan |publisher=Wordsworth Editions|year=1999|origyear=1974|isbn= 1-84022-213-1}}
* {{cite book| first=Milton|last=Shulman|authorlink=Milton Shulman| title=Defeat in the West|publisher=Cassell|year=2004| origyear=1947| isbn=0-304-36603-X}}
* {{cite book|first=Frank|last=Steer|title=Battleground Europe&amp;nbsp;– Market Garden. Arnhem&amp;nbsp;– The Bridge |publisher=Leo Cooper|year=2003|isbn=0-85052-939-5}}
* {{cite book|first=John|last=Waddy|authorlink=John Waddy (British Army officer)|title=A Tour of the Arnhem Battlefields|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword Books Limited|year=1999|isbn=0-85052-571-3}}
* {{cite book|first=Chester|last=Wilmot|authorlink=Chester Wilmot| title=The Struggle For Europe|publisher=Wordsworth Editions|year=1997|origyear=1952|isbn= 1-85326-677-9}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110721222924/http://www.market-garden.info/ Operation Market Garden] Battle of Arnhem books and photos
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100818084212/http://www.paradata.org.uk/events/arnhem-operation-market-garden Paradata&amp;nbsp;– Arnhem] The Official [https://web.archive.org/web/20090626175417/http://airborneassault.org.uk/home/html/index.html Airborne Assault Museum] online archive.
* [http://www.pegasusarchive.org/arnhem/frames.htm The Pegasus Archive] Comprehensive information about the battle and Allied units.
* [http://www.hill107.net/ Hill 107] Source material relating to the events at Arnhem.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090203172116/http://defendingarnhem.com/index.htm Defending Arnhem] Information about the German defenders of Arnhem.
* [http://www.historynet.com/operation-market-garden-last-stand-at-an-anhem-schoolhouse.htm Historynet: Last stand at an Arnhem Schoolhouse] An account of the fighting at the bridge.
* [http://www.holland-cycling.com/where-to-go/day-trips/93-arnhem-airborne-cycle-route.html Arnhem Airborne Cycle Route] Cycle route past the major landmarks of the Battle of Arnhem
* [http://www.airbornewandeltocht.nl/en/ The Airborne March at Oosterbeek] The world largest one day march in commemoration of the Battle of Arnhem – Every first Saturday in September

{{subject bar
| portal1=World War II
| portal2=Military of Germany
| portal3=Netherlands
| portal4=United Kingdom
| commons=y
| commons-search=Category:Battle of Arnhem
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Arnhem, Battle of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944|Battle of Arnhem]]
[[Category:1944 in the Netherlands|Battle of Arnhem]]
[[Category:Battles in Gelderland]]
[[Category:Arnhem|Battle of Arnhem]]
[[Category:Overbetuwe|Battle of Arnhem]]
[[Category:Renkum|Battle of Arnhem]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]
[[Category:Military history of the Netherlands during World War II]]
[[Category:Glider Pilot Regiment operations]]
[[Category:Parachute Regiment (United Kingdom)]]
[[Category:Operation Market Garden|Battle of Arnhem]]
[[Category:September 1944 events]]
[[Category:Western European Campaign (1944–1945)]]
[[Category:Last stand battles|Arnhem]]</text><sha1>8l7tauf6zhn7gjo56y9izlls98rkzka</sha1></revision></page>