<page><title>Battle of Crucifix Hill</title><ns>0</ns><id>8105200</id><revision><id>941288620</id><parentid>922232114</parentid><timestamp>2020-02-17T18:19:22Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>66.31.196.226</ip></contributor><comment>grammar, usage</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="4921" xml:space="preserve">{{more footnotes|date=October 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict 
|conflict=Battle of Crucifix Hill
|partof=[[World War II]]
|image=Aachen -Haarener Kreuz- 1939 by-RaBoe.jpg
|caption=&lt;noinclude&gt;German soldiers on the hill.&lt;/noinclude&gt;
|date=8 October 1944
|place={{coord|50|47|57.63|N|6|8|21.9|E|type:event|display=inline,title}}&lt;br/&gt;[[Aachen|Aachen, Germany]]
|result= American victory
|combatant2={{flag|United States|1912}}
|combatant1={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|commander2=[[Henry G. Leonard, Jr]].
|commander1=[[Gerhard Wilck]] 
}}
{{Campaignbox Siegfried Line}}

The '''Battle of Crucifix Hill''' was a [[World War II]] battle that took place on 8 October 1944, on Crucifix Hill (Haarberg, Hill 239), next to the village of [[Haaren (Aachen)|Haaren]] in Germany and was a part of the U.S. 1st Division's campaign to seize [[Aachen|Aachen, Germany]]. The [[Battle of Aachen]] was part of the [[Drive to the Siegfried Line]]. The hill was named after a large [[crucifix]] mounted on the top of the hill. The objective of the battle was to gain control of the hill, which was laced with a maze of [[Pillbox (military)|pillboxes]] and [[bunker]]s, so that the main objective of encircling Aachen could be completed. The hill was held by units of the [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[246th Volksgrenadier Division (Wehrmacht)|246. ''Volksgrenadierdivision'']].

==Battle==
The U.S. [[18th Infantry Regiment (United States)|18th Infantry Regiment]], [[1st Infantry Division (U.S.)|1st Infantry Division]], commanded by Col. George A. Smith Jr., directed its 1st Battalion (commanded by Lt. Col. Henry G. Leonard, Jr.) to take the hill employing special pillbox assault teams equipped with [[flamethrower]]s, [[Bangalore torpedo]]es, and demolition charges. A battery of tank destroyers and self-propelled guns were to provide supporting direct fire at the pillboxes. As the leading rifle [[platoon]] of C Company assaulted the first pillbox, flanking fire from a nearby pillbox gun emplacement took the platoon in crossfire. The pinned-down soldiers also experienced an intense artillery barrage on their exposed positions. Capt. [[Bobbie E. Brown]] was the company commander of C Company, a former boxer who had earned a battlefield commission in [[Operation Overlord|Normandy]]. During the onslaught of the nearby pillbox, Capt. Brown grabbed a [[pole charge]] and ran {{convert|100|yd|m|abbr=on}} under enemy fire and placed the charge in the pillbox, destroying it. He did this twice more to two other pillboxes, each time successfully destroying the pillbox; only on the third one was he wounded by a [[Mortar (weapon)|mortar]] round. Although he was wounded, he refused medical attention and continued up the hill. After the hill was secure, he went by himself on a  [[reconnaissance]] mission to locate enemy troops beyond the hill. He deliberately drew the enemy fire to find out where enemy emplacements were. While doing this, he was wounded twice more. The information he discovered about German emplacements allowed his company to repel two German counterattacks. Only after the position was completely secure did he allow treatment for his wounds. For his actions during the Battle of Crucifix Hill, Capt. Brown received the [[Medal of Honor]].&lt;ref&gt;Whitlock (2008), pp. 40–41&lt;/ref&gt;

==Attempted recapture==
On 12 October, two German infantry regiments attempted to retake Crucifix Hill. In fierce fighting the Germans temporarily took control of the hill, but were dislodged by the end of the day, with both regiments virtually destroyed.&lt;ref&gt;Yeide (2005), pp. 81–82&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
*In the 2005 video game [[Call of Duty 2 Big Red One]], the main protagonist and his squad fight for the summit of Hill 239 in the level "Crucifix Hill".

==See also==
*[[List of military engagements of World War II]]
*[[Battle of Aachen]]
*[[Battle of Hurtgen Forest]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
*Schur, Keith. [https://web.archive.org/web/20060320191315/http://www.wargamer.com/gamesdepot/details.asp?sid=172 "Combat Mission: Crucifix Hill."] Games Depot. 20 May 2003. Wargamer Publishing, Inc.. 24 Nov 2006
*{{cite book|chapterurl=http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/Siegfried/Siegfried%20Line/siegfried-ch12.htm|chapter=CHAPTER XII Closing the Circle|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]|year=25 Nov 2006|id=}}

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070625091914/https://www.infantry.army.mil/museum/inside_tour/photo_tour/40_case01.htm National Infantry Museum Medal of Honor of Captain Bobbie E. Brown]

[[Category:Conflicts in 1944|Crucifix Hill]]
[[Category:1944 in Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States|Crucifix Hill 1944]]
[[Category:Allied advance from Paris to the Rhine|Crucifix Hill]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany|Crucifix Hill 1944]]
[[Category:October 1944 events]]
[[Category:History of Aachen]]</text><sha1>goewvpsyqy9896vadhclayt9kivcpl3</sha1></revision></page>