<page><title>Battle of Overloon</title><ns>0</ns><id>6593273</id><revision><id>963377421</id><parentid>963374504</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-19T13:47:55Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Eastfarthingan</username><id>11187569</id></contributor><minor /><comment>inline coord</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="9099" xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=December 2009}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Overloon
|partof=[[World War II]]
| image= The British Army in North-west Europe 1944-45 B10821.jpg
| image_size = 300
|caption=Churchill tanks with infantry advance during the attack by [[3rd Division (United Kingdom)|3rd Division]] on a German pocket near Overloon, 14 October 1944.
|date=30 September – 18 October 1944
|place=[[Overloon]], [[Netherlands]]
|coordinates={{Coord|51|34|13|N|5|57|30|E|type:event|display=inline}}
|result=Allied victory
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br /&gt;{{Flag|United States|1912}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1={{Flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Lashmer Whistler]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Lindsay McDonald Sylvester]]
|commander2={{Flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Kurt Student]]
|strength1=2 divisions
|strength2= 1 division?
|casualties1=1,878 men&lt;br /&gt;3 aircraft&lt;br /&gt;40 tanks
|casualties2=600 infantry&lt;br /&gt;unknown number of tanks
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Siegfried Line}}{{Campaignbox Liberation of the Netherlands}}
}}
The '''Battle of Overloon''' was a battle fought in the [[World War II|Second World War]] battle between [[Allies of World War II|Allied forces]] and the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German Army]] which took place in and around the village of [[Overloon]] in the south-east of the [[Netherlands]] between 30 September and 18 October 1944. The battle, which resulted in an Allied victory, ensued after the Allies launched ''Operation Aintree''. The Allies went on to liberate the town of [[Venray]].

==Background==
In September 1944, the Allies had launched [[Operation Market Garden]], a major offensive from the Dutch-Belgian border across the south of the Netherlands through [[Eindhoven]] and [[Nijmegen]] toward the [[Rhine]] bridge at [[Arnhem]], with the goal of crossing the [[Rhine]] and bypassing the [[Siegfried Line]] in preparation for the final drive toward [[Berlin]]. Allied [[Airborne forces|airborne troops]] were [[Battle of Arnhem|defeated at the Rhine bridge in Arnhem]] and the advance stopped south of the [[Nederrijn|Lower Rhine]], resulting in a narrow [[Salients, re-entrants and pockets|salient]] that ran from the north of [[Belgium]] across the south-east of the Netherlands.

German forces attacked this salient from a bridgehead west of the bend in the river [[Meuse]] (known as ''Maas'' in [[Dutch language|Dutch]] and [[German language|German]]) near the city of [[Venlo]]. The bridgehead was established by retreating German forces who were reinforced with troops arriving from nearby Germany by crossing the Meuse in Venlo. The western edge of this bridgehead ran through the [[Peel, Netherlands|Peel]], a region with [[bogs]] and several canals blocking an Allied advance. The Allies decided to attack the bridgehead from the north, and this meant they had to capture Overloon and [[Venray]], which were on the road toward Venlo.

''Operation Aintree'' (named after [[Aintree racecourse]]) had the goal of securing the narrow salient the Allies had established between [[Eindhoven]] and [[Nijmegen]] during ''Operation Market Garden'' and destroying the German bridgehead west of the Meuse, in preparation for the eventual Allied advance into the nearby German [[Rhineland]].

==Battle==
The battle of Overloon ensued as the Allies in ''Operation Aintree'' advanced from nearby positions south toward the village of Overloon. After a failed attack on Overloon by the [[7th Armored Division (United States)|U.S. 7th Armored Division]], the [[3rd Division (United Kingdom)|British 3rd Infantry Division]] and the [[11th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|British 11th Armoured Division]] took over. The U.S. 7th Armored Division was moved south of Overloon to the Deurne – Weert area. Here they were attached to the [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|British Second Army]], and ordered to make demonstration attacks to the east in order to divert enemy forces from the Overloon and [[Venlo]] areas.

Suffering heavy losses the British captured Overloon and moved towards Venray. The advance on Venray resulted in heavy losses, especially around the Loobeek creek, which was swollen due to heavy autumn rains and was flooded and mined by the Germans. Casualties were heavy here among the 1st Battalion, [[Royal Norfolk Regiment]] which was serving in [[185th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|185th Infantry Brigade]] of the British 3rd Division. During the battle, the village of Overloon was destroyed. In and around Overloon, some 2,500 soldiers died, making it one of the bloodiest battles in the Netherlands during the Second World War. Dozens of tanks, mainly American, were destroyed.

==Aftermath==
Despite the fact that both Overloon and eventually Venray were taken by the Allies, the advance toward the bend of the Meuse near Venlo was postponed. This was due to the number of casualties the Allies had sustained and because troops were needed to secure more essential targets: the [[Battle of the Scheldt|Scheldt estuary]], leading to the vital port of [[Antwerp]] and the west of the province of [[North Brabant]], in between Antwerp and the salient that had been established. The offensive was eventually resumed, and by early December the German bridgehead west of the Meuse was destroyed. [[Blerick]] (near [[Venlo]]) was liberated in the first days of December 1944; Venlo and other districts east of the Meuse were liberated on the 1st March 1945 (during [[Operation Grenade]]). Some days before, [[Wehrmacht]] units had left the [[Maas-Rur-Stellung]] between [[Wassenberg]] (at the river [[Rur]]) and Venlo (at the river [[Meuse]]).

==Remembrance==
The battle of Overloon has become known as the second [[Battle for Caen|battle of Caen]]{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}} due to its ferocity and also as the forgotten battle, because like the other engagements in the Peel area it is not well known in much of the Netherlands.{{Citation needed|date=September 2016}}}

The [[tank]]s and other armoured vehicles which were left on the battlefield have been preserved and in Overloon a museum, which opened in 1946, was erected to commemorate the battle. Today, two museums occupy the original museum grounds, which have been renamed Liberty Park. The [[National War and Resistance Museum of the Netherlands]] focuses on the Dutch experience of war and German occupation between 1940 and 1945. The Marshall Museum holds a collection of armoured vehicles, weaponry and aircraft from the Second World War, much of it left on the Overloon battlefield, and focuses on the battle of Overloon and other military aspects of the Second World War.

Two memorials have been erected on the battle site. On the banks of the Loobeek creek, where it is crossed by the road between Overloon and [[Venray]], stands the Norfolk monument, dedicated to the 1st Battalion of the [[Royal Norfolk Regiment]]. The liberation of Venray is one of their [[battle honour]]s. There is also another memorial in the museum grounds of Liberty Park. (see below).
&lt;gallery class="center" widths="250px" heights="200px"&gt;
Image:Gedenksteen te Overloon.JPG|Memorial to the battle in [[Overloon]]
File:Panzer V Ausf.G Panther of the German 107th Panzer Brigade at the Overloon War Museum, was knocked out by the 2nd Battallion, East Yorkshire Regiment, on 13 October 1944 at Overloon foto1.jpg|Panther tank at the Overloon War Museum, which was knocked out by the 2nd Battalion, East Yorkshire Regiment during the battle
&lt;/gallery&gt;

'''''The text of the memorial:'''''&lt;br /&gt;
'''Dutch:'''
''STA EEN OGENBLIK STIL bezoeker en bedenk dat de grond waarop gij nu vertoeft eens een van de felst omstreden sectoren was van het slagveld Overloon. Bitter is hier gevochten in man tegen man gevechten. Vele jonge levens ontkomen aan de slagvelden van Nettuno en Normandië vonden onder deze bomen hun einde.''

'''English translation:'''
''TAKE PAUSE FOR A MOMENT visitor, and consider that the ground you are now on was once one of the most fiercely contested sectors of the Overloon battlefield. Bitter hand-to-hand combat ensued here. Many young lives, having escaped from the battlefields of [[Battle of Anzio|Nettuno]] and [[Operation Overlord|Normandy]], met their ends under these trees.''

==See also==
* [[Overloon War Museum]]
* [[Kenneth Mayhew]]

==External links==
* [http://www.landmarkscout.com/the-jackal/ LandmarkScout - The Jackal, a churchill tank left behind in the forgotten Battle of Overloon]
* [http://www.landmarkscout.com/tank-driver-bob-dare-the-jackal/ LandmarkScout - Tank Driver Bob Dare recounts the fate of the Jackal in the Battle of Overloon]

{{Commons category|Battle of Overloon}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2017}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Overloon}}
[[Category:Allied advance from Paris to the Rhine|Overloon]]
[[Category:1944 in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany|Overloon, Battle of]]
[[Category:Boxmeer]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:September 1944 events]]
[[Category:October 1944 events]]</text><sha1>e5rij5e6mb7i4wkh9swlllftdd9ejhk</sha1></revision></page>