<page><title>Operation Clipper</title><ns>0</ns><id>6976755</id><revision><id>954881641</id><parentid>954878008</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-04T19:47:52Z</timestamp><contributor><username>AnomieBOT</username><id>7611264</id></contributor><minor /><comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Fact}}</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="17183" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Allied offensive during World War II}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2013}}
{{EngvarB|date=August 2019}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Operation Clipper
|partof=[[World War II]]
|map = CoA Geilenkirchen.png
|Wappengröße = 81
|lat_deg = 50 |lat_min = 57 |lat_sec = 55
|lon_deg =  6 |lon_min = 07 |lon_sec = 10
|image=Tanks near geilenkirchen.jpg
|image_size=300px
|caption=Column of British [[Churchill tank]]s near Geilenkirchen
|date=10–22 November 1944
|place={{coord|50|57|56|N|6|7|19|E|type:city|name=Geilenkirchen|display=inline}}&lt;br&gt;[[Geilenkirchen]], [[Germany]]
|result=Allied victory
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|United States|1912}}
|combatant2={{flag|Nazi Germany|name=Germany}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Brian Horrocks]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Günther Blumentritt]]
|strength1=
|strength2=
|casualties1={{flagicon|United States|1912}} &lt;br&gt;2,000 casualties,&lt;br&gt; (including 169 killed,&lt;br&gt; 752 missing &lt;br&gt;&amp; 500 nonbattle)
|casualties2={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} &lt;br&gt;Killed? &lt;br&gt;Wounded?&lt;br&gt;Captured?&lt;br&gt;Missing?
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Siegfried Line}}
{{Campaignbox Western Europe (1944-1945)}}
{{Campaignbox Western Front (World War II)}}
}}

During the [[World War II|Second World War]], '''Operation Clipper''' was an Allied offensive by the British [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]] (which included the American [[84th Division (United States)|84th Infantry Division]]) to reduce the [[Geilenkirchen]] [[Salients, re-entrants and pockets|salient]] in mid-November 1944. ''Clipper'' was the preliminary to a wider Allied operation, [[Operation Queen]], to gain control of the [[Roer]] valley and [[Battle of Hürtgen Forest|of the Hürtgen Forest]].

Geilenkirchen is situated on the [[Wurm]] River, some {{convert|20|km|mi|abbr=on}} north of [[Aachen]]. The surrounding area is undulating, alternating between woodland, farmland and industrial villages. The area was crossed by a network of passable minor roads, some major roads and a railway line. The Wurm is the major geographic feature.&lt;ref name=us545-6&gt;U.S. History, pp545-546&lt;/ref&gt;

The salient was a German position on the [[Siegfried Line]] (''Westwall'') at the boundary between the British [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|Second Army]] and the American [[Ninth United States Army|9th Army]]. It restricted the movement of Allied forces and was a potential threat.

==The plan==
Anglo-American cooperation was prompted by the availability of British artillery and the specialised armour support of "[[Hobart's Funnies]]" (such as [[Mine flail|flail]] and [[Flame tank|flamethrower]] tanks). A two-pronged attack was planned on the salient and the temporary attachment of the 84th Infantry Division to XXX Corps, avoided problems of divided command.&lt;ref name=us545&gt;U.S. History, p545&lt;/ref&gt; The British part of the operation was coordinated from 13 November to 24 November in a house at ''Laurastraat'' 67 in [[Eygelshoven]] (now [[Kerkrade]]).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.kgv.nl/Laurastraat#British_Headquarters|title=Laurastraat - KGV|website=www.kgv.nl}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The operation was planned to take four phases. First, on 18 November the U.S. 84th Division – commanded by Major General [[Alexander R. Bolling]] – would pass through the troops manning the frontline, advance north-east {{convert|2|mi|km|abbr=on}} and take Prummern and the surrounding high ground, east of Geilenkirchen. Second, at midday, the British  [[43rd (Wessex) Infantry Division]] – commanded by Major-General [[Gwilym Ivor Thomas|Ivor Thomas]] – was to advance and capture the high ground north and west of the town (around Bauchem and Tripsrath). Once done, Geilenkirchen would be virtually encircled, and the 84th Division would occupy the town and its north-eastern suburbs (third phase) before, in the fourth phase, both divisions would advance north-east about {{convert|3|mi|km|abbr=on}}, clearing both sides of the Wurm. The final objectives were the villages of Hoven, Müllendorf, Würm and Beeck.&lt;ref name=us546&gt;U.S. History, p546&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=worcs&gt;{{cite web|last=|first=|authorlink=|title=The Battle for Tripsrath|work= Worcestershire Regiment|publisher=|date=|url=http://www.worcestershireregiment.com/wr.php?main=inc/h_tripsrath|format=|doi=|accessdate=22 Jan 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

For aerial support the operation had aircraft from [[RAF Second Tactical Air Force]] and the [[XXIX Tactical Air Command (Provisional)|XXIX Tactical Air Command]].{{fact|date=May 2020}}

==The defences==
The German defenders consisted of the bulk of the [[176th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|176th Infantry Division]], northwest of Geilenkirchen, and the extemporised [[183rd Volksgrenadier Division (Wehrmacht)|183rd ''Volksgrenadier'' Division]], in the town and southeast of it. [[General of the Infantry (Germany)|''General der Infantrie'']] [[Günther Blumentritt]]—commander of the [[XII SS Corps]] which the 176th and 183rd were subordinate to —had placed the bulk of his artillery in the area.&lt;ref name=us548&gt;U.S. History, p548&lt;/ref&gt;

South-east of Geilenkirchen, deep minefields had been laid from Geilenkirchen to [[Jülich]], via [[Immendorf]] and Puffendorf, about {{convert|10|km|mi|abbr=on}}. The area was at the point where a new section of the ''[[Siegfried Line|Westwall]]'', built while Aachen held out, joined the established defences. ''Westwall'' used the compact, stone-built buildings in the villages, which had been fortified, and purpose-built concrete bunkers.&lt;ref name=us548/&gt;

==The attack==
===Opening moves===
At 06:00, before dawn, on 18 November, giant [[searchlight]]s ("[[canal defence lights]]") of the 357th Searchlight Battery, [[Royal Artillery]] provided hazy indirect light for the mine-clearing flail tanks supporting the infantry. These tanks moved toward the German mine field between Geilenkirchen and Immendorf, but, on the wet ground, mud lessened the flails′ effectiveness and so engineers followed with mine detectors.&lt;ref name=us550&gt;U.S. History, p550&lt;/ref&gt;

After a brief artillery bombardment, the [[334th Infantry Regiment]] advanced through the cleared strips at 07:00 and easily secured the high ground east of Geilenkirchen. The right flank gave some concern to U.S. commanders as a counter-attack was expected and fresh German troops appeared to be in the area; the advance to Prummern was delayed until the flank was secured. When the attack resumed, supported by British [[M4 Sherman|Sherman tanks]], there was steady progress and the regiment′s objectives were achieved by late afternoon.&lt;ref name=us550-1&gt;U.S. History, pp550-551&lt;/ref&gt;

The British attack north and west of the town also achieved its objectives by nightfall. The [[Worcestershire Regiment]] advanced on Tripsrath, capturing its intermediate objectives of Rischden and intervening woods with little opposition and few casualties. The preparatory bombardment had reduced the Germans′ will to resist and rain had exposed much of the minefields. The rain, however, also made it difficult to bring-up armoured support, anti-tank guns and supplies. An unsupported British advance on a copse—using [[Universal Carrier]]s—was engaged by two [[self-propelled gun]]s and forced back, with heavy casualties.&lt;ref name= worcs/&gt;

Despite further counter-attacks and "[[friendly fire]]" casualties, the Worcestershires occupied Tripsrath after dark, aided by artillery, and held most of the village sometimes with Germans as next-door neighbours.&lt;ref name=worcs/&gt;

===Increased resistance===
Given the first day′s success, [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]]′ commander—Lieutenant General [[Brian Horrocks]]—directed that the last two phases—3 and 4—should be combined on the 19th. In order to facilitate this, the U.S. [[84th Division (United States)|84th Division]] continued its advance toward Süggerath, instead of consolidating overnight. A  reconnaissance patrol toward Beeck, however, reported an impending German counter-attack on Prummern by two companies of the [[9th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|9th ''Panzer'' Division]]′s [[10th Panzergrenadier Regiment|10th ''Panzergrenadier'' Regiment]], with six tanks. The night attack was fought off, but the American advance toward Beeck was delayed until just before dawn on the 19th.&lt;ref name=us551-2&gt;U.S. History, pp551-552&lt;/ref&gt; Resistance in Prummern continued until 20 November, when it was finally cleared with the support of British [[Churchill Crocodile]] flamethrower tanks: the adjacent high ground, "Mahogany Hill", which had held out for two days, was finally captured by an American surprise attack on 22 November.&lt;ref name =us552-3&gt;U.S. History, pp552-553&lt;/ref&gt;

On the 19th, the Worcestershires had been denied supply and support by the lack of a usable supply route, but they fought off a counter-attack by the [[104th Panzer Grenadier Regiment]] of the 15th ''Panzergrenadier'' Division. Five Shermans of the [[4th/7th Royal Dragoon Guards]]—equipped for traversing mud—arrived, but four were almost immediately knocked out by artillery and a ''[[Panzerfaust]]''. A second German attack, on Rischden, this time supported by two [[Tiger II]] tanks and two self-propelled guns, was engaged by [[PIAT]]s, anti-tank guns and tanks that had arrived and by flanking fire from Tripsrath and it was beaten off with severe losses for the Germans.&lt;ref name=worcs/&gt;

Events in the Prummern area had made American commanders cautious, particularly as there was now a gap in the American line between the 84th Division and the U.S. [[2nd Armored Division (United States)|2nd Armored Division]] {{convert|1.5|mi|km|abbr=on}} distant at [[Apweiler]]. This was plugged by the temporary attachment of the [[405th Infantry Regiment]].&lt;ref name=us553-4&gt;U.S. History, pp553-554&lt;/ref&gt;

===Geilenkirchen captured===
Geilenkirchen itself was subdued relatively easily by the [[333rd Infantry Regiment]] on 19 November, but the Allied advance suffered from the lack of artillery support which had been held back by the fear of friendly fire incidents, as had occurred earlier in the British sector. Two troops of tanks from the British [[Sherwood Rangers Yeomanry]] provided close support, although they could not make up entirely for lack of artillery. From Geilenkirchen, the advance continued northeast along the Wurm toward Süggerath. Crocodiles subdued the increasing German resistance, especially two pillboxes guarding the road into Süggerath. "A few squirts from the flame-throwers, and the Germans poured out ... The bastards are afraid of those flame-throwers and won’t be caught inside a pillbox ...", said one U.S. company commander.&lt;ref name=us554&gt;U.S. History, pp554&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:British infantry in action in the streets of Geilenkirchen, Germany, December 1944 BU1335.jpg|thumb|left|British infantry in action in the streets of [[Geilenkirchen]]]]

The capture of Geilenkirchen opened a supply route to Tripsrath. German artillery heavily bombarded Tripsrath for the next four days, but, sheltering in basements, the British infantry suffered few losses.&lt;ref name=worcs/&gt; On the other hand, German defenders of the neighbouring hamlet of Bauchem were subdued by a ferociously effective and uniquely concentrated four-hour artillery bombardment on the 20th, and advancing infantry occupied it with no effective resistance.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last= Hart|first=Stephen Ashley|authorlink=Stephen Ashley Hart|title=Montgomery and "colossal cracks": the 21st Army Group in northwest Europe|publisher=[[Greenwood Press]]|year=2000|location=| page=95|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lahfqPgEz_IC&amp;pg=PA79&amp;lpg=PA79&amp;dq=dunkirk+1944&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=bkzlS2YyHE&amp;sig=WnKMvoh9CkS1kqqhC_A2LgTYuQI&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=S45XS-mMGIa80gTd-Pj0BA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ved=0CAYQ6AEwADha#v=onepage&amp;q=dunkirk%201944&amp;f=false|doi=| isbn=0-275-96162-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The lead battalion of the 333rd passed through Süggerath, by-passing determined German strongholds. Augmented by a second, fresh battalion, Süggerath was cleared during the night of 19/20 November. The 333rd Infantry was still over a mile short of its final objective of Würm,&lt;ref name= us554/&gt; but there was the possibility of establishing a coherent frontline with XXX Corps on its left and 334th Infantry Regiment on its right.&lt;ref name=us555&gt;U.S. History, pp555&lt;/ref&gt; The weather, however, intervened.

===Rain intervenes===
Intermittent showers were followed by a downpour on 21 November, turning the fields into mudbaths that rendered the tanks ineffective and vulnerable. The direct road to Würm was mined and an alternative side road was blocked by debris and could not be cleared until a [[bulldozer]] was used. The U.S. infantry attempted to advance but, without tanks, they were beaten back. When the British Crocodiles were able to advance and assault the defences, there was rapid progress, with defenders surrendering. The mud intervened again, however, bogging down the Crocodiles′ armoured trailers. Without their support, infantry attacks on Müllendorf failed, particularly as the German defences had been strengthened by the 15th ''Panzergrenadier'' Division.&lt;ref name=us555-6&gt;U.S. History, pp555-556&lt;/ref&gt;

A flanking attack by the U.S. 405th Infantry Regiment toward Beeck on 22 November similarly bogged down against prepared defences. On the other side of the Wurm, British assaults were also beaten off by strengthened resistance.&lt;ref name=us556&gt;U.S. History, pp556&lt;/ref&gt;

===Operation ended===
Despite the frustrations of 21–22 November, and the failure to capture the final objectives, the purpose of the operation had, in fact, now been achieved. The Geilenkirchen salient had been substantially removed and the U.S. XIII Corps now had room to manoeuvre. The 84th Infantry Division reverted to U.S. command and further attacks were abandoned on the 23rd.&lt;ref name=us556/&gt;

On 23 November, the Worcestershires were relieved by 5th Battalion of the [[Wiltshire Regiment]], who had been holding the village of Birgden for the last 12 days. This was welcome for the Worcester men who had suffered continuous shelling in their forward positions in Tripsrath and Rischden.&lt;ref name=worcs/&gt;

==Order of battle==
===Allied===
British [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]]

:British 214 Infantry Brigade (assigned to the [[43rd (Wessex) Infantry Division|43rd Infantry Division]])
::7th Battalion, [[Somerset Light Infantry (Prince Albert's)|Somerset Light Infantry]] (attacking Niederheid)
::1st Battalion, [[Worcestershire Regiment]] (attacking Tripsrath and Rischden)
::5th Battalion, [[Duke of Cornwall's Light Infantry]] (attacking Hochheid)
::5th Battalion, [[Dorset Regiment]] (detached from 130 Brigade) (attacking Bauchem)
::4th/7th [[Royal Dragoon Guards]]

:U.S. [[84th Division (United States)|84th Infantry Division]]
::333rd Infantry Regiment (attacking Geilenkirchen and Sueggerath)
:::[[Sherwood Rangers Yeomanry|Sherwood Rangers]] (British)&lt;ref name=worcs /&gt;
::334th Infantry Regiment (attacking Prummern and Beeck)
:::Drewforce, two troops of flail and flame-throwing tanks (British)
:::one troop of 357th Searchlight Battery, [[Royal Artillery]] (British)
::405th Infantry Regiment (detached from [[102nd Infantry Division (United States)|102nd Infantry Division]]) (attacking Beeck)

===German===
XII SS Corps
:[[176th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|176th Infantry Division]]
::1218th Grenadier Regiment
::1219th Grenadier Regiment
::1220th Grenadier Regiment
:[[183rd Volksgrenadier Division (Wehrmacht)|183rd ''Volksgrenadier'' Division]]
::330th ''Volksgrenadier'' Regiment
::343rd Volksgrenadier Regiment
::351st Volksgrenadier Regiment
:104th ''[[Panzergrenadier]]'' Regiment (part of the [[15th Panzergrenadier Division (Wehrmacht)|15th Panzergrenadier Division]])
:10th ''Panzergrenadier'' Regiment (part of the [[9th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|9th ''Panzer'' Division]])

== References ==
'''Citations'''
{{Reflist}}
'''Bibliography'''
* {{cite book|last=MacDonald|first=Charles B.|authorlink=|title=The Siegfried Line Campaign|chapter=Chapter XXIII: The Geilenkirchen Salient|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]] |series=US Army in World War II: European Theater of Operations |id=CMH Pub 7-7-1| origyear=1963|year=1990|chapterurl=http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/Siegfried/Siegfried%20Line/siegfried-ch23.htm|url=|doi=|accessdate=22 January 2010}}
* {{cite web|last=|first=|authorlink=|title=The Battle for Tripsrath|work=Worcestershire Regiment|publisher=|date=|url=http://www.worcestershireregiment.com/wr.php?main=inc/h_tripsrath| format=|doi=|accessdate=22 January 2010}}
* {{cite book|last=Wilmot|first=Chester|authorlink=|title=The Struggle for Europe| publisher=Wordsworth Editions Ltd|year=997|location=Ware, UK|pages=566–568|url=|doi=|isbn= 1-85326-677-9}}

==External links==
{{Commonscatinline}}

[[Category:Allied advance from Paris to the Rhine|Clipper]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|O]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany|Clipper]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:November 1944 events]]
[[Category:1944 in Germany]]</text><sha1>1u7wpcx2itk9p8fh3tmgu14dmm0ss2x</sha1></revision></page>