<page><title>Battle of Alam el Halfa</title><ns>0</ns><id>1042635</id><revision><id>957309234</id><parentid>956959868</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-18T05:28:44Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Bilsonius</username><id>6216730</id></contributor><minor /><comment>/* Aftermath */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="34460" xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=March 2016}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Alam el Halfa
|partof=the [[Western Desert Campaign]] of the [[Second World War]]
|image= File:Karte - Schlacht bei Alam Halfa (1942).png
|image_size = 250px
|caption= Map of the battlefield (in German)
|date=30 August – 5 September 1942
|place={{coord|30|40|N|29|10|E|type:event|display=inline}}&lt;br /&gt;Near [[El Alamein]], [[Egypt]]
|casus=
|territory=
|result= British victory
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagcountry|Dominion of New Zealand}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Harold Alexander, 1st Earl Alexander of Tunis|Sir Harold Alexander]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Bernard Montgomery]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Ettore Bastico]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Erwin Rommel]]
|strength1=[[XIII Corps (United Kingdom)|XIII Corps]] ([[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]]):&lt;br /&gt; 4 divisions
|strength2=[[Panzer Army Africa]]:&lt;br /&gt;6 divisions
|casualties1=1,750 killed, wounded or captured&lt;ref name="Watson14"/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;68 tanks&lt;ref name= "Watson14"/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;67 aircraft&lt;ref name="FR"&gt;Buffetaut pp. 90–91&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2=2,900 killed, wounded or captured&lt;ref name="Watson14"&gt;Watson (2007), p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;49 tanks&lt;ref name="Watson14"/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;36 aircraft&lt;br /&gt;60 guns&lt;ref name="Watson14"/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;400 transport vehicles&lt;ref name="Watson14"/&gt;
|campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Western Desert}}
}}
The '''Battle of Alam el Halfa''' took place between 30 August and 5 September 1942 south of [[El Alamein]] during the [[Western Desert Campaign]] of the [[Second World War]]. ''[[Panzer Army Africa|Panzerarmee Afrika]]'' (''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'' [[Erwin Rommel]]), attempted an envelopment of the British  [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]] ([[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Bernard Montgomery]]). In {{lang|de|Unternehmen Brandung}} (Operation Surf), the last big [[Axis powers|Axis]] offensive of the Western Desert Campaign, Rommel intended to defeat the Eighth Army before [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] reinforcements arrived.

Montgomery knew of Axis intentions through [[Ultra (cryptography)|Ultra]] signals intercepts and left a gap in the southern sector of the front, knowing that Rommel planned to attack there and deployed the bulk of his armour and artillery around Alam el Halfa Ridge, {{convert|20|mi|km}} behind the front. Unlike in previous engagements, Montgomery ordered that the tanks were to be used as anti-tank guns, remaining in their defensive positions on the ridge. When Axis attacks on the ridge failed and short on supplies, Rommel ordered a withdrawal. The [[2nd New Zealand Division]] conducted Operation Beresford against Italian positions, which was a costly failure.

Montgomery chose not to exploit his defensive victory, preferring to continue the methodical build up of strength for his autumn offensive, the [[Second Battle of El Alamein]]. Rommel claimed that British air superiority determined the result, being unaware of British Ultra intelligence. Rommel adapted to the increasing Allied dominance in the air by keeping his forces dispersed. With the failure at Alam Halfa, the Axis forces in Africa lost the initiative and Axis strategic aims in Africa were no longer possible.

==Background==
A lull followed the Axis failure in the [[First Battle of El Alamein]] and the [[counterattack]]s by the Eighth Army ([[General (United Kingdom)|General]] [[Claude Auchinleck|Sir Claude Auchinleck]]) in July 1942. At Alamein, the Axis supply position was precarious because the main supply ports of [[Port of Benghazi|Benghazi]] and [[Tobruk]] were {{convert|800|mi|km|abbr=on}} and {{convert|400|mi|km|abbr=on}} from the front and Tripoli—{{convert|1200|mi|km|abbr=on}} away—was almost redundant because of its distance from the front.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 2004, p. 379&lt;/ref&gt; The original Axis plan for the [[Battle of Gazala]] in June had been to capture Tobruk then pause for six weeks on the [[Egypt]]ian frontier to prepare an invasion of Egypt. The magnitude of the Axis victory at Gazala led Rommel to pursue the Eighth Army to deny the Allies time to organise another defensive front west of Cairo and the [[Suez Canal]]. Axis air forces which had been allocated to [[Operation Herkules]], an attack on [[Malta]], were diverted into Egypt.&lt;ref name="Hinsley, pp. 418–419"&gt;Hinsley, pp. 418–419&lt;/ref&gt;

The British in Malta were able to rebuild their strength to resume attacks on Axis supply convoys to North Africa. From mid-August there was a big increase in Axis losses at sea, notably from a reinforced Mediterranean submarine force.&lt;ref name="Hinsley, pp. 418–419"/&gt; At the end of August, the Axis forces had been reinforced by troops flown from Crete but were short supplies, notably ammunition and petrol.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 2004, pp. 338, 379&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Playfair, 2004, p. 392"&gt;Playfair, 2004, p. 392&lt;/ref&gt; There was a recovery in the armoured strength of {{lang|de|Panzerarmee Afrika}} in August, German tank strength rising from 133 "runners" to 234 and the number of Italian runners increased from 96 to 281 (of which 234 were medium tanks).&lt;ref name="Hinsley412"&gt;Hinsley, p. 412&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' strength increased to 298 aircraft from 210 before the Battle of Gazala and the Italian number rising to 460 aircraft.&lt;ref name="Hinsley412"/&gt;

General [[Harold Alexander, 1st Earl Alexander of Tunis|Sir Harold Alexander]]—the new [[Commander-in-chief|Commander-in-Chief]] (C-in-C) of [[Middle East Command]]—had only a short distance from the supply bases and ports in Egypt to the front line but supplies from Britain, the Commonwealth and the United States still took a long time to arrive. By the summer of 1942, equipment receipts began to increase, notably of new [[M4 Sherman|Sherman tanks]] and [[Ordnance QF 6 pounder|six-pounder]] anti-tank guns to supplement obsolete [[Ordnance QF 2-pounder|two-pounders]]. The RAF and associated air forces under command, supported by new American squadrons maintained a considerable degree of air superiority.&lt;ref name="Playfair, 2004, p. 392"/&gt; Sources of military intelligence were integrated and by mid August, British and Allied forces were benefiting from tactically useful information.&lt;ref&gt;Hinsley, pp. 410–411&lt;/ref&gt;

German intelligence had warned Rommel of the arrival of a {{convert|100000|LT|t|lk=on|abbr=on}} Allied convoy bringing new vehicles for the Allies in Egypt; reinforcements for the British would tilt the balance of advantage against the Axis.&lt;ref name="CARVER"&gt;Carver p. 48&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fraser p. 351&lt;/ref&gt; Rommel demanded from the Italian {{lang|it|Comando Supremo}} in Rome {{convert|6000|ST|t|abbr=on}} of fuel and {{convert|2500|ST|t|abbr=on}} of ammunition before attacking at the end of the month but by 29 August, over 50 percent of the supply ships from Italy had been sunk and only {{convert|1500|ST|t|abbr=on}} of fuel had arrived at Tobruk. Rommel had to gamble on a quick victory before the increasing power of the Eighth Army made defeat inevitable. After [[Albert Kesselring]] had agreed to lend some Luftwaffe fuel, Rommel had enough for {{convert|150|mi|km|abbr=on}} per vehicle with the troops and {{convert|250|mi|km|abbr=on}} for other vehicles.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 2004, p. 382&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==

===Plan===
[[File:Italian column moving towards Alam el Halfa.jpg|thumb|left|{{centre|Italian XX Motorised Corps (XX {{lang|it|Corpo d'Armata}}, Generale Giuseppe de Stefanis)}}]]
At El Alamein an attack would have to pass between the coast and the [[Qattara Depression]] about {{cvt|40|mi|km}} to the south and impassable for tanks. The Eighth Army defences were quite strong but Rommel believed that the south end between Munassib and Qaret El Himeimat, was lightly held and not extensively mined.&lt;ref&gt;Watson p. 12&lt;/ref&gt; One account indicated the northern and central sectors of the front were so strongly fortified that the southern stretch of {{convert|15|mi|km|abbr=on}} between the New Zealand "box" on the Alam Nayil Ridge and the Qattara Depression, was the only place where an attack could quickly succeed. Since surprise in location was impossible, Rommel had to depend on achieving surprise by time and speed. By rapidly breaking through in the south, Axis forces might get astride the Eighth Army supply routes, throw it off balance and disorganise its defence.&lt;ref name="FRASER"&gt;Fraser pp. 355–357&lt;/ref&gt;

Rommel planned a night attack to be well beyond the Eighth Army minefields before sunrise. In the north, the XXI Infantry Corps ({{lang|it|[[:it:XXI Corpo d'armata (Regio Esercito)|XXI Corpo d'Armata]]}}, {{lang|it|Generale}} [[Enea Navarini]]) comprising the ''"Trento"'' and ''"Bologna"'' Divisions, the XXXI {{lang|it|Guastatori}} (Troublemakers) Battalion, the German 164th Light Division and elements of the Ramcke Parachute Brigade, was to conduct a frontal demonstration to fix the defenders. The main attack was to be led by the [[15th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|15th ''Panzer'' Division]] and the [[21st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|21st ''Panzer'' Division]] and the [[90th Light Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|90th Light Division]] to the south which would turn north once through the British minefields.&lt;ref name="FRASER"&gt;Fraser pp. 355–357&lt;/ref&gt; The Eighth Army would be surrounded and destroyed, leaving the Axis forces with a promenade through Egypt to the Suez Canal.&lt;ref name="CARVER2"&gt;Carver p. 49&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Stumpf|2001|p=755}}

===Allied defences===

[[File:Alamein1st1942 07.svg|thumb|Alam el Halfa battlefield, August 1942]]
British [[Ultra (cryptography)|Ultra decrypts]] had anticipated an Axis attack&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=Smith |first1=Kevin D. |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=b1rsIQMC-1QC&amp;printsec=frontcover |title=The contribution of Intelligence at the Battle of Alam Halfa|publisher=[[Military Review]] |page=74-77 |date=July-August 2002 |quote=Only a few days before the battle, Ultra confirmed that Montgomery's estimate of Rommel's intentions was correct.}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Harper |first1=Glyn |title=The battle for North Africa : El Alamein and the turning point for World War II |date=2017 |isbn=9780253031433 |page=95}}&lt;/ref&gt; and Auchinleck set out the basic defensive plan with several contingencies for defensive works around Alexandria and Cairo in case Axis armour broke through. On 13 August, command of the [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]] passed to [[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Bernard Montgomery]]. After visiting the front, Montgomery ordered that the contingency plans be destroyed and emphasised his intention to hold the ground around Alamein at all costs.&lt;ref&gt;Watson p. 10&lt;/ref&gt; In the northern sector, just south of Ruweisat Ridge to the coast, [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]] (Lieutenant-General [[William Havelock Ramsden|William Ramsden]]) comprising the [[9th Division (Australia)|9th Australian Division]], the [[1st Infantry Division (South Africa)|1st South African Infantry Division]] and the [[5th Infantry Division (India)|5th Indian Infantry Division]] with the [[23rd Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|23rd Armoured Brigade]] in reserve was deployed behind minefields.&lt;ref name="Playfair, 2004, p. 384"&gt;Playfair, 2004, p. 384&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="FRASER354"&gt;Fraser p. 354&lt;/ref&gt;

[[XIII Corps (United Kingdom)|XIII Corps]] (Lieutenant-General [[Brian Horrocks]]) held the ground south of Ruweisat Ridge. The [[2nd New Zealand Division]] was deployed on a {{convert|5|mi|km|abbr=on}} front south of the ridge in the New Zealand Box, which formed a corner to the main defences with its hinge of the higher ground at Alam Nayil. Since the featureless southern sector was hard to defend against an armoured attack, Montgomery chose to hold lightly the {{convert|12|mi|km|abbr=on}} front from the New Zealand Box to Qaret el Himeimat on the edge of the Qattara Depression, to encourage Rommel to take the bait and attack there. This gap would be mined and wired; the [[18th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|7th Motor Brigade Group]] and [[4th Infantry Brigade and Headquarters North East|4th Light Armoured Brigade]] ([[7th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|7th Armoured Division]]) would cover the minefields but withdraw when necessary.&lt;ref&gt;Fraser pp. 354–355&lt;/ref&gt;

The attackers would meet the main defensive positions when they swung north and approached the Alam el Halfa ridge, behind the Eighth Army front. The bulk of the British medium tanks (in [[22nd Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|22nd Armoured Brigade]]) and anti-tank units were dug in to wait for the Axis attack. Behind the British armour, on the high ground to the north east would be two infantry brigades of the [[44th (Home Counties) Division]] and concentrations of divisional and corps artillery.&lt;ref&gt;Walker 1967 p. 45&lt;/ref&gt; The [[10th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|10th Armoured Division]] had been refitting in the Nile Delta with [[M3 Lee|General Grant tanks]] with the effective {{convert|75|mm|in|2}} main gun and would reinforce the Alam El Halfa position when available. Most of the [[8th Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|8th Armoured Brigade]] had arrived by 30 August and took post to manoeuvre on the left of 22nd Armoured Brigade and on the flank of the enemy's expected advance.&lt;ref name="cgsc1"&gt;[http://www-cgsc.army.mil/carl/resources/csi/hart/hart.asp Roberts and Bayerlein]{{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071021084922/http://www-cgsc.army.mil/carl/resources/csi/hart/hart.asp |date=2007-10-21 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Playfair, 2004, p. 384"/&gt; Once Montgomery had seen the Axis dispositions after the initial advance, he released the 23rd Armoured Brigade, in XXX Corps reserve at the eastern end of Ruweisat Ridge, to XIII Corps, attached to the 10th Armoured Division. By 13:00 on 31 August,  100 [[Valentine tank]]s had moved to fill the gap between 22nd Armoured Brigade and the New Zealanders.&lt;ref name="Playfair, 2004, p. 387"&gt;Playfair, 2004, p. 387&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===30/31 August===

{{Further|Battle of Alam el Halfa order of battle}}

The attack started on the night of 30 August, taking advantage of a full moon. From the start, things went wrong for Rommel; the RAF spotted the Axis vehicle concentrations and unleashed several air attacks on them. [[Fairey Albacore]]s of the [[Royal Navy]] dropped flares to illuminate targets for [[Vickers Wellington]] [[medium bomber]]s and for the artillery;&lt;ref&gt;Watson p. 13&lt;/ref&gt; also, the minefields that were thought to be thin turned out to be deep. The British units covering the minefields were the two brigades of the 7th Armoured Division (7th Motor and 4th Armoured), whose orders were to inflict maximum casualties before retiring. This they did, and the Axis losses began to rise. They included General [[Walther Nehring]], the ''Afrika Korps'' commander, wounded in an air raid, and General [[Georg von Bismarck]], commander of the 21st Panzer Division, killed by a mine explosion.&lt;ref&gt;Lewin p. 157&lt;/ref&gt;

===31 August===
Despite these difficulties, Rommel's forces were through the minefields by midday the next day and had wheeled left and were drawn up ready to make the main attack originally scheduled for 06:00.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 2004, p. 386&lt;/ref&gt; The late running of the planned schedule and the continued harassing flank attacks from the 7th Armoured Division had forced them to turn north into Montgomery's flank further west than originally planned and directly toward the prepared defences on Alam el Halfa. At 13:00, the 15th Panzer Division set off, followed an hour later by 21st Panzer. The Allied units holding the ridge were the British 22nd Armoured Brigade with 92 Grants and 74 light tanks, supported by anti-tank units with six-pounder guns and the artillery of the 44th (Home Counties) Division and the 2nd New Zealand Division.&lt;ref name= "CARVER3"&gt;Carver p. 58&lt;/ref&gt;

The Axis forces had approximately 200 gun-armed tanks in the two ''Panzer'' divisions and 240 in the two Italian armoured divisions. The Italian tanks were mostly obsolete models, with the exception of the [[Semovente 75/18|Semovente da 75/18]], which could defeat Allied medium tanks using HEAT ammunition, which could penetrate 70&amp;nbsp;mm of armour at 50 meters.&lt;ref&gt;Cappellano, p. 35&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans had 74 up-armoured ''Panzer'' IIIs with long-barrelled {{convert|50|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} guns (Pz.Kpfw III Ausf.L) and 27 ''Panzer'' IVs with long 75&amp;nbsp;mm guns (Pz.Kpfw IV Ausf.F2).&lt;ref&gt;Jentz. Panzertruppen 1&lt;/ref&gt; The British had 700 tanks at the front, of which 160 were Grants. Only 500 of the British tanks were engaged in the armoured battle, which was brief.&lt;ref&gt;Liddell Hart 1970 p.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the ''Panzer'' divisions approached the ridge, the [[Panzer IV|''Panzer'' IV F2]] tanks opened fire at long range and destroyed several British tanks. The British [[M3 Lee#British variants|Grants]] were handicapped by their hull-mounted guns that prevented them from firing from ''hull-down'' positions. When the Germans came into range, they were exposed to the fire of the brigade and their tanks were hard hit. An attempt to outflank the British was thwarted by anti-tank guns and with night beginning to fall and fuel running short because of the delays and heavy consumption over the bad 'going', General [[Gustav von Vaerst]], the ''Afrika Korps'' commander, ordered the ''Panzers'' to pull back. During this engagement, the Germans lost 22 tanks and the British 21.&lt;ref name= "CARVER4"&gt;Carver p. 62&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Destroyed British plane.jpg|thumb|British fighter brought down by Italian anti-aircraft fire during the battle.]]
There had also been hard infantry fighting. In the central sector, the Italians of the 25th Infantry Division "''Bologna''" and German Infantry Regiment 433 attacked several Indian, South African and New Zealand units on Ruweisat Ridge, and managed to capture Point 211 but were later driven off by a counter-attack.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lonesentry.com/articles/ttt07/el-alamein-german-attack.html German Attack at El Alamein: August 31 – September 5, 1942" from Tactical and Technical Trends]&lt;/ref&gt; Although the ''[[Official History of New Zealand in the Second World War 1939–45]]'' refers to the Italo-German infantry action as simply 'feints',&lt;ref&gt;Murphy, 1966, p. 358&lt;/ref&gt; Captain [[Cyril Falls]], a British military historian, wrote that it was a strong counter-attack requiring an equal response.{{efn|"In the centre of the British front a good Italian division, the Bologna, delivered a strong attack on the Ruweisat Ridge, and a considerable counter-attack was required to expel it from the footing it gained."&lt;ref&gt;Falls 1948, p. 262&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===1–2 September===
The night of 31 August – 1 September brought no respite for the Axis forces, as the Albacore and Wellington bombers returned to the attack, concentrating on the Axis supply lines. This added to Rommel's supply difficulties as Allied action had sunk over 50 percent of the {{convert|5000|LT|t|abbr=on}} of petrol promised to him by Mussolini.&lt;ref&gt;Lightbody, p. 142&lt;/ref&gt; On 1 September the 21st Panzer Division was inactive (probably because of a lack of fuel) and operations were limited to an attack by the 15th Panzer Division toward the eastern flank of the 22nd Armoured Brigade.&lt;ref name="Playfair, 2004, p. 387"/&gt; The attack started at dawn but was quickly stopped by a flank attack from the 8th Armoured Brigade. The Germans suffered little, as the British were under orders to spare their tanks for the coming offensive but they could make no headway either and were heavily shelled.&lt;ref name="FRASER3"&gt;Fraser p. 359&lt;/ref&gt; The [[133rd Armoured Division Littorio]] and [[132nd Armoured Division Ariete]] had moved up on the left of the ''Afrika Korps'' and the 90th Light Division and elements of Italian X Corps had drawn up to face the southern flank of the New Zealand box.&lt;ref name="Playfair, 2004, p. 387"/&gt; Air raids continued throughout the day and night and on the morning of 2 September, realising his offensive had failed and that staying in the salient would only add to his losses, Rommel decided to withdraw.&lt;ref name="CARVER5"&gt;Carver p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;

====Axis withdrawal====

[[File:Martin A-30A.jpg|thumb|RAF [[Martin Baltimore|Baltimore]] day bomber]]
In a message to {{lang|de|[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]}} (OKW), Rommel justified his decision to abandon the offensive by the lack of fuel, Allied air superiority and the loss of surprise.&lt;ref&gt;Playfair, 2004, p. 388&lt;/ref&gt; On 2 September, [[Armored car (military)|Armoured cars]] of the 4/[[8th Hussars]] (4th Armoured Brigade) attacked 300 Axis supply lorries near Himeimat, destroying 57 and Italian armoured units had to be moved to protect Axis supply lines. In the air the [[Desert Air Force]] (DAF) flew 167 bomber and 501 fighter sorties.&lt;ref name="CARVER5"/&gt; Montgomery realised the ''Afrika Korps'' was about to withdraw and planned attacks by the 7th Armoured Division and the 2nd New Zealand Division (Lieutenant-General [[Bernard Freyberg, 1st Baron Freyberg|Bernard Freyberg]]) under the proviso that they were to avoid excessive losses. The 7th Armoured Division managed harassment raids but the New Zealand Division attacked with the experienced 5th New Zealand Brigade, the new [[132nd Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|132nd Infantry Brigade]] (Brigadier C. B. Robertson) of the 44th (Home Counties) Division under command and tank support from the [[46th (Liverpool Welsh) Royal Tank Regiment|46th Royal Tank regiment]] (46th RTR, 23rd Army Tank Brigade).&lt;ref name="Barr, pp. 245–246"&gt;Barr, pp. 245–246&lt;/ref&gt;

===3–4 September, Operation Beresford===
[[File:Valentine tank Mk3 desert.jpg|thumb|left|A British Valentine tank in North Africa.]]
Operation Beresford began at 22:30 on 3 September. The 5th New Zealand Brigade on the left inflicted many casualties on the Italian defenders and defeated Axis counter-attacks the next morning.&lt;ref name="Barr, pp. 245–246"/&gt; The Axis defenders were alerted by diversionary raids by the 6th New Zealand Brigade (Brigadier [[George Herbert Clifton|George Clifton]]) on the right flank of the 132nd Infantry Brigade which was an hour late arriving on their start line. The attack was a costly failure; the Valentine tanks of the 46th RTR got lost in the dark and ran onto a minefield where twelve were knocked out. The 90th Light Division inflicted 697 casualties on the 132nd Infantry Brigade and 275 casualties on the New Zealanders.&lt;ref name="CARVER7"&gt;Carver p. 70; Playfair, 2004, p. 389&lt;/ref&gt; Robertson was wounded and Clifton was captured by a patrol of the X Battalion of the Italian [[185th Paratroopers Division Folgore|''"Folgore"'' Division]].&lt;ref name="Playfair, 2004, p. 389"&gt;Playfair, 2004, p. 389&lt;/ref&gt; The vigorous Axis defence suggested to Freyberg that another attack was unlikely to succeed and advised that the troops should be withdrawn from their very exposed positions and the operation called off. Montgomery and Horrocks agreed and the troops were withdrawn on the night of 4 September.&lt;ref name="Playfair, 2004, p. 389"/&gt; ''Generalleutnant'' [[Fritz Bayerlein]] wrote later,

{{quote|An attack by our ''Luftwaffe'' against the 10th Indian Div [sic], which was in the assembly area for a counter attack against the centre of the front, caused the units which were assembled there to scatter to the winds. Also, all other attacks launched by other units against our flanks, especially the New Zealanders, were too weak to be able to effect a penetration—they could be repulsed. A night attack conducted against the X Italian Corps resulted in especially high losses for the British. Countless enemy dead lay on the battlefield and 200 prisoners were taken among whom was Gen (sic) Clifton, commanding general of the 6th New Zealand Brigade.|''Generalleutnant'' Fritz Bayerlein&lt;ref name="cgsc1"/&gt;}}

===5 September===
The position north of the New Zealand Division was held by 5th Indian Infantry Division, relieved by the [[4th Infantry Division (India)|4th Indian Infantry Division]] on 9 September. After this failure against the ''Folgore'' Division, the ''Afrika Korps'' retired unhindered, except for attacks by the DAF, which flew 957 sorties in 24 hours.&lt;ref name="FR4"&gt;Buffetaut p. 90&lt;/ref&gt; By 5 September, the Axis units were back almost on their starting positions and the battle was over.{{citation needed||date=July 2019}}

==Aftermath==
[[File:A British soldier inspects the grave of a German tank crewman, killed when his PzKpfw III tank was knocked out in the Western Desert, 29 September 1942. E17549.jpg|thumb|A British soldier inspects the grave of a German tank crewman, killed when his PzKpfw III tank was knocked out in the battle, 29 September 1942.]]
During the Battle of Alam el Halfa, the Allies suffered 1,750 casualties, compared to 2,930 for the Axis. The Allies lost more tanks than the Axis but for the first time in this campaign there was no great disproportion in tank losses. Constant harassment by the RAF cost the ''Panzerarmee Afrika'' many transport vehicles.&lt;ref name=Watson14/&gt; The battle was the last big offensive undertaken by the Axis in North Africa and the superior firepower of the Allies and their mastery of the skies brought them victory.&lt;ref name =Watson14/&gt; There has been criticism of Montgomery's leadership during the battle, especially his choice to avoid losses, which prevented the British tank formations from trying to finish off the ''Afrika Korps'' when it was strung out between the minefields and Alam Halfa.&lt;ref name="CARVER8"&gt;Carver p. 181&lt;/ref&gt; [[Friedrich von Mellenthin]] in ''[[Panzerschlachten|Panzer Battles]]'' painted a dramatic picture of ''Panzer'' divisions, paralysed by lack of fuel, under constant bombardment and awaiting a British onslaught.{{sfn|Mellenthin|1956|p=103}}

Montgomery pointed out that the Eighth Army was in a process of reformation with the arrival of new, untrained units and was not ready to take the offensive. Nor was his army yet prepared for a {{convert|1600|mi|km|abbr=on}} pursuit were they to break through, which had caused both sides to fail to end the desert campaign, after gaining tactical success. Montgomery did not want his tanks wasted on futile attacks against Rommel's anti-tank screen, something that had frequently happened in the past, handing the initiative to the Axis forces. Rommel complained to Kesselring, "The swine isn't attacking!".&lt;ref&gt;Walker, 1967, p. 180&lt;/ref&gt; Montgomery's refusal kept his forces intact and the Eighth Army accumulated supplies for the offensive in October that came to be known as the [[Second Battle of El Alamein]].&lt;ref&gt;Fraser p. 360&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|World War II}}
* [[North African Campaign timeline]]
* [[List of World War II Battles]]

{{clear}}

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==Citations==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Barr |first=N. |title=Pendulum of War: The Three Battles of Alamein |year=2005 |location=Woodstock |publisher=Overlook Press |isbn=1-58567-655-1}}
* {{cite book |last1=Beretta |first1=Davide |title=Batterie semoventi, alzo zero: quelli di El Alamein |trans-title=Self-propelled Batteries, Point Blank of El Alamein |date=1997 |publisher=Mursia |location=Milano |isbn=88-425-2179-5}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Stumpf|2001}}
|last1=Boog |first1=H. |last2=Rahn |first2=R. |last3=Stumpf |first3=R. |last4=Wegner |first4=B. |translator-last1=Osers |translator-first1=E. |translator-last2=Brownjohn |translator-first2=J. |translator3-last=Crampton |translator3-first=P. |translator4-last=Willmot |translator4-first=L. |editor-last=Osers |editor-first=E. |series=Germany and the Second World War |title=The Global War: Widening of the Conflict into a World War and the Shift of the Initiative 1941–1943 (Edited by the Militărgeschichtliches Forschungsamt [Research Institute for Military History] Potsdam, Germany) |volume=VI |year=2001 |chapter=(Part V) The War in the Mediterranean Area 1942–1943: Operations in North Africa and the Central Mediterranean. 2. The Battle of Alam Halfa (30 August–6 September 1942) |pages=748–764 |publisher=Clarendon Press |location=Oxford |language=English |isbn=0-19-822888-0}}
* {{cite book |last=Buffetaut |first=Yves |year=1995 |series=Les grandes batailles de la Seconde Guerre mondiale, Collection hors-série Militaria |number=16 |title=Operation Supercharge-La seconde bataille d'El Alamein |trans-title=Operation Supercharge: The Second Battle of El Alamein |publisher=Histoire Et Collections |location=Paris |language=French |oclc=464158829}}
* {{cite book |last1=Cappellano |first1=Filippo |title=Italian Medium Tanks: 1939–45 |year=2012 |publisher=Osprey  |location=Oxford |isbn=978-1-84908-775-9}}
* {{cite book |last=Carver |first=Michael |authorlink=Michael Carver, Baron Carver |year=1962 |title=El Alamein |publisher=Wordsworth Editions |isbn=1-84022-220-4}}
* {{cite web |first=Carl |last=Conetta |last2=Knight |first2=Charles |last3=Unterseher |first3=Lutz |title=Defensive Military Structures in Action: Historical Examples |date=September 1997 |url=http://www.comw.org/pda/webbtl.htm |work=Confidence-Building Defense: A Comprehensive Approach to Security &amp; Stability in the New Era, Study Group on Alternative Security Policy and Project on Defense Alternatives |publisher=Commonwealth Institute |location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |others=1994 |oclc=45377322}}
* {{cite book |last1=Cox |first1=Sebastian |last2=Gray |first2=Peter |year=2002 |title=Air Power History: Turning Points from Kitty Hawk to Kosovo |publisher=Frank Cass |location=London |isbn=0-7146-8257-8}}
* {{cite book |title=Knight's Cross: A Life of Field Marshal Erwin Rommel |last=Fraser |first=David |authorlink=|year=1993 |publisher=Harper Collins |location=London |isbn=0-00-638384-X}}
* {{cite journal |last=Falls |first=Cyril |title=Aftermath of War: The Eights Army from Alamein to Sangro |journal=The Illustrated London News |volume=212 |issue=5672–5684 |publisher=The Illustrated London News &amp; Sketch |year=1948 |issn=0019-2422}}
* {{cite book |last1=Hinsley |first1=F. H. |last2=Thomas |first2=E. E. |last3=Ransom |first3=C. F. G. |last4=Knight |first4=R. C. |authorlink1=Harry Hinsley |title=British Intelligence in the Second World War. Its influence on Strategy and Operations |volume=II |location=London |publisher=[[HMSO]] |year=1981 |isbn=0-11-630934-2}}
* {{cite book |first=Bradley |last=Lightbody |title=The Second World War: Ambitions to Nemesis |year=2004 |publisher=Routledge |location=London |isbn=0-415-22404-7}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Mellenthin|1956}}
|last=Mellenthin |first=Friedrich Wilhem von |translator-last=Turner |translator-first=L. C. F. |title=Panzer Battles: A Study of the Employment of Armour in the Second World War |year=1956 |publisher=Ballantine |location=New York |oclc=638823584}}
* {{cite book |first=W. E. |last=Murphy |series=Official History of New Zealand in the Second World War 1939–1945 |title=2nd New Zealand Divisional Artillery |publisher=War History Branch |location=Wellington |year=1966 |orig-year=1966 |oclc=226971027}}
* {{cite book |first=Shimon |last=Naveh |title=In Pursuit of Military Excellence; The Evolution of Operational Theory |publisher=Frank Cass |location=London |year=1997 |isbn=0-7146-4727-6 |orig-year=1991}}
* {{cite book |first1=Major-General I. S. O. |last1=Playfair |author1-link=Ian Stanley Ord Playfair |first2=Captain F. C. |last2=with Flynn [[Royal Navy|RN]] |first3=Brigadier C. J. C. |last3=Molony |first4=Group Captain T. P. |last4=Gleave |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=J. R. M. |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |series=History of the Second World War United Kingdom Military Series |title=The Mediterranean and Middle East: British Fortunes reach their Lowest Ebb (September 1941 to September 1942) |volume=III |publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |year=2004 |orig-year=1st. pub. [[HMSO]] 1960 |isbn=1-84574-067-X |lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{cite web |title=U.S. Combat Studies Institute Battle Report: Alam Halfa |first1=Major-General G. P. B. |last1=Roberts |authorlink=George Philip Bradley Roberts |last2=Bayerlein |first2=Generalleutnant Fritz |authorlink2=Fritz Bayerlein |editor=[[Basil Liddell Hart]] |accessdate=5 November 2007 |url=http://www-cgsc.army.mil/carl/resources/csi/hart/hart.asp |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20071021084922/http://www-cgsc.army.mil/carl/resources/csi/hart/hart.asp |archivedate=21 October 2007 |url-status=dead }}
* {{cite book |chapter-url=http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2Alam-c11.html |series=The Official History of New Zealand in the Second World War 1939–1945 |last=Walker |first=Ronald |year=1967 |title=Alam Halfa and Alamein |chapter=Chapter 11, Summary of the Battle |publisher=New Zealand Historical Publications Branch, Wellington |pages=165–181 |oclc=893102}}
* {{cite book |first=Bruce Allen |last=Watson |title=Exit Rommel |publisher=Stackpole |location=Mechanicsburg PA |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-8117-3381-6 |origyear=1999}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last=Montanari |first=Mario |translator-last=Doré |translator-first=Dominique |title=The Three Battles of El Alamein (June–November 1942 Parte Prima |year=2007 |publisher=L'Ufficio Storico dello Stato Maggiore dell'Esercito |location=Roma |url=https://issuu.com/rivista.militare1/docs/africa-occidentale-vol-iii-alamein-english-parte-1 |accessdate=11 December 2019 |edition=online scan abbr. trans, Le operazioni in Africa Settentrionale vol III |via=issuu |isbn=978-88-87940-79-4}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Battle of Alam el Halfa}}
* [https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/ww2peopleswar/timeline/factfiles/nonflash/a1125073.shtml?sectionId=4&amp;articleId=1125073 Fact File: Battle of Alam Halfa ''WW2 People's War''. BBC]

{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Alam El Halfa, Battle of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:1942 in Egypt]]
[[Category:North African Campaign]]
[[Category:Western Desert Campaign]]
[[Category:Egypt in World War II]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving New Zealand]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:August 1942 events]]
[[Category:September 1942 events]]</text><sha1>30fmj497mfpax1i2514l64cdlam3z5j</sha1></revision></page>