<page><title>Siege of Bastogne</title><ns>0</ns><id>886493</id><revision><id>965862055</id><parentid>965680020</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-03T21:01:54Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Davemck</username><id>326639</id></contributor><minor /><comment>Clean up [[:Category:Pages using duplicate arguments in template calls|duplicate template arguments]] using [[:en:User:Frietjes/findargdups|findargdups]]</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="39740" xml:space="preserve">{{more footnotes|date=December 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Siege of Bastogne
|partof= the [[Battle of the Bulge]] ([[World War II]])
|image=Bastogne resupply1944 sm.jpg
|image_size=300px
|caption=101st Airborne Division troops watch as [[Douglas C-47 Skytrain|C-47s]] drop supplies over Bastogne, 26 December 1944
|date= 20–27 December 1944
|map_type=Belgium
|map_size=290
|casus=
|territory=
|place= [[Bastogne]], [[Wallonia]], [[Belgium]]
|coordinates= {{Coord|50.0|N|5.7214|E|format=dms|type:event_region:BE_scale:50000|display=inline,title}}
|result= American victory
|combatant1={{flag|United States|1912}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1=[[Anthony McAuliffe]] (101st Airborne)&lt;br&gt;William L. Roberts (Combat Command B (CCB), 10th Armored Division)&lt;br&gt;[[Creighton Abrams]] (37th Tank Battalion, 4th Armored Division)&lt;br&gt;[[George S. Patton]] (Third Army)
|commander2=[[Hasso von Manteuffel]] (5th Panzer Army)&lt;br&gt;[[Heinrich Freiherr von Lüttwitz]] (XLVII Panzer Corps)&lt;br&gt;[[Wilhelm Mohnke]] ([[I SS Panzer Corps]])
|units1='''Initially parts of:'''&lt;br&gt;[[101st Airborne Division]]&lt;br/&gt;[[10th Armored Division (United States)|CCB of the 10th Armored Division]]&lt;br/&gt;[[9th Armored Division (United States)|CCR of the 9th Armored Division]]&lt;br/&gt;[[705th Tank Destroyer Battalion]]&lt;br&gt;35th and 158th Combat Engineer Battalions&lt;br/&gt;58th and 420th Armored Field Artillery Battalions&lt;br/&gt;755th and 969th Field Artillery Battalions of 8th Corps&lt;br/&gt;Team SNAFU&lt;ref name="Bando P.188"&gt;Bando P.188&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''Eventual Participants:'''&lt;br&gt;[[4th Armored Division (United States)|4th Armoured Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[26th Infantry Division (United States)|26th Infantry Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[6th Armored Division (United States)|6th Armoured Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[11th Armored Division (United States)|11th Armoured Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[35th Infantry Division (United States)|35th Infantry Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[87th Infantry Division (United States)|87th Infantry Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[90th Infantry Division (United States)|90th Infantry Division]]&lt;ref name="Bando P.188"&gt;Bando P.188&lt;/ref&gt;
|units2='''Initially parts of:'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = John C. Fredriksen| title = Fighting Elites: A History of U.S. Special Forces| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=LEqb2gnGq-cC&amp;pg=PA91| year = 2011| publisher = ABC-CLIO| isbn = 978-1-59884-810-6| page = 91 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[26th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|26th Volksgrenadier Division]]&lt;br/&gt;[[5th Parachute Division (Germany)|5th Parachute Division]]&lt;br/&gt;[[Panzer Lehr Division]]&lt;br/&gt;[[2nd Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|2nd Panzer Division]]&lt;br/&gt;'''Total:''' All or parts of 7 divisions&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| author = [[Samuel W. Mitcham]]| title = Panzers in Winter: Hitler's Army And the Battle of the Bulge| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=3ZNVME6-LHAC&amp;pg=PA133| year = 2006| publisher = Greenwood Publishing Group| isbn = 978-0-275-97115-1| page = 133 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''Eventual Participants:'''&lt;br&gt;[[1st SS Panzer Division Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler]]&lt;ref&gt;Bando P.188-189&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;[[Führerbegleitbrigade]]&lt;br&gt;[[12th SS Panzer Division Hitlerjugend]]&lt;br&gt;[[9th SS Panzer Division Hohenstaufen]]&lt;ref name="Bando P.188"&gt;Bando P.188&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength1= [[101st Airborne Division|101st]]: 11,000&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Hatfield| first = Ken| title = Heartland Heroes: Remembering World War II| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=mtxMN5NdmCsC&amp;pg=PA181| year = 2003| publisher = University of Missouri Press| isbn = 978-0-8262-6335-3| page = 181 }}&lt;/ref&gt; enlisted + 800 officers&lt;br&gt;Remaining units: 11,000+&lt;ref name="google188"&gt;{{cite book| last = Bando| first = Mark| title = 101st Airborne: The Screaming Eagles at Normandy| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=NmitTETNSxwC&amp;pg=PA188| year = 2011| publisher = Zenith Imprint| isbn = 978-1-61060-256-3| page = 188 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''Total:''' 22,800+ men (initially)
|strength2=54,000+ men&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last = Ballhausen| first = Hanno| title = Chronik des Zweiten Weltkriegs| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=Y3wFMlgitBIC&amp;pg=PA447| year = 2004| publisher = wissenmedia Verlag| isbn = 978-3-577-14367-7| page = 447 }}&lt;/ref&gt; (initially)
|casualties1=3,000+ total casualties (2,000 in the [[101st Airborne Division|101st]])&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| last1 = Avery| first1 = Derek| last2 = Lloyd| first2 = Mark| title = History of the United States fighting forces| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=r6xZAAAAYAAJ&amp;pg=PA103| year = 1989| publisher = Chevprime| isbn = 978-1-85361-107-0| page = 103 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2=Unknown
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Battle of the Bulge|state=autocollapse}}
}}

The '''Siege of Bastogne''' was an engagement in December 1944 between American and German forces at the [[Belgium|Belgian]] town of [[Bastogne]], as part of the larger [[Battle of the Bulge]]. The goal of the German offensive was the harbor at [[Antwerp]]. In order to reach it before the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] could regroup and bring their superior air power to bear, German [[armoured warfare|mechanized forces]] had to seize the roadways through eastern Belgium. Because all seven main roads in the densely wooded [[Ardennes]] highlands converged on Bastogne (''Bastnach'' in German), just a few miles away from the border with neighboring [[Luxembourg]], control of its crossroads was vital to the German attack. The siege was from 20 to 27 December, until the besieged American forces were relieved by elements of General [[George Patton]]'s [[United States Army Central|Third Army]]. 
{{TOC limit|2}}

==Background==
After the successful [[invasion of Normandy]] and the subsequent eastward push through [[France]], the Allied front lines extended from [[Nijmegen]] in the north down to neutral [[Switzerland]] in the south. The valuable port city of [[Antwerp]] had been captured during the push, and by the time winter arrived, the Allies even had control of German territory near the city of [[Aachen]]. [[Adolf Hitler]] soon laid out a plan to attack the Allied lines in Belgium and Luxembourg; 25 divisions would launch a surprise attack through the Ardennes, with the aim of crossing the [[Meuse River]] (called ''Maas'' in German and Dutch) and recapturing Antwerp. Despite major misgivings from his senior commanders, including [[Gerd von Rundstedt]] and [[Walther Model]], the plan was not modified and the jump-off date was eventually set as 16 December 1944. Meanwhile, the Allied commanders considered the Ardennes area to be unsuitable for a large-scale German attack, mainly because of terrain issues. In addition, intelligence reports suggested that the only German divisions stationed in the area were weary, and in the weeks leading up to the assault, no Allied commander saw reason to believe that an attack was imminent. Bastogne, a hub city that commanded several important roads in the area, was defended mainly by the [[28th Infantry Division (United States)|28th Infantry Division]], which had seen continuous fighting from 22 July to 19 November, before being assigned to this relatively quiet area. The Allies believed only an infantry division was present opposite the 28th Infantry, and they believed any attack along this sector would be limited in scale. The seven roads in and out of Bastogne were critical to the movement of German armor, making Allied retention of the roads imperative.

[[Hasso von Manteuffel]]—commanding the 5th Panzer Army—gave [[Heinrich Freiherr von Lüttwitz]]′s [[XLVII Panzer Corps]] the responsibility of capturing Bastogne, before crossing the Meuse near [[Namur (city)|Namur]]. Lüttwitz planned to attack a {{convert|7|mi|km|abbr=on}} front with three divisions: the [[26th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|26th Volksgrenadier]] and the [[2nd Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|2nd Panzer]] would lead the assault, with the ''[[Panzer-Lehr-Division]]'' behind them. Opposing this significant force were two battalions of the [[110th Infantry Regiment (United States)|110th Infantry Regiment]] (the third was held back as a division reserve), responsible for a {{convert|9|mi|km|abbr=on}} front along the [[Our River]] which forms the border between Germany and neighboring Luxembourg. The Allied forces were gathered into small groups at major Luxembourgish villages, with outposts along the river manned only during the daytime. The forces were too thin to maintain an even battle line, they focused their attention on the four roads that crossed the Our. Due to heavy rain preceding the German attack, only one of the roads was in good enough condition to be used as a crossing point—the northernmost road, which crossed the Our at [[Dasburg]] on its way to the Luxembourgish town of [[Clervaux]] (in German: ''Klerf'', in Luxembourgish: ''Klierf'') and Bastogne. The 2nd Panzer Division was assigned to cross the river along this road, while the 26th Volksgrenadier Division would construct a bridge near [[Gemünd]] for its crossing. Lüttwitz realized the importance of the road network of Bastogne—he knew that the town had to be captured before his corps could venture too far westward. Therefore, he ordered the ''Panzer-Lehr'' Division' to push forward to Bastogne as soon as his other troops had crossed the [[Clerve|Clerf River]] in Northern Luxembourg.

==Prelude==

===The attack===
On the evening of 15 December, the 26th Volksgrenadier established an outpost line on the west bank of the Our, something they did routinely during the nighttime. At 03:00, engineers began ferrying men and equipment over the river where they began assembling at the departure point, quite close to the American garrisons. At 05:30, the German artillery began bombarding the American positions, knocking out telephone lines, as the infantry started to advance. The Germans attacked swiftly, their advances made possible by sheer weight of numbers. In the Luxembourgish village of [[Weiler, Luxembourg|Weiler]], one American company, supported by some mortars and a platoon of anti-tank guns, lasted until nightfall against repeated attacks from multiple German battalions. German engineers completed bridges over the Our before dark, and armor began moving to the front, adding to the Germans' vast numerical superiority. But in the end, the Germans were significantly delayed by the American defenders—their plan to cross the Clerf River by nightfall on the first day was delayed by three days.

On 19 December, the 28th Division command post transferred to Bastogne from [[Wiltz]], a large Luxembourgish town to the southeast. At Wiltz, the division put up its last stand; 3rd Battalion of the 110th—supported by armor and artillery—arrived at the town around noon of that day. The [[44th Engineer Battalion]] was set up north of the town, but they were soon overwhelmed and retreated into the town, blowing up a bridge behind them. This small force—numbering no more than 500 in total—held out until the evening, when their position became completely untenable and they retreated to the west. With the 110th Infantry completely destroyed as an effective combat unit, it would be up to the rest of the Allied army to defend Bastogne.

===Commitment of reserves===
Despite several notable signs in the weeks preceding the attack, the Ardennes Offensive achieved virtually complete surprise. By the end of the second day of battle, it became apparent that the 28th Infantry was near collapse. To assist in the defense of Bastogne, [[Major general (United States)|Major General]] [[Troy H. Middleton]], already commander of [[VIII Corps (United States)|VIII Corps]], was given Combat Command B of the [[10th Armored Division (United States)|10th Armored Division]]. CCB consisted of the 3rd Tank Battalion, 20th Armored Infantry Battalion, C Company 21st Tank Battalion, B Company 54th Armored Infantry Battalion, C Company, 609th Tank Destroyer Battalion, 419th Armored Field Artillery Battalion, and three companies of support troops. [[General (United States)|General]] [[George S. Patton]], commander of the [[United States Army Central|U.S. Third Army]] was not happy about giving up the CCB unit right before he planned an offensive near [[Mainz]] but General [[Omar Bradley]], commander of the [[Twelfth United States Army Group|12th Army Group]], ordered General Patton to release the unit. Meanwhile, General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]], the [[Supreme Allied Commander]], ordered forward the [[Supreme Headquarters Allied Expeditionary Force|SHAEF]] reserve, composed of the [[82nd Airborne Division]], commanded by Major General [[James M. Gavin|James Gavin]], and the [[101st Airborne Division]], temporarily under command of [[Brigadier general (United States)|Brigadier General]] [[Anthony McAuliffe]], at [[Reims]]. These were veteran troops that had served with distinction since the [[American airborne landings in Normandy|parachute drops in Normandy]] and were resting and re-equipping after two months of combat in the [[Netherlands]] after [[Operation Market Garden]]. Both divisions were alerted on the evening of 17 December, and not having transport automatically assigned for their use, began arranging trucks for movement forward. The 82nd—longer in reserve and thus better re-equipped—moved out first. The 101st left Camp Mourmelon on the afternoon of 18 December, with the order of march of the [[101st Airborne Division Artillery|division artillery]], division trains, [[501st Infantry Regiment (United States)|501st Parachute Infantry Regiment]] (PIR), [[506th Infantry Regiment (United States)|506th PIR]], [[502nd Infantry Regiment (United States)|502nd PIR]], and [[327th Infantry Regiment (United States)|327th Glider Infantry Regiment]] (GIR). Much of the convoy was conducted at night in drizzle and sleet, using headlights despite threat of air attack to speed the movement, and at one point the combined column stretched from [[Bouillon]], Belgium, back to Reims, a distance of {{convert|120|km|mi}}.

The 101st Airborne was originally supposed to go to Werbomont on the northern shoulder but was rerouted to Bastogne, located {{convert|107|mi|km}} away on a {{convert|1463|ft|m}} high [[plateau]], while the 82nd Airborne, because it was able to leave sooner, went to Werbomont to block the critical advance of the ''[[Kampfgruppe Peiper]]'' ("Combat Group Peiper"). The [[705th Tank Destroyer Battalion]]—in reserve {{convert|60|mi|km}} to the north—was ordered to Bastogne to provide anti-tank support to the armor-less 101st Airborne on 18 December and arrived late the next evening. The first elements of the 501st PIR entered the division assembly area {{convert|4|mi|km}} west of Bastogne shortly after midnight of 19 December, and by 09:00 the entire division had arrived.

Brigadier General Anthony McAuliffe sent the 501st PIR southeast through Bastogne at 06:00 to develop the situation. By 09:00, it had advanced and deployed on either side of the highway to Magéret and Longvilly, where the ''Panzer-Lehr-Division'' (''Armored Training Division'') was engaged in an all-day action to destroy the armor-infantry combat teams assigned to slow the German advance. The 506th followed shortly thereafter, its 1st Battalion was sent to Noville to reinforce Major Desobry's team from the 10th Armored CCB while the other two battalions were ordered to act as reserves north of Bastogne. The 502nd PIR marched north and northwest to establish a line from Champs east to [[Recogne]], while the 327th GIR, newly arrived, protected the division service area southwest of Bastogne until German intentions could be deciphered.

===Initial combat at Noville===
On 19–20 December, the 1st Battalion of the 506th PIR was ordered to support Team Desobry (Maj. William R. Desobry), a battalion-sized tank-infantry task force of the [[U.S. 10th Armored Division|10th Armored Division]] assigned to defend [[Noville-lez-Bastogne|Noville]]&lt;ref name=Restorer/&gt; located north-northeast of both [[Foy, Belgium|Foy]] and of Bastogne just {{convert|4.36|mi|km|2|abbr=on}} away. With just four&lt;ref name=Restorer&gt;[[Military Channel]], Program "Tank Overhaul" ca 22:51, Wednesday 13 August 2008 (UTC) "18:00–19:00 hrs EDST", mixed documentary featuring [[M18 Hellcat]] refurbishment with interviews of World War II veterans and expert commentary by World War II historians.&lt;/ref&gt; [[M18 Hellcat]] [[tank destroyer]]s of the 705th Tank Destroyer Battalion to assist, the paratroopers attacked units of the [[2nd Panzer Division|2. ''Panzerdivision'']], whose mission was to proceed by secondary roads via Monaville (just northwest of Bastogne) to seize a key highway and capture, among other objectives, fuel dumps—for the lack of which the overall German counter-offensive faltered and failed. Worried about the threat to its left flank in Bastogne, it organized a major combined arms attack to seize Noville. Team Desobry's high speed highway journey to reach the blocking position is one of the few documented cases&lt;ref name=Restorer/&gt; in which the top speed of the [[M18 Hellcat]] ({{convert|55|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}) was actually used to get ahead of an enemy force as envisioned by its specifications.&lt;ref name=Restorer/&gt;

The attack of 1st Battalion and the M18 Hellcat tank destroyers of the 705th TD Battalion together destroyed at least 30 German tanks and inflicted 500–1,000 casualties on the attacking forces in what amounted to a spoiling attack.{{Citation needed|date=September 2009}} The 3rd Battalion was ordered forward from a reserve position north of Bastogne to ease the pressure on 1st Battalion by occupying a supporting position in Foy to the south.

The heavy losses inflicted by the tank-destroyers&lt;ref name=Restorer/&gt; deceived the German commander into believing the village was being held by a much stronger force&lt;ref name=Restorer/&gt; and he recoiled from further attacks on the village, committing a strategic error while seeking tactical advantage—significantly delaying the German advance and setting the stage for the Siege of Bastogne just to the south.&lt;ref name=Restorer/&gt; This delay also gave the [[101st Airborne Division]] enough time to organize defenses around Bastogne. After two days, the 2nd Panzer Division finally continued on its original mission to the Meuse River. As a consequence of its involvement at Bastogne, and its failure to dislodge the airborne forces, the column ultimately ran out of fuel at [[Celles, Houyet|Celles]], where it was destroyed by the U.S. [[2nd Armored Division (United States)|2nd Armored Division]] and the British [[29th Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|29th Armoured Brigade]].&lt;ref name=Restorer/&gt;

By the time the 1st Battalion pulled out of Noville on the 20th, the village of Foy half-way to Bastogne center had been captured from the 3rd Battalion by a separate attack, forcing the 1st Battalion to then fight its way through Foy. By the time 1st Battalion made it to the safety of American lines, it had lost 13 officers and 199 enlisted men, out of about 600 troops, and was assigned as the division reserve. Team Desobry lost a quarter of its troops and was reduced to just four medium tanks when it passed through the lines of 3rd Battalion.

==Battle==
[[File:Bastogne Map December 19-23 1944.jpg|thumb|upright=1.8|19–23 December 1944]]

The 101st Airborne formed an all-round perimeter using the 502nd PIR on the northwest shoulder to block the 26th Volksgrenadier, the 506th PIR to block entry from Noville, the 501st PIR defending the eastern approach, and the 327th GIR scattered from Marvie in the southeast to Champs in the west along the southern perimeter, augmented by engineer and artillery units plugging gaps in the line. The division service area to the west of Bastogne had been raided the first night, causing the loss of almost its entire medical company, and numerous service troops were used as infantry to reinforce the thin lines. CCB of the 10th Armored Division, severely weakened by losses to its Team Desobry (Maj. William R. Desobry), Team Cherry (Lt. Col. Henry T. Cherry), and Team O'Hara (Lt. Col. James O'Hara) in delaying the Germans, formed a mobile "fire brigade" of 40 light and medium tanks (including survivors of CCR 9th Armored Division and eight replacement tanks found unassigned in Bastogne).

Three artillery battalions were commandeered and formed a temporary artillery group. Each had twelve {{convert|155|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} howitzers, providing the division with heavy firepower in all directions restricted only by its limited ammunition supply. Col. Roberts, commanding CCB, also rounded up 600+ stragglers from the rout of VIII Corps and formed [[Team SNAFU]] as a further stopgap force.

Many of the artillery guns were used in a direct fire role against enemy armor, with over 2000 rounds used for this purpose on December 20. The division's antiaircraft batteries were also moved into the front lines to fire against enemy armor to augment their [[Ordnance QF 6-pounder|57mm anti-tank guns]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://cgsc.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/singleitem/collection/p4013coll8/id/367/rec/3 101st Airborne Division's defense of Bastogne]. R.M. Mitchell, 1986, p. 37-38&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box|quote= ''The antitank batteries were also positioned on the [[Main line of resistance|MLR]], where, in conjunction with the larger vehicles of the tank destroyer battalion, they formed a defense in depth that the Germans could not penetrate without unacceptable losses. The (anti-aircraft batteries) would engage the German tanks at maximum range, slow the German tanks, and thus give the more mobile tank and tank destroyer units time to move to the point of the German attack and defeat the enemy's armor. Time and again, this technique was used to counter uncoordinated enemy thrusts that came from all directions.''|source=—Ralph M. Mitchell, ''[http://cgsc.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/singleitem/collection/p4013coll8/id/367/rec/3 101st Airborne Division's defense of Bastogne. 1986] p. 38''|width=30%|align=right|style=padding:8px;}}

As a result of the powerful American defense to the north and east, XLVII Panzer Corps commander Gen. von Lüttwitz decided to encircle Bastogne and strike from the south and southwest, beginning the night of 20/21 December. German ''Panzer'' reconnaissance units had initial success, nearly overrunning the American artillery positions southwest of Bastogne before being stopped by a makeshift force. All seven highways leading to Bastogne were cut by German forces by noon on 21 December, and by nightfall the conglomeration of airborne and armored infantry forces were recognized by both sides as being surrounded.

The American soldiers were outnumbered approximately 5-1 and were lacking in [[Winter clothing|cold-weather gear]], ammunition, food, medical supplies, and senior leadership (as many senior officers, including the 101st's commander—Major General [[Maxwell D. Taylor|Maxwell Taylor]]—were elsewhere). Due to the worst winter weather in memory, the surrounded U.S. forces could not be resupplied by air nor was tactical air support available due to cloudy weather.

However, the two Panzer divisions of the XLVII Panzer Corps—after using their mobility to isolate Bastogne, continued their mission towards the Meuse on 22 December, rather than attacking Bastogne with a single large force. They left just one regiment behind to assist the [[26th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|26th Volksgrenadier Division]] in capturing the crossroads. The XLVII Panzer Corps probed different points of the southern and western defensive perimeter in echelon, where Bastogne was defended by just a single airborne regiment and support units doubling as infantry. This played into the American advantage of [[interior lines]]; the defenders were able to shift artillery fire and move their limited ''ad hoc'' armored forces to meet each successive assault.

[[File:McAuliffeBastogneChristmasLetter101Airborne.jpg|thumb|right|Letter from General McAuliffe on Christmas Day to the 101st Airborne troops defending Bastogne, containing a report of the famous one-word reply to the Germans: ''NUTS!''.]]
It was on the 22nd of December that General von Lüttwitz submitted the following demand for surrender to his American counterpart commanding the American forces in Bastogne, Brigadier General [[Anthony McAuliffe]]:

{{quote|To the U.S.A. Commander of the encircled town of Bastogne.

The fortune of war is changing. This time the U.S.A. forces in and near Bastogne have been encircled by strong German armored units. More German armored units have crossed the river Our near Ortheuville, have taken Marche and reached St. Hubert by passing through Hompre-Sibret-Tillet. Libramont is in German hands.

There is only one possibility to save the encircled U.S.A. troops from total annihilation: that is the honorable surrender of the encircled town. In order to think it over a term of two hours will be granted beginning with the presentation of this note.

If this proposal should be rejected one German Artillery Corps and six heavy A. A. Battalions are ready to annihilate the U.S.A. troops in and near Bastogne. The order for firing will be given immediately after this two hours term.

All the serious civilian losses caused by this artillery fire would not correspond with the well-known American humanity.

The German Commander.}}

Shortly thereafter, McAuliffe sent the following communication to von Lüttwitz in response to the German demand:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/Bastogne/bast-14.htm S.L.A. Marshall, ''Bastogne: The First Eight Days''], Chapter 14, describing the incident in detail and sourcing it.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
To the German Commander.

NUTS!

The American Commander
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The commander of the 327th GIR interpreted it to the German truce party as "Go to hell!".&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/Bastogne/bast-14.htm S.L. A. Marshall, ''Bastogne: The First Eight Days''], Chapter 14, detailing and sourcing the incident.&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite the defiant American response to the surrender demand, the 26th VG received one Panzergrenadier regiment from the [[33rd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|15th Panzergrenadier Division]] on [[Christmas Eve]] for its main assault the next day. That night, at about 7:00 PM, [[Luftwaffe]] [[bombers]] attacked Bastogne, killing 21 in an aid station. Because it lacked sufficient troops and those of the 26th VG Division were near exhaustion, the XLVII Panzer Corps concentrated its assault on several individual locations on the west side of the perimeter in sequence rather than launching one simultaneous attack on all sides. The assault—led by 18 tanks carrying a battalion of infantry—pierced the lines of the 327th's 3rd Battalion (officially, the 1st Battalion, 401st Glider Infantry), and advanced as far as the battalion command post at Hemroulle.

However, the 327th held its original positions and repulsed infantry assaults that followed, capturing 92 Germans. The panzers that had achieved the penetration divided into two columns, one trying to reach Champs from the rear, and were destroyed in detail by two companies of the 1st Battalion 502nd PIR under Lt. Col. [[Patrick F. Cassidy]] and four tank destroyers of the [[705th Tank Destroyer Battalion]].

Allied control of Bastogne was a major obstacle to the German armored advance, and the morale of Allied forces elsewhere on the Western Front was boosted by news of the stubborn defense of the besieged town.

===333rd Field Artillery Battalion – The Black Battalion===
{{Main|333rd Field Artillery Battalion (United States)}}

A rarity in the World War II era American Army, the 333rd Battalion was a combat unit composed entirely of [[African American]] soldiers, led by white officers. At the start of the [[Battle of the Bulge]], the 333rd was attached to the [[106th Infantry Division (United States)|106th Infantry Division]]. Prior to the German offensive, the 106th division was tasked with holding a 26-mile (41.8 kilometers) long length of the front, despite the Army Field manual stating that a single infantry division could hold no more than 5 miles (8 kilometers) of front.&lt;ref name="youtube.com"&gt;{{YouTube|zPndGKudCc4|Narrow Escapes of World War II}}{{reliable source|date=December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; As a result, in the initial days of the assault, two of the division's three overstretched regiments were brushed aside by the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German Army]], yielding 6000 prisoners. The 333rd was badly affected, losing nearly 50% of its soldiers including its commanding officer. Eleven of its soldiers were cut off from the rest of the unit and attempted to escape German capture, but were massacred on sight by the [[Waffen SS]]. The remnants of the battalion retreated to [[Bastogne]] where they linked up with the 101st.&lt;ref name="youtube.com"/&gt; The vestiges of the 333rd were attached to its sister unit the [[969th Artillery Battalion (United States)|969th Battalion]]. The remains of the 333rd were given carbines and assigned to defend the town. Despite low supplies of food and ammunition, and being limited to only 10 artillery rounds per day, the 333rd fought tenaciously, successfully holding their sector of the front despite repeated German assaults. For their heroism, the 333rd was awarded the [[Presidential Unit Citation (United States)|Presidential Unit Citation]].&lt;ref name="youtube.com"/&gt;

===Breaking the encirclement===
{{quote box|quote= ''An in-depth analysis of the Battle of Bastogne, focusing on the ability of a light division to defeat heavier ones, leads to predictable conclusions. At Bastogne, well-coordinated combined arms teams defeated uncoordinated armored and infantry forces committed to an unrealistic plan. Results of isolated cases in which American infantry fought German armored forces point out how important the attached package of tanks and tank destroyers was to the 101st. Without them, even the bravest of infantry actions would have been no match for the tanks. The infantry, fighting alone, would have lost Bastogne early in the battle. Coordinated German attacks in mass, rather than the small unit attacks they employed, might also have resulted in a decisive German victory over the 101st and its attachments.''|source=—Ralph M. Mitchell, ''[http://cgsc.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/singleitem/collection/p4013coll8/id/367/rec/3 101st Airborne Division's defense of Bastogne. 1986] p. 44''|width=30%|align=right|style=padding:8px;}}

Elements of General [[George Patton]]'s [[2nd Armored Division (United States)|Third Army]] succeeded in reaching Bastogne from the southwest, arriving from the direction of Assenois. The spearhead reached the lines of the 326th Engineers on December 26, [[Cobra King (tank)|Cobra King]] being the first tank to make contact at approximately 16:50.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |first=Jennifer H. |last=Svan |work=[[Stars and Stripes (newspaper)|Stars and Stripes]] |date=27 December 2008 |title=Vilseck tank confirmed as 'Cobra King' |url=http://www.stripes.com/news/vilseck-tank-confirmed-as-cobra-king-1.86612 |accessdate=8 September 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Fox&gt;{{cite book |last=Fox |first=Don M. |title=Patton's Vanguard: The United States Army 4th Armored Division |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=kBctf2Sa30EC&amp;pg=PA407 |accessdate=June 30, 2020 |year=2003 |publisher=McFarland |isbn=978-0786415823 |pages=407-410}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 101st's ground communications with the American supply dumps were restored on 27 December, and the wounded were evacuated to the rear. Gen. Taylor reached Bastogne with the 4th Armored Division and resumed command.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=101st Airborne War Stories|url=http://www.101airborneww2.com/warstories3.html|accessdate=16 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the encirclement broken, the men of the 101st expected to be relieved, but were given orders to resume the offensive. The [[506th Infantry Regiment (United States)|506th]] attacked north and recaptured Recogne on 9 January 1945, the Bois des Corbeaux (''Crows' Wood''), to the right of Easy Company, on 10 January, and Foy on 13 January. The [[327th Infantry Regiment (United States)|327th]] attacked towards Bourcy, northeast of Bastogne, on 13 January and encountered stubborn resistance. The 101st Airborne Division along with the forces from the Third Army faced the elite of the German military which included elements from [[1st SS Panzer Division Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler]], [[Führerbegleitbrigade]], [[12th SS Panzer Division Hitlerjugend]], and the [[9th SS Panzer Division Hohenstaufen]].&lt;ref name="Bando P.188"&gt;Bando P.188&lt;/ref&gt; The 506th retook Noville on 15 January and Rachamps the next day. The [[502nd Infantry Regiment (United States)|502nd]] reinforced the 327th, and the two regiments captured Bourcy on 17 January, pushing the Germans back to their point of advance on the day the division had arrived in Bastogne. The next day the 101st Airborne Division was relieved.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Battle of Bastogne Facts|url=http://www.worldwar2facts.org/battle-of-bastogne.html|work=World War 2 Facts|accessdate=16 December 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==

The 101st Airborne Division's casualties from 19 December 1944 to 6 January 1945 were 341 killed, 1,691 wounded, and 516 missing. Several regiments within the 101st were nicknamed "[[List of nicknames of United States Army divisions#Airborne divisions|The Battered Bastards of Bastogne]]", due to their part in holding the important crossroads town during the Battle of the Bulge.

The 10th Armored Division's CCB incurred approximately 500 casualties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|chapterurl=http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/Bastogne/bast-notes.htm|chapter=Notes|first=S.L.A.|last=Marshall|title=Bastogne: The First Eight Days|series=U.S. Army in Action Series|url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/Bastogne/bast-fm.htm|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]|edition=Facsimile reprint of 1946|year=1988}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Augusta Chiwy]], a nurse who administered aid to the wounded during the siege, was honored with the [[Civilian Award for Humanitarian Service]] by the Ambassador to Belgium [[Howard Gutman]] in December 2011.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-16136007 WWII Belgian nurse Augusta Chiwy honoured by US army]&lt;/ref&gt;

For its defense of Bastogne, the headquarters of the 101st Airborne Division was awarded the Presidential Unit Citation (PUC), with a streamer, embroidered BASTOGNE, for the division's colors.  Also, the division was awarded the Belgian Croix de Guerre 1940 with Palm, Streamer embroidered BASTOGNE, and cited in the Order of the Day of the Belgian Army for action at Bastogne.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://history.army.mil/html/forcestruc/lineages/branches/div/101abdb.htm|title=101st Airborne Division Lineage and Honors|last=|first=|date=|website=US Army Center of Military History|url-status=live|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=17 December 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Gallery ==

&lt;gallery widths="240" heights="160"&gt;
File:Wacht am Rhein map (Opaque).svg|Map of troop movements during the battle of the Bulge. Bastogne is near the middle.
File:SUPPLY BY AIR 2.jpg|101st Airborne troops picking up air-dropped supplies during the siege.
File:Infantry &amp; Tanks near Bastogne.jpg|44th Armored Infantry soldiers and [[6th Armored Division (United States)|6th Armored Division]] tanks near Bastogne, 31 December 1944
File:Pattons-jeep-bastogne-1945.jpg|General [[George Patton|Patton]]'s jeep in Bastogne, 1 January 1945.
File:9th Armored Engineer Battalion Bastogne memorial service2.jpg|Members of [[9th Engineer Battalion (United States)|C Company, 9th Engineers]], conduct a [[funeral|memorial service]] for those killed during the siege, 22 January 1945.
File:Infantry near Bastogne.png|Infantry of relief force near Bastogne, December 1944.
File:1944 Cobra King first in Bastogne.jpg|The 'Cobra King' crew poses for a celebratory photo
File:PZ IV Ardenne3.jpg|A Panzer IV H of Kampgruppe Peiper of the 1st SS Panzer Division Leibstandarte SS Adolf Hitler. The 101st Airborne Division fought this [[Waffen SS]] division when the 101st attacked towards Bourcy, northeast of Bastogne, on 13 January 1945.
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* {{cite book| author = Stephen E. Ambrose| title = Band of Brothers: E Company, 506th Regiment, 101st Airborne: From Normandy to Hitler's Eagle's Nest| url = https://archive.org/details/bandofbrothers00ambr| url-access = registration| year = 1993| publisher = Touchstone Books| isbn = 978-0-671-86736-2 }}
* {{cite book| last = Turow| first = Scott| title = Ordinary Heroes: A Novel| year = 2005| publisher = Macmillan| isbn = 978-0-374-18421-6 }}
* Winters, Richard D., Cole C. (Cole Christian) Kingseed, and Inc ebrary. ''Beyond Band of Brothers: The War Memoirs of Major Dick Winters''. New York: Berkley Caliber, 2006. Web. 26 October 2012.
* Atkinson, Rick. ''The Guns at Last Light'', 2013
* ''101st Airborne: The Screaming Eagles in World War Two'' by Mark Bando

== Further reading ==
* [[R. V. Cassill|Cassill, R. V.]] (1955), ''The General Said "Nuts":  The Exciting Moments of Our History—As Recalled by Our Favorite American Slogans'', New York: Birk.
* {{Cite book |last=Collins |first= Michael |last2=King |first2=Martin |title= The Tigers of Bastogne: Voices of the 10th Armored Division in the Battle of the Bulge |publisher =Casemate |year=2013|ISBN = 9781612001814}}
* {{cite book|url=http://www.history.army.mil/documents/WWII/501PIRBulge.htm|title=The 501st Parachute Infantry at Bastogne, Belgium December 1944|first=Major Gary F. |last=Evans|id=[[United States Army Center of Military History]] Historical Manuscripts Collection 8-3.1 BB 2|date=22 June 1972|accessdate=June 9, 2010}}
* {{cite book |last=Makos |first=Adam |authorlink1=Adam Makos |date=2019 |title=[[Spearhead (Makos novel)|Spearhead]] |edition=1st |location=New York |publisher=[[Ballantine Books]] |pages=69, 70n, 88 |isbn=9780804176729 |lccn=2018039460 |ol=27342118M}}
* {{cite book|url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/Bastogne/bast-fm.htm|title=Bastogne: The Story of the First Eight Days in Which the 101st Airborne Division Was Closed within the Ring of German Forces|first=Colonel S. L. A. |last=Marshall|year=1946|edition=1988 reprint|id=CMH Pub 22-2| publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]|accessdate=June 9, 2010}}

==External links==
{{Wikisource|The_Ardennes:_Battle_of_the_Bulge/Chapter_XIX|THE ARDENNES:&lt;br/&gt;BATTLE OF THE BULGE.&lt;br&gt;CHAPTER XIX:&lt;br&gt;THE BATTLE OF BASTOGNE}}
* [http://www.101airborneww2.com/warstories3.html Summary of the battle]
* [http://www.militaryhistoryonline.com/wwii/articles/bastogne.aspx The Battle of the Bulge – Fortunes of War]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070930210627/http://www.historynet.com/historical_conflicts/3031921.html Battle of the Bulge – 4th Armored Division Help End the Siege of Bastogne]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J9FktEyCpwM The Battle of Bastogne on YouTube]
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/USA-E-Last/maps/USA-E-Last-I.jpg Map: The Western Front – 3 January 1945]
* {{cite web | title =The Ardennes Offensive: Air resupply by paradrops and gliders (23–27 Dec. 1944) | publisher =National WWII Glider Pilots Association, Inc. | url = http://www.ww2gp.org/ardennessituation.php }}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bastogne}}
[[Category:1944 in Belgium]]
[[Category:Bastogne|Siege]]
[[Category:Battle of the Bulge|Bastogne]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Last stand battles]]
[[Category:Sieges involving Germany|Bastogne]]
[[Category:Sieges involving the United States|Bastogne]]
[[Category:Sieges of World War II|Bastogne]]
[[Category:World War II sites in Belgium]]
[[Category:December 1944 events]]</text><sha1>ekq4mi4c3q3r3kz9q4hx66kky2t251x</sha1></revision></page>