<page><title>Operation Veritable</title><ns>0</ns><id>3103862</id><revision><id>954080442</id><parentid>954080113</parentid><timestamp>2020-04-30T15:40:40Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>163.182.220.151</ip></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="27550" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2012}}
{{more citations needed|date=February 2011}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Operation Veritable
|partof= the [[Western Allied invasion of Germany]] in the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]] of the [[European theatre of World War II]]|European theatre]] of [[World War II]]
|image=Veritable grenade.png
|image_size=300px
|caption= Operations Veritable and Blockbuster (yellow) and Grenade (green)
|date= 8 February – 11 March 1945&lt;br&gt;({{Age in years, months, weeks and days|month1=02|day1=08|year1=1945|month2=03|day2=11|year2=1945}})
|place=[[Klever Reichswald|Reichswald Forest]] (Germany), and adjacent areas
|coordinates={{coord|51|44|N|6|02|E|region:DE-NW_type:event_scale:50000|display=inline}}
|result=Allied victory
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}} &lt;br&gt;{{flag|Canada|1921}}
|combatant2={{flag|Nazi Germany|name=Germany}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Bernard Montgomery]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[Harry Crerar]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Brian Horrocks]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Alfred Schlemm]]
|strength1=400,000 men{{citation needed|date=July 2012}}&lt;br&gt;2,400 guns&lt;br&gt;35,000 vehicles
|strength2=90,000 men&lt;br&gt;1,054 guns&lt;br&gt;700 mortars
|casualties1=15,634 casualties{{efn|First Canadian Army losses from "8 February ... [to] ... 10 March were ... 1,049 officers and 14,585 other ranks; the majority of these were British soldiers". Canadian losses amounted to 379 officers and 4,925 other ranks, the vast majority being lost during Operation Blockbuster. Total allied losses in Operations Veritable/Blockbuster and Grenade amounted to 22,934 men.&lt;ref name="Stacey, p. 522"&gt;Stacey, Chap 19, p. 522&lt;/ref&gt;}}
|casualties2=~44,239 casualties{{efn|Canadian First Army captured 22,239 prisoners during the operation, and the intelligence section estimated the number of German soldiers killed or made "long-term wounded" to have amounted to 22,000 men. In conjunction with Operation Grenade, the combined allied effort inflicted approximately 90,000 casualties on the German army.&lt;ref name="Stacey, p. 522"/&gt;}}
|campaignbox =
{{Campaignbox Central Europe}}
{{Campaignbox Western Europe (1944-1945)}}
}}
&lt;!--[[File:Map of the territory of Operation Veritable (1945).jpg|thumb|right|500px]]--&gt;
'''Operation Veritable''' (also known as the '''Battle of the Reichswald''') was the northern part of an [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[pincer movement]] that took place between 8 February and 11 March 1945 during the final stages of the [[World War II|Second World War]]. The operation was conducted by [[Field marshal (United Kingdom)|Field Marshal]] [[Bernard Montgomery]]'s Anglo-Canadian [[21st Army Group]], primarily consisting of the [[First Canadian Army]] under [[Lieutenant-general (Canada)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Harry Crerar]] and the [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|British XXX Corps]] under [[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Brian Horrocks]].

''Veritable'' was a northern pincer movement and started with XXX Corps advancing through the [[Klever Reichswald|Reichswald]] (German: Imperial Forest) while the [[3rd Canadian Division|3rd Canadian Infantry Division]], in amphibious vehicles, cleared German positions in the flooded Rhine plain. The Allied advance proceeded more slowly than expected and at greater cost. This delayed the US offensive [[Operation Grenade]], the southern pincer and at the same time allowed German forces under local German commander, [[Alfred Schlemm]] to be concentrated against the Commonwealth advance.

The fighting was hard, but the Allied advance continued. On 22 February, once clear of the Reichswald, and with the towns of [[Kleve]] and [[Goch]] in their control, the offensive was renewed as [[Operation Blockbuster]] and linked up with the U.S. Ninth Army near [[Geldern]] on 4 March after the execution of Operation Grenade.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
 |title = Geilenkirchen to the Rhine
 |work = A Short History of the 8th Armoured Brigade
 |year = 2000
 |url = http://www.warlinks.com/armour/8th_armoured/chapter_5.html
 |accessdate =26 May 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Fighting continued as the Germans sought to retain a bridgehead on the west bank of the Rhine at [[Wesel]] and evacuate as many men and as much equipment as possible. Finally, on 10 March, the German withdrawal ended and the last bridges were destroyed.

==Background==
[[General (United States)|General]] [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]], the Allied Commander, had decided that the best route into Germany would be across the relatively flat lands of northern Europe, taking the industrial heartland of the [[Ruhr]]. This first required that Allied forces should close up to the Rhine along its whole length. Montgomery's 21st Army Group had established a front along the [[River Maas]] in late 1944 and had also considered several offensive operations to enlarge and defend the [[Nijmegen]] bridgehead and its important bridges (captured during the [[Operation Market Garden|operation to capture Arnhem]]). One such proposal, ''Valediction'' (a development of an earlier plan; ''Wyvern'') - an assault south-eastwards from Nijmegen between the Rhine and Maas rivers, initially had been shelved by Montgomery. A conference was convened at [[Maastricht]] on 7 December 1944 between Allied generals, to consider ways of maintaining pressure on the Germans throughout the winter. Consequently, ''Valediction'' was brought forward and allocated to the First Canadian Army. British XXX Corps were attached to the Canadians for the operation and the date was provisionally set as 1 January 1945. At this point, the name ''Veritable'' was attached to the operation in place of ''Valediction''.&lt;ref name=stacey436&gt;Stacey, Chapter 17, pp 436 - 439&lt;/ref&gt;

In the event, ''Veritable'' was delayed by the diversion of forces to stem the German attack through the [[Ardennes]] in December, ([[Battle of the Bulge]]) and the advantages to the Allies of hard, frozen ground were lost.

The objective of the operation was to clear German forces from the area between the Rhine and Maas rivers, east of the German/Dutch frontier, in the [[Rhineland]]. It was part of Eisenhower's "broad front" strategy to occupy the entire west bank of the Rhine before its crossing. The Allied expectation was that the northern end of the [[Siegfried Line]] was less well defended than elsewhere and an outflanking movement around the line was possible and would allow an early assault against the industrial Ruhr region.

''Veritable'' was the northern arm of a pincer movement. The southern pincer arm, [[Operation Grenade]], was to be made  by [[Lieutenant general (United States)|Lieutenant General]] [[William Hood Simpson]]'s U.S. Ninth Army. The operation had complications. First, the heavily forested terrain, squeezed between the Rhine and Maas rivers, reduced Anglo-Canadian advantages in manpower and armour; the situation was exacerbated by soft ground which had thawed after the winter and also by the deliberate flooding of the adjacent Rhine [[flood plain]].

==Order of battle==

===Allied===
At this stage, [[21st Army Group]] consisted of the [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|British Second Army]] ([[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Miles Dempsey|Miles C. Dempsey]]), [[First Canadian Army]] ([[Lieutenant-general (Canada)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Harry Crerar]]) and the U.S. Ninth Army (Lieutenant General William Simpson). In ''Veritable'', the reinforced [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|British XXX Corps]] (one of two such formations in the First Canadian Army), under Lieutenant-General [[Brian Horrocks]], would advance through the Reichswald Forest and its adjacent flood plains to the Kleves – Goch road.

The First Canadian Army had had a severe time clearing the approaches to [[Antwerp]] during the previous autumn. It was, numerically, the smallest of the Allied armies in northern Europe and, despite its name, contained significant British units as part of its structure. For ''Veritable'', it was further strengthened by XXX Corps. At the start of the operation, Allied deployment was, from left to right across the Allied front:
* [[3rd Canadian Division|3rd Canadian Infantry Division]] ([[Major general|Major-General]] [[Daniel Spry]])
* [[2nd Canadian Division|2nd Canadian Infantry Division]] (Major-General [[Bruce Matthews (General)|Albert Bruce Matthews]])
* [[4th Canadian Division|4th Canadian Armoured Division]] (Major-General [[Christopher Vokes|Chris Vokes]])
* [[15th (Scottish) Infantry Division]] ([[Acting (rank)|Acting]] [[Major-general (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[Colin Muir Barber]])
* [[53rd (Welsh) Infantry Division]] (Major General [[Robert Knox Ross (British Army officer)|Robert Knox Ross]])
* [[51st (Highland) Division|51st (Highland) Infantry Division]] (Temporary Major-General [[Tom Rennie|Thomas Rennie]])

Further divisions were committed as the operation progressed:
* [[43rd (Wessex) Infantry Division]] (Acting Lieutenant-General [[Gwilym Ivor Thomas]]) – Part of XXX Corps' reserve at the start of the operation.
* [[Guards Armoured Division]] (Temporary Major-General [[Allan Adair]]) – Part of XXX Corps' reserve at the start of the operation.
* [[11th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|11th Armoured Division]] (Temporary Major-General [[George Philip Bradley Roberts|George Roberts]]) – transferred across the Maas from the British Second Army as the operation progressed.

===German===
Assessments by the [[OKH|German High Command]] were that an Allied advance through the Reichswald would be too difficult and the expected assault would be by the British Second Army from the [[Venlo]] area.&lt;ref name=Stacey463&gt;Stacey, Chap 18, p 463&lt;/ref&gt; Reserves were therefore placed to respond to this. [[Alfred Schlemm]], the local German commander, strongly disagreed, believing, correctly, that the Reichswald was the more likely route. He acted against the assessments of his superiors and therefore ensured that the area was well fortified, strengthened the Siegfried Line defences and quietly moved some of his reserves to be nearer this line of attack which meant that fresh, elite troops were readily available to him.
* 84th Infantry Division (Major-General [[Heinz Fiebig]])
:This was an inexperienced and under-equipped division re-formed after its destruction at [[Falaise pocket|Falaise]] in Normandy. It was augmented by the well-equipped Luftwaffe 2nd Parachute Regiment, which was placed between the western tip of the Reichswald and the Maas. Two regiments, 1062nd Grenadier Regiment and 1051st Grenadier Regiment, covered the edge of the forest facing the Allies and the 1052nd Grenadier Regiment defended the Rhine flood plain on the German right. Two more, ineffective, units were held in the rear area: the Sicherungs Battalion Münster (a small unit of elderly men used to guard static installations) and the 276th [[Stomach division|''Magen'' ("Stomach") Battalion]], whose personnel had chronic digestive ailments that made them unsuited for active roles in the defence.
* 655th Heavy Anti-Tank Battalion
:Around 36 self propelled [[assault gun]]s, the only German armour immediately available in the Reichswald.
* 180th Infantry Division ([[Bernhard Klosterkemper|Klosterkemper]])
:Guarding the Maas river bank, facing the [[British 2nd Army]].
* [[6th Parachute Division (Germany)|6th Parachute Division]] ([[Hermann Plocher|Plocher]])
:Elements fought in defensive positions at Kleve and Goch.
* [[7th Parachute Division (Germany)|7th Parachute Division]] ([[Wolfgang Erdmann|Erdmann]])
:Elements in reserve at Geldern, as a result of Schlemm's expectation of an offensive through the Reichswald.
* [[47th Panzer Corps]] (General [[Heinrich Freiherr von Lüttwitz]])
:Army Group H's armoured reserve, at [[Dülken]], south-east of [[Venlo]]. After the fighting in the [[Ardennes]], its two divisions, the [[116th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|116th Panzer]] and the 15th Panzer Grenadier, were at just over 50 per cent strength with no more than 90 tanks between them.
* [[15th Panzergrenadier Division (Germany)|15th Panzer Grenadier Division]] ([[Wolfgang Maucke]])
:A possible reserve formation, according to Allied assessments, that might be in place within six hours of the assault.
* 346th Division ([[Steinmueller]])

==Terrain==
[[File:Loading British rockets Reichswald 08-02-1945 IWM BU 1756.jpg|thumb|[[RP-3]] rockets being loaded into [[Mattress (rocket)|Land Mattress]] launchers in preparation for the offensive in the Reichswald, Germany]]
The Allied advance was from [[Groesbeek]] (captured during Operation Market Garden) eastwards to [[Kleve]] and [[Goch]], turning south eastwards along the Rhine to [[Xanten]] and the US advance. The whole battle area was between the Rhine and Maas rivers, initially through the Reichswald and then across rolling agricultural country.

The Reichswald is a forested area close to the Dutch-German border. The Rhine flood plain, {{convert|2-3|mi}} wide (and which, at the time of the operation, had been allowed to flood after a wet winter), is the northern boundary of the area and the Maas flood plain is the southern boundary. The Reichswald ridge is a glacial remnant which, when wet, easily turns to mud. At the time of the operation, the ground had thawed and was largely unsuitable for wheeled or tracked vehicles and these conditions caused breakdowns to significant numbers of tanks.

Routes through the forest were a problem for the Allies, both during their advance through the forest and later for supply and reinforcements. The only main roads passed to the north (Nijmegen to Kleve) and south (Mook to Goch) of the forest - no east-west [[Road metal|metalled]] route passed through it. There were three north-south routes: two radiating from [[Hekkens]] to [[Kranenburg, North Rhine-Westphalia|Kranenburg]] (between two and five kilometres behind the German frontline) and to Kleve; and Kleve to Goch, along the eastern edge of the Reichswald. The lack of suitable roads was made worse by the soft ground conditions and the deliberate flooding of the flood plains, which necessitated the use of amphibious vehicles. The few good roads were rapidly damaged and broken up by the constant heavy traffic that they had to carry during the assaults.

The Germans had built three defence lines. The first was from [[Wyler, North Rhine-Westphalia|Wyler]] to the Maas along the western edge of the Reichswald, manned by the 84th Division and the 1st Parachute Regiment; this was a "trip-wire" line intended only to delay an assault and alert the main forces. The second, beyond the forest, was [[Rees, Germany|Rees]], Kleve, Goch and the third ran from Rees, through the Uedemer Hochwald to Geldern.

==Operation Veritable (Battle of the Reichswald)==
Preparations for the operations were complicated by the poor condition of the few routes into the concentration area, its small size, the need to maintain surprise and, therefore, the need to conceal the movements of men and materiel. A new rail bridge was constructed that extended rail access to Nijmegen, a bridge was built across the Maas at [[Mook en Middelaar|Mook]] and roads were repaired and maintained.&lt;ref name=Stacey458&gt;Stacey, Chap 17, p 458
&lt;/ref&gt; Elaborate and strict restrictions were placed on air and daytime land movements; troop concentrations and storage dumps were camouflaged.

Operation Veritable was planned in three separate phases:
&lt;blockquote&gt;"'''Phase 1''' The clearing of the Reichswald and the securing of the line Gennep-Asperden-Cleve.

"'''Phase 2''' The breaching of the enemy's second defensive system east and south-east of the Reichswald, the capture of the localities Weeze-Üdem-Kalkar-Emmerich and the securing of the communications between them.

"'''Phase 3''' The 'break-through' of the Hochwald 'lay-back' defence lines and the advance to secure the general line Geldern-Xanten."&lt;ref name=stacey464&gt;Stacey, Chap 18, p 464&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
[[File:The British Army in North-west Europe 1944-45 BU1749.jpg|thumb|left|British infantrymen advance through the Reichswald during Operation Veritable, 8 February 1945.]]

The operation started as an infantry frontal assault, with armoured support, against prepared positions, in terrain that favoured the defenders. On 7 February more than 750 RAF heavy bombers deluged Kleve and Goch with high explosive.&lt;ref&gt;Note, Kleve was bombed by a force of 295 [[Avro Lancaster|Lancasters]] and 10 [[de Havilland Mosquito|Mosquitoes]] of [[No. 1 Group RAF|No. 1]] and [[No. 8 Group RAF|No. 8]] Groups, Goch by 292 [[Handley Page Halifax|Halifaxes]], 156 Lancasters and 16 Mosquitoes of [[No. 4 Group RAF|No. 4]], [[No. 6 Group RCAF|No. 6]] and [[No. 8 Group RAF|No. 8]] Groups. The attack on Goch was stopped after 155 aircraft had bombed as the smoke from the resulting fires on the ground was stopping the [[Master Bomber]] from controlling the remaining crews bombing accurately. The attack on Kleve had been offered to Horrocks by the RAF, and he had accepted the offer, and was later to state it was "the most terrible decision I had ever taken in my life".&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book | url=https://books.google.com/?id=eDoRBQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=RA2-PA100&amp;lpg=RA2-PA100&amp;dq=kleve+bombed#v=onepage&amp;q=kleve%20bombed&amp;f=false |title = The Bomber Command War Diaries: An Operational Reference Book|isbn = 9781473834880|last1 = Everitt|first1 = Chris|last2 = Middlebrook|first2 = Martin|date = 2 April 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; In order to reduce the defenders' advantages, a large scale artillery bombardment was employed, the biggest British barrage since the [[Second Battle of El Alamein]]. Men were literally deafened for hours by the noise of 1,034 guns.&lt;ref&gt;War Monthly (1976). ''Operation Veritable: A dirty slogging-match in the mud of the Rhineland'', by William Moore (p. 2).&lt;/ref&gt; It was hoped that this would not only destroy the German defences throughout the Reichswald but also destroy the defenders' morale and their will to fight. Air raids were also undertaken to isolate the battle area from further reinforcement.&lt;ref name=Stacey465&gt;Stacey, Chap 18, pp 465-466&lt;/ref&gt;

Operation Veritable began on 8 February 1945, at 10:30 five infantry divisions, 50,000 men with 500 tanks, attacked in line – respectively from the north, the 3rd and 2nd Canadian, the 15th (Scottish) in the center and the 53rd (Welsh) and 51st (Highland) on the right.&lt;ref&gt;War Monthly (1976). ''Operation Veritable: A dirty slogging-match in the mud of the Rhineland'', by William Moore (p. 3).&lt;/ref&gt; The next day the Germans released water from the largest [[Roer]] dam, sending water surging down the valley, and irreparably jammed the sluices to ensure a steady flow for many days. The next day they added to the flooding by doing the same to dams further upstream on the Roer and the [[Urft]]. The river rose at two feet an hour and the valley downstream to the Maas stayed flooded for about two weeks.

XXX Corps advanced with heavy fighting along the narrow neck of land between the Meuse and the [[Waal (river)|Waal]] east of Nijmegen, but Operation Grenade had to be postponed for two weeks when the Germans released the waters from the Roer dams and river levels rose. The U.S. Ninth Army was unable to move and no military actions could proceed across the Roer until the water subsided. During the two weeks of flooding, Hitler forbade Field Marshal [[Gerd von Rundstedt]] to withdraw east behind the Rhine, arguing that it would only delay the inevitable fight. Rundstedt was ordered to fight where his forces stood. The imposed American standstill allowed German forces to be concentrated against the Anglo-Canadian assault.

At first, XXX Corps made rapid progress across most of its front but after the first day, German reinforcements appeared and violent clashes were reported with a regiment of the [[6th Parachute Division (Germany)|6th Parachute Division]] and armored detachments. Horrocks ordered the 43rd (Wessex) Division to advance past Kleve into the German rear. This resulted in the greatest [[Traffic congestion|traffic jam]] in the history of [[modern warfare]]. With only one road available, units of the 43rd, 15th and Canadian divisions became inextricably mixed in a column {{convert|10|mi}} long.&lt;ref&gt;War Monthly (1976). ''Operation Veritable: A dirty slogging-match in the mud of the Rhineland'', by William Moore (pp. 3–5).&lt;/ref&gt; Two "natural" impediments to the Allied advance, flooding and the dense forest, failed to disrupt it.

The 15th Division had orders to capture Kleve, but on the night of 9 February they were held up on the outskirts. The [[XLVIII Panzer Corps|47 Panzer Corps]] under General [[Heinrich Freiherr von Lüttwitz]] was directed to Kleve and the Reichswald. On 11 February the 15th had cleared the town. Having expanded the front line to {{convert|14|mi}}, the [[II Canadian Corps]], with the 2nd and 3rd Divisions and the 4th Armoured Division, became responsible for the drive along the Rhine to [[Kalkar]] and Xanten. XXX Corps were to operate on the right and take Goch before swinging towards the Rhine and linking with the Americans – once Operation Grenade had been launched.&lt;ref&gt;War Monthly (1976). ''Operation Veritable: A dirty slogging-match in the mud of the Rhineland'', by William Moore (p. 5).&lt;/ref&gt;

The 3rd Division used [[Landing Vehicle Tracked|Buffalo]] amphibious vehicles to move through the flooded areas; the water rendered the German field defences and minefields ineffective and isolated their units on islands where they could be picked off, one by one. XXX Corps had rehearsed forest warfare tactics and were able to bring armour forward with them (despite a high rate of damage due to the natural conditions combined with the age of the tanks).&lt;ref name=34ab/&gt; The German defences had not anticipated such tactics, so these tanks, including [[Churchill Crocodile]] flame-throwers, had great shock value.

===Operation Blockbuster===
{{main article|Operation Blockbuster}}
[[File:The British Army in North-west Europe 1944-45 B14779.jpg|thumb|A [[Valentine tank|Valentine]] Mk XI Royal Artillery OP tank (left) and a [[Churchill tank]] (right) in Goch, 21 February 1945]]
Once the Reichswald had been taken, the Allied forces paused to regroup before continuing their advance towards the Hochwald forested ridge, plus Xanten to the east of it, and the US 9th Army. This stage was Operation Blockbuster. As planned, it would start on 22 February when the 15th (Scottish) Division would attack woods north-east of [[Weeze]], to be followed two days later on the 24th when the 53rd (Welsh) Division would advance southwards from Goch, take Weeze and continue south-westward. Finally, the II Canadian Corps would launch, on 26 February, the operation intended to overcome the German defences based on the Hochwald and then exploit to Xanten.&lt;ref name=Staceych19&gt;Stacey, Chap 19&lt;/ref&gt;

By the time the waters from the Roer dams had subsided and the US 9th Army was able to cross the Roer on 23 February, other Allied forces were also close to the Rhine's west bank. Rundstedt's divisions which had remained on the west bank of the Rhine were cut to pieces in the Rhineland and 230,000 men were taken prisoner.&lt;ref name=Stacey524&gt;Stacey, Chap 19, p 524&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
After the battle, [[34 Armoured Brigade]] conducted a review of its own part in the forest phase of the battle, in order to highlight the experiences of the armoured units and learn lessons.&lt;ref name=34ab&gt;{{cite web|first= Lt-Col P.N.
  |last = Veale, MC
  |title = REPORT ON 34 ARMOURED BRIGADE OPERATIONS: The Reichswald Forest Phase, 8 to 17 February 1945
  |url = http://www.royaltankregiment.com/9_RTR/tech/reichswald/Reichswald%20Report.htm
  |accessdate =3 October 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the war, Eisenhower commented this "was some of the fiercest fighting of the whole war" and "a bitter slugging match in which the enemy had to be forced back yard by yard". Montgomery wrote "the enemy parachute troops fought with a fanaticism un-excelled at any time in the war" and "the volume of fire from enemy weapons was the heaviest which had so far been met by British troops in the campaign."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Thacker
 |first = Toby
 |authorlink =Toby Thacker
 |title = The End of the Third Reich
 |pages = 92–93
 |publisher = Tempus Publishing
 |location = [[Stroud]]
 |year = 2006
 |isbn = 0-7524-3939-1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
{{Portal|World War II}}
* [[Western Front (World War II)#Invasion of Germany|Western Front]]

==Notes==
'''Footnotes'''
{{Notelist}}
'''Citations'''
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{Cite book|first=Colonel Charles Perry|last=Stacey|authorlink=|author2=Bond, Major C.C.J.|title=Official History of the Canadian Army in the Second World War: Volume III. The Victory Campaign: The operations in North-West Europe 1944–1945|publisher=The Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery Ottawa| year=1960|origyear=|isbn=}}
{{Refend}}
:Chapter 17 {{cite web
 |last =
 |first =
 |title = Winter on the Maas - 9 November 1944-7 February 1945
 |work = &lt;!-- The Official History of the Canadian Army --&gt;
 |page =
 |publisher = &lt;!-- Department of National Defense --&gt;
 |url = http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/Canada/CA/Victory/Victory-17.html
 |accessdate =30 October 2013 }}
:Chapter 18: {{cite web
 |last =
 |first =
 |title = The Battle of the Rhineland: Part I: Operation "VERITABLE", 8–21 February 1945
 |work = &lt;!-- Official History of the Canadian Army
 |publisher = Department of National Defense --&gt;
 |url = http://ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/Canada/CA/Victory/Victory-18.html
 |accessdate =26 May 2009 }}
:Chapter 19: {{cite web
 |title = The Battle of the Rhineland; Part II: Operation "BLOCKBUSTER", 22 February-10 March 1945
 |work = &lt;!-- The Official History of the Canadian Army --&gt;
 |publisher = &lt;!-- [[Department of National Defence (Canada)|Department of National Defense]] --&gt;
 |url = http://www.ibiblio.net/hyperwar/UN/Canada/CA/Victory/Victory-19.html
 |accessdate =28 May 2009}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Operation Veritable}}
* [http://www.ncf.ca/~em575/rhine.htm The 3rd Canadian Infantry Division in the Rhineland]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080508182252/http://www.bills-bunker.privat.t-online.de/65990.html A detailed, personal account of the battle]
* [http://www.junobeach.org/e/3/can-pep-can-crerar-e.htm A biography of Henry Crerar]
* [http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.com/en/article/battle-of-the-rhineland/ "Battle of the Rhineland"]. ''The Canadian Encyclopedia''.
* [http://www.secondlincs.co.uk/operation%20veritable.htm 2nd Lincolnshires' history]
* [http://www.51hd.co.uk/history/reichswald 51st (Highland) Division – Reichswald]
* [http://www.legionmagazine.com/en/index.php/2003/05/the-battle-for-xanten/ Battle for Xanten]

{{Dwight D. Eisenhower|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Veritable}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1945]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Military history of Canada during World War II]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|O]]
[[Category:History of the Rhineland]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:20th century in North Rhine-Westphalia]]
[[Category:Rhine Province]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the Netherlands]]
[[Category:History of Limburg (Netherlands)]]
[[Category:History of Gelderland]]
[[Category:February 1945 events]]
[[Category:March 1945 events]]</text><sha1>f0aa5iersydgk4wu4wy8suuifc5v45d</sha1></revision></page>