<page><title>Operation Plunder</title><ns>0</ns><id>535273</id><revision><id>966201324</id><parentid>965693923</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-05T17:51:54Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Jim.henderson</username><id>2255048</id></contributor><comment>/* Military rivalries */ Plan vs events</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="14067" xml:space="preserve">{{More footnotes|date=January 2010}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2018}}
{{Infobox military conflict
 |conflict    = Operation Plunder
 |partof      = the [[Western Allied invasion of Germany]] in the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]] of the [[European theatre of World War II]]|European theatre]] of [[World War II]]
 |image       = Crossingtherhine.jpg
 |image_size  = 300
 |caption     = U.S. 89th Division crossing the Rhine under fire
 |date        = {{start and end date|1945|03|23|1945|03|27|df=y}}
 |place       = [[Lower Rhine region]], Germany
 |result      = [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] victory
 |combatant1  = {{ubl|{{flagcountry|UK}}|{{flagcountry|US|1912}}|{{flagcountry|CAN|1921}}}}
 |combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
 |commander1  = {{ubl|{{flagdeco|UK}} [[Bernard Montgomery]]
                     |{{flagdeco|UK}} [[Miles Dempsey]]
                     |{{flagdeco|US|1912}} [[William H. Simpson]]}}
 |commander2  = {{ubl|{{flagdeco|Nazi Germany}} [[Johannes Blaskowitz]]
                     |{{flagdeco|Nazi Germany}} [[Alfred Schlemm]]}}
 |units1      = {{ubl|[[21st Army Group]]}}
* [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|British 2nd Army]]
* [[Ninth United States Army|U.S. 9th Army]]
 |units2      = {{ubl|[[Army Group H]]}}
* [[1st Parachute Army (Wehrmacht)|1st Parachute Army]]
 |strength1   = {{ubl|1,284,712 men|5,481 artillery pieces{{sfn|MacDonald|1973|p=297}}}}
 |strength2   = {{ubl|69,000 men|45 tanks}}
 |casualties1 = {{ubl|'''United Kingdom'''}}
* 3,968 casualties{{sfn|Ford|2007|p=91}}
                {{ubl|'''United States'''}}
* 2,813 casualties{{sfn|Ford|2007|p=91}}
                {{ubl|6,781 casualties total}}
 |casualties2 = 16,000 captured{{sfn|Ford|2007|p=91}}
 |campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Central Europe}}
}}

'''Operation Plunder''' was a military operation to cross the [[Rhine]] on the night of 23 March 1945, launched by the [[21st Army Group]] under Field Marshal&amp;nbsp;[[Bernard Montgomery]]. The crossing of the river was at [[Rees, Germany|Rees]], [[Wesel]], and south of the river [[Lippe (river)|Lippe]] by the [[Second Army (United Kingdom)|British Second Army]] under Lieutenant General Sir [[Miles Dempsey]], and the [[Ninth United States Army|United States Ninth Army]] under Lieutenant General [[William Hood Simpson|William H. Simpson]].

The [[First Allied Airborne Army]] conducted [[Operation Varsity]] on the east bank of the Rhine in support of Operation Plunder, consisting of [[XVIII Airborne Corps|U.S. XVIII Airborne Corps]], the [[6th Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|British 6th]] and the [[17th Airborne Division (United States)|U.S. 17th Airborne Divisions]].

==Background==
{{expand section|date=January 2018}}
Preparations such as accumulation of supplies, road construction, and the transport of 36 [[Royal Navy]] [[landing craft]], were hidden by a massive smoke screen from 16 March. The operation commenced on the night of 23 March 1945. It included the ''Varsity'' parachute and glider landings near Wesel, and [[Operation Archway]], by the [[Special Air Service]]. The landing areas were flooded, deserted farmland rising to woodland.

==Battle==
[[File:British commandos in the shattered outskirts of Wesel.jpg|thumb|left|[[British Commandos]] on the outskirts of Wesel]]
Four thousand Allied guns fired for four hours during the opening bombardment. British bombers contributed with [[Bombing of Wesel in World War II|attacks on Wesel]] during the day and night of 23 March 1945.

On the night of 23 March, companies E and C of the [[17th Armored Engineer Battalion]], part of the [[2nd Armored Division (United States)|U.S. 2nd Armored Division]], constructed treadway rafts to prepare the crossing of the Rhine about five kilometers south of Wesel. [[17th Armored Engineer Battalion#Rhine Crossing|Bridge construction]] started at 9:45am and by 4:00pm the first truck crossed the floating [[pontoon bridge]]. Over {{convert|1152|ft}} of M2 treadway and 93 pneumatic floats were laid in the six hours and fifteen minute construction project, a record setting for the size of the bridge. It took twenty-five 2-and-a-half ton [[GMC CCKW]] trucks to transport the bridge parts to the construction site, part of the [[Red Ball Express]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.writecorner.com/they_remember_war_5.asp They Remember War]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.facesbeyondthegraves.com/2nd%20armored%20division.html 2nd Armored WW2] facesbeyondthegraves.com&lt;/ref&gt;

Three Allied formations made the initial assault: the [[XII Corps (United Kingdom)|British XII Corps]] and [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]] and the [[XVI Corps (United States)|U.S. XVI Corps]]. The [[79th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|British 79th Armoured Division]]—under [[Major-general (United Kingdom)|Major General]] [[Percy Hobart]] — had been at the front of the [[Normandy landings]] and provided invaluable help in subsequent operations with specially adapted armored vehicles (known as [[Hobart's Funnies]]). One "funny" was the [[Landing Vehicle Tracked#Variants|"Buffalo"]] operated by the [[4th Royal Tank Regiment]], under the command of [[Lieutenant colonel (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Alan Jolly]], an armed and armoured amphibious tracked personnel or cargo transporter, which was able to cross soft and flooded ground. These were the vehicles for the spearhead infantry.

[[File:8th Royal Scots mortar under fire 24-03-1945.jpg|thumb|[[Ordnance ML 3 inch mortar|3-inch mortar]] of the 8th [[Royal Scots]] under enemy fire during the Rhine crossing, 24 March 1945]]
The first part of ''Plunder'' was initiated by the [[51st (Highland) Division|51st (Highland) Infantry Division]], led by the 7th Battalion, [[Black Watch|Black Watch (Royal Highland Regiment)]] of [[154th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|154th Brigade]] at 21:00 on 23 March, near [[Rees, Germany|Rees]], followed by the 7th Battalion, [[Argyll and Sutherland Highlanders]] (also of 154th Brigade). At 02:00 on 24 March, the [[15th (Scottish) Infantry Division]] landed between Wesel and Rees. At first, there was no opposition, but later they ran into determined resistance from machine-gun nests. On the same day the 51st Division's commander, Major-General [[Tom Rennie]], was killed by [[Mortar (weapon)|mortar]] fire. The British [[1st Special Service Brigade|1st Commando Brigade]] entered Wesel.

The [[30th Infantry Division (United States)|U.S. 30th Infantry Division]] landed south of Wesel. The local resistance had been broken by artillery and air bombardment. Subsequently, the [[79th Infantry Division (United States)|U.S. 79th Infantry Division]] also landed. American casualties were minimal. German resistance to the British landings continued with some effect, and there were armored counter-attacks. Landings continued, however, including tanks and other heavy equipment. U.S. forces had a bridge across by the evening of 24 March.

[[Operation Varsity]] started at 10:00 on 24 March, to disrupt enemy communications. Despite heavy resistance to the airdrops and afterward, the airborne troops made progress and repelled counterattacks. The hard lessons of [[Operation Market Garden]] were applied. In the afternoon, the 15th (Scottish) Division linked up with both airborne divisions.

Fierce German resistance continued around Bienen, north of [[Rees, Germany|Rees]], where the entire [[9th Canadian Infantry Brigade]] was needed to relieve the Black Watch. The bridgehead was firmly established, however, and Allied advantages in numbers and equipment were applied. By 27 March, the bridgehead was {{convert|35|mi|km}} wide and {{convert|20|mi|km}} deep.

==Aftermath==

===Impact on German forces and command===
[[File:Wesel 1945.jpg|thumb|250px|The city of Wesel lies in ruins after Allied bombardment, March 1945]]
The Allied operation was opposed by the [[German 1st Parachute Army]], commanded by {{lang|de|[[General (Germany)|General]]}} [[Alfred Schlemm]], a part of [[Army Group H]]. Although this formation was considered to be the most effective German force in the area, it was severely depleted from its previous action in the [[Battle of the Reichswald]]. Unable to withstand Allied pressure, the 1st Parachute Army withdrew northeast toward [[Hamburg]] and [[Bremen (city)|Bremen]], leaving a gap between it and the [[15th Army (Wehrmacht)|15th Army]] in the [[Ruhr]].

[[Joseph Goebbels]] was well aware of Plunder's potential impact from the beginning. On 24 March, he began his diary entry with, "The situation in the West has entered an extraordinarily critical, ostensibly almost deadly, phase." He went on to note the crossing of the Rhine on a broad front, and foresaw Allied attempts to encircle the Ruhr industrial heartland.

On 27 March, command of the 1st Parachute Army was passed to {{lang|de|General}} [[Günther Blumentritt]], because Schlemm had been wounded. Blumentritt and his superior, {{lang|de|[[Colonel general|Generaloberst]]}} [[Johannes Blaskowitz]], both recognised that the situation was lost. The army's front was incomplete, there were no reserves, weak artillery, no air support and few tanks. Communications were weak, indeed, one corps was never contacted. The reinforcements were so poor that the generals decided against using them, to avoid needless casualties.

Although Blumentritt had strict orders from Supreme Command to hold and fight, from 1 April, he managed a withdrawal with minimal casualties, eventually withdrawing beyond the [[Dortmund-Ems Canal]] to the [[Teutoburg Forest]]. Within a week of the start of ''Plunder'', the Allies had taken 30,000 prisoners of war north of the Ruhr.

===Winston Churchill===
[[File:Churchill on the east bank of the Rhine.jpg|thumb|[[Winston Churchill|Churchill]], [[Alan Brooke, 1st Viscount Alanbrooke|Brooke]], and [[Bernard Montgomery|Montgomery]] on the German-held east bank of the Rhine, 25 March 1945]]
[[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|British Prime Minister]] [[Winston Churchill]] was present at Field Marshal Montgomery's headquarters near [[Venlo]] on the eve of ''Plunder''. Subsequently, Churchill and Montgomery watched the ''Varsity'' air landings on 24 March.

The next day, 25 March, Churchill and Montgomery visited General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]′s headquarters. After lunch and a briefing, the party went to a sandbagged house overlooking the Rhine and a quiet, undefended stretch of the German-held riverbank. After Eisenhower's departure, Churchill, Montgomery, and a party of U.S. commanders and armed guards commandeered a river launch and landed for 30 minutes in enemy territory, without challenge. They next visited the destroyed railway bridge at Wesel, departing when German artillery appeared to target them.

===Military rivalries===
The Plunder crossings in the third week of March were planned as the primary assault across the Rhine, but at the [[Malta Conference (1945)|Malta Conference]] in early February 1945, it was decided to add another crossing to the south of the Ruhr. The additional crossing was intended to draw off any concentration of forces in opposition to Plunder. Two earlier crossing actually happened.

On 7 March, U.S. troops unexpectedly captured the [[Ludendorff Bridge]] during the [[Battle of Remagen]]. Within the next 10 days six divisions and 25,000 troops established a bridgehead on the eastern side of the Rhine.

On 22 March, General [[George S. Patton]] sent his [[Third United States Army|Third Army]] across the Rhine, at [[Nierstein]], to form another bridgehead. His superior, General Bradley, released news of this crossing to the press "at a time calculated to take some of the luster from the news of Montgomery′s crossing."{{sfn|MacDonald|1973|p=273}}
Bradley later remembered that Patton had strongly urged the announcement saying "I want the world to know that Third Army made it before Monty starts across".{{sfn|Saunders|2006|p=15}}

== In culture ==
* "Crossing the Rhine", Episode 8 of ''[[The Lost Evidence]]'', The History Channel, UK, 2004
* Heinz Bosch, Wilhelm Haas: ''Der Krieg am Niederrhein'', Kreis Kleve, 1976 (German)

== See also ==
* [[Ludendorff Bridge]], ''the bridge at Remagen''

==Notes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==Bibliography==
{{Commons category}}
* {{cite book |last=Churchill |first=Winston |authorlink=Winston Churchill |title=[[The Second World War (book series)|The Second World War]] |publisher=Cassell |year=1960 |location=London |pages=301–305 |oclc=}}
* {{cite book |last=Delaforce |first=Patrick |title=Onslaught on Hitler’s Rhine: Operations Plunder and Varsity, March 1945 |publisher=Fonthill Media |year=2015 |location=England |isbn=1-78-155441-2}}
* {{cite book |last=Ford |first=K. |title=The Rhine Crossings 1945 |publisher=Osprey |year=2007 |isbn=978-1-84-603026-0 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=MacDonald |first=Charles B |authorlink=Charles B. MacDonald |chapter=Chapter XIII The Rhine Crossings in the South |series=United States Army in World War II European Theater of Operations |title=The Last Offensive |publisher=Office of the Chief of Military History, Department of the Army |year=1973 |chapter-url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/USA-E-Last/USA-E-Last-13.html |accessdate=9 February 2011 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Moore |first=William |title=Decisive Battles |publisher=Windward |year=1986 |location=England |pages=118–124 |isbn=0-7112-0453-5}}
* {{cite book |last=Saunders |first=Tim |title=Operation Plunder |publisher=Pen &amp; Sword |series=Battleground Europe |year=2006 |location=Barnsley |isbn=1-84415-221-9 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Shulman |first=Milton |title=Defeat in the West |publisher=Masquerade |year=1995 |location=Chailey |pages=310–311 |isbn=1-872947-03-4}}

{{coord missing|Germany}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Plunder, Operation}}
[[Category:Operation Plunder| ]]
[[Category:1945 in Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|O]]
[[Category:March 1945 events]]</text><sha1>5q26leuz12t11ucqjb2jthugautv9je</sha1></revision></page>