<page><title>Operation Amherst</title><ns>0</ns><id>420301</id><revision><id>963371500</id><parentid>963359040</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-19T13:00:32Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Eastfarthingan</username><id>11187569</id></contributor><minor /><comment>Cleaned up using [[WP:AutoEd|AutoEd]]</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="5454" xml:space="preserve">{{Refimprove|date=February 2009}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Operation Amherst
| partof = the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front of 1944-45]] in the [[European theatre of World War II|European theatre]] of [[World War II]]
| image = Amherst monument frontaal.jpg
| caption = Monument in Assen, the Netherlands
| date = 7–8 April 1945
| place = [[Drenthe]], [[Netherlands]]
| casus =
| territory =
| result = Allied victory
| combatant1 = {{flagdeco|France|1830}} [[Provisional Government of the French Republic|France]]&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Netherlands}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Canada|1921}}
| combatant2 = {{flagdeco|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]
| commander1 = {{flagdeco|United Kingdom}} [[Mike Calvert]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|France|1830}} [[Pierre Sicaud]]
| commander2 =
| strength1 = {{flagdeco|France|1830}} [[Special Air Service]]
* [[1st Marine Infantry Parachute Regiment|3 SAS (French)]]
* [[2nd Parachute Chasseur Regiment|4 SAS (French)]]
{{flagdeco|Canada|1921}} [[8th Reconnaissance Regiment (14th Canadian Hussars)|8th Reconnaissance Regiment]]
| strength2 = Elements of the [[25th Army (Wehrmacht)|25th Army]]
| casualties1 =34 killed&lt;br&gt;60 wounded&lt;br&gt;69 captured&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.go2war2.nl/artikel/2621/Operation-Amherst.htm?page=7 Operation Amherst- Execution of the operation]&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 =300 killed or wounded&lt;br&gt;187 captured&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.go2war2.nl/artikel/2621/Operation-Amherst.htm?page=7 Operation Amherst- Execution of the operation]&lt;/ref&gt;
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Liberation of the Netherlands}}
}}

'''Operation Amherst''' was a [[Free French Forces|Free French]] and [[British Army during the Second World War|British]] [[Special Air Service|SAS]] attack designed to capture intact Dutch canals, bridges and airfields during [[World War II]]. It was led by [[Brigadier]] [[Mike Calvert]] of [[Chindit]] fame.

==The battle==
The operation began with the drop of 700 French [[Special Air Service]] troopers of the [[1st Marine Infantry Paratroopers Regiment|3rd]] and [[2nd Parachute Chasseur Regiment|4th]] SAS (French) on the night of 7 April 1945.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Horn | first = Bernd | title = Casting Light on the Shadows | publisher = Dundurn Press | location = Toronto | year = 2007 | isbn = 1-55002-694-1|page=187|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=E2ReYRiHmMQC&amp;pg=PA187 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The teams spread out to capture and defend key facilities from the Germans. Advancing Canadian troops of the [[8th Reconnaissance Regiment (14th Canadian Hussars)|8th Reconnaissance Regiment]] relieved the isolated French SAS.

The majority of the French paratroopers were dropped over the north-western part of the province of [[Drenthe]]. Here they occupied a series of bridges and conducted hit and run attacks on the withdrawing German troops. A small group of paratroopers under the command of Captain [[Pierre Sicaud]] were dropped in south-east Friesland close to the border of Drenthe. Under the cover of heavy clouds, several sticks consisting of approximately 15 paratroopers each managed to land without being detected by the Germans. Captain Sicaud, however, landed in a pine tree and his eye was pierced by a branch, seriously limiting the use of his eye.

Some of the French paratroopers were discovered by a band of Dutch resistance fighters who had made their shelter in the vast forests south of the small village of [[Appelscha]]. Led by an agent of the Dutch government in exile in England, the paratroopers re-grouped and conducted a series of attacks on German troops retreating through the area to Germany.

Sicaud and his paratroopers occupied an important bridge, seriously frustrating German troop movements. A series of running battles between the French, the Germans, and Dutch Nazi collaborators were conducted near the bridge. The civilian population of Appelscha, after a relatively calm five years of German occupation, experienced five days of heavy fighting that left no civilian casualties but plenty of German dead.

One group of paratroopers was dropped too far from Captain Sicaud and ended up on the outskirts of the small village of [[Haulerwijk]], ten kilometers north of Appelscha. German troops discovered the French in the early morning of 8 April and a fire fight broke out between the French and the Germans. One French SAS trooper was killed, while some of the French were captured and some managed to flee and catch up with the French fighting in and around Appelscha.

Eventually, in disarray, the Germans managed to counterattack with the rest of their troop. Some SAS and civilians were killed, but the remaining SAS troops forced the Germans to withdraw. This mini battle was referred to as "the last Amherst" where part of the town was destroyed, and a huge conflict ensued.

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* {{cite book |title=Qui Ose Vaincra| last=Bonnecarrère |first=Paul | year=1985 |publisher=Marabout Université |isbn=2-501-00748-4}}

{{coord missing|Netherlands}}

{{British Commando raids of the Second World War}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Amherst, Operation of 1945}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1945]]
[[Category:History of Drenthe|Operation Amherst]]
[[Category:Special Air Service]]
[[Category:Western European Campaign (1944–1945)]]
[[Category:World War II British Commando raids]]
[[Category:April 1945 events]]
[[Category:1945 in the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Military history of the Netherlands during World War II]]</text><sha1>pbae47dijhwdgczjemhahu0gcikfj8z</sha1></revision></page>