<page><title>Battle of Groningen</title><ns>0</ns><id>4353398</id><revision><id>966875381</id><parentid>960749474</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-09T18:36:05Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Eik Corell</username><id>6136027</id></contributor><comment>elements off -&gt; Elements of</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="6846" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Second World War battle from April 14-18, 1945}}
{{more citations needed|date=April 2011}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Battle of Groningen
|partof = the [[North-West Europe Campaign (World War II)|North-West Europe campaign]] in the [[Western Front (World War II)|Western Front]] of the [[European theatre of World War II]]
|image = Canadian soldiers during the Battle of Groningen.jpg
|image_size = 300px
|caption = Canadian troops in action at Groningen.
|date = April 14–18, 1945
|place = [[Groningen (city)|Groningen]], [[Netherlands]] 
|territory =
|result = Allied victory
|combatant1 = {{flag|Canada|1921}}
|combatant2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]
|commander1 ={{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[Bruce Matthews (Canadian Army officer)|Bruce Matthews]]
|commander2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Karl Böttcher]]
|units1 = {{flagicon|Canada|1921}} [[2nd Canadian Infantry Division|2nd Infantry Division]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Netherlands}} [[Dutch Resistance]]
|units2 =  Elements of:&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[408th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|408th Infantry Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[Image:Flag Schutzstaffel.svg|20px]] [[34th SS Volunteer Grenadier Division Landstorm Nederland|34th Panzergrenadier Division]]&lt;br&gt;[[Image:Flag Schutzstaffel.svg|20px]] [[Sicherheitsdienst]], and scattered [[Luftwaffe]], [[Kriegsmarine]] and [[Hitler Youth]]
|strength1 = ~14,000
|strength2 = ~7,500
|casualties1 = 43 dead&lt;br&gt;166 wounded 
|casualties2 = 130 dead &lt;ref&gt;(It was estimated in 1951 after extensive research that 130 Germans lost their lives during the fighting.) http://www.calgaryhighlanders.com/history/highlanders/1939-45/groningen.htm&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br&gt;5,212 captured &lt;ref&gt;[http://www.canadiansoldiers.com/mediawiki-1.5.5/index.php?title=Groningen#Aftermath Groningen - www.canadiansoldiers.com&lt;!-- Bot generated title --&gt;] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070926225535/http://www.canadiansoldiers.com/mediawiki-1.5.5/index.php?title=Groningen#Aftermath |date=September 26, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|notes =
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Liberation of the Netherlands}}
}}

The '''Battle of Groningen''' took place during the penultimate month of [[World War II|Second World War in Europe]], from April 14 to 18, 1945, in the city of [[Groningen (city)|Groningen]] between a mixture of German soldiers, Dutch and Belgian [[SS]] troops numbering 7,000 against the entire [[2nd Canadian Infantry Division]], though the whole division was never in combat at any given time. There were also substantial amounts of ''Luftwaffe'' units manning flak guns in the area. Groningen was also the site of the headquarters for the [[Sicherheitsdienst]] in the North of the Netherlands. The German command structure was poor and the defenders had never exercised together.

The Canadian division, consisting of nine infantry battalions, a machine gun battalion, and [[8th Reconnaissance Regiment (14th Canadian Hussars)|a reconnaissance battalion]], three combat engineer companies (Royal Canadian Engineers), was battle experienced with a proportion of partially trained reinforcements. Armour from the [[10th Armoured Regiment (The Fort Garry Horse)]] and the [[9th Armoured Regiment (The British Columbia Dragoons)]] was used in support.

==German objectives==
German soldiers in the city were determined to keep enemy forces from German soil while their Dutch SS colleagues had reason to fear for their lives if forced to surrender. German troops also needed to control the city to cover the withdrawal of forces from [[Friesland]] to [[Germany]] and defending the [[Ems (river)|Ems]] entrance into Germany, important because German surface vessels and [[U-Boats]] still used [[Emden]] as a port.

==Allied objectives==
Wary of advancing into the western Netherlands and incurring heavy casualties (as well as losses to the densely packed civilian population) at a late stage of the war (fighting in [[Langstraat]] and [[Betuwe]] showed that conditions were very favourable to the defence), the [[First Canadian Army]] instead moved northeast, supporting the flank of the British 2nd Army as they entered Germany proper.

==Battle==
German forces were mainly deployed in the ancient city centre shielded in part by an ancient canal. Some troops were deployed in the southern suburbs. A German pocket in the power station surrendered after the fall of the inner city. The inner city was reached on 14 April.

Western approaches to the old town (''Oude Stad'') were blocked because the bridges over the canal were destroyed. The ''Herebrug'' bridge in the south of the old town was not destroyed, but it took a day before the Germans with machine guns were defeated in the buildings north of a circular 'circus' on the north side of the bridge. The Canadians managed to enter the north of the city centre, ''Nieuwe Stad'', after two hours of fighting in the ''Noorderplantsoen'' park, which was placed where the city walls used to be in the 19th century and before.

The fight in the central market square, ''Grote markt'', was the fiercest part of the battle. There were several German machine guns in the buildings north of the square. The buildings had to be destroyed by tanks. The ''Nieuwe Stad'' was conquered, but the Canadians could not reach the ''Oude Stad'' from the north, due to fierce German resistance.

The German commander surrendered on 16 April once it was clear further resistance was useless.

The Canadians used armour effectively in co-operation with their infantry. Artillery support was forbidden out of fear of harming the civilian population.

==Result==
The death toll included approximately 130 Germans, 43 Canadians, and 100 Dutch civilians. Some 270 buildings were damaged or destroyed in the fighting. Over 5,200 Germans surrendered (including 95 officers) and the remaining Germans (about 2,000) fled northeast, and the 2nd Division again met them in battles such as the [[Battle of Grüppenbühren]] near [[Delmenhorst]].

==Significance==
Groningen was one of the largest urban battles of the war for the Canadian Army; while [[Battle of Ortona|Ortona]] was made famous by news reports referring to it as "Little Stalingrad", Groningen involved five times as many Canadian soldiers in direct combat.

==References==
{{Reflist}}
* Ashworth, G. J., ''The city as Battlefield. The Liberation of Groningen, April 1945'' (Groningen 1995).

==External sources==
* [http://www.calgaryhighlanders.com/history/highlanders/1939-45/groningen.htm www.calgaryhighlanders.com]

{{coord|53.2186|N|6.5672|E|source:wikidata-and-enwiki-cat-tree_region:CA|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Groningen, battle of}}
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:History of Groningen (city)|Battle of Groningen]]
[[Category:Urban warfare]]
[[Category:Western European Campaign (1944–1945)]]</text><sha1>iem4bs2t6dk8doixs98bwy94q7t34d0</sha1></revision></page>