<page><title>Battle of the River Plate</title><ns>0</ns><id>31570</id><revision><id>965645596</id><parentid>963732388</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-02T15:22:27Z</timestamp><contributor><username>FrescoBot</username><id>9021902</id></contributor><minor /><comment>Bot: [[User:FrescoBot/galleries|galleries syntax]] and minor changes</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="41053" xml:space="preserve">{{About|the naval battle|the film depiction|The Battle of the River Plate (film)}}
{{Short description|First naval battle of the Second World War}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of the River Plate
| partof      = the [[American Theater of World War II|American Theatre]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = HMS Achilles (70).jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = HMS ''Achilles'' as seen from HMS ''Ajax'' during the battle
| date        = 13 December 1939
| place       = Off the [[Río de la Plata|River Plate]], [[South Atlantic]]
| coordinates = {{Coord|32|S|47|W|source:enwiki-plaintext-parser|display=inline,title}}
| result      = Allied victory&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara 2004, p. 7.&lt;/ref&gt;
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|United Kingdom}} &lt;br&gt; {{flagcountry|Dominion of New Zealand}}
| commander2  = {{flagdeco|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[Hans Langsdorff]]
| commander1  = {{flagdeco|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Henry Harwood]]
| strength2   = 1 heavy cruiser 
| strength1   = 1 heavy cruiser &lt;br&gt; 2 light cruisers
| casualties2 = 96 killed and wounded &lt;br&gt; 1 heavy cruiser scuttled
| casualties1 = 100 killed and wounded &lt;br&gt; 1 heavy cruiser damaged &lt;br&gt; 2 light cruisers damaged
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Atlantic Campaign}}{{North American Theater}}
}}

The '''Battle of the River Plate''' was the first naval battle in the [[Second World War]] and the first one of the [[Battle of the Atlantic#South Atlantic (May 1942 - September 1943)|Battle of the Atlantic]] in [[South America]]n waters. The [[Kriegsmarine|German]] heavy cruiser {{ship|German cruiser|Admiral Graf Spee||2}} had sailed into the South Atlantic two weeks before the war began, and had been [[commerce raiding]] after receiving appropriate authorisation on 26 September 1939. One of the hunting groups sent by the British Admiralty to search for ''Admiral Graf Spee'', comprising three [[Royal Navy]] [[cruiser]]s, {{HMS|Exeter|68|6}}, {{HMS|Ajax|22|2}} and {{Ship|HMS|Achilles|70|2}} (the last from the [[New Zealand Division of the Royal Navy|New Zealand Division]]), found and engaged their quarry off the [[estuary]] of the [[Río de la Plata|River Plate]] close to the coast of [[Uruguay]] and [[Argentina]] in South America.

In the ensuing battle, ''Exeter'' was severely damaged and forced to retire; ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' suffered moderate damage. The damage to ''Admiral Graf Spee'', although not extensive, was critical; her fuel system was crippled. ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' shadowed the German ship until she entered the port of [[Montevideo]], the capital city of [[Neutrality (international relations)|neutral]] Uruguay, to effect urgent repairs. After ''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s captain [[Hans Langsdorff]] was told that his stay could not be extended beyond 72 hours, he [[Scuttling|scuttled]] his damaged ship and committed suicide rather than face the overwhelmingly superior force that the British had led him to believe was awaiting his departure.&lt;ref&gt;Churchill 1948, pp. 525–526.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
''Admiral Graf Spee'' had been at sea at the start of the Second World War in September 1939, and had sunk several merchantmen in the [[Indian Ocean]] and [[South Atlantic Ocean]] without loss of life, due to her captain's policy of taking all crews on board before sinking the victim.
[[File:Panzerschiff Admiral Graf Spee in 1936.jpg|thumb|left|''Admiral Graf Spee'']]

The [[Royal Navy]] assembled nine forces to search for the surface raider. Force&amp;nbsp;G, the South American Cruiser Squadron, comprised the ''County''-class heavy cruiser {{HMS|Cumberland|57|6}} of {{convert|10570|LT|lk=on}} with eight {{convert|8|in|mm|adj=on}} guns in four turrets, the {{sclass-|York|cruiser|0}} heavy cruiser HMS ''Exeter'' of {{convert|8390|LT}} with six {{convert|8|in|mm|adj=on}} guns in three turrets, and two {{sclass-|Leander|cruiser|0||1931}} [[light cruiser]]s, HMS ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'', both of {{convert|7270|LT|t}} with eight {{convert|6|in|mm|adj=on}} guns. Although technically a heavy cruiser because of the calibre of her guns, ''Exeter'' was a scaled-down version of the {{sclass2-|County|cruiser|4}}. The force was commanded by Commodore [[Henry Harwood]] from ''Ajax'', which was captained by [[Charles Woodhouse]].&lt;ref&gt;Churchill 1948, p. 516&lt;/ref&gt; ''Achilles'' was of the New Zealand Division (precursor to the [[Royal New Zealand Navy]]) and captained by [[Edward Parry (Royal Navy officer)|Edward Parry]]. ''Exeter'' was commanded by [[F. S. Bell|Captain Frederick Secker Bell]]. During the period before and at the immediate time of the battle, ''Cumberland'' (commanded by Captain Walter Herman Gordon Fallowfield) was refitting in the [[Falkland Islands]] but was available for sea at short notice.&lt;ref name="Churchill 1948, p.519"&gt;Churchill 1948, p. 519&lt;/ref&gt;
Force G was supported by the [[Replenishment oiler|oilers]] {{RFAux|Olna|X47|6}}, {{RFAux|Olynthus||2}}, and {{RFAux|Orangeleaf|1917|2}}. ''Olynthus'' replenished HMS ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' on 22 November 1939, and ''Exeter'' on 26 November, at [[San Borombon Bay]]. ''Olynthus'' was also directed to keep observation between Medanos and [[Cape San Antonio, Argentina|Cape San Antonio]], off Argentina south of the River Plate estuary (see chart below).
[[File:HMSO Graf Spee cruise.jpg|thumb|left|The route of ''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s cruise from the British HMSO report.]]

Following a raider-warning radio message from the merchantman ''[[Doric Star]]'', which was sunk by ''Admiral Graf Spee'' off South Africa, Harwood suspected that the raider would try to strike next at the merchant shipping off the River Plate estuary between Uruguay and Argentina. He ordered his squadron to steam toward the position [[32nd parallel south|32° south]], [[47th meridian west|47° west]]. Harwood chose this position, according to his despatch, because of its being the most congested part of the shipping routes in the South Atlantic, and therefore the point where a raider could do the most damage to enemy shipping.&lt;ref name="Churchill 1948, p.519" /&gt; A Norwegian freighter saw ''Admiral Graf Spee'' practising the use of its searchlights and radioed that its course was toward South America.

The three available cruisers of Force G rendezvoused off the estuary on 12 December and conducted manoeuvres. The British combat instructions for engaging a pocket battleship with a cruiser squadron (which had been devised by Harwood during his period at the [[Royal Naval College, Greenwich|Royal Naval War College]] between 1934 and 1936) specified an attack at once, day or night. If during the day, the ships would attack as two units, in this case with ''Exeter'' separate from ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles''. If at night, the ships would remain in company, but in open order. By attacking from two sides, Harwood hoped to give his lighter warships a chance of overcoming the German advantage of greater range and heavier broadside by dividing the enemy's fire.&lt;ref&gt;Barnett, 83.&lt;/ref&gt; By splitting his force, Harwood would force the Germans to either split their fire, reducing its effectiveness, or keep it focused on one opponent, allowing the other vessels to attack with less fear of return fire.

Although outgunned by ''Admiral Graf Spee'' and therefore at a tactical disadvantage, the British did have the upper hand strategically since any raider returning to Germany would have to run the blockade of the [[North Sea]] and might reasonably be expected to encounter the [[Home Fleet]]. For victory, the British only had to damage the raider enough so that she was either unable to make the journey or unable to fight a subsequent battle with the Home Fleet (by contrast the Germans would have to destroy the British force without being severely damaged). Because of overwhelming numerical superiority, the loss of even all three cruisers would not have severely altered Britain's naval capabilities, whereas ''Admiral Graf Spee'' was one of the [[Kriegsmarine]]'s few [[capital ship]]s. The British could therefore afford to risk a tactical defeat if it brought strategic victory.

==Battle==
&lt;gallery class="center" widths="250px" heights="230px"&gt;
File:HMS Exeter off Sumatra in 1942.jpg|HMS ''Exeter''
File:HMNZS Achilles SLV AllanGreen.jpg|HMS ''Achilles''
File:HMS Ajax.jpg|HMS ''Ajax''
&lt;/gallery&gt;

On 13 December at 05:20, the British squadron was proceeding on a course of 060° at 14 knots with ''HMS Ajax'' at 34° 34′ South 48° 17′ West, {{convert|390|nmi|km|abbr=on}} east of Montevideo. At 06:10, smoke was sighted on a bearing of Red-100, or 320° (to the north-west).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://ahoy.tk-jk.net/macslog/TheBattleoftheRiverPlate..html|title=Ahoy – Mac's Web Log – The Battle of the River Plate. 13th. December 1939|website=ahoy.tk-jk.net|accessdate=5 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Harwood ordered the ''Exeter'' to investigate. She swung out of line and at 06:16 she signaled by lamp: "I think it is a pocket-battleship", and Captain Bell ordered Flag N hoisted to the yard arm — "Enemy in sight".&lt;ref&gt;War Monthly (1977). Battle of the River Plate, by David Thomas (p. 3).&lt;/ref&gt; ''Admiral Graf Spee'' had already sighted mastheads and identified ''Exeter'', but initially suspected that the two light cruisers were smaller destroyers and that the British ships were protecting a merchant convoy, the destruction of which would be a major prize. Since ''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s reconnaissance aircraft was out of service, Langsdorff relied on his lookouts for this information. He decided to engage, despite having received a broadly accurate report from the German naval staff on 4 December, outlining British activity in the River Plate area. This report included information that ''Ajax'', ''Achilles'', ''Cumberland'' and ''Exeter'' were patrolling the South American coast.

Langsdorff realised too late that he was facing three cruisers. Calling on the immediate acceleration of his diesel engines, he closed with the enemy squadron at {{convert|24|kn|mph km/h|lk=in|abbr=on}} in the hope of engaging the steam-driven British ships before they could work up from cruising speed to full power.&lt;ref&gt;Barnett, 84.&lt;/ref&gt; This strategy may seem an inexplicable blunder: Langsdorff could perhaps have manoeuvred to keep the British ships at a range where he could destroy them with his {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns while remaining out of the effective range of their smaller 6" and 8" guns. On the other hand, he knew the British cruisers had a {{convert|4|–|6|kn|mph km/h|abbr=on}} speed advantage over ''Admiral Graf Spee'' and could in principle stay out of range should they choose to do so, standard cruiser tactics in the presence of a superior force, while calling for reinforcements.
[[File:HMS Exeter River Plate.jpg|thumb|Painting depicting the cruisers HMS ''Exeter'' (foreground) and HMS ''Achilles'' (right center background) in action with the German heavy cruiser ''Admiral Graf Spee'' (right background)]]

The British executed their battle plan: ''Exeter'' turned north-west, while ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'', operating together, turned north-east to spread ''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s fire. ''Admiral Graf Spee'' opened fire on ''Exeter'' at {{convert|19000|yd|m|abbr=on}} with her six {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns at 06:18. ''Exeter'' opened fire at 06:20, ''Achilles'' at 06:21, ''Exeter''{{'}}s aft guns at 06:22 and ''Ajax'' at 06:23. Lieutenant-Commander Richard Jennings,&lt;ref name=Pope /&gt; ''Exeter''{{'}}s gunnery officer remembers:

&lt;blockquote&gt;As I was crossing the compass platform [to his Action Station in the Director Control Tower], the captain hailed me, not with the usual rigmarole of 'Enemy in sight, bearing, etc', but with 'There's the fucking ''[[German cruiser Admiral Scheer|Scheer]]''! Open fire at her!' Throughout the battle the crew of the ''Exeter'' thought they were fighting the [sister ship] ''Admiral von Scheer''. But the name of the enemy ship was of course the ''Graf Spee''.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur, Max – ''Forgotten Voices of The Second World War'' , 2004, Random House, {{ISBN|0091897343}} p.29&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;

From her opening salvo, ''Admiral Graf Spee''′s gunfire proved fairly accurate, her third salvo straddling ''Exeter''. At 06:23, a {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}} [[shell (projectile)|shell]] burst just short of ''Exeter'', abreast the ship. Splinters from this shell killed the torpedo tubes' crews, damaged the ship's communications, riddled the ship's funnels and searchlights and wrecked the ship's [[Supermarine Walrus|Walrus]] aircraft, just as it was about to be launched for gunnery spotting. Three minutes later, ''Exeter'' suffered a direct hit on her "B" turret, putting it and its two guns out of action.&lt;ref&gt;Churchill 1948, p. 520&lt;/ref&gt; Shrapnel swept the bridge, killing or wounding all bridge personnel except the captain and two others. Captain Bell's communications were wrecked. Communications from the [[aft]] conning position were also destroyed; the ship had to be steered via a chain of messengers for the rest of the battle.

Meanwhile, ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' closed to {{convert|13000|yd|m|abbr=on}} and started making in front of ''Admiral Graf Spee'', causing her to split her main armament at 06:30 and otherwise use her {{convert|149|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns against them. Shortly after, ''Exeter'' fired two [[torpedo]]es from her [[starboard]] tubes but both missed. At 06:37, ''Ajax'' launched her [[Fairey Seafox]] spotter [[floatplane]] from its [[Aircraft catapult|catapult]]. At 06:38, ''Exeter'' turned so that she could fire her [[Port (nautical)|port]] torpedoes and received two more direct hits from {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}} shells. One hit "A" turret and put it out of action, the other entered the hull and started fires. At this point, ''Exeter'' was severely damaged, having only "Y" turret still in action under 'local' control, with Jennings on the roof shouting instructions to those inside.&lt;ref&gt;Arthur, pp. 29–30&lt;/ref&gt; She also had a 7° [[List (watercraft)|list]], was being flooded and being steered with the use of her small boat's [[compass]]. However, ''Exeter'' dealt the decisive blow; one of her 8-inch shells had penetrated two decks before exploding in ''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s funnel area, destroying her raw fuel processing system and leaving her with just 16 hours fuel, insufficient to allow her to return home.
[[File:HMSO Graf Spee battle map.jpg|thumb|left|HMSO chart of the engagement]]

At this point, nearly one hour after the battle started, ''Admiral Graf Spee'' was doomed; she could not make fuel system repairs of this complexity under fire. Two-thirds of her anti-aircraft guns were knocked out, as well as one of her secondary turrets. There were no friendly naval bases within reach, nor were any reinforcements available. She was not seaworthy and could make only the neutral port of Montevideo.&lt;ref&gt;Maier, Rohde, Stegemann and Umbreit 1991, p. 166.&lt;/ref&gt;

''Admiral Graf Spee'' hauled round from an easterly course, now behind ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'', towards the north-west and [[smoke screen|laid smoke]]. This course brought Langsdorff roughly parallel to ''Exeter''. By 06:50, ''Exeter'' listed heavily to starboard, taking water forward. Nevertheless, she still steamed at full speed and fired with her one remaining turret. Forty minutes later, water splashed in by a {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}} near-miss short-circuited her electrical system for that turret. Captain Bell was forced to break off the action. This would have been the opportunity to finish off ''Exeter''. Instead, the combined fire of ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' drew Langsdorff's attention as both ships closed the German ship.&lt;ref&gt;Barnett, 85.&lt;/ref&gt;

Twenty minutes later, ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' turned to starboard to bring all their guns to bear, causing ''Admiral Graf Spee'' to turn away and lay a [[smoke screen]]. At 07:10, the two light cruisers turned to reduce the range from {{convert|8|mi|nmi km|lk=on|abbr=on}}, even though this meant that only their forward guns could fire. At 07:16, ''Admiral Graf Spee'' turned to port and headed straight for the badly damaged ''Exeter'', but fire from ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' forced her at 07:20 to turn and fire her {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns at them, while they turned to starboard to bring all their guns to bear. ''Ajax'' turned to starboard at 07:24 and fired her torpedoes at a range of {{convert|4.5|mi|nmi km}}, causing ''Admiral Graf Spee'' to turn away under a smoke screen. At 07:25, ''Ajax'' was hit by a {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}} shell that put "X" turret out of action and jammed "Y" turret, causing some casualties. By 07:40, ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' were running low on resources, and the British decided to change tactics, moving to the east under a smoke screen. Harwood decided to shadow ''Admiral Graf Spee'' and try to attack at night, when he could attack with torpedoes and better use his advantages of speed and manoeuvrability, while minimising his deficiencies in armour. ''Ajax'' was again hit by a {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}} shell that destroyed her mast and caused more casualties; ''Admiral Graf Spee'' continued to the south-west.

==Pursuit==
[[File:Exeter'sDamage1939.jpg|thumb|Damage received by ''Exeter'' during the Battle of the River Plate]]

The battle now turned into a pursuit. Captain Parry of ''Achilles'' wrote afterwards: "To this day I do not know why the ''Admiral Graf Spee'' did not dispose of us in the ''Ajax'' and the ''Achilles'' as soon as she had finished with the ''Exeter''".&lt;ref name="Pope"&gt;Dudley Pope (1956), ''The Battle of the River Plate'', Chatham Publishing, UK, 1999, {{ISBN|1-86176-089-2}} p. ix&lt;/ref&gt; The British and New Zealand cruisers split up, keeping about {{convert|15|mi|nmi km|abbr=on}} from ''Admiral Graf Spee''. ''Ajax'' kept to the German's port and ''Achilles'' to the starboard. At 09:15, ''Ajax'' recovered her aircraft. At 09:46, Harwood signalled to ''Cumberland'' for reinforcement and the Admiralty also ordered ships within {{convert|3000|mi|nmi km|abbr=on}} to proceed to the River Plate. At 10:05, ''Achilles'' had overestimated ''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s speed and she came into range of the German guns. ''Admiral Graf Spee'' turned and fired two three-gun salvoes with her fore guns. ''Achilles'' turned away under a smoke screen.

According to Pope, at 11:03 a merchant ship was sighted close to ''Admiral Graf Spee''.&lt;ref name="Pope" /&gt; After a few minutes, ''Admiral Graf Spee'' called ''Ajax'' on W/T, probably on the international watchkeeping frequency of 500&amp;nbsp;kHz, using both ships' pre-war call-signs, with the signal: "please pick up lifeboats of English steamer". The German call-sign was DTGS, confirming to Harwood that the pocket-battleship he had engaged was indeed ''Admiral Graf Spee''. ''Ajax'' did not reply but a little later the British flagship closed with SS ''Shakespeare'' with its lifeboats still hoisted and men still on board. ''Admiral Graf Spee'' had fired a gun and ordered them to stop but when they did not obey orders to leave the ship, Langsdorff decided to continue on his way and ''Shakespeare'' had a lucky escape. The shadowing continued for the rest of the day until 19:15, when ''Admiral Graf Spee'' turned and opened fire on ''Ajax'', which turned away under a smoke screen.

It was now clear that ''Admiral Graf Spee'' was entering the River Plate estuary. Since the estuary had [[sandbank]]s, Harwood ordered ''Achilles'' to shadow ''Admiral Graf Spee'' while ''Ajax'' would cover any attempt to double back through a different channel. The sun set at 20:48, with ''Admiral Graf Spee'' [[silhouette]]d against the sun. ''Achilles'' had again closed the range and ''Admiral Graf Spee'' opened fire, forcing ''Achilles'' to turn away. During the battle, a total of 108 men had been killed on both sides, including 36 on ''Admiral Graf Spee''.

''Admiral Graf Spee'' entered Montevideo in [[Neutral country|neutral]] Uruguay, dropping anchor at about 00:10 on 14 December. This was a political error, since Uruguay, while neutral, had benefited from significant British influence during its development and it favoured the Allies. The [[British Hospital (Montevideo)|British Hospital]], for example (where the wounded from the battle were taken), was the leading hospital in the city. The port of [[Mar del Plata]] on the Argentine coast and {{convert|200|mi|nmi km|abbr=on}} south of Montevideo would have been a better choice for ''Admiral Graf Spee''.&lt;ref&gt;Millington-Drake, Eugen: ''The Drama of Graf Spee and the Battle of the Plate: A Documentary Anthology, 1914–1964.'' P. Davies, 1965. pp. 226 and 228&lt;/ref&gt; Also, had ''Admiral Graf Spee'' left port at this time, the damaged ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' would have been the only British warships that it would encounter in the area.

==Trap of Montevideo==
{{more citations needed section|date=December 2012}}
[[File:HMSO Graf Spee map of River Plate.jpg|thumb|left|Map of the [[Río de la Plata|River Plate]] showing possible exit channels.]]
[[File:Graf Spee Seetakt.jpg|thumb|''Admiral Graf Spee'' in [[Montevideo]], with battle damage]]

In Montevideo, the 13th [[Hague Conventions (1899 and 1907)|Hague Convention]] came into play. Under Article 12, "belligerent war-ships are not permitted to remain in the ports, roadsteads or territorial waters of the said Power for more than twenty-four hours." Under Article 14, "[a] belligerent war-ship may not prolong its stay in a neutral port beyond the permissible time except on account of damage." British diplomats duly pressed for the speedy departure of the ''Graf Spee''. Also relevant was Article 16, of which part reads, "A belligerent war-ship may not leave a neutral port or roadstead until twenty-four hours after the departure of a merchant ship flying the flag of its adversary."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://avalon.law.yale.edu/20th_century/hague13.asp|title=The Avalon Project: Text of the 13th Hague Convention}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Germans released 61 captive British merchant seamen who had been on board in accordance with their obligations. Langsdorff then asked the Uruguayan government for two weeks to make repairs. Initially, the British diplomats in Uruguay — principally [[Eugen Millington-Drake]] — made several requests for ''Admiral Graf Spee'' to leave port immediately. After consultation with London, which was aware that there were no significant British naval forces in the area, Millington-Drake continued to demand that ''Admiral Graf Spee'' leave. At the same time, he arranged for British and French merchant ships to steam from Montevideo at intervals of 24 hours, whether they had originally intended to do so or not, thus invoking Article 16. This kept ''Admiral Graf Spee'' in port and allowed more time for British forces to reach the area.

At the same time, the British attempted to feed false [[military intelligence|intelligence]] to the Germans that an overwhelming British force was being assembled, including [[Force H]] (the [[aircraft carrier]] {{HMS|Ark Royal|91|6}} and the [[battlecruiser]] {{HMS|Renown|1916|6}}) by broadcasting a series of signals, on frequencies known to be intercepted by German intelligence. In fact the two cruisers had been joined only by ''Cumberland'' which had arrived at 22:00 on 14 December, after steaming {{convert|1,014|nmi}} from the Falkland Islands in 34 hours, at an average of over 90% of her full trials speed attained over much shorter distances. The older and larger ''Cumberland'' was more powerful than ''Exeter'', with an additional aft turret containing two more 8-inch guns, but was no match on paper for ''Admiral Graf Spee'' whose guns had significantly longer range and fired much heavier shells (660 lb against 256 lb). Overwhelming British forces (HMS ''Renown'', ''Ark Royal'', {{HMS|Shropshire|73|2}}, {{HMS|Dorsetshire|40|2}}, and {{HMS|Neptune|20|2}}) were ''en route'', but would not assemble until 19 December, although they could intercept earlier if ''Admiral Graf Spee'' headed north or north east from Montevideo shadowed by ''Cumberland'' and her smaller consorts. For the time being, the total force comprised the undamaged ''Cumberland'' with a full ammunition load, and the damaged ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' with depleted stocks of shells. To reinforce the propaganda effect, these ships — which were waiting just outside the [[three-mile limit]] — were ordered to make smoke, which could be clearly seen from the Montevideo waterfront.

On 15 December 1939, ''Olynthus'' refuelled ''Ajax'', which proved a difficult operation; the ship had to use hurricane [[hawser]]s to complete the replenishment. On 17 December ''Achilles'' was replenished from ''Olynthus'' off Rouen Bank.

The Germans were entirely deceived, and expected to face a far superior force on leaving the River Plate. ''Admiral Graf Spee'' had also used two-thirds of her {{convert|283|mm|in|abbr=on}} ammunition and had only enough left for approximately a further 20 minutes of firing. Such a reduced ammunition stock was hardly sufficient for the ship to fight her way out of Montevideo, let alone get back to Germany, when contrasted with the previously unengaged ''Cumberland''{{'}}s ability to fight at full capacity for about 90 minutes and pursue at equal or higher speed for at least another {{convert|2,000|nmi}} before requiring replenishment at sea.

While the ship was prevented from leaving the harbour, Captain Langsdorff consulted with his command in Germany. He received orders that permitted some options, but not internment in Uruguay. The Germans feared that Uruguay could be persuaded to join the Allied cause. Ultimately, he chose to [[Scuttling|scuttle]] his ship in the River Plate estuary on 17 December, to avoid unnecessary loss of life for no particular military advantage, a decision that is said{{by whom|date=September 2018}} to have infuriated [[Adolf Hitler]]. The crew of ''Admiral Graf Spee'' were taken to [[Buenos Aires]], [[Argentina]], where Captain Langsdorff committed suicide by gunshot on 19 December. He was buried there with full military honours, and several British officers who were present attended. Many of the crew members were reported to have moved to Montevideo with the help of local people of German origin. The German dead were buried in the [[Cementerio del Norte, Montevideo]].

==Aftermath==
[[File:Admiral Graf Spee Flames.jpg|thumb|left|''Admiral Graf Spee'' in flames after being scuttled in the River Plate estuary]]
[[File:Hans Langsdorff.jpg|thumb|Captain Langsdorff at the funeral of crew members who were killed in the battle.]]

The German [[propaganda]] machine had reported that ''Admiral Graf Spee'' had sunk a heavy cruiser and heavily damaged two light cruisers while only being lightly damaged herself. ''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s scuttling however was a severe embarrassment and difficult to explain on the basis of publicly available facts. The battle was a major victory for the British, as the damage to ''Ajax'' and ''Achilles'' was not sufficient to reduce their fighting efficiency, while ''Exeter'', as badly damaged as she was, was able to reach the Falkland Islands for emergency repairs, before returning to [[HMNB Devonport|Devonport]] for a 13-month refit, thus enhancing the reputation of [[First Lord of the Admiralty]] [[Winston Churchill]].

Prisoners taken from merchant ships by ''Admiral Graf Spee'' who had been transferred to her supply ship ''Altmark'' were freed by a boarding party from the British destroyer {{HMS|Cossack|F03|6}}, in the [[Altmark Incident]] (16 February 1940)—whilst in [[Jøssingfjord]], at the time neutral [[Norway|Norwegian]] waters. Prisoners who had not been transferred to ''Altmark'' had remained aboard ''Admiral Graf Spee'' during the battle; they were released on arrival in Montevideo.

On 22 December 1939 over 1,000 sailors from ''Admiral Graf Spee'' were taken to Buenos Aires and interned there; at least 92 were transferred during 1940 to a camp in [[Rosario, Santa Fe|Rosario]], some were transferred to [[Club Hotel de la Ventana]] in [[Buenos Aires Province]] and another group to [[Villa General Belgrano]], a small town founded by German [[immigration in Argentina|immigrants]] in 1932. Some of these sailors later settled there.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.vgb.org.ar/historia.php] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090101125632/http://www.vgb.org.ar/historia.php |date=1 January 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt; After the war many German sailors settled permanently in various parts of Uruguay, some returning after being repatriated to Germany. Rows of simple crosses in the Cementerio del Norte, in the north of the city of Montevideo, mark the burial places of the German dead. Three sailors killed aboard ''Achilles'' were buried in the British Cemetery in Montevideo, while those who died on ''Exeter'' were [[Burial at sea|buried at sea]].

==Intelligence gathering and salvage==
{{update-section|date=September 2019}}
[[File:Graf Spee Wreck USNphoto 3.jpg|thumb|''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s Number Four 14.9&amp;nbsp;cm/55 gun mount (second gun in the forward port side group). Twin gun barrels at upper left are those of the ship's Number Two 10.5&amp;nbsp;cm/65 anti-aircraft gun mount]]
Immediately after her scuttling, the wreck of ''Admiral Graf Spee'' rested in shallow water, with much of the ship's superstructure remaining above water level, but over the years, the wreck has subsided into the muddy bottom and today{{when|date=September 2019}} only the tip of the mast remains above the surface.

A radar expert was sent to Montevideo shortly after the scuttling and reported a rotating aerial, probably for gunlaying, transmitting on either 57 or 114 centimetres.&lt;ref&gt;Johnson, Brian. ''The Secret War'', BBC 1979, pp. 101–102 {{ISBN|0-563-17769-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1940, the wreck was boarded by US Navy sailors from the light cruiser {{USS|Helena|CL-50|6}}.

In 1964 a memorial to the ship was erected in Montevideo's port. Part of it is ''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s anchor.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.darrellpeck.com/travel/2009-5-south-america/Images/10-29_graf-spee.JPG|title=Anchor of the Graf Spee, Montivideo|publisher=|accessdate=5 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1997, one of ''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s {{convert|149|mm|in|abbr=on}} secondary gun mounts was raised and restored; it can now be seen outside Montevideo's National Maritime Museum.

In February 2004, a salvage team began work raising the wreck. The operation is being funded in part by the government of Uruguay, in part by the private sector, as the wreck is now a hazard to navigation. The first major section, the {{convert|27|LT|t|abbr=on}} heavy gunnery control station, was raised on 25 February 2004. It is expected to take several years to raise the entire wreck. [[James Cameron]] filmed the salvage operation. After it has been raised, it was planned that the ship may be restored and put on display at the National Marine Museum.

Many German veterans did not approve of this restoration attempt, as they considered the wreck to be a [[war grave]] and an underwater historical monument that should be respected. One of them, Hans Eupel, a former specialist torpedo mechanic, 87 years old in 2005, said that "this is madness, too expensive and senseless. It is also dangerous, as one of the three explosive charges we placed did not explode."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/25/world/americas/25ship.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=1&amp;oref=slogin|title=A Swastika, 60 Years Submerged, Still Inflames Debate|last=Rohter| first=Larry|date=25 August 2006|work=The New York Times|accessdate=19 May 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 10 February 2006, the {{convert|2|m|ftin|abbr=on}}, 400&amp;nbsp;kg eagle and [[Swastika#As the symbol of Nazism|swastika]] crest of ''Admiral Graf Spee'' was recovered from the [[stern]] of the ship.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/americas/4702832.stm |title=Graf Spee's eagle rises from deep |website=BBC News|date=10 February 2006 |author= |accessdate= 6 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; This spread-wing statue of a Nazi eagle with a wreath in its talons containing a swastika was attached to the stern, not the bow like traditional figureheads. It was a common feature of prewar Nazi warships. In other cases, it was removed for a variety of practical reasons on the outbreak of the war, but because ''Admiral Graf Spee'' was already at sea when the war began, she went into action (and was scuttled) with it attached, thus permitting its recovery. To protect the feelings of those with painful memories of [[Nazi Germany]], the swastika at the base of the figurehead was covered as it was pulled from the water. The figurehead was stored in a Uruguayan naval warehouse following German complaints about exhibiting "Nazi paraphernalia".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-latin-america-30471063 |title=What should Uruguay do with its Nazi eagle? |website=BBC News |date=15 December 2014 |author= |accessdate= 6 June 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Legacy==
In 1956, the film ''[[The Battle of the River Plate (film)|The Battle of the River Plate]]'' (US title: ''Pursuit of the Graf Spee'') was made of the battle and ''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s end, with [[Peter Finch]] as Langsdorff and [[Anthony Quayle]] as Harwood. Finch portrays Langsdorff sympathetically as a gentleman. HMS ''Achilles'', which had been recommissioned in 1948 as [[INS Delhi (C74)|HMIS ''Delhi'']], flagship of the Royal Indian Navy, played herself in the film. &lt;!-- RIN Delhi: http://www.rjerrard.co.uk/royalnavy/sutton/sutton.html --&gt; HMS ''Ajax'' (twin turrets) was "played" by HMS ''Sheffield'' (triple turrets), HMS ''Exeter'' (twin turrets) by HMS ''Jamaica'' (triple turrets) and HMS ''Cumberland'' by herself (although de-gunned as a trials platform). ''Admiral Graf Spee'' (two turrets) was portrayed by the U.S. heavy cruiser {{USS|Salem|CA-139|6}} (three turrets).

The battle was for many years re-enacted with large-scale model boats throughout the summer season at Peasholm Park in the [[UK|British]] seaside resort of [[Scarborough, North Yorkshire|Scarborough]]. The re-enactment now portrays an anonymous battle between a convoy of British ships and an unspecified enemy in possession of the nearby shore.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Naval Warfare|website=Friends of Peasholm Park|url=http://www.peasholmpark.com/about/naval-warfare.html}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the battle, the new town of [[Ajax, Ontario]], in Canada, constructed as a Second World War munitions production centre, was named after HMS ''Ajax''. Many of its streets are named after Admiral Harwood's crewmen on ''Ajax'', ''Exeter'' and ''Achilles''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The Second World War created Ajax. Here's how|url=http://tvo.org/article/current-affairs/the-next-ontario/the-second-world-war-created-ajax-heres-how|website=TVO|first=Daniel|last=Kitts|date=10 November 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Its main street is named after Admiral Harwood, while a small street was named (after some controversy) for Captain Langsdorff. According to an article in the German language paper ''Albertaner'' on 6 October 2007, Steve Parish, the mayor of Ajax, defended the decision, declaring that Langsdorff had not been a typical Nazi officer. An accompanying photograph (above) from the funeral of crew members shows Langsdorff paying tribute with a traditional naval salute, while people beside and behind him—even some clergymen—are giving the Fascist salute.

A number of streets in [[Nelson Bay, New South Wales]], have been named after the battle including ''Montevideo'' Pde, ''Achilles'' St, ''Ajax'' Ave, ''Harwood'' Ave, ''Exeter'' Rd (now called Shoal Bay Rd). In Auckland, home port for the [[Royal New Zealand Navy]], streets have been named for Achilles, Ajax and Exeter.

The names of the ships, and the commander of Force G, have also been used for the Cadet Corps. The Royal Canadian Sea Cadet Corps (RCSCC) Ajax No. 89 in Guelph, Ontario; the Navy League Cadet Corps (NLCC) Achilles No. 34 in Guelph, Ontario; the Navy League Wrenette Corps (NLWC) Lady Exeter (now disbanded) and the camp shared by all three corps, called Camp Cumberland (this camp no longer exists; it was decommissioned around 1999). RCSCC Harwood No. 244 and NLCC Exeter No. 173 are situated in Ajax, Ontario.

The battle is also significant as it was the first time the current [[Flag of New Zealand]] was flown in battle, from HMS ''Achilles''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://paperspast.natlib.govt.nz/newspapers/auckland-star/1940/2/23/9|title=Captain Parry's Story of the Battle|quote=The "Diggers' " flag, the New Zealand Ensign, flying at the masthead of Achilles during the naval battle|work=The Auckland Star|volume=LXXI|issue=46|date=23 February 1940|page=9|accessdate=3 November 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Four mountain peaks in the Two Thumb Range region of the South Island of New Zealand are named to mark the battle. These are Achilles (2,544m), Exeter (2,327m), Ajax (2,319m) and Graf Spee (2,267m).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.topomap.co.nz/NZTopoMap?v=2&amp;ll=-43.55547,170.810532&amp;z=12|title=New Zealand Topographic Map – NZ Topo Map|website=NZ Topo Map|accessdate=5 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;gallery class="center" widths="250px" heights="230px"&gt;
File:Graves_of_sailors_H.M.S._Achilles,_Battle_of_the_River_Plate.jpg|Graves of the sailors from HMS ''Achilles'' in The British Cemetery, Montevideo, Uruguay
File:Graf Spee telémetro 01.jpg|''Admiral Graf Spee''{{'}}s salvaged [[rangefinder]] in Montevideo
File:HMS Achilles (HMNZS from 1941) (15333552416).jpg|HMS ''Achilles'', painting by Frank Norton is part of the National Collection of War Art held by [[Archives New Zealand]]
&lt;/gallery&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{Cite book|last=Churchill|first=Winston|title=The Second World War: The Gathering Storm|publisher =Houghton Mifflin Company|year=1948|edition=1st|volume=I}}
* Dick, Enrique. (2014) ''In the Wake of the Graf Spee''. Billerica, MA: WIT Press. {{ISBN|978-1-84564-932-6}}
* Hayes, James (producer &amp; director), ''[https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/programmes/timewatch/diary_plate_01.shtml Battle of the River Plate]'', episode 24.2 (2006) of ''[[Timewatch]]'', [[BBC]]
* Maier, Klaus; Rohde, Horst; Stegemann, Bernd; Umbreit, Hans. (1991) ''Germany and the Second World War: Germany's initial conquests in Europe''. Clarendon, Oxford. {{ISBN|0-19-822885-6}}
* {{Cite book|last=O'Hara|first=Vincent|title=The German fleet at war, 1939–1945|publisher=Naval Institute Press|year=2004|isbn=}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Battle of the River Plate}}
* [http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/battle_of_the_river_plate.htm History learning site articles with much detail on The Battle of the River Plate and ''Admiral Graf Spee'' in Montevideo]
* {{Cite journal |last=Jilani |first=Capt (Retd) AA |title=The Battle of the River Plate |journal=Defence Journal |url=http://www.defencejournal.com/dec99/river.htm |date=December 1999 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20030223133211/http://www.defencejournal.com/dec99/river.htm |archivedate=23 February 2003 |df=dmy }}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20041221122338/http://www.rnzncomms.net.nz/jackharker/achillesHMSO.html Official HMSO report]
* [http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2Navy-c4.html Royal New Zealand Navy (official history)]
* [http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2-1Epi-t1-g1-t2.html Achilles at the River Plate (official history)]
* {{in lang|es}} [http://juanjoseflores.blogspot.com/2004/12/los-tripulantes-del-graf-spee.html "The crew of the ''Graf Spee''"] – Largely anecdotal information on activities of the interned crew after the battle.
* {{cite book|last=Laurence|first=Ricardo E.|year=2000|title=Tripulantes del Graf Spee en tres atrapantes historias|location=Rosario|isbn=987-43-1754-X|publisher=Edición del Autor|language=es}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20061210055119/http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/lawofwar/hague13.htm 13th Hague Convention (Convention Concerning the Rights and Duties of Neutral Powers in Naval War)]
* [http://www.nzhistory.net.nz/node/14227 Battle of the River Plate (NZHistory.net.nz)]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20120402164730/http://www.cementeriobritanico.org/batrivpla1939.html Memorial to those lost]

{{Use British English|date=November 2012}}

{{Latin America during World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:River Plate, Battle of The}}
[[Category:Battle of the River Plate| ]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1939]]
[[Category:1939 in Uruguay]]
[[Category:Uruguay in World War II]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in Uruguay]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving New Zealand]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]
[[Category:Battle of the Atlantic]]
[[Category:Argentina in World War II]]
[[Category:December 1939 events]]
[[Category:Nazis in South America]]</text><sha1>nef8pc8lkugttvaq3q6pozhkhq24yr5</sha1></revision></page>