<page><title>Convoy SC 7</title><ns>0</ns><id>4526555</id><revision><id>964275479</id><parentid>925630607</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-24T15:25:12Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Xyl 54</username><id>2844289</id></contributor><comment>/* Aftermath */ add link</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="10990" xml:space="preserve">{{other uses|SC 7 (disambiguation)}}
{{More footnotes|date=April 2009}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2018}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Convoy SC 7
| partof      = [[World War II]]
| date        = 16–19 October 1940
| place       = [[Western Approaches]]
| result      = German victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|Nazi Germany}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[Karl Dönitz]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|UK|naval}} [[Lachlan Donald Ian Mackinnon|L. D. I. Mackinnon]]
| strength1   = 7 U-boats
| strength2   = 35 ships&lt;br /&gt;5 escorts
| casualties1 = None
| casualties2 = 20 merchant ships sunk, 141 dead&lt;br /&gt;total {{GRT|79,592|disp=long}}
}}
{{Campaignbox Atlantic Campaign}}

'''SC 7''' was the code name for a large [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[World War II]] [[convoy]] of 35 merchant ships and six escorts, which sailed eastbound from [[Sydney, Nova Scotia]], for [[Liverpool]] and other [[United Kingdom]] ports on 5 October 1940. While crossing the Atlantic, the convoy was intercepted by one of the first ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' [[U-boat|submarine]] [[Wolfpack (naval tactic)|wolfpacks]]. During the ensuing battle, the escort was completely overwhelmed and 20 of the 35 cargo vessels were sunk and 2 more damaged, with 141 lives lost. The disastrous outcome of the convoy demonstrated the German submarines' potential of being able to work more efficiently using wolfpack [[Naval_tactics_in_the_Age_of_Steam#Development_of_the_wolf_pack|tactics]] and the inadequacy of British [[anti-submarine]] tactics at the time.

==Ships of the convoy==
{{details|Order of battle for Convoy SC 7}}
The slow convoy SC 7 left [[Sydney, Nova Scotia]] on 5 October 1940 bound for Liverpool and other British ports. The convoy was supposed to make {{convert|8|kn|abbr=on}} but several merchant ships were much slower, necessitating a further reduced speed.. The convoy consisted of older, smaller ships, mostly with essential cargoes of bulk goods. Much of the freight on these ships originated on Canada's east coast, especially from points to the north and east of Sydney. Typical cargoes included pit props from eastern [[New Brunswick]] for British [[coal mine]]s, lumber, pulpwood, grain from the [[Great Lakes]] ports, steel and steel ingots from the Sydney plant and [[iron ore]] from [[Dominion of Newfoundland|Newfoundland]], bound for the huge steel plants of [[Wales]]. The largest ship in the convoy was the 9,512-ton oil tanker {{MV|Languedoc}}, belonging to the [[Admiralty]], which was bound for the [[River Clyde|Clyde]] with fuel for the [[Royal Navy]]. Another ship, the British {{SS|Empire Brigade}}, carried a valuable cargo of trucks.

Many of the ships were British but the convoy included Greek, Swedish, Norwegian and Dutch vessels. The [[convoy commodore]], [[Vice Admiral]] [[Lachlan Donald Ian Mackinnon]], a retired naval officer who volunteered for this civilian duty, sailed in {{SS|Assyrian|1914|6}}, a British ship of {{GRT|2962}}. As convoy commodore, Mackinnon was in charge of the good order of the merchant ships but did not command the escort. The {{sclass-|Hastings|sloop|0}} [[Sloop-of-war|sloop]] {{HMS|Scarborough|L25|6}} was sole naval escort for the first three quarters of the journey. There was no aircraft protection in 1940 for Allied ships in the Atlantic Ocean after leaving coastal regions. ''Scarborough'' would have had little chance against a surface attack by a [[Merchant raider|German raider]]. Many of the merchant ship captains were resentful at having to sail in convoy and would have preferred to take their chances on their own, rather than risk such a slow crossing with a weak escort. They were often uncooperative; at one point early in the voyage ''Scarborough''{{'}}s captain was shocked to find a Greek merchant ship in the convoy travelling at night with her lights on.

==Battle==

===5–18 October===
The convoy sailed on Saturday 5 October 1940. On the first day, one ship, {{SS|Winona||2}} dropped out with mechanical trouble, and had to return to port. The convoy "ran into a gale" on 8 October and then were engaged by [[U-boat]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Keegan (2002), p. 230&lt;/ref&gt; As bad weather set in on 11 October, several ships became separated and were forced to sail independently. One of these, {{SS|Trevisa||2}}, was a small [[Canada|Canadian]] [[Lake freighter|Laker]] of 1,813 tons, with a cargo of lumber destined for [[Scotland]]. She was sighted by {{GS|U-124|1940|2}} on 16 October and sunk. The [[Greece|Greek]] freighter {{SS|Aenos|1910|2}} was seen by {{GS|U-38|1938|2}}  and sunk on the 17 October but {{SS|Eaglescliffe Hall||2}}, another Laker, avoided this fate and was able to rescue survivors from ''Aenos'', before arriving safely at [[Rothesay, Bute|Rothesay]] on 19 October. A fourth straggler regained the convoy on 15 October.

On 17 October, as the convoy entered the [[Western Approaches]], ''Scarborough'' was joined by the sloop {{HMS|Fowey|L15|2}} and the new [[corvette]] {{HMS|Bluebell|K80|2}}. Later that day they were sighted by {{GS|U-48|1939|2}}, which attacked, sinking two ships including the tanker ''Languedoc''. ''Scarborough'' counter-attacked, driving ''U-48'' deep so she was unable to shadow or report but the attack was prolonged unwisely and the convoy moved so far ahead that ''Scarborough'' was unable to rejoin. On 18 October SC 7 was joined by the sloop {{HMS|Leith|U36|2}} and the corvette {{HMS|Heartsease|K15|2}}, with ''Leith'' assuming command. Later that day ''U-38'', sighted the convoy and attacked, damaging {{SS|Carsbreck||2}}. ''Leith'' and ''Heartsease'' attacked without success, though ''U-38'' was driven off and ''Heartsease'' was detailed to escort ''Carsbreck'' home, weakening the escort further.

===18/19 October===

On the night of 18/19 October, {{GS|U-46|1938|2}}, {{GS|U-99|1940|2}}, {{GS|U-100|1940|2}}, {{GS|U-101|1940|2}} and {{GS|U-123|1940|2}} made a concerted attack. ''U-99'' was captained by the famous ace ''[[Korvettenkapitän]]'' [[Otto Kretschmer]]. The attack was coordinated from [[Lorient]] by Admiral [[Karl Dönitz]] and his staff. An early casualty was the iron ore ship, {{SS|Creekirk||2}}, bound for [[Cardiff]], Wales. With her heavy cargo, she sank quickly, taking all 36 crew members with her. Later that night, SC 7 lost many of its members, including ''Empire Brigade'' with her cargo of trucks and six of her crew and  {{SS|Fiscus||2}} with her cargo of steel ingots from Sydney. She sank quickly as well, taking with her 38 of her 39-man crew. Also among the casualties was the commodore's ship, ''Assyrian'', which went down with 17 crew (Mackinnon was rescued after a long immersion in the chilly waters). In all, 16 ships were lost in this six-hour period.

===18–20 October===
On 18 October, {{SS|Blairspey||2}} was torpedoed by ''U-101'' and was abandoned. She was torpedoed again on 19 October by ''U-100'' but remained afloat. She was towed to the [[River Clyde|Clyde]] and later repaired at [[Greenock]].&lt;ref name=Ships&gt;{{cite book | first = and Sawyer, L A| last = Mitchell, W H | year = 1995| month = | title = The Empire Ships| pages = 395| publisher = Lloyd's of London Press Ltd| location = London, New York, Hamburg, Hong Kong|isbn=1-85044-275-4 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The escorts were unable to prevent any of these losses; their responses were uncoordinated and ineffective. They never realised that the attacking submarines did not attack submerged or from outside the convoy, but were actually running surfaced between the ships inside the convoy. Therefore, the escorts were unable to mount any serious attacks on the U-boats, and had to spend much of their time rescuing survivors.{{citation needed|date=December 2015}} During 19 October, the escorts, loaded with survivors, gathered together those ships that remained. ''Fowey'' collected eight ships and made for the Clyde, arriving there a few days later. ''Scarborough'' passed through the scene of the battle later on 19 October; she found wreckage, but no survivors. Later that afternoon ''Leith'' met ''Heartsease'', still escorting the damaged ''Carsbreck''; together they headed for [[Gourock]], [[Renfrewshire]], collecting two more stragglers on the way. ''Bluebell'' with over 200 survivors on board, headed directly for the Clyde, arriving on 20 October.

==Aftermath==
SC 7 had lost 20 ships out of 35, of which seven fell to Kretschmer's ''U-99''. The total tonnage lost was {{GRT|79,592}}. The arrival of [[convoy HX 79]] in the vicinity had diverted the U-boats and they went on to sink 12 ships from HX 79 that night.
No U-boats were lost in either engagement. The loss of 28 ships in 48 hours made 18 and 19 October the worst two days for shipping losses in the entire Atlantic campaign. The attack on SC 7 was a vindication of the [[U-boat Arm]]'s wolfpack tactic, and was the most successful U-boat attack of the Atlantic campaign. The convoy escort was ineffective in guarding against the attack. Convoy tactics were rudimentary at this early stage of the war. The escorts' responses were uncoordinated, as the ships were unused to working together with a common battle-plan. Command fell to the senior officer present, and could change as each new ship arrived.&lt;ref name="Lund, Ludlum p"&gt;Lund, Ludlum p&lt;/ref&gt; The escorts were torn between staying with the convoy, abandoning survivors in the water, as [[Defensively Equipped Merchant Ships|DEMS]] regulations demanded, and picking them up, leaving the convoy unprotected and risking being torpedoed themselves.&lt;ref name="Lund, Ludlum p"/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Battle of the Atlantic]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
* Paul Lund, Harry Ludlam: The Night of the U-Boats  (1973)  {{ISBN|0-572-00828-7}}
* {{cite book |series=[[History of the Second World War]] United Kingdom Military Series |title=War at Sea |volume=I |last=Roskill |first=S. W. |authorlink=Stephen Roskill |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=J. R. M |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |year=1957 |orig-year=1954 |publisher=HMSO |location=London |edition=4th impr. |oclc=881709135}}
* [[Dan van der Vat]] : The Atlantic Campaign (1988)  {{ISBN|0-340-37751-8}}
* Arnold Hague : The Allied Convoy System 1939–1945 (2000) . {{ISBN|1-55125-033-0}} (Canada).  {{ISBN|1-86176-147-3}} (UK)
* John Keegan : Intelligence In War (2002)  {{ISBN|0-375-70046-3}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last=Terraine |first=John |authorlink=John Terraine |title=Business in Great Waters: The U-Boat Wars, 1916–1945 |publisher=Leo Cooper |location=London |year=1999 |orig-year=1989 |edition=Wordsworth Editions |isbn=1-84022-201-8}}&lt;!--pp 265-268, 288, 448--&gt;

{{Uboat}}
{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Convoy SC 007}}
[[Category:North Atlantic convoys of World War II|SC007]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]</text><sha1>fc2wxkn375cp0qnrais71556vxywb0c</sha1></revision></page>