<page><title>Action of 4 April 1941</title><ns>0</ns><id>29657040</id><revision><id>936383490</id><parentid>933865228</parentid><timestamp>2020-01-18T14:10:57Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>91.110.109.164</ip></contributor><comment>/* Background */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="5876" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Action of 4 April 1941
|partof=[[World War II|Second World War]], [[Battle of the Atlantic]]
|image=
|caption=''The Thor.''
|date=4 April 1941
|place=mid [[Atlantic Ocean]]
|coordinates= {{coord|14.5|-40.5|display=inline,title}}
|result=German victory
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}
|combatant2={{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} J.A. Blackburn
|commander2={{flagicon|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[Otto Kähler]]
|strength1=1 [[auxiliary cruiser]]
|strength2=1 [[auxiliary cruiser]]
|casualties1=74 killed&lt;br/&gt;~100 wounded&lt;br/&gt;195 captured&lt;br/&gt;1 auxiliary cruiser sunk
|casualties2=none&lt;br/&gt;1 auxiliary cruiser damaged
}}
{{Campaignbox Atlantic Campaign}}

The '''Action of 4 April 1941''' was a naval battle fought during the [[Battle of the Atlantic|Atlantic Campaign]] of the [[World War II|Second World War]]. A [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[commerce raider]] encountered a [[United Kingdom|British]] [[auxiliary cruiser]] and sank her with heavy losses after an hour of fighting.&lt;ref name="bismarck-class1"&gt;{{cite web |author=John Asmussen |url=http://www.bismarck-class.dk/hilfskreuzer/thor.html |title=Hilfskreuzer (Auxiliary Cruiser / Raider) - Thor |publisher=Bismarck-class.dk |date= |accessdate=2014-06-21 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140305061411/http://www.bismarck-class.dk/hilfskreuzer/thor.html |archive-date=5 March 2014 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
The ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' [[auxiliary cruiser]] {{Ship|German auxiliary cruiser|Thor||2}} was raiding in the mid Atlantic in early 1941. On that cruise, the Germans engaged two other British armed merchant cruisers (HMS ''Alcantara'' and HMS ''Carnavon Castle'') in surface battles but they ended indecisively. So when ''Thor'' encountered ''Voltaire'', her crew were already battle tested and anxious to sink an enemy combatant. ''Thor'' was {{convert|122|m|ftin|abbr=on}} long and weighed {{convert|9200|LT|t|abbr=on}}, she was armed with six {{convert|150|mm|in|1|abbr=on}}, two {{convert|37|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} and four {{convert|20|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} [[naval gun]]s along with four {{convert|533|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} [[torpedo tube]]s. The raider also carried an [[Arado Ar 196]]A-1 [[floatplane]] for reconnaissance and had a complement of 349 officers and crewmen.&lt;ref name="bismarck-class1"/&gt;

HMS ''Voltaire'' was larger than the raider—displacing {{convert|13245|LT|t|abbr=on}}—but with a smaller crew of 269 men and officers. She had eight {{convert|152|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} and two {{convert|76|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} naval guns, including at least one [[anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft]] mount. ''Thor'' was returning to Germany when she found ''Voltaire'' heading to [[Freetown]] about {{convert|900|mi|nmi km|lk=on|abbr=on}} southwest of the [[Cape Verde Islands]].&lt;ref name="bismarck-class1"/&gt;

==Action==
It was about 06:15 on 4 April when crewmen of ''Thor'' spotted smoke on the horizon. [[Captain (naval)|Captain]] [[Otto Kähler]] assumed the vessel to be a coal burning ship so he altered course into the direction of the smoke. When the Germans were able to make visual contact with HMS ''Voltaire'', they suspected she was a neutral [[ocean liner]] as she did not attempt to escape. The British—under Captain J.A. Blackburn—sighted the approaching Germans coming head on, so they fired a burst of anti-aircraft fire as signal for identification. A signal from ''Thor'' was not returned, but the British soon discovered the identity of the approaching ship at about 06:45, when it replaced the flag of [[Greece]] with a German naval ensign and fired a shot across ''Voltaire''{{'}}s bow. The British responded by manning their guns and firing a broadside with their mixed armament, but to no avail; they were outgunned and outranged.&lt;ref name="bismarck-class1"/&gt;

After only four minutes of dueling at around {{convert|9000|m|yd|abbr=on}} away, the Germans began striking ''Voltaire'' with their {{convert|150|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} guns. The first shots entered the radio room and the generator room of ''Voltaire'', heavily damaging the vessel, knocking out communications and steering gear and putting her into a list. Heavy fires also broke out and nearly covered the entire deck of the British ship. Despite the fire the [[Royal Navy]] gunners continued fighting for nearly an hour. For the next several minutes, the two sides fired; only one British shot managed to hit ''Thor'', and it caused no casualties, the shot tearing off some radio equipment attached to the main mast. By 07:15, only two of the British {{convert|152|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} guns were in action, while ''Thor'' circled around ''Voltaire'', firing rapidly.&lt;ref name="bismarck-class1"/&gt;

At 08:00, the German's {{convert|150|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} guns overheated so Captain Kähler decided on a torpedo attack to end the engagement. But just as ''Thor'' was lining up to fire a spread, a white flag was observed aboard ''Voltaire'' and so the firing ceased. Captain Blackburn—having lost 72 men killed in action—gave the order to abandon ship and for the next five hours the Germans rescued 197 survivors, two of whom died later on and the rest became prisoners of war. Kähler also recorded that half of the rescued sailors were wounded. After the battle, ''Thor'' continued on to Germany to refit for a second raiding voyage. She had fired 724 rounds in a 55-minute battle, more than 50 percent of her ammunition.&lt;ref name="bismarck-class1"/&gt;

==See also==
*[[Single ship action]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2017}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:19410404}}
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|A]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battle of the Atlantic]]
[[Category:April 1941 events]]
[[Category:Germany–United Kingdom military relations]]</text><sha1>9zfvwd0p6368y3fxllvetm8zj5raxwe</sha1></revision></page>