<page><title>Action of 6 June 1942</title><ns>0</ns><id>30057202</id><revision><id>948320247</id><parentid>928545629</parentid><timestamp>2020-03-31T11:23:37Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Mad Bunny</username><id>4350530</id></contributor><comment>/* Aftermath */Fixed the internal link and corrected information regarding the number of ships that have been awarded the Gallant Ship citation. Also removed the reference to the US Navy as being the source of the citation.</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="7289" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Action of 6 June 1942
|partof=[[World War II]], [[Battle of the Atlantic]]
|image=
|caption=''The Stanvac Calcutta.''
|date=6 June 1942
|place=off [[Recife]], [[Brazil]], [[Atlantic Ocean]]
|coordinates=
|result=German victory
|combatant1={{flag|United States|1912}}
|combatant2={{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1=[[File:US Naval Jack 48 stars.svg|23px]] [[Gustav O. Karlsson]] {{KIA}}&lt;br/&gt;[[File:US Naval Jack 48 stars.svg|23px]] [[Edward L. Anderson]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[Horst Gerlach]]
|strength1=1 [[liberty ship]]
|strength2=1 [[auxiliary cruiser]]
|casualties1=17 killed,&lt;br/&gt;14 wounded,&lt;br/&gt;37 captured,&lt;br/&gt;1 liberty ship sunk
|casualties2=2 wounded,&lt;br/&gt;1 auxiliary cruiser damaged
}}
{{Campaignbox Atlantic Campaign}}

The '''Action of 6 June 1942''' was a [[single ship action]] fought during [[World War II]]. The [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[commerce raiding|raider]] {{ship|German auxiliary cruiser|Stier||2}} encountered and sank the [[United States|American]] tanker {{SS|Stanvac Calcutta}}  while cruising in the [[South Atlantic Ocean]] off [[Brazil]].

==Background==
''Stanvac Calcutta'' was a 10,170 ton [[Tanker (ship)|tanker]] with a crew of forty-two [[merchant marine]]rs and nine [[United States Navy Armed Guard|armed guards]] aboard. The ship was commanded by [[Captain (naval)|Gustav O. Karlsson]] and the guards by [[Ensign (rank)|Ensign]] [[Edward L. Anderson]]. Throughout World War II merchant ships were lightly armed and out of the six to be attacked by German raiders, only ''Stanvac Calcutta'' and {{SS|Stephen Hopkins||2}} offered serious resistance and both were sunk. When Ensign Anderson was assigned to the ship he was responsible for finding armaments and it proved to be difficult. Anderson acquired one {{convert|4|in|mm|adj=on|0}}/50-caliber [[naval gun]] salvaged from [[World War I]] and an {{convert|5|in|mm|abbr=on|0}}/25-caliber [[anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft gun]] from the same era to arm his ship. ''Stier'' was heavily armed, she was under the command of Captain [[Horst Gerlach]] and mounted six {{convert|150|mm|in|adj=on|0}} guns, one {{convert|37|mm|in|abbr=on}} gun, two {{convert|20|mm|in|abbr=on}} cannons and two [[torpedo tube]]s. Captain Karlsson left [[Montevideo]] on 29 May 1942 headed north along the coast for [[Caripito, Venzuela|Caripito]], [[Venezuela]].&lt;ref name="Gleichauf130-131"&gt;Gleichauf, pg. 130-133&lt;/ref&gt;

==Action==
A week after leaving Montevideo at 10:12 am on 6 June, the American ship was {{convert|500|mi}} east of [[Pernambuco]], Brazil, weather was overcast and the sea rough. Suddenly gunfire was heard and the Americans observed ''Stier'' sailing out of a squall and quickly heading towards ''Stanvac Calcutta'' almost head on and signaling the Americans to cut their engines. The Germans apparently believed the tanker was an unarmed merchantman. Beforehand Captain Karlsson and Ensign Anderson had planned a course of action for defending the vessel. As soon as the Germans were spotted, ''Stanvac Calcutta'' turned to the side to bring her guns to bear and when the raider closed to an estimated {{convert|3,500|yd|m}}, Ensign Anderson ordered his gunners to open fire. In succession the armed guards fired five shots with the aft 4-inch gun and several rounds of the bow anti-aircraft gun. The last of the five shells struck and disabled a 150&amp;nbsp;mm gun aboard ''Stier'' just before it began delivering broadsides of four cannons and [[machine gun]] fire.&lt;ref name="Gleichauf130-131"/&gt;

Merchant sailors were trained and used to man the anti-aircraft gun, it fired continually throughout the battle though it misfired a few times because of old ammunition. In fifteen minutes of fighting the ''Stanvac Calcutta'' was struck several times in the bridge and elsewhere, killing Captain Karlsson and a few other men. After hitting the ''Stier'' the guards manning the 4-inch gun were reported to have been encouraged and continued firing accurately until shrapnel damaged their weapon. The sights were destroyed but the Americans continued shooting until the ammunition on deck was exhausted. At this time Ensign Anderson ordered two men to retrieve more ammunition from below deck though as soon as they left, Captain Gerlach maneuvered his ship for a torpedo attack. When lined up, ''Stier'' fired one torpedo and it dove into the water and headed straight for ''Stanvac Calcutta'' where it detonated on the port side. Water began flowing in and the vessel started listing. A number of additional men were killed in the torpedo explosion and when it was clear that the American ship could not be saved, Ensign Anderson ordered the survivors to abandon ship and he began to lower life rafts.&lt;ref name="Gleichauf130-131"/&gt;

While operating the crank a piece of shrapnel entered Anderson's back, paralyzing his legs but he continued to lower the boat and after looking around to see if anybody else needed help, the ensign slipped over the side into an oil slick. With a broken leg Anderson swam over to a wounded officer in the water and attempted to pull him to one of the life rafts but the man died of his wound first and a few moments later the Germans lowered boats and began rescuing the Americans. The Germans fired 148 shells and one torpedo while ''Stanvac Calcutta'' fired only twenty-five, hundreds of machine gun rounds were also expended by both sides.&lt;ref name="Gleichauf130-131"/&gt;

==Aftermath==
Sixteen merchant sailors and armed guards were killed in action, thirty-seven prisoners were taken, of whom fourteen were wounded, one armed guard died later aboard ''Stier''. Two Germans were wounded and ''Stier'' continued raiding for 4 months, sinking only two more ships before being sunk by {{SS|Stephen Hopkins}} in a mutually destructive battle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usmm.org/calcutta.html |title=Stanvac Calcutta: the Gallant Ship that Fought a German Raider |publisher=Usmm.org |date=1942-05-29 |accessdate=2014-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; SS ''Stanvac Calcutta'' was one of the few World War II merchant ships to be awarded the [[Merchant Marine Gallant Ship Citation]]. Ensign Anderson was promoted to the rank of [[Lieutenant commander (United States)|lieutenant commander]] before leaving the navy sometime after the war. The American prisoners were eventually turned over to the [[Japan]]ese.&lt;ref name="Gleichauf130-131"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.usmm.org/pow.html |title=American Merchant Marine Prisoners of War during World War II |publisher=Usmm.org |date= |accessdate=2014-06-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Pacific War]]
*[[Battle of the Mediterranean]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
*{{cite book |last=Gleichauf|first=F. Justin|coauthors= |edition= |title=Unsung sailors: the Naval Armed Guard in World War II|year=2003|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=1-55750-420-2}}

{{coord|8|40|57|S|26|26|5|W|display=title}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2017}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:19420606}}
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battle of the Atlantic]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:June 1942 events]]
[[Category:Germany–United States military relations]]</text><sha1>kq0qr65s99o977ejs4ozulhqmx79wsl</sha1></revision></page>