<page><title>Convoy PQ 17</title><ns>0</ns><id>240494</id><revision><id>965335330</id><parentid>965334962</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-30T18:45:06Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Xyl 54</username><id>2844289</id></contributor><comment>Infobox/ add ships</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="51984" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Code name for an Allied World War II convoy in the Arctic Ocean}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Convoy PQ 17
| partof      = [[Second World War]], [[Arctic naval operations of World War II|Arctic Campaign]]
| campaign    = Arctic Campaign
| image       = Convoy PQ 17 sailing in Hvalfjord.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = Escorts and merchant ships at [[Hvalfjord]] May 1942 before the sailing of Convoy ''PQ 17''.
| date        = 27 June – 10 July 1942
| place       = [[Arctic Ocean]]
| result      = German victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|United Kingdom}} &lt;br /&gt; {{flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[John Tovey, 1st Baron Tovey|Adm. J. C. Tovey]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Louis Henry Keppel Hamilton|Rear-Adm. L.H.K. Hamilton]] &lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Jack Broome|Cpt. J. E. Broome]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Commodore (rank)|Commodore]] John Dowding
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[Erich Raeder|''Großadmiral'' Erich Raeder]] &lt;br /&gt; {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[Karl Dönitz|''Admiral'' Karl Dönitz]] &lt;br /&gt; {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|naval}}  [[Hans-Jürgen Stumpff|''Generaloberst'' Hans-Jürgen Stumpff]]
| strength1   =  2 battleships, 6 cruisers, 13 destroyers (did not engage):&lt;br /&gt;6 destroyers, &lt;br /&gt; 2 anti-aircraft ships,&lt;br /&gt; 2 submarines,&lt;br /&gt; 11 smaller craft, &lt;br /&gt; 35 merchant ships &lt;br /&gt; 6 auxiliary ships&lt;ref&gt;Schofield pp. 77–78&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 1 battleship, 3 cruisers, 12 destroyers (did not engage):&lt;br /&gt;11 U-boats:&lt;br /&gt; 33 torpedo aircraft, &lt;br /&gt; 6 bombers. &lt;br /&gt; (''Flying over 200 sorties'')
| casualties1 = 24 merchant ships sunk,&lt;br /&gt;153 merchant mariners killed
| casualties2 = 5 aircraft
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Arctic Naval Operations of WWII}}
}}
'''PQ 17''' was the code name for an [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[Arctic convoys|Arctic convoy]] during the [[Second World War]]. On 27 June 1942, the ships sailed from [[Hvalfjord]], [[Iceland]], for the [[Port of Arkhangelsk|port]] of [[Arkhangelsk]] in the [[Soviet Union]]. The convoy was located by [[Nazi Germany|German]] forces on 1 July, after which it was shadowed continuously and attacked. The [[First Sea Lord]] Admiral [[Dudley Pound]], acting on information that [[Kriegsmarine#Surface ships|German surface units]], including the [[German battleship Tirpitz|German battleship ''Tirpitz'']], were moving to intercept, ordered the [[covering force]] built around the Allied battleships [[HMS Duke of York|HMS ''Duke of York'']] and the [[USS Washington (BB-56)|USS ''Washington'']] away from the convoy and told the convoy to scatter. Due to vacillation by ''[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]'' (OKW, German armed forces high command), the ''Tirpitz'' raid never materialised.&lt;ref&gt;Patrick Beesly, "Convoy PQ 17: A Study of Intelligence and Decision-Making," ''Intelligence &amp; National Security'' (1990) 5#2 pp. 292–322&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=churchill235&gt;{{citation|last =Churchill|title=The Second World War, Volume IV|page=235|title-link=#Churchill}}&lt;/ref&gt; The convoy was the first large joint Anglo-American naval operation under British command; in Churchill's view this encouraged a more careful approach to fleet movements.&lt;ref name="Churchill_a"&gt;{{citation|last= Churchill|title=The Second World War, Volume IV|page=236|title-link=#Churchill}}&lt;/ref&gt;

As the close escort and the covering cruiser forces withdrew westwards to intercept the German raiders, the merchant ships were left without escorts.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hill|title=Destroyer Captain|pages=45–46|title-link=#Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt; The merchant ships were attacked by ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' aircraft and [[U-boat]]s and of the 35 ships, only eleven reached their destination, delivering {{convert|70000|ST|MT|abbr=off}} of cargo.&lt;ref name="Churchill_c"&gt;{{citation|last=Churchill|title=The Second World War, Volume IV|page=237|title-link=#Churchill}}&lt;/ref&gt; The convoy disaster demonstrated the difficulty of passing adequate supplies through the Arctic, especially during the summer [[midnight sun]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Churchill|title=The Second World War, Volume IV|page =240|title-link=#Churchill}}&lt;/ref&gt; Convoy PQ 17 lost 24 of its 35 merchant ships during a week of daylight attacks by U-boats and aircraft.&lt;ref name=longaz1&gt;{{citation|title=London Gazette, Friday, 13 October 1950|page=5139|title-link= #LonGaz}}&lt;/ref&gt; The German success was possible through German [[signals intelligence]] and cryptological analysis.&lt;ref&gt;Albert Praun, German Radio Intelligence&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
With [[Operation Barbarossa]], the beginning of the German war against the USSR, the British and American governments agreed to send unconditional aid to their Soviet allies. The [[Max Aitken, 1st Baron Beaverbrook|Beaverbrook]]-[[W. Averell Harriman|Harriman]] Anglo-American Mission visited [[Moscow]] in October 1941, agreeing to a series of munitions deliveries to the Soviet Union.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation| last=Langer|title=The Harriman-Beaverbrook Mission and the Debate over Unconditional Aid for the Soviet Union, 1941|pages=463–482|title-link=#Langer}}&lt;/ref&gt; The most direct way to carry these supplies was by sea around the [[North Cape, Norway|North Cape]], through Arctic waters to the ports of Murmansk and Arkhangelsk.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Churchill|title=The Second World War, Volume IV |page=228|title-link=#Churchill }}&lt;/ref&gt; The agreement stated that the Soviet government was responsible for receiving the supplies in Soviet ships at British or American ports. However, since the Soviets did not have enough ships for the quantities of aid being sent by the Western allies to the Soviet Union, British and American ships began to constitute an increasing proportion of the convoy traffic.&lt;ref name="Churchill"&gt;{{citation| last=Churchill|title=The Second World War, Volume IV|page=229|title-link=#Churchill}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the defence of the Arctic convoys was the responsibility of the [[Royal Navy]], the American [[Admiral (United States)|Admiral]] [[Ernest King]] assigned Task Force 39 (TF 39) – built around the carrier {{USS|Wasp|CV-7|6}} and the battleship {{USS|Washington|BB-56|6}} – to support the British.&lt;ref name=miller309&gt;{{citation|last=Miller|title=War at Sea: A Naval History of World War II|page=309|title-link=#miller}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The first convoy sailed from the United Kingdom in August 1941, two months after the beginning of Operation Barbarossa. By the spring of 1942, twelve more convoys had made the passage with the loss of only one out of 103 ships.&lt;ref name=longaz1 /&gt; From then, the threat of attacks on the convoys increased, with the Germans preparing to stop the flow of supplies to the USSR with every means at their disposal, including the basing of heavy ships in [[Norway]].&lt;ref name=longaz1 /&gt; In 1941, the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' had already begun concentrating its strength in Norway in winter, to prevent a British invasion of Norway and to obstruct Allied supply lines to the Soviet Union. The battleship {{Ship|German battleship|Tirpitz||2}} was moved to [[Trondheim]] in January, where she was joined by the heavy cruiser {{Ship|German cruiser|Admiral Scheer||2}} and in March by the [[heavy cruiser]] {{Ship|German cruiser|Admiral Hipper||2}}.&lt;ref name=longaz2&gt;{{citation|title= London Gazette, Friday, 13 October 1950|page=5140|title-link=#LonGaz}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[battleship]]s {{Ship|German battleship|Scharnhorst||2}}, {{Ship|German battleship|Gneisenau||2}} and the heavy cruiser {{Ship|German cruiser|Prinz Eugen||2}} were also sent to Arctic waters but fell victim to Allied air attacks and had to turn back for repairs.&lt;ref name="Churchill" /&gt; The Germans had bases along the Norwegian coast, which meant, until [[escort carrier]]s became available, Allied convoys had to be sailed through these areas without adequate defence against aircraft and submarine attack.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hill|title=Destroyer Captain|page=26|title-link=#Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==British plans==

[[File:Convoy PQ-17 map 1942-en.svg|thumb|Track of PQ 17, showing approximate positions of sinkings]]
British naval intelligence in June reported the [[Operation Rösselsprung (Naval)|Operation Rösselsprung]] (''Unternehmen Rösselsprung'') the German plan to bring out major naval units to attack the next eastbound convoy, east of [[Bear Island (Norway)|Bear Island]].&lt;ref name=longaz2/&gt;&lt;ref name="Winton"&gt;{{citation|last=Winton|title=Ultra at sea|page=61|title-link=#Winton}}&lt;/ref&gt; Thus German forces would operate close to the Norwegian coast, with support of shore-based air reconnaissance and striking forces, with a screen of U-boats in the channels between [[Svalbard]] and Norway.&lt;ref name=longaz3&gt;{{citation|title=London Gazette, Friday, 13 October 1950|page=5143|title-link=#LonGaz}}&lt;/ref&gt; Allied covering forces, on the other hand, would be without air support, one thousand miles from their base, and with the destroyers too short on fuel to escort a damaged ship to harbour.&lt;ref name=longaz2/&gt;

To prevent such a situation, the Admiralty issued instructions on 27 June, which allowed the convoy to be turned back temporarily in order to shorten the distance to the nearest Allied base.&lt;ref name=longaz3/&gt; In the event, enemy surface movements took place later than expected, making these instructions unnecessary.&lt;ref name="churchill235" /&gt; The Admiralty also instructed the safety of the convoy from surface attack to the westward of Bear Island depended on Allied surface forces, while to the eastward it was to be met by Allied submarines. Furthermore, the convoy's cruiser covering force was not to go east of Bear Island, unless the convoy was threatened by the presence of a surface force which the cruiser force could fight, nor to go beyond 25° East under any circumstance.&lt;ref name="Churchill_a" /&gt;&lt;ref name=longaz4&gt;{{citation|title=London Gazette, Friday, 13 October 1950|pages=5144–5145|title-link=#LonGaz}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A decoy convoy was also organised to divert enemy forces, consisting of the First Minelaying Squadron and four colliers, escorted by [[HMS Sirius (82)|HMS ''Sirius'']] and {{HMS|Curacoa|D41|2}}, five destroyers and some trawlers. This diversionary force assembled at [[Scapa Flow]] for a week, sailing two days after the convoy.&lt;ref name=longaz5&gt;{{citation|title=London Gazette, Friday, 13 October 1950|page=5145|title-link=#LonGaz}}&lt;/ref&gt; German reconnaissance of Scapa during the period of assembly failed to notice the diversion, which was also not sighted on its passage. The operation was repeated on 1 July, again without success.&lt;ref name=longaz5/&gt; Additionally on 26 June the Admiralty took the opportunity to pass a westbound [[convoy QP 13]], in conjunction with PQ 17. The former was made up of returning merchant ships from Arkhangelsk, with some ships leaving [[Murmansk]].&lt;ref name=longaz5/&gt; It consisted of 35 ships and was escorted by five destroyers, three corvettes, one anti-aircraft ship, three minesweepers, two trawlers and, as far as the Bear Island area, one submarine. It was sighted by German aircraft on 30 June and 2 July. However, QP 13 was not attacked, since the German tactic was to concentrate on eastbound (laden) convoys,&lt;ref name=longaz5/&gt; rather than westbound convoys in [[ballast tank|ballast]].

A fresh ice reconnaissance done on 3 July found the passage north of Bear Island had widened. The Admiralty suggested the convoy should pass at least {{convert|50|mi|km|abbr=on}} north of it.&lt;ref name=longaz6&gt;{{citation|title=London Gazette, Friday, 13 October 1950|page=5146|title-link=#LonGaz}}&lt;/ref&gt; The senior officer of the escort (SOE), Commander [[Jack Broome|J. E. Broome]], preferred to stay in the low visibility on the original route, and to make ground to the eastward. [[Rear Admiral]] [[Louis Hamilton (Royal Navy officer)|L. H. K. Hamilton]], in command of the cruiser squadron, later decided that a more northerly route was necessary, ordered the SOE to alter the convoy's course to pass {{convert|70|mi|km}} north of Bear Island and, later on to open to {{convert|400|mi|km|abbr=on}} from [[Banak, Norway|Banak]].&lt;ref name=longaz6/&gt;

==Covering forces==
[[Image:PQ17 HMS London and USS Wichita.png|thumb|right|{{USS|Wichita|CA-45|6}} and {{HMS|London|69|6}}, part of PQ 17's cruiser covering force.]]
The convoy's close escort was the First Escort Group (EG1), under [[Commander|Cdr]]. [[Jack Broome|J Broome]], and included six destroyers, 11 [[corvette]]s, [[minesweeper (ship)|minesweepers]] or [[naval trawler|armed trawlers]] and two anti-aircraft auxiliaries. The destroyers were {{HMS|Keppel|D84|6}} (SOE), {{HMS|Fury|H76|2}}, {{HMS|Leamington|G19|2}}, {{HMS|Ledbury|L90|2}}, {{HMS|Offa|G29|2}} and {{HMS|Wilton||2}}. The anti-aircraft auxiliaries were {{HMS|Palomares||6}} and {{HMS|Pozarica}}. The other escorting ships were the corvettes {{HMS|Lotus|K130|6}}, {{HMS|Poppy|K213|6}}, {{HMS|La Malouine|K46|2}} and {{HMS|Dianella}}, the minesweepers {{HMS|Halcyon|J42|6}}, {{HMS|Salamander|J86|6}} and {{HMS|Britomart|J22|2}}, and the anti-submarine trawlers [[HMT Lord Middleton (FY219)|HMT ''Lord Middleton'']], ''Lord Austin'', ''Ayrshire'' and [[HMT Northern Gem|''Northern Gem'']].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation|last=Admiralty|title=ADM 199/427: Home Fleet Destroyer Command – April to December 1942|publisher=HMSO|title-link=#admy}}&lt;/ref&gt; In a more distant covering role was the First Cruiser Squadron (CS1), under the command of [[Rear Admiral]] [[Louis Hamilton (Royal Navy officer)|L. H. K. Hamilton]], consisting of the British cruisers {{HMS|London|69|6}} (flagship) and {{HMS|Norfolk|78|2}}, the American cruisers {{USS|Wichita|CA-45|6}} and {{USS|Tuscaloosa|CA-37|2}}, and four destroyers, of which two belonged to the [[United States Navy]]. As further protection, the convoy was to be tracked at about {{convert|200|mi|km|abbr=on}} by [[Home Fleet]] [[battleship]]s.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Churchill|title=The Second World War, Volume IV|page=234|title-link=#Churchill}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second, heavy covering force, under the command of [[Admiral]] [[John Tovey, 1st Baron Tovey|John Tovey]], was made up of the British aircraft carrier {{HMS|Victorious|R38|2}}, battleship {{HMS|Duke of York|17|2}} (flagship), cruisers {{HMS|Cumberland|57|2}} and {{HMS|Nigeria|60|2}}, the American battleship {{USS|Washington|BB-56|6}}, and nine destroyers.&lt;ref name="Wilton"&gt;{{citation|last= Wilton|title=Ultra at sea|page=62|title-link=#Wilton}}&lt;/ref&gt; As the convoy began its preliminary movements, the covering forces planned by the Admiralty were moving to positions. Hamilton's First Cruiser Squadron left Seidisfjord in the night of 30 June/1 July.&lt;ref name=longaz5/&gt; It arrived in a covering position north of the convoy on 2 July. The cruisers were not sighted by the Germans until late on 3 July.&lt;ref name=longaz5 /&gt; The heavy cover force was shadowed for a short period while north-east of [[Iceland]] on 1 July, while the cruiser screen was refuelling at Seidisfiord. It was shadowed for a short period early on 3 July, while in a covering position south of the convoy.&lt;ref name=longaz5/&gt; Later that day, course was altered northwards to cross the convoy's track and to reach a position north-west of Bear Island. This would place ''Victorious'' within air striking range of the convoy on the morning of 4 July. This was calculated to occur at the same time at which a surface attack was expected to materialise. While en route to the new covering area, the force was joined by {{HMS|Manchester|15|6}} and {{HMS|Eclipse|H08|2}} from Spitzbergen.&lt;ref name=longaz6/&gt;

Air reconnaissance of the Norwegian harbours had been hindered by weather but information showed German heavy units were probably moving northwards and an air photograph of Trondheim late on 3 July showed that ''Tirpitz'' and ''Hipper'' had sortied.&lt;ref name=longaz6/&gt; The [[flying boat]] patrol and the two lines of submarines between North Cape and Bear Island were being adjusted to cover the line of approach to the convoy as it moved eastwards. In view of the uncertainty of the two German ships' positions, Rear Admiral Hamilton decided to continue to provide close cover with the cruiser squadron and to pass east of Bear Island.&lt;ref name=longaz6/&gt;

==German forces==
Ranged against PQ 17 were German Navy’s surface and submarine forces.
The U-boat Arm had deployed a patrol group, codenamed ''Eisteufel'', to intercept the convoy; three U-boats were in a patrol line north of the [[Denmark Strait]] to give advance warning, and another five further north off [[Jan Mayen Island]]. 

The ''Kriegsmarine'' also had two battlegroups in Norwegian ports, totalling four capital ships (the battleship  ''[[German battleship Tirpitz|Tirpitz]]'', and the cruisers ''[[German cruiser Admiral Hipper|Hipper]]'', ''[[German cruiser Admiral Scheer|Scheer]]'' and ''[[German cruiser Deutschland|Lutzow]]'') and twelve destroyers, ready to carry out a surface attack on the convoy. This was orchestrated as a complex two-stage operation codenamed ''[[Operation Rösselsprung (1942)|Rosselsprung]]''; the force was the strongest yet assembled for a convoy attack, but was hampered by a complex command process, with the authority to attack resting with Hitler himself, and a contradictory mission statement; the forces were instructed not only to attack and destroy the convoy, but also to avoid any action that would lead to damage to the capital ships, particularly ''Tirpitz''.

These forces were supported by aircraft of ''[[Luftflotte 5]]'', some 243 aircraft based at various airfields in northern Norway.

==Convoy movement, covering forces and escort==
[[Image:PQ17 USS Wainwright.png|thumb|right|{{USS|Wainwright|DD-419|6}} broke up an air attack on the convoy on 4 July.]]

The convoy sailed from Hvalfjord on 27 June, under the command of [[Convoy Commodore]] [[John Dowding (naval officer)|John Dowding]]. In addition to the 34 merchant ships, an oiler (RFA ''Grey Ranger'') for the escort, and three rescue ships (''Rathlin'', ''Zamalek'' and ''Zaafaran'')&lt;ref name="Turner1"&gt;{{citation|last=Turner|title= Fight for the sea: naval adventures from World War II|page=103|title-link= #Turner}}&lt;/ref&gt; sailed with the convoy. The escort was made up of six destroyers, four corvettes, three minesweepers, four trawlers, two anti-aircraft ships and two submarines. The route was longer than earlier convoys, since the ice allowed for a passage north of Bear Island with an evasive detour in the [[Barents Sea]]. Moreover, all the convoy was bound for [[Arkhangelsk]], because recent heavy air raids had destroyed most of Murmansk.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Connell|title=Arctic destroyers: the 17th Flotilla|page=80|title-link=#Connell}}&lt;/ref&gt; One ship suffered mechanical failure just out of port and was forced to turn back. Another, SS ''Exford'', turned back after sustaining ice damage.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=[[National Maritime Historical Society|NMHS]]|title=Sea history, Issues 61-68|page=58|title-link=#NMHS}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Part of the convoy ran into drifting ice in thick weather of the [[Denmark Strait]]. Two merchant ships were damaged and had to turn back. ''Grey Ranger'' was also damaged,&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hill |title=Destroyer Captain|page=29|title-link=#Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt; her speed reduced to {{convert|8|kn|mph km/h|lk=in|abbr=on}}, and since it was doubtful if she could face heavy weather, it was decided to transfer her to the fuelling position northeast of [[Jan Mayen Island|Jan Mayen]] in exchange for the [[RFA Aldersdale (X34)|RFA ''Aldersdale'']].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hill|title=Destroyer Captain|page=37|title-link=#Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly after it entered the open sea, PQ 17 was sighted and tracked by ''U-456'', and shadowed continuously except for a few short intervals in fog. This was augmented by ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' [[Blohm &amp; Voss BV 138|BV 138s]] on 1 July. On 2 July, the convoy sighted the returning convoy QP 13. It suffered its first air attack, by nine torpedo aircraft, later the same day. The planes were unsuccessful, one being shot down.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hill|title=Destroyer Captain|page= 39|title-link=#Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt; At 13:00 on 3 July, PQ 17's destroyer screen was steering east to pass between Bear Island and Spitsbergen.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hill|title=Destroyer Captain|page=41|title-link=#Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the morning of 4 July, a German [[Heinkel He 115]], from  [[Küstenfliegergruppe 906]], scored a hit on the [[Liberty ship]] {{SS|Christopher Newport}}, around {{cvt|35|mi}} northeast of [[Bear Island (Norway)|Bear Island]], at {{coord|75|49|N|22|15|E|display=inline}}. The escort ship, submarine [[Oruç Reis-class submarine|HMS ''P-614'']], attempted to [[scuttling|scuttle]] her but she remained afloat. {{GS|U-457||6}} sank the abandoned Liberty ship at 08:08.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://uboat.net/allies/merchants/ship/1887.html |title= Christopher Newport |accessdate= 17 February 2020&lt;/ref&gt; There was an unsuccessful attack by six bombers in the evening.&lt;ref name="Turner"&gt;{{citation|last=Turner|title= Fight for the sea: naval adventures from World War II|page=105|title-link= #Turner}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{citation| last=Hill|title=Destroyer Captain|page=42|title-link=#Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{USS|Wainwright|DD-419|6}} successfully broke up an air attack on the convoy the same day.&lt;ref name="Turner2"&gt;{{citation|last= Turner|title=Fight for the sea: naval adventures from World War II|page=110|title-link=#Turner}}&lt;/ref&gt; Later the same evening, another attack – by 25 torpedo bombers – took place, sinking {{SS|William Hooper}}.&lt;ref name="Turner3"&gt;{{citation|last=Turner|title=Fight for the sea: naval adventures from World War II|page=106|title-link=#Turner}}&lt;/ref&gt; Two ships were now sunk, and at least four aircraft were shot down.&lt;ref name="Hill"&gt;{{citation|last=Hill|title=Destroyer Captain|page=43|title-link=#Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=='Convoy is to scatter'==
&lt;div style="font-size: 85%"&gt;
{| class="wikitable" style="text-align: right; margin:0em 0em 1em 1em;"
|+Excerpts of signals between the Admiralty (ADMY) and&lt;br /&gt;the First Cruiser Squadron (CS1)&lt;ref name="churchill235" /&gt;
|-
!colspan="1" style="text-align: center; background: #EFEFEF" width="40" | TIME
!colspan="1" style="text-align: center; background: #EFEFEF" width="40" | FROM
!colspan="1" style="text-align: center; background: #EFEFEF" width="40" | TO
!colspan="1" style="text-align: left; background: #EFEFEF" width="450" | MESSAGE
|-
! valign=top style="background: #EFEFEF" | 21:11
| valign=top align=center | ADMY || valign=top align=center | CS1 || width="450" valign=top align="left"|Cruiser Force withdraw to the westward at high speed.
|-
! valign=top style="background: #EFEFEF" | 21:23
| valign=top align=center | ADMY || valign=top align=center | CS1 || width="450" valign=top align="left"|Owing to threat from surface ships, convoy is to disperse and proceed to Russian ports.
|-
! valign=top style="background: #EFEFEF" | 21:36
| valign=top align=center | ADMY || valign=top align=center | CS1 || width="450" valign=top align="left"|Convoy is to scatter.
|}
&lt;/div&gt;

At 12:30 on 4 July, the Admiralty gave Hamilton permission to proceed east of 25° east, should the situation demand, unless contrary orders were received from Admiral Tovey. This was a reversal of previous orders and as no information in Tovey's possession justified this change, Hamilton was ordered to withdraw when the convoy was east of 25° east or earlier at his discretion, unless the Admiralty assured him ''Tirpitz'' would not be met. At 18:58 the Admiralty informed Hamilton further information was expected shortly and instructed him to remain with the convoy pending further instructions.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hinsley, Eastaway Thomas|title=British intelligence in the Second World War|pages=213–214|title-link=#HinEas}}&lt;/ref&gt; At 21:11, the Admiralty sent a message prefixed "Most Immediate" ordering Hamilton to withdraw westwards at high speed.&lt;ref name="Hill" /&gt; This was due to U-boat information, a fact not shared with Hamilton. At 21:23, the Admiralty—in a message prefixed "Immediate"—ordered the convoy to disperse and proceed to Russian ports owing to threat from surface ships.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hill|title=Destroyer Captain|page=44|title-link=#Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt; At 21:36, the Admiralty sent another "Most Immediate" message, ordering the convoy to scatter.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hinsley, Eastaway Thomas|title=British intelligence in the Second World War|pages=216–219|title-link=#HinEas}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Ref label|A|a|none}}
{|class="wikitable" align=right style="margin:0 0 1em 1em"
|+'''''Luftwaffe'' and ''Kriegsmarine'' aircraft'''&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Northern Norway, June 1942&lt;/small&gt;{{sfn|PRO|2001|p=114}}
|-
|Bomber||Ju 88||align="right"|103
|-
|Bomber||He 111||align="right"|42
|-
|Floatplane||He 115||align="right"|15
|-
|Dive bomber||Ju 87||align="right"|30
|-
|Reconnaissance||Fw 200&lt;br&gt;Ju 88&lt;br&gt;BV 138||align="right"|74
|-
|Total || ||align="right"|'''264'''
|}
Admiral Hamilton, Commander Broome and Commodore Dowding took these signals to indicate an attack by ''Tirpitz'' was imminent.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hill|title=Destroyer Captain|page=45|title-link=#Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt; The convoy was immediately ordered to scatter, with the escorting destroyers ordered to join the cruiser force and the merchantmen to proceed independently.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hill|title= Destroyer Captain|page=50|title-link= #Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Admiralty's decision and orders would not have been so vehement had only British warships been concerned but the idea the first joint Anglo-American operation under British command might involve the destruction of American as well as British units may well have influenced the decisions of [[First Sea Lord]] [[Dudley Pound|Pound]].&lt;ref&gt;{{citation |last=Churchill|title=The Second World War, Volume IV|pages=235–236|title-link=#Churchill}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Allied cruiser squadron was already beyond the standing orders set by the Admiralty and if no new orders had gone out, the cruisers would have had to withdraw some time afterwards in any case. The earlier cruiser movement did not influence the tactical situation but in light of later knowledge, the decision was deemed precipitate.&lt;ref name="Churchill_a" /&gt;

Unbeknownst to the escort and convoy commanders, ''Tirpitz'' and its battlegroup was not actually advancing toward the convoy or in the vicinity.  ''Tirpitz'' had left Trondheim on July 2 to the port of [[Vestfjorden|Vestfjord]]; the next day, ''Kriegsmarine'' Commander-in-Chief Admiral [[Erich Raeder|Raeder]] received permission to move the ''Tirpitz'' to [[Altafjord|Altenfjord]] to join up with friendly ships.&lt;ref&gt;{{Irving|The Destruction of Convoy PQ.17|pages=75-76&lt;/ref&gt; Prior to issuing the orders, Pound visited Whitehall and consulted intelligence officer Lieutenant Commander [[Norman Denning]] to confirm that ''Tirpitz'' had left Altentfjord.  Though Denning couldn't answer if she was still anchored there he did explain that his sources would have confirmed if the ship had or was about to put to sea at that time.  It would not be until several hours after Pound's orders that ''Tirpitz'' was confirmed as still being anchored at Altenfjord.{{fact|date=February 2019}}  Although the ''Tirpitz's'' battlegroup did set out to open sea on July 5, the operation by surface ships to attack the convoy was canceled and the ships returned to Altenfjord that same day.{{fact|date=February 2019}}

==Convoy losses==
{{See also|Order of battle for Convoy PQ 17}}
[[Image:PQ17 U255 back.jpg|thumb|''U-255'' after the attacks on PQ 17, flying four victory pennants and the captured flag of the merchant ship SS ''Paulus Potter''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web
|title=SS Paulus Potter
|last=Helgason
|first=Guðmundur
|website=German U-boats of WWII – uboat.net
|url=https://uboat.net/allies/merchants/ship/1929.html
|accessdate=19 March 2018
}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
When the order to scatter the convoy was received, it had covered more than half of its route and lost three ships. The consequences for the merchantmen were dire, the ships were spread over a wide area, stripped of mutual protection and their trained escort. As the larger escort vessels retreated from the suspected German surface force, messages on [[Merchant Navy (United Kingdom)|Merchant Navy]] wavelengths began to be received by the destroyers: "Am being bombed by a large number of planes", "On fire in the ice", "Abandoning ship", "Six U-boats approaching on the surface."&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hill|title=Destroyer Captain|page=48|title-link=#Hill}}&lt;/ref&gt; With the majority of the escorts ordered to return to [[Scapa Flow]], only the close escort of anti-aircraft auxiliaries, corvettes, minesweepers and armed trawlers was left to protect the scattered ships.

On 5 July, six merchantmen, including SS ''Fairfield City'' and SS ''Daniel Morgan'', were sunk by the ''Luftwaffe'' and six more by four ''U-boats''. Among the losses that day were SS ''[[Pan Kraft]]'', ''Washington'', ''Carlton'', ''Honomu'', the Commodore's flagship {{SS|River Afton||2}}, {{SS|Empire Byron||2}} and ''Peter Kerr'' (''Kerr'' was abandoned after a fire got out of control.)&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Moore|title=A careless word – a needless sinking|page=220|title-link=#Moore}}&lt;/ref&gt; Commodore Dowding's refusal to accept defeat contributed to the rescue of most of the ships that eventually survived the convoy.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Connell|title=Arctic destroyers: the 17th Flotilla|page=101|title-link=#Connell}}&lt;/ref&gt; SS ''Paulus Potter'' had been abandoned by her crew after an aerial attack on 5 July; the ship was boarded by sailors from {{Ship|German submarine|U-255||2}} on 13 July; after taking the ship's documents and flag, ''Kptlt''. [[Reinhart Reche|Reche]] sank the ''Potter'' with a torpedo.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last= Wynn|title=U-boat Operations of the Second World War|page=178|title-link=#Wynn}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 July, SS ''Pan Atlantic'' was sunk by the ''Luftwaffe'' and SS ''John Witherspoon'' by ''U-255''. On 7–8 July, five more ships were sunk (two by ''U-255''), including SS ''Olapana'' and SS ''Alcoa Ranger''. The remaining escort withdrew into the [[Arctic Ocean]] on 9 July but the merchant ships suffered no more that day. The last losses were SS ''Hoosier'' and SS ''El Capitan'' on 10 July. The ''Luftwaffe'' flew over 200 sorties and lost only five aircraft in exchange for the eight merchantmen.&lt;ref name="uboat.net"&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://uboat.net/ops/convoys/pq-17.htm
|title=PQ-17 The Greatest Convoy Disaster
|last=Helgason
|first=Guðmundur
|website=German U-boats of WWII – uboat.net
|accessdate=2009-04-16
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On receiving the third order to scatter on 4 July 1942, RNVR T/Lt [[Leo Gradwell]] commanding the ASW adapted {{convert|575|long ton}} [[Middlesbrough]]-built [[Naval trawler|trawler]] HMS ''Ayrshire'' (FY 225), concluded that as he was heading north to the Arctic [[ice shelf]], nothing prevented him from escorting merchantmen.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.hulltrawler.net/Sidewinder/Vessel%20-%20A/AYRSHIRE%20H113.htm|title=Ayshire H113|publisher=Hull Trawler|accessdate=2 January 2014|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20140103170429/http://www.hulltrawler.net/Sidewinder/Vessel%20-%20A/AYRSHIRE%20H113.htm|archive-date=3 January 2014|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; Leading his convoy of ''Ayrshire'' and three US merchant vessels, the Panamanian-registered ''Troubador'', ''Ironclad'' and ''Silver Sword'', he proceeded north, using only a [[sextant]] and ''The Times World Geographic Pocket Book''.&lt;ref name=UWW7&gt;{{cite book|author=Richard Woodman|title=Arctic Convoys 1941–1945|year=1994}}&lt;/ref&gt; On reaching the Arctic ice pack, the convoy stuck fast and so the ships stopped engines and then banked their fires.&lt;ref name=UWW7/&gt; Gradwell arranged a defence, formulated around the fact that ''Troubador'' was carrying a cargo of bunkering coal and drums of white paint: the crews painted all the vessels white; covered decks with white linen; and arranged the [[Sherman tank]]s on the merchant vessels decks into a defensive formation, with loaded main guns.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine|url=http://www.spectator.co.uk/arts/television/9096362/jeremy-clarkson-brings-yuletide-joy-to-the-delingpole-household/|title=Jeremy Clarkson brings Yuletide joy to the Delingpole household|author=James Delingpole|magazine=[[The Spectator]]|date=14 December 2013|accessdate=2 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; After a period of waiting and having evaded ''Luftwaffe'' reconnaissance aircraft, finding themselves unstuck, they proceeded to the [[Matochkin Strait]].&lt;ref name=CBRNP/&gt; They were found there by a flotilla of [[corvette]]s, who escorted the four-ship convoy plus two other merchant vessels to the Russian port of Archangel, arriving on 25 July.&lt;ref name=CBRNP&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.cbrnp.com/RNP/Flower/ARTICLES/Poppy/Beardmore-1.htm|title=The PQ17 Story – The Worst Journey in the World|author=John Beardmore|publisher=CBRNP.com|accessdate=2 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=ObitCathHer/&gt; Gradwell was awarded the [[Distinguished Service Cross (United Kingdom)|Distinguished Service Cross]] on 15 September 1942.&lt;ref name=ObitCathHer&gt;{{cite news|url=http://archive.catholicherald.co.uk/article/14th-november-1969/10/obituary|title=Obituary – Leo Gradwell|newspaper=[[Catholic Herald]]|date=14 November 1969|accessdate=2 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=uBoat&gt;{{cite web
|url=http://uboat.net/allies/commanders/6990.html
|title=Leo Joseph Anthony Gradwell DSC, RNVR
|last=Helgason
|first=Guðmundur
|website=German U-boats of WWII – uboat.net
|accessdate=2 January 2014
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In the voyage to the Russian ports, some of the ships and lifeboat craft took refuge along the frozen coast of [[Novaya Zemlya]], landing at [[Matochkin Strait|Matochkin]].&lt;ref name=Riesenberg&gt;{{citation|last=Riesenberg|title= Sea War, Part 773.|page=320|title-link= #Riesenberg}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet tanker ''Azerbaijan'' had lost her cargo of linseed oil and much of SS ''Winston-Salem'''s cargo had been jettisoned in Novaya Zemlya.&lt;ref name=Morison&gt;{{citation|last=Morison|title=History of United States Naval Operations in World War II|page=187|title-link=#Morison}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Many of the ships' locations were unknown, in spite of searches by [[Coastal Command]] aircraft, which had proceeded to north Russia after their patrols, and by minesweepers and corvettes in the waters. A fortnight elapsed before the results of these attacks and the fate of the various ships of the convoy were fully known.&lt;ref name="Churchill_a" /&gt; Of the 34 ships which had left Iceland, 23 were sunk and 11 made port. Two British, four American, one [[Panama]]nian and two Russian merchant ships reached Arkhangelsk. Two American ships, the SS ''Samuel Chase'' and ''Benjamin Harrison'', docked at Murmansk.&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last= Bunker|title=Liberty ships: the ugly ducklings of World War II|page=67|title-link=#bunker}}&lt;/ref&gt; The total deliveries amounted to {{convert|70000|ST|t|abbr=on}} out of the {{convert|200000|ST|t|abbr=on}} which had started from Iceland.&lt;ref name="Churchill_c" /&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|Prime Minister]] [[Winston Churchill]] called the event, "one of the most melancholy naval episodes in the whole of the war."&lt;ref name="Churchill_c"/&gt; An inquiry assigned no blame to anyone, since orders were issued by the First Sea Lord, and blaming the First Sea Lord himself was considered politically unacceptable.&lt;ref name= Churchill238&gt;{{citation|last=Churchill|title=The Second World War, Volume IV|page= 238|title-link=#Churchill}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Union did not believe so many ships could be lost in one convoy and openly accused the Western Allies of lying. Despite the help provided by the material delivered, PQ 17 actually worsened Soviet-Allied relations over the short term, with the Soviets never acknowledging the efforts of Allied merchant seaman or sailors in either navy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://www.historynet.com/world-war-ii-convoy-pq-17.htm/6|title=World War II: Convoy PQ-17|last= Denkhaus|first=Richard A.|date=February 1997|accessdate=2009-04-16}}&lt;/ref&gt; [[Joseph Stalin]], and Soviet naval experts, found it difficult to understand the order to scatter given by the Admiralty, given "that the escorting vessels of the PQ 17 should return, whereas the cargo boats should disperse and try to reach the Soviet ports one by one without any protection at all."&lt;ref name=wykes&gt;{{citation|last=Wykes|title=1942, The Turning Point|page=107|title-link=#wykes}}&lt;/ref&gt; Admiral King, already known to distrust the British, was furious with what he perceived as Admiral Pound's bungling and promptly withdrew TF 39, sending it to the [[Pacific Ocean|Pacific]]. He hesitated to conduct further joint operations under British command.&lt;ref name=miller312&gt;{{citation| last=Miller|title=War at Sea: A Naval History of World War II|page=312|title-link=#miller}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Admiral [[Daniel V. Gallery|Dan Gallery]], USN, serving in Iceland at that time, called  PQ 17 "a shameful page in naval history".&lt;ref name=gallery&gt;{{citation|last= Gallery|title=Eight Bells and All's Well|page=133|title-link=#gallery}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In view of PQ 17, the Admiralty proposed to suspend the Arctic convoys at least until the ice receded and perpetual daylight passed.&lt;ref name =Churchill238/&gt; At a conference with [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]], ''Kriegsmarine'' Commander-in-Chief [[Erich Raeder|Admiral Raeder]] stated, "...our submarines and aircraft, which totally destroyed the last convoy, have forced the enemy to give up this route temporarily..."&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Churchill|title=The Second World War, Volume IV|page=243|title-link=#Churchill}}&lt;/ref&gt; At a meeting with the head of the Soviet Military Mission, Admiral [[Nikolay Mikhaylovich Kharlamov|Nikolay Kharlamov]] and the Soviet ambassador in London, [[Ivan Maisky]], the Soviets requested to know the scheduled departure of PQ 18. Pound said nothing could be done until better Russian air cover was arranged, after which Kharlamov criticised the order to withdraw the cruisers from PQ 17. Pound was furious, and deeply resented the Russian attitude. Pound angrily admitted that PQ 17 was scattered by his personal order while Maisky stated that "even British admirals make mistakes".&lt;ref&gt;{{citation|last=Hawkins|last2=Deighton|title=Destroyer|page=176|title-link=#hawkins}}&lt;/ref&gt;

It was not until September that [[PQ 18|another convoy]] set out for North Russia. The convoy's defence scheme was revised, with a very strong constant close escort of sixteen destroyers and the first of the new escort carriers, {{HMS|Avenger|D14|6}}, herself equipped with twelve fighters.&lt;ref name= chu244&gt;{{citation|last=Churchill|title=The Second World War, Volume IV|page=244|title-link=#Churchill}}&lt;/ref&gt; After the war there was criticism of this incident, both from American and Soviet sources.&lt;ref name=chu244/&gt; Soviet historians give varying reasons for the suspension and reduction in supply caused by the halt in the Arctic convoys. Some considered it the result of "the fact that in 1942, Anglo-American (ocean) communications were destroyed."&lt;ref name=howarth&gt;{{citation|last= Howarth|title=The Battle of the Atlantic 1939-1945|page=554|title-link=#howarth}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At least sixteen officers and men of the Merchant Navy were honoured for gallantry or distinguished service for the actions in the convoy. A supplement to the ''[[London Gazette]]'' published on 6 October 1942 carried notification of two [[George Medal]]s, six appointments to various grades of the [[Order of the British Empire]], six [[British Empire Medal]]s and two [[King's Commendation for Brave Conduct]].&lt;ref&gt;See {{citation|url=http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/catalogue/externalrequest.asp?requestreference=T335/47|title=Piece details T 335/47—Merchant Navy Awards (Awards for convoy PQ 17): London Gazette 6 October 1942|work=The Catalogue|publisher=[[The National Archives (United Kingdom)|The National Archives]]|accessdate=16 April 2010}} and {{London Gazette|issue=35732 |supp=y|pages=4349–4350|date=2 October 1942}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In December 2012 the [[Arctic Star]] [[military decoration|medal]] was created and on 19 March 2013 the first medals were presented to approximately 40 [[veteran]]s, in London.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Bannister|first=Sam|title=Veterans presented with their Arctic Star medals in London|url=http://www.portsmouth.co.uk/news/campaigns/veterans-presented-with-their-arctic-star-medals-in-london-1-4912447|accessdate=19 March 2013|newspaper=The News|date=19 March 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==''Broome v Cassell &amp; Co Ltd'', the David Irving Libel Case==
In 1968, [[David Irving]] published a controversial book about PQ 17. It concentrated on Allied blunders and shortcomings, alleging that Broome's decision to withdraw his destroyers was the primary cause of the disaster to the convoy. Broome mounted a libel action, ''[[Broome v Cassell &amp; Co Ltd]]'', to defend his reputation. He was successful, winning £40,000 in damages and securing the withdrawal of all copies of the offending book from circulation (it has since been republished, with corrections.) The damages payment (donated by Broome to charity) was the highest paid in legal history until [[Jeffrey Archer#Daily Star libel case|Jeffrey Archer's controversial action]] against the ''Daily Star'' newspaper.{{cn|date=November 2019}}

==In popular culture==
* ''[[Action in the North Atlantic]]'', a 1943 war movie starring Humphrey Bogart and Raymond Massey, includes a section which is drawn from Lt. Gradwell's actions after PQ-17 scattered.
* ''[[HMS Ulysses (novel)|HMS Ulysses]]'' (1955), a novel written by [[Alistair MacLean]], who served on {{HMS|Royalist|89|6}} on Arctic convoys and against {{Ship|German battleship|Tirpitz}}.
* ''[[The Captain (1967 novel)|The Captain]]'', a 1967 novel based on the experiences of this convoy by [[Netherlands|Dutch]] writer [[Jan de Hartog]], also translated into [[Dutch language|Dutch]] as ''De kapitein''.
* ''A Northern Saga'', a 1976 novel written by Steven C. Lawrence, a World War II U.S. merchant marine officer, recounts the story of PQ-17.
* ''[[Requiem for Convoy PQ-17]]'', a novel by [[Valentin Pikul]] is dedicated to the fate of the convoy. The book is also interesting since it describes the Soviet belief that [[Soviet submarine K-21Soviet submarine ''K-21'']] hit the Tirpitz. From 2003–04, a film was released in Russia based on this book.
* ''Requiem for Convoy PQ-17'' is also the title of a dance, orchestra, and choir piece based on the events surrounding the sinkings. Choreographer and dancer Bill Coleman's father was a merchant mariner on board the Bolton Castle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last1=Everett-Green|first1=Robert|title=Requiem for Convoy PQ-17|url=https://www.theglobeandmail.com/arts/requiem-for-convoy-pq-17/article4152108/?page=all|accessdate=26 June 2017|work=The Globe &amp; Mail|date=21 March 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://colemanlemieux.com/company/billcoleman/] Retrieved 11 November 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;
* In January 2014, the hour-long [[BBC Two]] documentary ''PQ17: An Arctic Convoy Disaster'', written and narrated by [[Jeremy Clarkson]], retold the story of the convoy with first-hand testimony from the men who served.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b03n3297 |title=PQ17: An Arctic Convoy Disaster |publisher=bbc.co.uk |date=2 January 2014 |accessdate=2 January 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Convoy Battles of World War II]]

==Notes==
{{refbegin}}
'''a.''' {{Note label|A|a|none}} This latter signal was intended merely as a correction of technical wording from "disperse" to "scatter", but this was not known at the time. The order to scatter was only used under immediate threat of surface attack. Detailed instructions in each ship's signal book laid down the actions that were to be taken by each ship on receipt of this order.&lt;ref name=churchill235/&gt;
{{refend}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="admy"&gt;{{cite book |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |series=Admiralty War Diaries |title=Home Fleet Destroyer Command, April to June 1942 ADM 199/427 |publisher=[[HMSO]] |url=http://www.naval-history.net/xDKWD-HF1942b.htm |accessdate=31 July 2015}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="admy"&gt;{{cite book |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |series=Admiralty War Diaries |title=Home Fleet Destroyer Command, July to September 1942ADM 199/427 |publisher=[[HMSO]] |url=http://www.naval-history.net/xDKWD-HF1942c.htm |accessdate=31 July 2015}}
* {{cite journal |last=Beesly |first=Patrick |title=Convoy PQ 17: A Study of Intelligence and Decision-Making |journal=Intelligence &amp; National Security |year=1990 |volume=5 |issue=2 |pages=292–322 |location=London |publisher=Frank Cass |issn=1743-9019 |doi=10.1080/02684529008432054}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="admy"&gt;{{cite book |last=Bunker |first=John |title=Liberty ships: The ugly ducklings of World War II |publisher=Naval Institute Press |year=1972 |isbn=978-0-87021-340-3 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/libertyshipsugly00bunk}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="Churchill"&gt;{{cite book |last=Churchill |first=Winston S. |series=The Second World War |volume=IV |title=The Hinge of Fate |publisher=Cassell |year=1951 |oclc=153203701}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="Connell"&gt;{{cite book |last=Connell |first=G. G. |title=Arctic destroyers: The 17th Flotilla |publisher=W. Kimber |year=1982 |isbn=978-0-7183-0428-7}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="hawkins"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hawkins |first1=Ian |last2=Deighton |first2=Len |title=Destroyer: An Anthology of First-hand Accounts of the War at Wea, 1939–1945 |publisher=Conway Maritime Press |year=2003 |isbn=978-0-85177-947-8}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="Hill"&gt;{{cite book |last=Hill |first=Roger P. |title=Destroyer Captain |publisher=Periscope |year=1986 |isbn=1-904381-25-1}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="HinEas"&gt;{{cite book |last1=Hinsley |first1=F. H. |last2=Eastaway Thomas |first2=Edward |title=British Intelligence in the Second World War: Its Influence on Strategy and Operations |volume=II |publisher=[[HMSO]] |location=London |year=1990 |isbn=978-0-11-630934-1}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="howarth"&gt;{{cite book |last=Howarth |first=Stephen |title=The Battle of the Atlantic 1939–1945: The 50th Anniversary International Naval Conference |issue=770 |publisher=Greenhill |year=1994 |isbn=978-1-55750-058-8}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="Langer"&gt;{{cite journal |last=Langer |first=John D. |title=The Harriman-Beaverbrook Mission and the Debate over Unconditional Aid for the Soviet Union, 1941 |journal=Journal of Contemporary History |volume=14 |issue=3 |pages=463–482 |location=London |publisher=Sage |year=1979 |issn=0022-0094|doi=10.1177/002200947901400306}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="miller"&gt;{{cite book |last=Miller |first=Nathan |title=War at Sea: A Naval History of World War II |publisher=Oxford University Press US |year=1997 |isbn=978-0-19-511038-8}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="Moore"&gt;{{cite book |last=Moore |first=Arthur R. |title="A careless word...a needless sinking": A History of the Staggering Losses Suffered by the U.S. Merchant Marine, both in Ships and Personnel during World War II |publisher=American Merchant Marine Museum |location=Kings Point, NY |year=1984 |oclc=475918989}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="Morison"&gt;{{cite book |last=Morison |first=Samuel E. |title=History of United States Naval Operations in World War II: The Battle of the Atlantic, September 1939 – May 1943 |volume=I |series=History of United States Naval Operations in World War II |publisher=University of Illinois Press |year=2001 |isbn=978-0-252-06963-5}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="NMHS"&gt;{{cite book |last=[[National Maritime Historical Society|NMHS]] |title=Sea History |issue=61–68 |publisher=National Maritime Historical Society |year=1992}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="Riesenberg"&gt;{{cite book |last=Riesenberg |first=Felix |title=Sea War |url=https://archive.org/details/seawarstoryofthe00ries |url-access=registration |publisher=Rinehart |location=New York |year=1956 |oclc=1263591}}
* {{cite book |last=Schofield |first=Bernard |year=1964 |title=The Russian Convoys |url=https://archive.org/details/russianconvoys0000scho |url-access=registration |publisher=B. T. Batsford |location=London |oclc=862623}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="Bookseller"&gt;{{cite book |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |title=The Bookseller |issue=3394–3405 |publisher=Authors Publishers' Association, Booksellers Association of Great Britain and Ireland |year=1971 |isbn=978-0-340-12512-0}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|PRO|2001}}
|title=The Rise and Fall of the German Air Force |id=Air 41/10 No. 248 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |year=2001 |orig-year=1948 |publisher=Air Ministry |location=Richmond, Surrey |edition=repr. Public Record Office War Histories |isbn=978-1-903365-30-4}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="LonGaz"&gt;{{London Gazette |issue=39041 |supp=y |pages=5139–5145 |date=17 October 1950}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="Turner"&gt;{{cite book |last=Frayn Turner |first=John |title=Fight for the Sea: Naval Adventures from World War II |publisher=Naval Institute Press |year=2002 |isbn=978-1-55750-884-3}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="Winton"&gt;{{cite book |last=Winton |first=John |title=Ultra at Sea |publisher=Leo Cooper |year=1988 |isbn=0-85052-883-6}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="wykes"&gt;{{cite book |last=Wykes |first=Alan |title=1942, The Turning Point |publisher=Macdonald |year=1972 |isbn=978-0-356-03969-5}}
* &lt;cite style="font-style:normal" id="Wynn"&gt;{{cite book |last=Wynn |first=Kenneth G. |title=U-boat Operations of the Second World War: Career Histories, U1-U510 |publisher=Chatham |year=1997 |isbn= 978-1-55750-860-7}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Geroux |first=William. |title=The Ghost Ships of Archangel: The Arctic Voyage that Defied the Nazis |publisher=Viking |location=New York |year=2017 |isbn=978-0-525-55746-3}}
* {{cite book |last=Ransome Wallis |first=R. |title=Two Red Stripes |publisher=Ian Allan |location=London |year=1973 |isbn=0-7110-0461-7}}
* {{cite book |last=Winn |first=G. |authorlink=Godfrey Winn |title=P.Q. 17: A Story of a Ship |publisher=Universal Book Club |location=London |year=1948 |oclc=560650526}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060202095710/http://www.history.navy.mil/faqs/faq104-2.htm U.S. Naval Historical Center account of PQ 17]
* [http://www.bismarck-class.dk/tirpitz/history/tiroperrosselsprung.html Description of ''Rösselsprung'']
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20071013090624/http://lib.aldebaran.ru/author/pikul_valentin/pikul_valentin_rekviem_karavanu_pq17/ The Requiem on Convoy PQ-17], Russian novel by [[Valentin Pikul]]
* [http://www.naval-history.net/WW2Memoir-PQ17-Carswell.htm Memoirs of Chief Steward Horace Carswell DSM, MM, BEM during Convoy PQ.17]
* [http://www.naval-history.net/WW2Memoir-RussianConvoyCoxswain.htm Coxswain Sid Kerslake of armed trawler "Northern Gem" in PQ.17]
* [http://www.pq17.eclipse.co.uk/ Convoy PQ.17], a primary source diary and supporting material by Jack Bowman, ERA aboard HMS ''La Malouine''.
* [http://www.convoyweb.org.uk/pq/index.html PQ 17 at Convoyweb]
* {{cite web
|url=http://uboat.net/ops/convoys/convoys.php?convoy=PQ-17
|title=PQ 17
|last=Helgason
|first=Guðmundur
|website=German U-boats of WWII – uboat.net
}}

{{Arctic convoys}}

[[Category:Arctic convoys of World War II|PQ 17]]
[[Category:White Sea]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|C]]</text><sha1>2e0dyv8yhijnmxbuiasbwzya2273vcz</sha1></revision></page>