<page><title>Battle of the Barents Sea</title><ns>0</ns><id>1000710</id><revision><id>964487381</id><parentid>964436861</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-25T19:52:39Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Eastfarthingan</username><id>11187569</id></contributor><minor /><comment>inline coord</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="16700" xml:space="preserve">{{EngvarB|date=April 2018}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict       = Battle of the Barents Sea
|image          = The Battle of the Barents Sea.jpg
|image_size     = 300px
|caption        = ''Battle of the Barents Sea'', Erwin J. Kappes
|partof         = [[World War II]]
|date           = 31 December 1942
|place          = [[Barents Sea]], [[Arctic Ocean]]
|coordinates    = {{coord|73.25|N|29|E|display=inline}}
|result         = British victory
|combatant1     = {{flagcountry|United Kingdom}}
|combatant2     = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1     = {{flagdeco|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Robert Burnett]] &lt;br&gt; {{flagdeco|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Robert Sherbrooke]] 
|commander2     = {{flagdeco|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[Oskar Kummetz]]
|strength1      = 2 light cruisers &lt;br&gt; 6 destroyers &lt;br&gt; 2 corvettes &lt;br&gt; 1 minesweeper &lt;br&gt; 2 trawlers
|strength2      = 2 heavy cruisers &lt;br&gt; 6 destroyers
|casualties1    = 250 killed &lt;br&gt; 1 destroyer sunk &lt;br&gt; 1 minesweeper sunk &lt;br&gt; 1 destroyer damaged
|casualties2    = 330 killed &lt;br&gt; 1 destroyer sunk &lt;br&gt; 1 heavy cruiser damaged
|campaignbox=
{{Campaignbox Arctic Naval Operations of WWII}}}}

The '''Battle of the Barents Sea''' was a [[World War II]] naval engagement on 31 December 1942 between warships of the [[Kriegsmarine|German Navy]] (''[[Kriegsmarine]]'') and British ships escorting [[convoy JW 51B]] to [[Kola Inlet]] in the [[USSR]]. The action took place in the [[Barents Sea]] north of [[North Cape, Norway]]. The German raiders' failure to inflict significant losses on the convoy infuriated Hitler, who ordered that German naval strategy would concentrate on the U-boat fleet rather than surface ships.

==Background==
===JW 51B===
[[Convoy JW 51B]] comprised fourteen merchant ships carrying war materials to the [[USSR]] — some 202 tanks, 2,046 vehicles, 87 fighters, 33 bombers, {{convert|11500|ST|t LT|0|abbr=on}} of fuel, {{convert|12650|ST|t LT|0|abbr=on}} of [[aviation fuel]] and just over {{convert|54000|ST|t LT|0|abbr=on}} of other supplies. They were protected by the [[destroyer]]s {{HMS|Achates|H12|6}}, {{HMS|Orwell|G98|2}}, {{HMS|Oribi|G66|2}}, {{HMS|Onslow|G17|2}}, {{HMS|Obedient|G48|2}} and {{HMS|Obdurate|G39|2}}; the {{sclass2-|Flower|corvette}}s {{HMS|Rhododendron|K78|6}} and {{HMS|Hyderabad|K212|2}}; the [[minesweeper]] {{HMS|Bramble|J11|6}}; and [[Naval trawler|trawlers]] {{HMT|Vizalma|FY286|2}} and {{ship|HMT|Northern Gem||2}}. The escort commander was [[Captain (Royal Navy)|Captain]] [[Robert St Vincent Sherbrooke|Robert Sherbrooke]] RN (flag in ''Onslow''). The convoy sailed in the dead of winter to preclude attacks by German aircraft, like those that devastated [[Convoy PQ 17]].{{sfn|Woodman|2004|pp=312–313}} Force R (Rear-Admiral [[Robert L. Burnett]]), with the [[cruiser]]s {{HMS|Sheffield|C24|6}} and {{HMS|Jamaica|44|2}} and two destroyers, were independently stationed in the [[Barents Sea]] to provide distant cover.{{sfn|Roskill|1962|pp=291–292}}

===Operation Regenbogen===

{{main|Operation Regenbogen (Arctic)#Operation Regenbogen|l1=Operation Regenbogen}}

On 31 December, a German force, based at [[Alta, Norway|Altafjord]] in northern Norway, under the command of Vice-Admiral [[Oskar Kummetz]], on ''Admiral Hipper'' set sail in {{lang|de|Unternehmen Regenbogen}} (Operation Rainbow). After Convoy PQ 18, the force had waited to attack the next Arctic convoy but their temporary suspension by the British during [[Operation Torch]] in the Mediterranean and [[Operation FB]], the routing of single ships to Russia, had provided no opportunity to begin the operation.{{sfn|Woodman|2004|pp=296–300}} The force comprised the [[heavy cruiser]]s {{Ship|German cruiser|Admiral Hipper||2}}, ''[[German cruiser Deutschland|Lützow]]'' (the renamed ''Deutschland''), and destroyers ''[[German destroyer Z16 Friedrich Eckoldt|Friedrich Eckoldt]]'', ''[[German destroyer Z4 Richard Beitzen|Richard Beitzen]]'', ''[[German destroyer Z6 Theodor Riedel|Theodor Riedel]]'', {{ship|German destroyer|Z29||2}}, {{ship|German destroyer|Z30||2}} and {{ship|German destroyer|Z31||2}}.{{sfn|Roskill|1962|p=292}}

==Prelude==
JW 51B sailed from [[Loch Ewe]] on 22 December 1942 and met its escort off [[Iceland]] on 25 December. From there the ships sailed north-east, meeting heavy gales on 28–29 December that caused the ships of the convoy to lose station. When the weather moderated, five merchantmen and the escorts ''Oribi'' and ''Vizalma'' were missing and ''Bramble'' was detached to search for them. Three of the straggling merchantmen rejoined the following day; the other ships proceeded independently towards Kola Inlet.{{sfn|Roskill|1962|pp=291}}{{sfn|Woodman|2004|pp=312–315}} On 24 December the convoy was sighted by German reconnaissance aircraft and from 30 December was shadowed by {{GS|U-354||2}} (''Kptlt.'' Karl-Heinz Herbschleb).{{sfn|Woodman|2004|p=313}} When the report was received by the German Naval Staff, Kummetz was ordered to sail immediately to intercept the convoy. Kummetz split his force into two divisions, led by ''Admiral Hipper'' and ''Lützow'', respectively.{{sfn|Woodman|2004|pp=315–317}}

==Battle==

[[File:Battle of the Barents Sea.jpg|thumb|Battle of the Barents Sea]]
At 08:00 on 31 December, the main body of JW 51B, twelve ships and eight warships, were some {{convert|120|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}}  north of the coast of [[Finnmark]] heading east. Detached from the convoy were the destroyer ''Oribi'' and one ship, which took no part in the action; {{convert|15|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}} astern (north-east) of the convoy ''Bramble'' was searching for them. North of the convoy, at {{convert|45|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}} distance, was ''Vizalma'' and another ship, while Burnett's cruisers were {{convert|15|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}} southeast of them, and {{convert|30|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}} from the convoy. To the east, {{convert|150|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}} away, the home-bound convoy RA 51 was heading west. To the north of the convoy, ''Admiral Hipper'' and three destroyers were closing, while {{convert|50|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}} away ''Lützow'' and her three destroyers were closing from the south. At 08:00 the destroyer ''Friedrich Eckholdt'' sighted the convoy and reported it to ''Admiral Hipper''.{{sfn|Kemp|1993|p=118}}

At 08:20 on 31 December, ''Obdurate'', stationed south of the convoy, spotted three German destroyers to the rear (west) of the convoy. Then, ''Onslow'' spotted ''Admiral Hipper'', also to the rear of the convoy, and steered to intercept with ''Orwell'', ''Obedient'' and ''Obdurate'', while ''Achates'' was ordered to stay with the convoy and make smoke. After some firing, the British ships turned, apparently to make a [[torpedo]] attack. Heavily outgunned, Sherbrooke knew that his torpedoes were his most formidable weapons; the attack was feigned as once the torpedoes had been launched their threat would be gone. The ruse worked: ''Admiral Hipper'' temporarily retired, since Kummetz had been ordered not to risk his ships. ''Admiral Hipper'' returned to make a second attack, hitting ''Onslow'' causing heavy damage and many casualties including 17 killed. Although ''Onslow'' ultimately survived the action, Sherbrooke had been badly injured by a large steel splinter and command passed to ''Obedient''.{{sfn|Woodman|2004|pp=318–320}}

''Admiral Hipper'' then pulled north of the convoy, stumbled across ''Bramble'', a {{sclass-|Halcyon|minesweeper|2}}, which opened fire; ''Admiral Hipper'' returned fire with her much heavier guns. The destroyer ''Friedrich Eckholdt'' was ordered to finish off ''Bramble'', which sank with all hands, while ''Admiral Hipper'' shifted aim to ''Obedient'' and ''Achates'' to the south. ''Achates'' was badly damaged but continued to make smoke until eventually she sank; the trawler ''Northern Gem'' rescued many of the crew. The Germans reported sinking a destroyer but this was owing to the misidentification of the minesweeper ''Bramble''; they had not realised ''Achates'' had been hit.{{sfn|Woodman|2004|pp=321–323}}

The shellfire attracted the attention of Force R, which was still further north. ''Sheffield'' and ''Jamaica'' approached unseen and opened fire on ''Admiral Hipper'' at 11:35, hitting her with enough six-inch shells to damage (and cause minor flooding to) two of her boiler rooms, reducing her speed to {{convert|28|kn|lk=in}}. Kummetz initially thought that the attack of the two cruisers was coming from another destroyer but upon realising his mistake, he ordered his ships to retreat to the west. In another case of mistaken identity, ''Friedrich Eckholdt'' and ''Richard Beitzen'' mistook ''Sheffield'' for ''Admiral Hipper''; after attempting to form up with the British ships, they were engaged by ''Sheffield'' with ''Friedrich Eckholdt'' breaking in two and sinking with all hands.{{sfn|Woodman|2004|pp=323–324}}

''Lützow'' approached from the east and fired ineffectively at the convoy, still hidden by smoke from the crippled ''Achates''. Heading north-west to join ''Admiral Hipper'', ''Lützow'' also encountered ''Sheffield'' and ''Jamaica'', which opened fire. Coincidentally, both sides decided to break off the action at the same time, each side fearing imminent torpedo attacks upon their heavy ships from the other's remaining destroyers. This was shortly after noon. Burnett with Force&amp;nbsp;R continued to shadow the German ships at a distance until it was evident that they were retiring to their base, while the ships of the convoy re-formed and continued towards Kola Inlet.{{sfn|Woodman|2004|pp=324–326}}

==Aftermath==

===Analysis===

The encounter took place in the middle of the months-long [[polar night]] and both the German and British forces were scattered and unsure of the positions of the rest of their own forces, much less their opponent. The battle became a rather confused affair and sometimes it was not clear who was firing on whom or how many ships were engaged.{{sfn|Woodman|2004|p=317}} Despite this German attack on convoy JW 51B, all 14 of its merchant ships reached their destinations in the USSR undamaged.{{sfn|Woodman|2004|p=327}}

[[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]] was infuriated at what he regarded as the uselessness of the surface raiders, seeing that two heavy cruisers were driven off by mere destroyers. There were serious consequences: this failure nearly made Hitler enforce a decision to scrap the surface fleet and order the German Navy to concentrate on [[U-boat]] warfare. Admiral [[Erich Raeder]], supreme commander of the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'', offered his resignation—which Hitler accepted. Raeder was replaced by Admiral [[Karl Dönitz]], the commander of the U-boat fleet.{{sfn|Woodman|2004|pp=329–330}}

Dönitz saved the German surface fleet from scrapping; though ''Admiral Hipper'' and two ({{ship|German cruiser|Emden||2}} and {{ship|German cruiser|Leipzig||2}}) of the [[light cruiser]]s were laid up until late 1944, while repairs and rebuilding of the [[battleship]] {{ship|German battleship|Gneisenau||2}} were abandoned. Although German [[E-boat]]s continued to operate off the coast of France, only one more big surface operation was executed after the battle.  This was the attempted raid on [[Convoy JW 55B]] by the battleship {{Ship|German battleship|Scharnhorst||2}}.{{sfn|Roskill|1960|pp=89}} The battleship was sunk by an escorting British task force in what later became known as the [[Battle of the North Cape]].{{sfn|Woodman|2004|pp=355–375}}

==Victoria Cross==
Captain Robert Sherbrooke was awarded the [[Victoria Cross]]. He acknowledged that it had really been awarded in honour of the whole crew of ''Onslow''. In the action he had been badly wounded and he lost the sight in his left eye.{{sfn|Woodman|2004|pp=329, 320}} He returned to active duty and retired from the navy in the 1950s with the rank of [[Rear admiral (Royal Navy)|rear-admiral]].{{citation needed|date=April 2018}}

==Commemoration==
At the memorial for ''Bramble'', Captain Harvey Crombie said of the crew

{{quote|They had braved difficulties and perils probably unparalleled in the annals of the British Navy, and calls upon their courage and endurance were constant, but they never failed. They would not have us think sadly at this time, but rather that we should praise God that they had remained steadfast to duty to the end.{{sfn|Bramble|2010|nopp=y}}}}

The battle was the subject of the book ''73 North'' by [[Dudley Pope]] and the poem ''JW51B: A Convoy'' by [[Alan Ross]], who served on ''Onslow''.

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==Bibliography==
'''Books'''
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Kemp|1993}} |first=Paul |last=Kemp |title=Convoy! Drama in Arctic Waters |publisher=Arms and Armour |location=London |year=1993 |isbn=978-1-85409-130-7 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/convoydramainarc0000kemp_k9q5 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Roskill|1962}}
|last=Roskill |first=S. W. |series=[[History of the Second World War]]: The War at Sea 1939–1945 |title=The Period of Balance |volume=II |publisher=[[HMSO]] |location=London |year=1962 |orig-year=1956 |edition=3rd impr. |url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/UK-RN-II/index.html |accessdate=22 March 2018 |oclc=174453986}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Roskill|1960}}
|last=Roskill |first=S. W. |authorlink= |series=History of the Second World War United Kingdom Military Series |title=The War at Sea 1939–1945: The Offensive 1st June 1943 – 31st May 1944 |volume=III |others=Part I |publisher=HMSO |location=London |year=1960 |edition=1st |oclc=277168049}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Woodman|2004}}
|first=Richard |last=Woodman |year=2004 |orig-year=1994 |title=Arctic Convoys 1941–1945 |publisher=John Murray |location=London |isbn=978-0-7195-5752-1}}

'''Websites'''
* {{cite web |ref={{harvid|Bramble|2010}}
|url=http://www.halcyon-class.co.uk/Bramble/bramble1942.htm |title=HMS Bramble 1942 |date=7 November 2010 |publisher=halcyon-class.co.uk |accessdate=29 May 2011}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
'''Books'''
* {{cite book |last=Pope |first=Dudley |title=73 North: The Battle of the Barents Sea |year=1958 |publisher=Wyman and Sons |location=London |oclc=464156754}}
* {{cite book |last=Hinsley |first=F. H. |series=History of the Second World War |title=British Intelligence in the Second World War: Its Influence on Strategy and Operations |location=London |publisher=[[HMSO]] |year=1994 |orig-year=1993 |edition=2nd rev. abr. |isbn=978-0-11-630961-7}}
* {{cite book |last=O'Hara |first=Vincent P. |title=The German Fleet at War |year=2004 |publisher=Naval Institute press |location=Annapolis, MD |isbn=978-1-59114-651-3}}
* {{cite book |last1=Richards |first1=Denis |last2=St G. Saunders |first2=H. |url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/UK-RAF-II/index.html |accessdate=22 March 2018 |series=History of the Second World War, Military Series |title=Royal Air Force 1939–1945: The Fight Avails |volume=II |location=London |publisher=[[HMSO]] |year=1975 |orig-year=1954 |edition=pbk. |isbn=978-0-11-771593-6}}
* {{cite book |title=The Rise and Fall of the German Air Force |id=Air 41/10 |number=248 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |year=2001 |orig-year=1948 |publisher=Air Ministry |location=Richmond, Surrey |edition=repr. Public Record Office War Histories |isbn=978-1-903365-30-4}}

'''Websites'''
* {{Cite web |url=http://uboat.net/boats/u354.html |title=The Type VIIC boat U-354 |last=Helgason |first=Guðmundur |website=German U-boats of WWII - uboat.net |accessdate=22 December 2015}}
* {{cite web |last=Kappes |first=Irwin J. |date=23 February 2010 |title=Battle of the Barents Sea |publisher=German-Navy.De |url=http://www.german-navy.de/kriegsmarine/articles/feature5.html |accessdate=29 May 2011 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110607120149/http://www.german-navy.de/kriegsmarine/articles/feature5.html |url-status=live |archivedate=7 June 2011}}

==External links==
* [http://www.german-navy.de/kriegsmarine/articles/feature5.html Battle of the Barents Sea] — comprehensive article by Irwin J. Kappes
* [http://www.naval-history.net/WW2Memoir-RussianConvoyCoxswain.htm Coxswain Sid Kerslake of armed trawler "Northern Gem" during Convoy JW.51B and the Battle of the Barents Sea]
{{Kriegsmarine}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle of the Barents Sea}}
[[Category:Arctic naval operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Arctic convoys of World War II|Barents Sea]]
[[Category:Barents Sea]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:December 1942 events]]
[[Category:Germany–United Kingdom military relations]]</text><sha1>ah76ou70zjm4e2oizj3ruqewiuxxyib</sha1></revision></page>