<page><title>Operation Stonewall</title><ns>0</ns><id>3401316</id><revision><id>924223388</id><parentid>892291126</parentid><timestamp>2019-11-02T15:39:32Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Le seul et l'unique toubib</username><id>37357378</id></contributor><minor /><comment>/* The operation */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="8046" xml:space="preserve">{{more footnotes|date=September 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2016}}
{{Campaignbox Atlantic Campaign}}

'''Operation Stonewall''' was a [[World War II]] operation to intercept blockade runners off the west coast of [[German military administration in occupied France during World War II|German-occupied France]]. It was an effective example of inter-service and international co-operation.

==Background==
From the start of the war, the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] had maintained a [[Blockade of Germany (1939–1945)|blockade against the import of seaborne goods to Germany]]. Although rich in many basic industrial materials, Germany, like Britain, could not produce some essentials. These included [[rubber]], tin and [[tungsten]].

Until [[Operation Barbarossa|Germany invaded the Soviet Union]] it evaded the blockade via the [[Trans-Siberian Railway]]. Large quantities of materials were shipped by this route. After this was closed, German and Italian ships, stranded in [[Japan]] and [[Japanese occupation of Singapore|Japanese-occupied Singapore]], were used as [[Blockade runner#Axis blockade runners|blockade runners]] to bring in these essential goods to ports in occupied France.

Although organised interdiction against these blockade runners was not set up until December 1943, the Allies intercepted and sank several ships in the [[Atlantic Ocean|Atlantic]] and [[Indian Ocean]]s. Few ships managed successful runs.

==The operation==
[[File:German freighter burning in Bay of Biscay Dec 1943.jpg|thumb|280px|German blockade runner {{MV|Alsterufer||2}} burning after a [[Czechoslovak government-in-exile|Czechoslovak]]-crewed RAF Liberator attacked her]]
The [[Royal New Zealand Navy]] [[light cruiser]] [[HMS Gambia (48)|HMNZS ''Gambia'']] joined the operation in December 1943, operating from [[Horta, Azores|Horta]] in the [[Azores]]. The [[Royal Navy]] light cruiser {{HMS|Glasgow|C21|6}} patrolled an area north of the islands.

On 23 December aircraft from the [[United States Navy]] [[escort carrier]] {{USS|Card}} sighted a suspected runner, and there were further reports of a flotilla of destroyers escorting another merchantman west from France. ''Gambia'', '' Glasgow'', and the light cruiser {{HMS|Enterprise|D52|6}} formed a cordon to intercept. Aircraft attacked the flotilla, now escorting a large incoming merchantman, the {{GRT|6951}} {{MV|Osorno||2}}, and reported a hit and a near-miss on her.

The light cruiser {{HMS|Penelope|97|2}}, [[minelayer]] {{HMS|Ariadne|M65|6}} and four [[Free French Naval Forces|Free French]] destroyers joined the patrol to intercept another runner. [[RAF Coastal Command]] aircraft acted in close cooperation.

On 27 December at 1535 hrs [[Consolidated B-24 Liberator#British Commonwealth nomenclature and sub-variants|Liberator GR Mk V]] [[heavy bomber]] of Coastal Command's [[Czechoslovak government-in-exile|Czechoslovak]]-crewed [[No. 311 Squadron RAF]] sighted a smaller blockade runner, the {{GRT|2729}} [[Reefer ship|refrigerated cargo ship]] {{MV|Alsterufer||2}}. The Liberator made a diving attack with eight wing-mounted SAP60 semi-armour piercing rocket projectiles, five of which hit the cargo ship above her waterline. The Liberator also dropped one {{convert|500|lb|abbr=on}} bomb, and one 250 lb (115 kg) bomb one of which hit the ship aft of her funnel. The ship immediately caught fire.{{sfn|Vančata|2013|p=64}}

''Alsterufer'' defended herself with anti-aircraft fire and rockets that released parachute cables. The Liberator's starboard outer engine was hit, but the aircraft successfully returned to base at [[RAF Beaulieu]] in England. Later that day two more RAF Liberators and four RAF [[Handley Page Halifax|Halifax]] heavy bombers attacked the ship, but claimed no hits. ''Alsterufer'' sank on the afternoon of 28 December. 74 members of her crew were rescued{{sfn|Vančata|2013|p=64}} by four Canadian [[corvette]]s.{{citation needed|date=February 2018}}

''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' destroyers and torpedo boats had set out to meet and escort ''Alsterufer'' in an operation codenamed ''Bernau''. Now ''Glasgow'' and ''Enterprise'' sought to intercept them. Guided by shadowing aircraft, the cruisers intercepted eight destroyers early in the afternoon of 28 December and exchanged fire with them. Despite accurate German gunfire and torpedoes, effective German evading action and an attack with guided bombs by a ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' aircraft, the Royal Navy ships maintained contact.
[[File:KerlogueT25T26.jpg|thumb|View from ''Z27'' of ''T25'' and ''T26'' being shelled. Drawn by Hans Helmut Karsch, a German sailor, while interned in the [[Curragh Camp]]. ([[National Maritime Museum of Ireland]])]]

===Battle of the Bay of Biscay===
{{Main|Battle of the Bay of Biscay}}

The German ships divided into two groups and the cruisers pursued one of these. By 1600 hrs the {{sclass2-|Elbing|torpedo boat}}s [[German torpedo boat T25|''T25'']] and [[German torpedo boat T26|''T26'']] and the {{sclass2-|Narvik|destroyer}} [[German destroyer Z27|''Z27'']] had been sunk and one had escaped, damaged. About 62 survivors were rescued by Royal Navy minesweepers, 168 by a {{GRT|335}} [[The Emergency (Ireland)|Irish]] coaster, {{MV|Kerlogue||2}}, and four by [[Francoist Spain|Spanish]] destroyers.{{sfn|Waters|1956|p=355}} The blockade runner ''Osorno'' reached the [[Gironde]] but struck a wreck in the estuary. She was beached and subsequently unloaded offshore.

''Glasgow'', ''Enterprise'' and ''Ariadne'' returned to [[HMNB Devonport|Plymouth]] and ''Penelope'' to [[Gibdock|Gibraltar]]. More blockade runners from the Far East were expected, so the ''Gambia'' and the light cruiser {{HMS|Mauritius|80|2}} patrolled north of the Azores for the next three days. ''Gambia'' then returned to Plymouth on 1 January 1944.

Three more German ships were sunk between 3 and 5 January by US Navy patrols in the South Atlantic. These were the last German blockade runners.

By Autumn, German armies were retreating out of France and the French ports were no longer open to Axis ships.

==Allied participants==
:'''Ships''': Canadian, French, New Zealand, United Kingdom, United States
:'''Aircraft''': United Kingdom (including one with Czechoslovak crew), United States

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* {{cite book |last=Blair |first=Clay |authorlink=Clay Blair |origyear=1998 |year=2000 |title=Hitler's U-Boat War |volume=2: The Hunted 1942–1945 |isbn=0-304-35261-6 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Morison |first=Samuel |authorlink=Samuel Eliot Morison |year=1947 |title=History of United States Naval operations in World War II |volume=I Battle of the Atlantic 1939–1943 |id= |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Roskill |first=Stephen |authorlink=Stephen Roskill |year=1960 |title=The War at Sea 1939–1945 |volume=III |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Šulc |first=Jiří |year=2011 |title=Operace Stonewall |place=Prague |publisher=Knižní klub |isbn=978-80-242-5788-4 |language=cs |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Vančata |first=Pavel |year=2013 |title=311 Squadron |place=Sandomierz |publisher=Stratus, for Mushroom Model Publications |isbn=978-83-61421-43-6 |page=64 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Waters |first=SD |year=1956 |title=Royal New Zealand Navy |chapter=23, The New Zealand Cruisers |place=Wellington |publisher=Historical Publications Branch |pages=352–356 |url= http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2Navy-c23.html |ref=harv}}
* https://fcafa.com/2013/12/27/70th-anniversary-of-the-alsterufer-sinking/
{{coord missing|Atlantic Ocean}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Stonewall}}

[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Czechoslovakia]]
[[Category:Naval aviation operations and battles]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving New Zealand]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]</text><sha1>72qbh0g1y9d4k6nf3t0y9wlbgba9zj3</sha1></revision></page>