<page><title>Battle of the Bay of Biscay</title><ns>0</ns><id>44067954</id><revision><id>933707982</id><parentid>915345512</parentid><timestamp>2020-01-02T16:20:49Z</timestamp><contributor><username>TGcoa</username><id>23671446</id></contributor><comment>/* Aftermath */ Deleted "Only 283 survivors"  ... the numbers don't add up... many more rescued than 283</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="16823" xml:space="preserve">{{For|the engagement during the Anglo-Spanish War (1585–1604)|Battle of the Bay of Biscay (1592)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2017}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of the Bay of Biscay
|partof= the [[Battle of the Atlantic]] of [[World War II]]
| image= Nmm nmmg bhc0686 large(2).jpg
| image_size = 300
|caption= Battle of the Bay of Biscay 1943 – Painting by [[Norman Wilkinson (artist)|Norman Wilkinson]]
|date=28 December 1943
|place=[[Bay of Biscay]], [[Atlantic]]
|result=British victory
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1 ={{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} Charles Clark&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Harold Taylor Wood Grant|Harold Grant]]
|commander2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[Franz Kohlauf]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[Hans Erdmenger]]{{KIA}}
|strength1=2 light cruisers
|strength2=5 destroyers&lt;br&gt;6 torpedo boats&lt;br&gt;1 aircraft
|casualties1=2 killed&lt;br&gt;1 cruiser damaged
|casualties2=532 killed &amp; wounded&lt;br&gt;1 destroyer sunk&lt;br&gt;2 torpedo boats sunk&lt;br&gt;1 torpedo boat damaged&lt;ref name="O'Hara"&gt;O'Hara pp. 280–282&lt;/ref&gt;
|campaignbox= {{Campaignbox Atlantic Campaign}}
}}

The '''Battle of the Bay of Biscay''' was a naval action that took place on 28 December 1943 during [[World War II]] as part of the [[Battle of the Atlantic|Atlantic campaign]]. The battle took place in the [[Bay of Biscay]] between two light cruisers of the British [[Royal Navy]], and a destroyer and a torpedo boat [[flotilla]] of the German [[Kriegsmarine]] hoping to intercept and escort a [[blockade runner]]. The battle was fought as part of the Allied [[Operation Stonewall]] which was to intercept German blockade runners off the west coast of France. In the confused action that followed the two British cruisers [[HMS Enterprise (D52)|HMS ''Enterprise'']] and  [[HMS Glasgow (C21)|HMS ''Glasgow'']] respectively sank [[German torpedo boat T26|''T26'']], together with her sister ship [[German torpedo boat T25|''T25'']] and the destroyer [[German destroyer Z27|''Z27'']].&lt;ref name="Blair"&gt;Blair p.454&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nesbit p. 126&lt;/ref&gt;

== Background ==
In late December 1943 a German ''Kriegsmarine'' destroyer flotilla, reinforced by six large [[Elbing-class torpedo boat]]s, was ordered to the Bay of Biscay in order to escort into a French port the [[blockade runner]]s ''Osorno'' and ''Alsterufer'', which were carrying vital cargo from [[Empire of Japan|Japan]]. The Germans codenamed this Operation ''Bernau''.&lt;ref name="Chesneau"&gt;Chesneau p. 238&lt;/ref&gt; The blockade runner ''Osorno'' reached the [[Gironde]] on 26 December, but struck a wreck in the estuary after being attacked by the [[RAF]]. She was beached and subsequently unloaded offshore. Meanwhile, ''Alsterufer'', carrying [[tungsten]] (''Wolfram'') and [[rubber]], was still much further behind.&lt;ref name="Tucker"&gt;Tucker pp. 96–97&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:HMS Glasgow and Enterprise Singapore 1942 AWM 302397.jpeg|thumb|left|HMS ''Glasgow'' and ''Enterprise'' shown together in 1942]]

''[[Korvettenkapitän]]'' [[Franz Kohlauf]] sailed from [[Brest, France|Brest]] on the morning of 27 December with the torpedo boats ''T23'', ''T24'', {{ship|German torpedo boat|T26||2}} and ''T22''. The 8th Destroyer Flotilla under ''[[Kapitän zur See]]'' [[Hans Erdmenger]] put out from the [[Gironde]] with destroyers {{ship|German destroyer|Z24||2}}, ''Z37'', {{ship|German destroyer|Z32||2}} and {{ship|German destroyer|Z27||2}}, accompanied by two torpedo boats, {{ship|German torpedo boat|T25||2}}, under the command of ''[[Korvettenkapitän]]'' [[Wirich von Gartzen]], and ''T27''.&lt;ref name="O'Hara1"&gt;O'Hara pp. 277–279&lt;/ref&gt;

The British Admiralty were also aware of the impending arrival of ''Alsterufer'' through the decryption of German [[Enigma machine|Enigma messages]] at [[Bletchley Park]] and sent out dispatches to the nearest ships in the area for the interception. The closest ship, the light cruiser {{HMS|Glasgow|C21|6}}, which had sailed from the [[Azores]] on 24 December, was soon joined by {{HMS|Enterprise|D52|6}}. In support, but further away; {{HMS|Mauritius|80|6}} had been ordered out from [[Gibraltar]]; {{HMS|Penelope|97|6}} steamed past [[Lisbon]]; and {{HMS|Gambia|48|6}} was in the Western Atlantic.&lt;ref name="Chesneau"/&gt;

By 04:00 the next day the 4th Flotilla was 300 miles due south of [[Cape Clear Island|Cape Clear]], the 8th Flotilla standing to the south, and were ready to meet ''Alsterufer''. She was however nowhere to be seen. The German flotillas were completely unaware that during the previous afternoon a [[Consolidated B-24 Liberator|B-24 Liberator]] bomber of [[No. 311 (Czechoslovak) Squadron RAF]] had attacked and set ''Alsterufer'' on fire. Abandoned by her crew, the ship was finished off by Liberators of [[No. 86 Squadron RAF|No. 86 Squadron]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Royal Air Force, 1939–1945: |volume=Volume III The Fight Is Won |url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/UK-RAF-III/ |chapter=Chapter III: Stratagems and Spoils |publisher=H.M. Stationery Office, 1975|page=71  |first=Hilary St. George |last=Saunders}}&lt;/ref&gt; This released the ''Glasgow'' and ''Enterprise'', who were some 300 [[nautical mile]]s south-west of the German forces and were now steaming eastwards along the [[45th parallel north|45th Parallel]].&lt;ref name="Tucker"/&gt;

Just after midday, Erdmenger's 8th Destroyer Flotilla sighted Kohlauf's 4th Flotilla to the east, whereupon the torpedo boats turned east astern of the northernmost destroyers, taking station on their [[Port and starboard|port]] side.&lt;ref name="Stubner"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Stubner|first1=Helmut|title=Das Kampfflugzeug Heinkel 177 Greif und seine Weiterentwicklung|date=2012|publisher=Eurodoc|pages=191–192|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=N4sgAQAAIAAJ&amp;q=GLASGOW+ENTERPRISE+ERDMENGER&amp;dq=GLASGOW+ENTERPRISE+ERDMENGER&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=_Tc1VObwDufN7QbCwIH4Cw&amp;ved=0CF4Q6AEwCQ }}(German)&lt;/ref&gt;

== Battle ==
[[File:Battle of the Bay of Biscay 28 December 1943 map.png|thumb|General map of the battle]]
Allied aircraft had already reported the position of the German ships about 1300. About the same time a lone German [[Focke-Wulf Fw 200 Condor]] sighted and attacked both cruisers only to be repelled by anti-aircraft gunfire. The German aircrew immediately turned north-east, reporting the position of the British cruisers more than half an hour later to Erdmenger.&lt;ref name="O'Hara1"/&gt; Captain Charles Clark on HMS ''Glasgow'', assuming that he had been reported then also turned north-east, working around Erdmenger's position to intercept. The sea was becoming rougher and the wind had increased to 30 [[Knot (unit)|knots]], making sailing difficult for the destroyers and torpedo boats.&lt;ref name="Whitley"&gt;{{cite book|last1=Whitley|first1=M. J.|title=Destroyer!: German Destroyers in World War II|date=1983|publisher=Arms &amp; Armour Press|pages=193–199|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5awCAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=glasgow+enterprise+1943+Alsterufer&amp;dq=glasgow+enterprise+1943+Alsterufer&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=8W8xVODwBM3VauXegugI&amp;ved=0CEgQ6AEwBjgK}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Sailing into rough seas and gale force winds, ''Glasgow'' sighted the destroyers at 1332 hours at a range of 16 miles. The two cruisers then intercepted at [[flank speed|full speed]] and altered course to cut the German ships off from their base.&lt;ref name="O'Hara1"/&gt;
Soon after Clarke gave the order for ''Glasgow'' to open fire with her [[BL 6 inch Mk XXIII naval gun|6-inch]] 'A' and 'B' turrets using her [[List of World War II British naval radar#Type 273 radar|Type 273 radar]] for ranging. ''Enterprise'' opened fire a few minutes later. The two leading German destroyers however remained unscathed as shells splashed 100–150 metres from their targets.&lt;ref name="O'Hara"/&gt; The Germans counter-attacked: ''Z23'' launched six  torpedoes, three from each bank of tubes, when the range was down to 17,000 metres, but missed. Both destroyers also opened up with their [[15 cm TbtsK C/36 naval gun|15 cm guns]] and their first shots fell only 200 metres over on Glasgow's port quarter.&lt;ref name="Tucker"/&gt; At about 1405 hours, a German shell hit ''Glasgow'' which exploded in 'A' boiler room, killing two members of the port [[QF 2-pounder naval gun|pom-pom]] crew and wounding six others. ''Enterprise'' was continually straddled by near misses.&lt;ref name="Whitley"/&gt;
[[File:The Royal Navy during the Second World War HMS Glasgow 4-inch AA gun crew A 21143.jpg|thumb|left|180px|Sailors aboard HMS ''Glasgow'' clear cartridge cases ejected from the twin [[QF 4 inch Mk XVI naval gun|4 inch Mark XVI guns]]]]

By 1418 hours both of the German flotillas were involved in the fight. The 4th Torpedo Boat Flotilla attempted to attack with torpedoes a number of times but was frustrated by the heavy seas. ''Z32'' and ''Z37'' turned towards the cruisers, and closing to 12,800 metres, launched six and four torpedoes respectively as the cruisers continued to give heavy and accurate fire.&lt;ref name="Stubner"/&gt; The torpedo attack forced ''Glasgow'' to make an emergency turn to port as the track of one torpedo passed no more than thirty metres from her port quarter and two more near the port side. ''Enterprise'' had by this time separated from ''Glasgow'' and both acted independently.&lt;ref name="Whitley"/&gt; After the torpedo attack, the destroyers [[Smoke screen|laid smoke]] and then retired back towards the flotilla line. The formation was as follows: ''Z32'', ''Z24'', ''Z37'', ''T23'', ''T27'', ''T26'', ''T22'', ''T25'', ''Z27'' and ''Z25'' while ''Z32'' and ''Z37'' being off to port in the course of their torpedo attack.&lt;ref name="O'Hara"/&gt;

The German force then split up, whereupon ''Glasgow'' reversed course at 1435 hours to chase the northerly group of destroyers; ''Enterprise'' had already altered course to the west to head them off.&lt;ref name="Whitley"/&gt; The Germans then launched another torpedo attack but shortly after ''Z27'' had fired hers, she received a shell hit from ''Enterprise'' which struck the boiler room, passing through an oil bunker which caused a huge fire. Clouds of steam gushed from her forward funnel as her speed fell off.&lt;ref name="Tucker"/&gt; After being hit she fired her second salvo of four torpedoes, but all missed.&lt;ref name="O'Hara"/&gt;

''Glasgow'' meanwhile concentrated on ''T25'', which soon after sustained hits in the region of the [[aft]] torpedo tubes, the ''[[2 cm Flak 30/38/Flakvierling|Flakvierling]]'' and the [[3.7 cm Flak 18/36/37/43|3.7 cm flak]] platforms, which killed or wounded all their crews. Then a second shell struck the German torpedo boat, which completely destroyed the mast as well as the funnel. ''T25'' was now a sitting duck and requested ''T22'' to attempt to come alongside and take off her crew.&lt;ref name="Tucker"/&gt; ''Glasgow'' shifted to ''T26'', which was quickly [[wikt:bracket#Verb|bracketed]] by near misses. ''T22'' had both cruisers on her port side, and, in an effort to drive them off while she closed in on her damaged consort, she fired her full spread of torpedoes and opened fire with her guns. The torpedoes passed harmlessly by their targets, and as ''T22'' turned to starboard towards ''T25'', she too was bracketed by near misses. ''T22'' abandoned the rescue after suffering another hit, then laid smoke, fired her guns and withdrew to the south-west. ''T26'' was still under fire and was soon severely hit in the boiler room, and as ''T22'' laid smoke to screen her, the damaged ship signalled that she was sinking; ''T22'' turned northwards and broke away.&lt;ref name="Whitley"/&gt;

The two cruisers reversed course, chasing and soon catching ''T26''. Clarke ordered ''Enterprise'' to finish her off while he turned ''Glasgow'' north again to look for the other damaged German vessels, particularly ''T25''. ''Glasgow'' soon came across not ''T25'' but ''Z27'', drifting and silent. Closing to [[point-blank range]], ''Glasgow'' fired, hitting the destroyer's magazines. The hit caused a large explosion which killed Erdmenger, his staff and the captain.&lt;ref name="Whitley"/&gt; At the same time ''Enterprise'' finished off ''T26'' with a single torpedo and then moved in for the kill on ''T25''. The German ship's bridge and upper deck were a twist of metal and her after superstructure wrecked but she remained afloat. ''Enterprise'' closed to 3000 metres, firing her guns and then fired a torpedo; within minutes ''T25'' was an abandoned, burning and sinking wreck.&lt;ref name="Tucker"/&gt;
[[File:KerlogueT25T26.jpg|thumb|200px|A sketch from ''Z27'' of ''T25'' and ''T26'' being shelled during the battle ([[National Maritime Museum of Ireland]])]]

== Aftermath ==
The two British cruisers met up once more and, seeing no further signs of the German squadron and having accounted for three of them at no significant damage to themselves, withdrew toward [[Plymouth]]. They arrived on the evening of 29 December, low on both fuel and ammunition. ''Glasgow'' had received one hit that killed two crew members and wounded another three, while ''Enterprise'' had no real damage except for shell splinters.&lt;ref name="O'Hara"/&gt;

The two German survivors, ''T22'' and ''Z23'', reunited and headed towards [[Saint-Jean-de-Luz]] near the Spanish border. The rest of the German ships headed back to the [[Gironde]].&lt;ref name="Tucker"/&gt;

Of the 672 men on the three sunken ships, many were rescued: 93 from ''Z27'', 100 from ''T25'' and 90 from ''T26''. British and Irish ships, Spanish destroyers and German [[U-boat]]s took part in the rescue.&lt;ref name="O'Hara"/&gt; About 62 survivors were picked up by British minesweepers as prisoners. 168 were rescued by a small Irish steamer, the {{MV|Kerlogue}}, and four by Spanish destroyers, and they were all [[interned]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.nzetc.org/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2Navy-c23.html ''Achilles'' at Royal NZ Navy]&lt;/ref&gt; Morale for the German Navy was lowered even further when news filtered through of the battleship ''[[German battleship Scharnhorst|Scharnhorst]]'' being [[Battle of the North Cape|sunk in the North Cape]], marking a sour note to the end of the year for the Kriegsmarine.&lt;ref name="Whitley"/&gt;

As it turned out, ''Osorno'' was the last of the blockade runners to get through. Three other German blockade runners were sunk between 3 and 5 January 1944 by Allied patrols in the South Atlantic.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Lambert|title=Warship, Volume 10|date=1986|publisher=Naval Institute Press|page=98|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=b3LdcoU3lrEC&amp;dq=orsono+gironde+1943&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Germans thereafter ceased all surface blockade running and switched to movement by [[submarine]]; these became known as [[Yanagi missions]].&lt;ref&gt;Oldfield p. 158&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book|last1=Beverhoudt|first1=Arnold van|title=These Are The Voyages|date=2011|publisher=Lulu.com|isbn=9780557178254}}
* {{cite book|last1=Blair|first1=Clay|title=Hitler's U-Boat War: The Hunted 1942–45 Volume 2|date=2012|publisher=Hachette UK|isbn=9780297866220}}
* {{cite book|last1=Chesneau|first1=Roger|title=Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1922–1946|date=1997|publisher=Conway Maritime Press Ltd|isbn=978-0851771465}}
*{{cite journal |last1=McBride |first1=K. D. |title=Es and Super-Es |journal=Warship International |date=1996 |volume=XXXIII |issue=3 |pages=257–278 |issn=0043-0374}}
* {{cite book|last1=Nesbit|first1=Roy Conyers|title=Ultra Versus U-Boats: Enigma Decrypts in the National Archives|date=2008|publisher=Casemate Publishers|isbn=9781844158744}}
* {{cite book|last=O'Hara|first=Vincent P.|title=The German Fleet at War, 1939–1945|year=2004| publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=1-59114-651-8|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=z85Xh21qniEC&amp;dq|location=Annapolis, Maryland}}
* {{cite book|last1=Oldfield|first1=Paul|title=Cockleshell Raid: Battleground Europe: French coast|date=2013|publisher=Casemate|isbn=9781781592557}}
* {{cite book|last1=Tucker|first1=Spencer|title=World War II at Sea: An Encyclopedia, Volume 1|date=2011|publisher=ABC-CLIO|isbn=9781598844573}}
* {{cite book|last=Whitley|first=M. J.|title=German Destroyers of World War Two|publisher=Naval Institute Press|date=1991|isbn=1-55750-302-8|location=Annapolis, Maryland}}

== External links ==
* [http://www.britishpathe.com/video/with-the-navy-bay-of-biscay British PATHE: ''With The Navy – Bay Of Biscay'']
{{Kriegsmarine}}
{{coord missing|Atlantic Ocean}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Bay of Biscay, Battle of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1943]]
[[Category:Battle of the Atlantic]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:December 1943 events]]
[[Category:Germany–United Kingdom military relations]]</text><sha1>7luf38foa97m39adhort2xw3mllv06j</sha1></revision></page>