<page><title>Action of 9 February 1945</title><ns>0</ns><id>31498061</id><revision><id>966286888</id><parentid>939982815</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-06T07:02:33Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Belevalo</username><id>39513455</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="9845" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Action of 9 February 1945
|partof=Second World War, [[Battle of the Atlantic]]
|image=HMS Venturer (P68) (IWM FL 004031).jpg
|image_size = 300px
|caption=HMS ''Venturer'' in August 1943
|date= {{Start date|1945|02|09|df=y}}
|place=off [[Fedje (island)|Fedje]], [[Occupation of Norway by Nazi Germany|Norway]]
|coordinates=
|result=British victory
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Commander]] [[Jimmy Launders]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Nazi Germany|naval}} ''[[Korvettenkapitän]]'' [[Ralf-Reimar Wolfram]]{{KIA}}
|strength1= [[HMS Venturer (P68)]]
|strength2={{GS|U-864||2}}
|casualties1=None
|casualties2=Submarine sunk,&lt;br/&gt;All 73 crew killed
|campaignbox ={{Campaignbox Norwegian Campaigns (1941 - 1945)}}
}}

During the '''action of 9 February 1945''', the [[Royal Navy]] [[submarine]] [[HMS Venturer (P68)|HMS ''Venturer'']] attacked and sank German [[U-boat]] {{GS|U-864||2}} in the [[North Sea]] off the [[Norway|Norwegian]] island of [[Fedje (island)|Fedje]]. 

This sinking is the only incident of its kind where one submarine has sunk another submarine in combat while both were at periscope depth.&lt;ref name="U864"&gt;''U864: Hitler's Deadly Last Secret'', Discovery Communications, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
''U-864'' was a [[Type IX U-boat]] on a covert mission, [[Operation Caesar|Operation ''Caesar'']], to the [[Empire of Japan]]. &lt;ref name=dnv&gt;{{cite web|title=Salvage of U864 – Supplementary Studies – Study No. 7: Cargo |work=Det Norske Veritas Report No. 23916 |publisher=[[Det Norske Veritas]] |date=4 July 2008 |url=http://www.kystverket.no/arch/_img/9818147.pdf |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090306045458/http://www.kystverket.no/arch/_img/9818147.pdf |archivedate=6 March 2009 }} pg 8&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.geneall.net/D/per_page.php?id=1666663|title=Rudolf Heinrich Julius von Chlingensperg auf Berg, * 1904 - Geneall.net}}&lt;/ref&gt;  On 6 February 1945, ''U-864'' passed through the [[Fedje (island)|Fedje]] area (off the coast of [[Norway]]) without being detected. During this transit, a normally quiet engine{{clarify|date=January 2019|reason=diesel engine, electric motor, or motor drive geartrain?}} began making an abnormally loud and rhythmic noise that could be easily detected by any [[anti-submarine warfare|anti-submarine]] (A/S) detection gear in the area.  There were many Allied (primarily British) ships, submarines and aircraft in the area on anti-submarine patrol. ''U-864''{{'}}s commander, [[Ralf-Reimar Wolfram]], decided to return to the [[submarine pen|pens]] at [[Bergen]] to repair the engine.

By this stage of the war the German machine cypher, [[Enigma code|Enigma]], had been broken by the British and was being decrypted, and the Royal Navy were concerned the secret cargo might enable the Japanese to extend the duration of the [[Pacific War|war in the Pacific]].{{cn|date=January 2019}} They dispatched ''Venturer'' to intercept and destroy ''U-864''.

''Venturer'', under the command of [[Lieutenant (navy)|Lieutenant]] [[Jimmy Launders]],&lt;ref name="U864"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mikekemble.com/ww2/britsublist.html |title=Listing of British Submarines of WW2|url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100414104731/http://www.mikekemble.com/ww2/britsublist.html |archivedate=14 April 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt; received a brief message from the Admiralty (probably [[Rear Admiral Submarines]]) as to the estimated whereabouts of ''U-864'', along with instructions to destroy her. Launders set about the task, making one risky decision: he decided to switch off ''Venturer''{{'}}s [[ASDIC]] (active sonar) and rely solely on [[hydrophone]]s, to try to detect ''U-864'' without being detected.&lt;ref name="U864"/&gt;

Wolfram's decision to return for repairs at the U-boat pens at Bergen to fix the abnormal engine noise problem brought ''U-864'' back past Fedje and the area where ''Venturer'' was located.

==The Action==
{{Refimprove section|date=February 2012}}
As ''Venturer'' continued her patrol of the waters around Fedje, her hydrophone operator noticed a strange sound which he could not identify. He thought that the noise sounded as though some local fisherman had started up a boat's diesel engine.&lt;ref name="U864"/&gt; Launders decided to track the strange noise. Then the officer of the watch on ''Venturer's'' periscope noticed what they thought was another periscope above the surface of the water.&lt;ref name="U864"/&gt; It is highly likely he had, in fact, spotted  the U-boat{{'}}s [[Submarine snorkel|snorkel]]. The snorkel was still a new device at that time and probably unknown to Launders and his crew.

The snorkel limited the U-boat's speed and depth. For Launders' hydrophone operator to hear diesel noises from a submerged U-boat, the snorkel would have had to be in operation. In addition, the noise of the diesel engines made the U-boat's own hydrophones much less effective and it is doubtful ''U-864'' would have heard ''Venturer'' running slowly on her electric motors.

Combined with the hydrophone reports of the strange noise, which he determined to be coming from a submerged vessel, Launders surmised they had found ''U-864''.&lt;ref name="U864"/&gt; He tracked the U-boat by hydrophone, hoping she would surface and allow a clear shot. ''U-864'' remained at snorkel depth,&lt;!--not, as a fact, the same thing--&gt; and as the hydrophone plot emerged, she was seen to be zigzagging. This made the German submarine quite safe according to the assumptions of the time.

It is very likely&lt;!--virtually damn certain, unless he's a complete nitwit--&gt; Launders tracked the U-boat's snorkel by periscope as well, which would greatly improve the accuracy of his [[fire-control system|fire control]] solution.

Launders tracked the U-boat for several hours, and it became obvious she was not going to surface, but he needed to attack her anyway – his batteries had only a limited life. It was theoretically possible to compute a firing solution in all four dimensions – time, distance, bearing and target depth – but this had never been attempted in practice because it was assumed that performing the complex calculations would be impossible, plus there were unknown factors that had to be approximated.

In most torpedo attacks, the target would have been visually acquired; the target's angle relative to the attacker and its bearing would be observed, then a [[rangefinder]]  in the periscope used to establish the distance to the target; from this speed could be derived, and a basic mechanical computer would offset the aiming point for the torpedo. In addition, any torpedo depth had to be set based on target identification. Too deep and the torpedo would pass under the target, too shallow (in this instance) it would miss above. Launders could only estimate the depth of his target. In terms of a challenge, this was far outside what they had trained for, as they tried to manoeuvre into a firing position without giving their own position away by creating excessive noise, or exhausting their own batteries.

Nevertheless, Launders&lt;!--CO, by tradition, gets full credit--&gt; made the necessary calculations, made assumptions about ''U-864'''s defensive manoeuvres, and ordered the firing of all four of his bow [[torpedo tube]]s. The torpedoes were fired with a 17.5 second delay between each pair, and at variable depths. ''U-864'' attempted to evade once it heard the torpedoes coming, but was not agile when diving or turning; additionally, time would have been needed to retract the snorkel, disengage the diesel, and start the electric motors.{{cn|date=January 2019|reason=wouldn't she have been running on her motors, with the diesels on charge?}} The fourth torpedo hit. Her [[pressure hull]] punctured, ''U-864'' instantaneously imploded with the loss of all hands.

==Aftermath==
[[File:U-864 map.png|thumb|Location of ''U-864'']]
''U-864'' sank {{convert|31|nmi|km|0}} from the relative safety of the U-boat pens in Bergen. Launders was awarded a bar to his [[Distinguished Service Order|DSO]] for this action, while several members of ''Venturer''{{'}}s crew were decorated by the Royal Navy. Launders' career in the Navy continued well after the war.&lt;ref name="ServRec"&gt;United Kingdom Royal Navy Museum, Commander Launders' Service Record, Public Records&lt;/ref&gt; The action was the first and so far only battle ever to have been fought entirely under water.&lt;ref name="U864"/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book|last1=Akermann|first1=Paul|title=Encyclopaedia of British Submarines 1901–1955|date=2002|publisher=Periscope Publishing Ltd|isbn=978-1-904381-05-1}}

==External links==
*{{cite web
 |accessdate=28 May 2007 
 |url=http://www.history.ca/ontv/titledetails.aspx?titleid=103001 
 |title=U-864: Hitler's Deadly Last Secret 
 |publisher=History Television 
 |url-status=dead 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070927074336/http://www.history.ca/ontv/titledetails.aspx?titleid=103001 
 |archivedate=27 September 2007 
}}
*{{cite web
|url=http://uboat.net/allies/warships/ship/3585.html
|title=HMS ''Venturer''
|last=Helgason
|first=Guðmundur
|website=German U-boats of WWII - uboat.net
}}
*{{cite web
|url=http://uboat.net/boats/u864.htm
|title=''U-864''
|last=Helgason
|first=Guðmundur
|website=German U-boats of WWII - uboat.net
}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2012}}
{{coord missing|Norway}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:19450209}}
[[Category:Battle of the Atlantic]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|A]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Submarine warfare in World War II]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1945]]
[[Category:1945 in Norway]]
[[Category:February 1945 events]]</text><sha1>gom7nz7bzci5ruuitu0547y2ozestap</sha1></revision></page>