<page><title>Battle of Jordanów</title><ns>0</ns><id>3721810</id><revision><id>965788568</id><parentid>965788556</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-03T12:26:08Z</timestamp><contributor><username>The Anome</username><id>76</id></contributor><comment>Changing [[Wikipedia:Short description|short description]] from "Battle during the Nazi nvasion of Poland" to "Battle during the Nazi invasion of Poland" ([[Wikipedia:Shortdesc helper|Shortdesc helper]])</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="7749" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Battle during the Nazi invasion of Poland}}
{{Refimprove|date=July 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Jordanów
| image       = [[File:Dzialon armaty PPanc wz 36.jpg|300px|Battle of Jordanów]]
| caption     = Soldiers of the [[10th Motorized Cavalry Brigade (Poland)|10th Motorized Cavalry Brigade]] using a [[Bofors 37 mm|Bofors 37mm gun]]
| partof      = [[Invasion of Poland (1939)|Invasion of Poland]]
| date        = 1–3 September 1939
| place       = [[Jordanów]], [[Kraków Voivodeship (1919–39)|Kraków Voivodeship]], [[Second Polish Republic|Poland]]
| result      = Pyrrhic German victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|Poland}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Poland}} [[Stanisław Maczek]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Poland}} Jan Wójcik
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Eugen Beyer]]&lt;ref name="wrzesien.za.pl"&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://wrzesien.za.pl/wehr.htm |title=Archived copy |access-date=28 July 2012 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090830014614/http://wrzesien.za.pl/wehr.htm |archive-date=30 August 2009 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;
| units1 = {{flagicon|Poland}} Army Kraków:
* [[10th Motorized Cavalry Brigade (Poland)|10th Motorized Cavalry Brigade]]
* 1st Regiment of [[Border Protection Corps|KOP]]
* [[battalion]] from 12th IR
| units2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} XXII Panzer Corps:
* [[2nd Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|2nd Panzer Division]]
* [[9th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|4th Light Division]]
* [[3rd Mountain Division (Wehrmacht)|3rd Mountain Division]]
| strength1   = 5,000 soldiers &lt;br&gt; 58 tanks and AFVs &lt;br&gt; 16 field guns &lt;br&gt; [[armoured train]] No.51 "Pierwszy Marszałek"&lt;ref name=Majka1&gt;{{cite book|last=Majka|first=Jerzy|title=Brygada Motorowa płk. Maczka 10.brygada kawalerii 1937-1939|year=2007|publisher=Libra|location=Rzeszów|isbn=978-83-89183-39-2|pages=199}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 3/109 heavy artillery&lt;ref name="wrzesien.za.pl"/&gt; &lt;br&gt; 50,000 soldiers &lt;br&gt; 498 tanks and AFVs &lt;br&gt; 128 field guns&lt;ref name=Majka1 /&gt;
| casualties1 = 3+ tanks
| casualties2 = 70+ tanks and AFVs
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Polish September Campaign}}
}}

The '''Battle of Jordanów''' took place on 1–3 September 1939, during the [[Invasion of Poland (1939)|Invasion of Poland]] and the opening stages of [[World War II]]. It was fought between the [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[XXXXVIII Panzer Corps|XVIII Panzer Corps]] of Gen.E.Beyer and the [[Polish 10th Motorized Cavalry Brigade]] under Col. [[Stanisław Maczek]].

== Opening hostilities ==
[[File:Armia krakow 1939.png|thumb|left|Positions of Polish and German forces before the battle. Map by [https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Lonio17 Lonio17]]]
On 1 September 1939, the XVIII Panzer Corps, part of the German [[14th Army (Wehrmacht)|14th Army]], crossed the Polish border from [[Slovakia]]. In an attempt to outflank the positions of the Polish [[Kraków Army]] under Gen. [[Antoni Szylling]] defending [[Silesia]] and western [[Lesser Poland]], the Germans crossed the [[Tatra mountains|Tatra]] passes and assaulted the towns of [[Chabówka]] and [[Nowy Targ]]. Their orders were to seize the town of [[Myślenice]] not later than on 3 September thus encircling the entire Polish army fighting in the area.

== Opposing forces ==
The area assaulted by the XVIII Corps was only lightly defended by a single infantry regiment of the [[Border Defence Corps]] under Lt.Col. [[Jan Wójcik]]. Hard pressed by a combined force of [[German 3rd Mountain Division|3rd Mountain Division]], [[German 2nd Panzer Division|2nd Panzer Division]] and [[German 4th Light Division|4th Light Division]] under Gen. [[Alfred Ritter von Hubicki]], the Border Defence Corps, aided by the local volunteers and units of the [[National Defense (Poland)|National Defence]], withstood the attack, but also suffered heavy losses. Despite stopping the Germans in the vicinity of [[Nowy Targ]], the town was taken by the Germans and the risk of breaking through the Polish lines became apparent.

== Polish counterattack ==
To counter the threat, General Szylling ordered the [[10th Motorized Cavalry Brigade]], until then held in reserve, to move to the area and block the area of [[Jordanów]] and [[Rabka-Zdrój|Rabka]]. Overnight the brigade was transported to the area and Col. Maczek installed his headquarters in the village of Krzeczów. The detachments of the Polish unit entered combat almost instantly. Particularly heavy fights occurred in the hills to the south of Jordanów, around the mountain of Wysoka (not to be confused with the Wysoka in northern Poland), where the 24th Motorized Regiment under Col. {{ill|Kazimierz Dworzak|pl}}, aided by the KOP and anti-tank artillery defended the area against the 2nd Panzer Division. Heavy artillery barrage started at 5 AM and soon afterwards the entire division started an all-out assault of the Polish positions. Despite suffering heavy losses, the Poles managed to stop the German assault and by noon the Germans withdrew losing approximately 30 tanks. However, the numerical and technical superiority of the [[Wehrmacht]] was tremendous and after three failed assaults, in the late evening the Germans finally seized the mountain of Wysoka and the village at its feet. The Poles withdrew under cover of an [[armoured train]]. The village of Wysoka became a centre for German service units and munitions depot. However, during the night the civilian inhabitants set two oil tanks on fire. The explosion destroyed a number of previously damaged tanks of the 2nd division, also killing a number of resting soldiers of the [[German 3rd Mountain Division|3rd Mountain Division]].

==Losses==
Altogether, in the battle of Jordanów the Germans lost approximately 50 tanks and a number of other [[armoured fighting vehicle]]s. Polish losses were also significant, and especially so in the ill-equipped volunteer units.

== Aftermath ==
===Beskids withdrawal and ambush===
Having reconed the German units in the area, Gen. Szylling ordered the 10th Cavalry Brigade to slowly withdraw along the [[Beskids]] and organize delaying actions along the rivers and mountain ranges. Despite being badly outnumbered, the following day the Polish unit organized an [[ambush]] near [[Lubień, Lesser Poland Voivodeship|Lubień]] and [[Sucha Beskidzka]], in which the German tanks suffered additional losses. The same day the 24th Recce Escadrille composed of 6 [[PZL.23 Karaś]] bombers destroyed a number of tanks around Jordanów and the village of Podwilko. The 31st Recce Escadrille, forming part of the [[organic (military)|organic]] aviation of the [[Karpaty Army]] successfully bombed the tanks of the 4th Light Division on the road between [[Nowy Targ]] and [[Chabówka]].

===Ambushes of Kasina Wielka and Myślenice===
Afterward, the Poles withdrew again, this time to the area of [[Kasina Wielka]], where two ambushes were organized on 4 September. The following day the Poles followed the road towards [[Myślenice]], where yet another ambush was organized. This tactics proved to be a good weapon against the German [[blitzkrieg]] as the Germans in the area could not advance faster than mere 10 to 20 kilometres a day and suffering heavy losses in men and equipment. Because of its success, the 10th Motorized Cavalry Brigade remained a fully operational unit until 19 September 1939, when it was ordered to cross the border with [[Hungary]].

==References==
&lt;references/&gt;

{{coord|49.648720|19.829728|format=dms|display=title|type:event}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2017}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Jordanow}}
[[Category:Battles of the Invasion of Poland|Jordanow]]
[[Category:Kraków Voivodeship (1919–1939)]]
[[Category:September 1939 events]]</text><sha1>pql4ywbmteojpaeh6sge0a71takgj0y</sha1></revision></page>