<page><title>Battle of Wizna</title><ns>0</ns><id>1175035</id><revision><id>956658438</id><parentid>946063397</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-14T15:29:47Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>78.87.53.99</ip></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="21576" xml:space="preserve">{{refimprove|date=May 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Wizna
| image       =
| caption     = Polish soldiers positioned with an anti tank gun, at Wizna in September 1939.
| partof      = the [[Invasion of Poland]]
| date        = September 7–10, 1939
| place       = [[Wizna]], near [[Łomża]], Poland
| result      = German victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|Nazi Germany}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|Second Polish Republic|name=Poland}}
| commander1  = {{flagdeco|Nazi Germany}} [[Heinz Guderian]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Nazi Germany}} [[Ferdinand Schaal]]
| commander2  = {{flagdeco|Poland}} [[Władysław Raginis]]{{KIA|Suicide}} &lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Poland}} Stanisław Brykalski{{KIA|Suicide}}
| strength1   = 42,200 infantry&lt;br&gt;350 tanks&lt;br&gt;657 artillery pieces
| strength2   = 350-720 infantry&lt;ref name="Moczulski-765"&gt;Moczulski, p.765&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;6 [[76 mm divisional gun M1902|76 mm guns]]&lt;br&gt;42 MGs&lt;br&gt;2 [[Anti-tank rifle, model 35|anti-tank rifles]]
| casualties1 = ~1400 casualties&lt;br&gt;10 tanks destroyed&lt;br&gt;1 aircraft destroyed
| casualties2 = ~660 casualties&lt;br&gt;40 captured
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Polish September Campaign}}
}}

The '''Battle of Wizna''' was fought between September 7 and September 10, 1939, between the forces of [[Second Polish Republic|Poland]] and [[Nazi Germany|Germany]] during the initial stages of [[invasion of Poland]]. According to Polish historian [[Leszek Moczulski]], between 350 and 720 Poles defended a fortified line for three days against more than 40,000 Germans.&lt;ref name="Moczulski-765" /&gt; Although defeat was inevitable, the Polish defence stalled the attacking forces for three days and postponed the encirclement of [[Independent Operational Group Narew]] fighting nearby.&lt;ref name="Dobronski-21"&gt;Dobroński, p.21&lt;/ref&gt; Eventually the tanks broke through the Polish line and German engineers eliminated all the bunkers one by one. The last bunker surrendered around midday on September 10.&lt;ref name="Moczulski-767"&gt;Moczulski, p.767&lt;/ref&gt;

Because the battle consisted of a small force holding a piece of fortified territory against a vastly larger invasion for three days at great cost before being annihilated, Wizna is sometimes referred to as the "[[Polish Thermopylae]]".&lt;ref name="Wiśniewski"&gt;Wiśniewski, op.cit.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Krajewski"&gt;Krajewski, pp.16-17&lt;/ref&gt; One of the symbols of the battle is Captain [[Władysław Raginis]], the commanding officer of the Polish force, who swore to hold his position as long as he was alive. When the last two bunkers under his command ran out of ammunition, he ordered his men to surrender their arms and committed suicide by throwing himself on a live grenade.

==History==

===Background===
[[File:Battle of Wizna.png|thumb|left|200px|Positions prior to the battle.]]Before the war, the area of the village of [[Wizna]] was prepared as a fortified line of defence. It was to shield the Polish positions further to the south and guard the crossing of the [[Narew]] and [[Biebrza]] rivers. The {{convert|9|km|mi}} long line of Polish defences stretched between the villages of [[Kołodzieje]] and [[Grądy-Woniecko]], with Wizna in the centre. The line ran some {{convert|35|km|mi}} from the border with [[East Prussia]], along an elevated banks of [[Narew]] and [[Biebrza]] rivers.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-448"/&gt; Units defending the line were subordinate to the Polish [[Independent Operational Group Narew]] shielding [[Łomża]] and providing defence of the northern approach to Warsaw.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-448"&gt;Komorowski, p.448&lt;/ref&gt; The Wizna fortified area was one of the most important nodes in Northern Poland, providing cover of both the river crossings, and the roads [[Łomża]]&amp;ndash;[[Białystok]] and roads towards [[Brest, Belarus|Brześć Litewski]] on the rear of Polish forces.

Construction started in June 1939, only two months before the outbreak of World War II.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-448"/&gt; The spot was chosen carefully; most of the concrete [[bunker]]s were built on hills overlooking a swampy Narew River valley. They could be reached either through direct assault through the swamps or by attack along the causeway leading from the bridge in Wizna. Before September 1, 1939, only 16 bunkers were built out of 60 planned.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-448"/&gt; Six bunkers were made of heavy concrete with reinforced steel cupolas weighing 8 tons each, armed with machine guns and anti-tank artillery.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-448"/&gt; Two were light concrete bunkers, armed with machine guns only.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-448"/&gt; The remaining eight were ad-hoc machine gun [[Bunker#Pillbox|pillbox]]es, protected mostly by sandbags and earthworks. Four additional heavy bunkers were under construction when World War II started. In addition, the area was reinforced with [[trench]]es, anti-tank and anti-personnel obstacles, [[barbed wire]] lines and [[land mine]]s. There were also plans to break the [[dam]]s on the [[Biebrza]] and [[Narew]] rivers to flood the area, but the summer of 1939 was one of the driest seasons in Polish history and the water level was too low.

Although not all bunkers were ready by the beginning of the war, the Polish lines of defence were well-prepared. The walls of an average bunker, 1.5 metres thick and reinforced with 20-centimetre-thick steel plates, could withstand a direct hit from even the heaviest guns available to the [[Wehrmacht]] at the time. The bunkers were situated on hills which gave good visibility of all the advancing forces.

=== Opposing forces ===

The Polish defensive line was initially manned by a single battalion from the 71st Infantry Regiment, commanded by Major Jakub Fober. However, shortly before the outbreak of World War II it was reinforced with a machine gun company from [[Osowiec Fortress]] under Captain [[Władysław Raginis]], as well as numerous smaller detachments from a variety of units.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-448"/&gt; On September 2, 1939, the III/71 battalion departed for Osowiec, and Fober passed command over Wizna to Raginis and his men. Altogether, the Polish defensive position was manned by 720 men: 20 officers and 700 NCOs and privates.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-448"/&gt; However, some sources claim that the Polish unit was even weaker, no more than 360 men strong.&lt;ref name="Rzepa"&gt;Zychowicz, p. A6&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the Polish units were almost entirely composed of conscripts mobilised in August 1939 rather than professional soldiers, their morale was very high.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-448"/&gt; After the war, Guderian had trouble explaining why his corps was stopped by such a small force. In his memoirs he attributes the delay to his officers "having trouble building bridges across the rivers".&lt;ref name="WPH-246"/&gt; During the [[Nuremberg Trials]] he remarked that Wizna was "well-defended by a local officer school".&lt;ref name="WPH-246"/&gt;

{{col-begin}}
{{col-break}}
{| class="wikitable" style="text-align:center; border:1px solid #ccc;"
|+ style="font-weight:bold;" | [[Polish Army]]
|-  style="vertical-align:top; background:#ccc;"
!  style="width:300px; font-weight:normal;"| [[Narew Independent Operational Group|Narew IOG]] &lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Czesław Młot-Fijałkowski|Młot-Fijałkowski]]&lt;/small&gt;
|-  style="vertical-align:top; background:#eee;"
| Odcinek Obrony "Wizna"&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Władysław Raginis|Raginis]]&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| 8th company of 135th Infantry Regiment&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Schmidt&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| 3rd heavy MG company of Osowiec fortress batt.&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Władysław Raginis|Raginis]]&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| Battery of positional artillery &lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Brykalski&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| 136th company of engineers
|-
| Platoon of engineers and platoon of field artillery of 71st Infantry Regiment
|-
| Platoon of mounted reconnaissance of 135th Infantry Regiment
|- style="border-bottom:1px solid gray;"
| &lt;small&gt;720 men, 12 bunkers, 6 pieces of artillery (76mm), 24 [[Heavy machine gun]]s, 18 [[machine gun]]s and two [[Kb ppanc wz.35]] anti-tank rifles&lt;/small&gt;
|}
{{col-break}}
{| class="wikitable" style="text-align:center; border:1px solid #ccc;"
|+ style="font-weight:bold;" | [[Wehrmacht]]
|-  style="vertical-align:top; background:#ccc;"
!  style="width:300px; font-weight:normal;"| 3rd Army &lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Georg von Küchler|Küchler]]&lt;/small&gt;
|-  style="vertical-align:top; background:#eee;"
| [[XIX Army Corps]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Heinz Guderian|Guderian]]&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| 3rd Panzer Division&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Leo Freiherr Geyr von Schweppenburg|Schweppenburg]]&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| 20th Motorised Division&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Mauritz von Wiktorin|Wiktorin]]&lt;/small&gt;
|-
|
|-
| 10th Panzer Division&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;[[Ferdinand Schaal|Schaal]]&lt;/small&gt;
|-
| [["Lötzen" Infantry Brigade (Wehrmacht)|"Lötzen" Infantry Brigade]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;Offenbacher&lt;/small&gt;
|- style="border-bottom:1px solid gray;"
| &lt;small&gt;42,000 men, 350 tanks, 108 [[howitzer]]s, 58 pieces of artillery, 195 anti-tank guns, 108 mortars, 188 grenade launchers, 288 [[heavy machine gun]]s and 689 [[machine gun]]s&lt;/small&gt;
|}
{{col-end}}

=== Before the battle ===
On September 1, 1939, the [[Invasion of Poland|Polish Defensive War]] and World War II started. The German 3rd Army was to advance from [[East Prussia]] towards [[Warsaw]], directly through the positions of Polish [[Narew Independent Operational Group|Narew Corps]]. On September 2 Captain [[Władysław Raginis]] was named the commander of the Wizna area. As his command post he chose the "GG-126" bunker near the village of [[Góra Strękowa]]. The bunker was located on a hill in the exact centre of the Polish lines. His forces numbered approximately 700 soldiers and [[Non-commissioned officer|NCOs]] and 20 officers armed with 6 pieces of artillery (75mm), 24 [[Heavy machine gun|HMG]]s, 18 [[machine gun]]s and two [[Kb ppanc wz.35]] [[anti-tank rifle]]s, with just 20 bullets.

After initial clashes at the border, the [[Podlaska Cavalry Brigade]] operating in the area, during the night of 3/4 September was ordered to withdraw and on September 5 it left the area and marched toward [[Mały Płock]] to cross the river Narew. On September 3 Polish positions were spotted from the air and strafed with machine gun fire from enemy fighters.

On September 7, 1939, the reconnaissance units of the [[German 10th Panzer Division|10th Panzer Division]] of General [[Nikolaus von Falkenhorst]] captured the village of Wizna. Polish mounted reconnaissance squads abandoned the village after a short fight and retreated to the southern bank of [[Narew]]. When German tanks tried to cross the bridge, it was blown up by Polish engineers. After dark, patrols of German infantry crossed the river and advanced towards Giełczyn, but were repelled with heavy casualties.

On September 8 General [[Heinz Guderian]], commander of the [[XIX Panzer Corps]], was ordered to advance through [[Wizna]] towards [[Brest, Belarus|Brześć]]. By early morning of September 9 his units reached the Wizna area and were joined with 10th Panzer Division and [["Lötzen" Infantry Brigade (Wehrmacht)|"Lötzen" Infantry Brigade]] already present in the area. His forces numbered some 1,200 officers and 41,000 soldiers and NCOs, equipped with over 350 [[tank]]s, 108 [[howitzer]]s, 58 pieces of artillery, 195 anti-tank guns, 108 [[mortar (weapon)|mortar]]s, 188 grenade launchers, 288 [[heavy machine gun]]s, and 689 [[machine gun]]s. Altogether, his forces were some 60 times stronger than the Polish defenders.

=== Defence of Wizna ===
[[File:POL Strekowa Góra2.jpg|thumb|right|200px|Ruins of one of the bunkers, now a memorial site.]]
In the early morning, German planes [[Airborne leaflet propaganda|dropped leaflets]] that urged the Poles to surrender and claimed that most of Poland was already in German hands, and that further resistance was futile. In order to strengthen the morale of his troops, Władysław Raginis and Lieutenant Brykalski swore that they would not leave their post alive and that resistance would continue.&lt;ref name="Moczulski-765"/&gt; Soon after that a German artillery barrage and aerial bombardment started.&lt;ref name="WPH-246"&gt;''Wojskowy Przegląd Historyczny'' (1960), p.246&lt;/ref&gt; The Polish artillery was much weaker and was soon forced to retreat towards [[Białystok]]. After preparation, the Germans attacked the northern flank of the Polish forces. Two platoons defending several bunkers located to the north of Narew were attacked from three sides by German tanks and infantry. Initially the losses among German infantry were high, but after heavy artillery fire, the commander of the Giełczyn area, First Lieutenant Kiewlicz, was ordered to burn the wooden bridge over Narew and withdraw to [[Białystok]]. The remnants of his forces broke through the German encirclement and reached Białystok, where they joined the forces of General [[Franciszek Kleeberg]].

At the same time, an assault on the southern part of Polish fortifications became a stalemate. The Polish bunkers lacked adequate anti-tank armament, but were able to rake the German infantry with machine gun fire. However, at 6 o'clock in the evening, the Polish infantry was forced to abandon the trenches and field fortifications and retreat into the bunkers. The German tanks could finally cross the Polish lines and advance towards [[Tykocin]] and [[Zambrów]]. However, the German infantry was still under heavy fire and was pinned down in the swampy fields in front of the Polish bunkers.

Although Raginis was subordinate to Lieutenant Colonel Tadeusz Tabaczyński, commander of the [[Osowiec Fortress|Osowiec]] fortified area located some 30 kilometres to the north, he could not expect any reinforcements. On September 8, the [[Marshal of Poland]], [[Edward Śmigły-Rydz]], ordered the 135th Infantry Regiment, which constituted the reserves of both Osowiec and Wizna, to be withdrawn to Warsaw. When the order was withdrawn and the unit returned to Osowiec, it was already too late to help the isolated Poles at Wizna.

Heavy fighting for each of the now isolated bunkers continued. Several assaults were repelled during the night and in the early morning of September 10.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-451"&gt;Komorowski, p.451&lt;/ref&gt; At approximately 11 o'clock, German engineers, with the help of tanks and artillery, finally managed to destroy all but two of the Polish bunkers. Both of them were located&lt;ref&gt;{{coord|53.2124837|22.4896574|format=dms|type:landmark|display=title,inline}}&lt;/ref&gt; in the centre of Strękowa Góra and continued fighting despite having much of the crew wounded or incapacitated and most of their machine guns destroyed. After the war, the Poles insisted that Guderian, in an attempt to end the Polish resistance, threatened the Polish commander that he would shoot the [[Prisoner of War|POWs]] if the remaining forces did not surrender.&lt;ref name="Williamson-180"&gt;Williamson, p.180: ''Guderian surrendered to the Americans but was not charged with war crimes, despite the Poles insisting that he had threatened to shoot Polish PoWs at the battle of Wizna unless their Polish commander ordered an immediate capitulation.''&lt;/ref&gt; The resistance, however, continued for another hour, when a German envoy arrived carrying a [[flag of truce]] and proposed a [[cease fire]].&lt;ref name="Komorowski-448"/&gt; It lasted until approximately 1:30 p.m. Raginis, realising that all of his men were wounded and his ammunition was almost depleted, ordered his men to surrender their arms to the Germans. He himself – seriously injured at the time – refused to surrender and committed suicide by throwing himself on a grenade.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-451"/&gt;

===Aftermath===
After the Polish resistance ended, the XIX Panzer Corps advanced towards [[Wysokie Mazowieckie]] and [[Zambrów]], where it fought the [[Battle of Zambrów]] against the [[18th Infantry Division (Poland)|Polish 18th Infantry Division]], finally encircling and destroying the Polish division during the [[Battle of Andrzejewo]]. Later it advanced further southwards and took part in the [[Battle of Brześć]].

Although all the bunkers were destroyed and the Polish resistance was finally broken, the fortified area of Wizna managed to halt the German advance for three days.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-451"/&gt; The heroic struggle against overwhelming odds is one of the symbols of the [[Invasion of Poland|Polish Defensive War]] of 1939 and is a part of Polish popular culture.

== Casualties ==
Exact Polish losses are unknown, mostly because very little is known of the soldiers that were taken as [[prisoners of war]] by the Germans. Out of 720 Polish soldiers only approximately 70 survived.&lt;ref name="Komorowski-451"/&gt; Some successfully withdrew and reached the Polish lines, others were taken prisoner. Some of the prisoners were subsequently killed by the Germans, others were beaten and abused but survived and were eventually taken to POW camps.&lt;ref name="Wiśniewski-029"&gt;Wiśniewski, 29&lt;/ref&gt;

German losses are not known either. An official release by the Wehrmacht mentioned "several dozen dead",&lt;ref name="Wiśniewski-035"&gt;Wiśniewski, 35&lt;/ref&gt; but at least several hundred bodies of fallen German soldiers were exhumed from a local war cemetery.{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

In his diaries, General [[Heinz Guderian]] noted that 900 German soldiers were killed in action. The [[Wehrmacht]] lost at least 10 tanks and several other [[Armored fighting vehicle|AFV]]s in the struggle.&lt;ref&gt;Zygmunt Kosztyła, ''Obrona odcinka "Wizna" 1939'', BKD (Bitwy, Kampanie, Dowódcy) [7/76], 1976. Also: P. Kupidura, M. Zahor, "Wizna", ''Wojskowy Przegląd Techniczny i Logistyczny'', nr 3, 1999&lt;/ref&gt;{{Citation needed|date=April 2010}}

The history of the 10th Tank Division for September 8 mentions 9 killed and 26 wounded in action for the ALA.{{clarify|date=June 2019|reason=What is ALA?}} The I./IR 86, which was the main unit of the capture of the bunkers reported on September 9 at 17:00 the loss of 40 men.&lt;ref&gt;Die Geschichte der 10. Panzer-Division 1939 - 1943 - Albert Schick, Hrsg. von der Trad.Gem. der ehem. 10. Pz.Div., Köln 1993&lt;/ref&gt; There are some losses of the Tank Regiment 8 reported as well. The following fighting at Wysokie-Mazowieckie and Andrzejewo make it difficult to differentiate the losses.

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

==See also==
* [[Battle of Zadwórze]]
* [[Battle of Westerplatte]]

== References ==
{{refbegin}}
;Articles

* {{cite journal | author =Adam Dobroński | year =1972 | month = | title =Pod Wizną | journal =Mówią wieki | volume =15 | issue =9 | pages = | id = | url = | accessdate = |language=pl}}
* {{cite journal | author =Andrzej Krajewski | date =2009-09-04 | month = | title =Polskie Termopile, czyli cud pod Wizną | journal =[[Polska The Times]] | volume = | issue = | pages =16–17 | issn =1898-3081 | url = | accessdate = |language=pl}}
* {{in lang|pl}} Zygmunt Kosztyła, ''Obrona odcinka "Wizna" 1939'', BKD (Bitwy, Kampanie, Dowódcy) [7/76], 1976
* {{in lang|pl}} P. Kupidura, M. Zahor, ''Wizna'', Wojskowy Przegląd Techniczny i Logistyczny, nr 3, 1999
* {{in lang|pl}} A. Wiktorzak, ''Wizna - Polskie Termopile'', Głos Weterana, nr 9, 1997
* {{cite journal | author =BD | year =1960 | month = | title =Heinz Guderian | journal =Wojskowy Przegląd Historyczny | volume =V | issue =1/4 | pages = | editor=Jerzy Bordziłowski | id = |language=pl}}
* {{cite journal |author=Piotr Zychowicz |date=2011-12-16 |title=Awans dla Raginisa |trans-title=Raginis promoted |journal=[[Rzeczpospolita (newspaper)|Rzeczpospolita]] |volume=293 |issue=9109 |page=A6 |location=Warsaw |publisher=Presspublica |isbn= |issn=0208-9130 |oclc=264077858|accessdate=2011-12-21 |url=http://www.rp.pl/artykul/774245.html?print=tak&amp;p=0 |quote=Do tej pory uważano, że Raginis dysponował 720 żołnierzami. Analiza nowych źródeł skłoniła nas do przekonania, że nie miał nawet tego. Pod jego komendą mogło znajdować się góra 360 ludzi |language=pl}}

;Books
* {{cite book | author =Krzysztof Komorowski | coauthors = | title =Boje polskie 1939-1945 | year =2009 | editor = | page =504 | chapter = | chapterurl = | publisher =Bellona | location =Warsaw | isbn= | url = | accessdate = |language=pl}}
* {{cite book | author =[[Leszek Moczulski]] | coauthors = | title =Wojna polska 1939. wydanie poprawione i uzupełnione | year =2009 | editor = | pages = | chapter = | chapterurl = | publisher =Bellona | location =Warsaw | isbn=978-83-11-11584-2 | url = | accessdate = |language=pl}}
* {{cite book| author = David G. Williamson| title         = Poland Betrayed: The Nazi-Soviet Invasions of 1939| series    = Stackpole Military History| year      = 2009| publisher = Stackpole Books| location  = Mechanicsburg, PA| isbn      = 978-0-8117-0828-9| page     = 272}}
* {{in lang|pl}} Kazimierz Stawiński, ''Bój pod Wizną''. Warszawa 1964. Wydawnictwo Ministerstwa Obrony Narodowej.
;Audio-visual
* {{cite video | people = Leszek Wiśniewski (director), Kamil Wertel (historical editor), Maria Mazurek (producer) | date = 2009 | title  = Polskie Termopile |trans-title=Polish Thermopylae | url = http://www.tvp.pl/historia/rocznice-i-wydarzenia/ii-wojna-swiatowa/wideo/fakty/polskie-termopile-film-dok/1158783 | medium      =  | publisher   = [[Telewizja Polska]] | location    = Warsaw | time        =  | quote       =  | ref         = |language=pl}}

{{refend}}

== External links ==
* {{in lang|pl}} [https://web.archive.org/web/20110522031907/http://www.wpk.p.lodz.pl/~bolas/main/bitwy/wizna/wizna.htm BITWA POD WIZNĄ]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Wizna}}
[[Category:Battles of the Invasion of Poland|Wizna]]
[[Category:Last stand battles|W]]
[[Category:September 1939 events]]</text><sha1>o1jyp6rvysafnddtpu7em15y3yo2ncm</sha1></revision></page>