<page><title>Soviet invasion of Poland</title><ns>0</ns><id>7884711</id><revision><id>967142900</id><parentid>965810120</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-11T11:24:30Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Joshhelfferich</username><id>18713374</id></contributor><minor /><comment>Replaced a comma with “and”</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="89794" xml:space="preserve">{{About|the invasion in 1939|the Soviet invasion of Poland in 1920|Polish–Soviet War}}
{{short description|1939 invasion of the Second Polish Republic by the Soviet Union during World War II}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2012}}
{{infobox military conflict
|conflict    =Soviet invasion of Poland
|partof      =the [[Invasion of Poland]] in [[World War II]]
|image       =[[File:Lviv 1939 Sov Cavalry.jpg|290px|Soviet parade in [[Lviv|Lwów]], 1939]]
|caption     =Soviet parade in [[Lwów]], 1939
|date        =17 September – 6 October 1939
|place       =[[Second Polish Republic|Poland]]
|coordinates =
|map_type    =
|latitude    =
|longitude   =
|map_size    =
|map_caption =
|map_label   =
|territory   = Territory of [[Kresy|Eastern Poland (Kresy)]] annexed by the [[Soviet Union]]
|result      = Soviet victory
|status      =
|combatant1  ={{flagcountry|Second Polish Republic|1928}}
|combatant2  ={{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
|commander1  ={{Unbulleted list
|[[Edward Rydz-Śmigły]]
|([[Marshal of Poland]])|item2_style=font-size: 95%;
}}
|commander2  ={{Unbulleted list
|[[Mikhail Kovalyov]]
|(Belarusian Front)|item4_style=font-size: 95%;
|[[Semyon Timoshenko]]
|(Ukrainian Front)|item6_style=font-size: 95%;
}}
|units1      =
|units2      =
|units3      =
|strength1   =20,000 [[Border Protection Corps]],&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;{{#tag:ref|Increasing numbers of [[Border Protection Corps (Poland)|Border Protection Corps]] units, as well as Polish Army units stationed in the East during peacetime, were sent to the Polish-German border before or during the German invasion. The Border Protection Corps forces guarding the eastern border numbered approximately 20,000 men.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;|group="Note"}}&lt;br /&gt;450,000 [[Polish Army]].&lt;ref name="PWN_KW_old" /&gt;{{#tag:ref|The retreat from the Germans disrupted and weakened Polish Army units, making estimates of their strength problematic. Sanford estimated that approximately 450,000 troops found themselves in the line of the Soviet advance and offered only sporadic resistance.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;|group="Note"}}
|strength2   =600,000–800,000 troops&lt;ref name="PWN_KW_old" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Krivosheev" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;33+ divisions&lt;br /&gt;11+ brigades&lt;br /&gt;4,959 guns&lt;br /&gt;4,736 tanks&lt;br /&gt;3,300 aircraft
|strength3   =
|casualties1 =3,000–7,000 killed or missing,&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Wojsko92" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;up to 20,000 wounded.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;{{#tag:ref|The figures do not take into account the approximately 2,500 prisoners of war executed in immediate reprisals or by anti-Polish [[Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists]].&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;|group="Note"}}&lt;br /&gt;320,000–450,000 captured&lt;ref name=Zaloga&gt;Zaloga, S.J., 2002, Poland 1939, Oxford: Osprey Publishing Ltd., {{ISBN|9781841764085}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|85}}
|casualties2 =1,475–3,000 killed or missing&lt;br /&gt;2,383–10,000 wounded.{{#tag:ref|Soviet official losses – figures provided by Krivosheev – are currently estimated at 1,475 KIA or MIA presumed dead (Ukrainian Front – 972, Belorussian Front – 503), and 2,383 WIA (Ukrainian Front – 1,741, Belorussian Front – 642). The Soviets lost approximately 150 tanks in combat of which 43 as irrecoverable losses, while hundreds more suffered technical failures.&lt;ref name="Krivosheev" /&gt; Sanford indicates that Polish estimates of Soviet losses are 3,000 dead and 10,000 wounded.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt; Russian historian Igor Bunich estimates Soviet losses at 5,327 KIA or MIA without a trace and WIA.&lt;ref name="WIF" /&gt;|group="Note"}}
|casualties3 =
|notes       =
|campaignbox ={{Campaignbox Soviet invasion of Poland}}{{Campaignbox Polish September Campaign}}{{Polish-Russian Wars}}
}}
The '''Soviet invasion of Poland''' was a military operation by the [[Soviet Union]] without a formal [[declaration of war]]. On 17 September 1939, the Soviet Union invaded [[Poland]] from the east, sixteen days after [[Nazi Germany|Germany]] [[Invasion of Poland|invaded Poland]] from the west. Subsequent military operations lasted for the following 20 days and ended on 6 October 1939 with the two-way division and annexation of the entire territory of the [[Second Polish Republic]] by [[Nazi Germany]] and the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name="Gross 17-18" /&gt; This division is sometimes called the [[Fourth Partition of Poland]]. The Soviet (as well as German) invasion of Poland was indirectly indicated in the [[Molotov–Ribbentrop_Pact#Secret_protocol|"secret protocol"]] of the [[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact]] signed on 23 August 1939, which divided Poland into "[[spheres of influence]]" of the two powers and questioned the future existence of the Polish state.&lt;ref&gt;http://legacy.fordham.edu/halsall/mod/1939pact.html&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Red Army]], which vastly outnumbered the Polish defenders, achieved its targets encountering only limited resistance. Some 320,000 Polish prisoners of war had been captured.&lt;ref name="Wojsko92" /&gt;&lt;ref name="PWN" /&gt; The campaign of mass persecution in the newly acquired areas began immediately. In November 1939 the [[Soviet government]] [[Territories of Poland annexed by the Soviet Union|annexed the entire Polish territory under its control]]. Some 13.5 million Polish citizens who fell under the [[military occupation]] were made into new Soviet subjects following [[show election]]s conducted by the [[NKVD]] secret police in the atmosphere of terror,&lt;ref name="Stosunki"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://old.bialorus.pl/index.php?secId=49&amp;docId=57&amp;&amp;Rozdzial=historia |title=Stosunki polsko-białoruskie pod okupacją sowiecką |publisher=Bialorus.pl |work=Internet Archive |date=2010 |accessdate=26 December 2014 |author=Contributing writers |trans-title=Polish-Byelorussian relations under the Soviet occupation |url-status=unfit |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100529211839/http://old.bialorus.pl/index.php?secId=49&amp;docId=57&amp;&amp;Rozdzial=historia |archivedate=29 May 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Wegner-74"&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=aESBIpIm6UcC&amp;pg=PA74 |title=From Peace to War: Germany, Soviet Russia, and the World, 1939–1941 |publisher=Berghahn Books |year=1997 |accessdate=26 December 2014 |author=Bernd Wegner |authorlink = Bernd Wegner |page=74 |isbn=1-57181-882-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; the results of which were used to legitimize the use of force. A [[Soviet repressions of Polish citizens (1939–1946)|Soviet campaign of political murders and other forms of repression]], targeting Polish figures of authority such as military officers, police and priests, began with a wave of arrests and [[Extrajudicial executions in the Soviet Union|summary executions]].{{#tag:ref|{{cite book |quote=In September, even before the start of the Nazi atrocities that would horrify the world, the Soviets began their own program of systematic individual and mass executions. On the outskirts of Lwów, several hundred policemen were executed at one time. Near Łuniniec, officers and noncommissioned officers of the Frontier Defence Cops together with some policemen, were ordered into barns, taken out and shot ... after December 1939, three hundred Polish priests were killed. And there were many other such incidents. |url=https://archive.org/details/polandsholocaust00piot |url-access=registration |title=Poland's Holocaust |author=Tadeusz Piotrowski |publisher=McFarland |year=1998 |page=[https://archive.org/details/polandsholocaust00piot/page/12 12] |isbn=0-7864-0371-3}}|group="Note"}}&lt;ref name="Rummel 130" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Rieber 30" /&gt; The Soviet NKVD sent hundreds of thousands of people from eastern Poland to [[Siberia]] and other remote parts of the Soviet Union in four major waves of deportation between 1939 and 1941.{{#tag:ref|The exact number of people deported between 1939 and 1941 remains unknown. Estimates vary between 350,000 and more than 1.5 million; Rummel estimates the number at 1.2 million, and Kushner and Knox 1.5 million.&lt;ref name="Rummel 132" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Kushner 219" /&gt;|group="Note"}}
Soviet forces occupied eastern Poland until the summer of 1941, when they were driven out by the German army in the course of [[Operation Barbarossa]]. The area was under German occupation until the Red Army reconquered it in the summer of 1944. An agreement at the [[Yalta Conference]] permitted the Soviet Union to annex almost all of their Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact portion of the Second Polish Republic, compensating the [[Polish People's Republic]] with the greater southern part of [[East Prussia]] and territories east of the [[Oder–Neisse line]].&lt;ref name="Wettig 47" /&gt; The Soviet Union appended the annexed territories to the [[Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic]], the [[Byelorussian Soviet Socialist Republic]] and the [[Lithuanian Soviet Socialist Republic]].&lt;ref name="Wettig 47" /&gt;

After the [[end of World War II in Europe]], the Soviet Union signed a [[Polish–Soviet border agreement of August 1945|Polish–Soviet border agreement]] with the new, internationally recognized Polish [[Provisional Government of National Unity]] on 16 August 1945. This agreement recognized the status quo as the new official border between the two countries with the exception of the region around [[Białystok]] and a minor part of [[Galicia (Eastern Europe)|Galicia]] east of the [[San (river)|San River]] around [[Przemyśl]], which were later returned to Poland.&lt;ref name="Fertacz"&gt;Sylwester Fertacz, [https://web.archive.org/web/20090425133017/http://www.alfa.com.pl/slask/200506/s19.html "Krojenie mapy Polski: Bolesna granica" (Carving of Poland's map).] ''Alfa''. Retrieved from the Internet Archive on 28 October 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==
In early 1939, several months before the invasion, the Soviet Union began strategic alliance negotiations with the [[United Kingdom]] and [[France]] against the crash militarization of Nazi Germany under [[Adolf Hitler]]. In August 1939 USSR made an offer to [[United Kingdom]] and [[France]] to send "120 infantry divisions (each with some 19,000 troops), 16 cavalry divisions, 5,000 heavy artillery pieces, 9,500 tanks and up to 5,500 fighter aircraft and bombers on Germany's borders".&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/russia/3223834/Stalin-planned-to-send-a-million-troops-to-stop-Hitler-if-Britain-and-France-agreed-pact.html|title=Stalin 'planned to send a million troops to stop Hitler if Britain and France agreed pact'|last=Holdsworth|first=Nick|date=2008-10-18|access-date=2019-12-23|language=en-GB|issn=0307-1235}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since USSR had no shared border with Germany, this would effectively mean overwhelming, voluntary occupation by [[Red Army]] of the territories of Poland which was previously the site of the [[Polish–Soviet War in 1920]]. The negotiations failed.&lt;ref name="Watson 713" /&gt;

As the terms were rejected, [[Joseph Stalin]] pursued the [[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact]] with Adolf Hitler, signed on 23 August 1939. The [[non-aggression pact]] contained a secret protocol dividing Northern and Eastern Europe into German and Soviet spheres of influence in the event of war.&lt;ref name="Watson 695-722" /&gt; One week after the signing of the Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact, German forces invaded Poland from the west, north, and south on 1 September 1939. Polish forces gradually [[Plan West|withdrew to the southeast]] where they prepared for a long defence of the [[Romanian Bridgehead]] and awaited the French and British support and relief that they were expecting, but neither French or British come to their rescue. On 17 September 1939 the Soviet [[Red Army]] invaded the [[Kresy]] regions in accordance with the secret protocol.&lt;ref name="Kitchen 74" /&gt;{{#tag:ref|The Soviet Union was reluctant to intervene until the fall of [[Warsaw]] to the Germans.&lt;ref name="Davies96 440" /&gt; The actual attack was delayed for more than a week after the decision to invade Poland was already communicated to the German ambassador [[Friedrich Werner von der Schulenburg]] on 9 September. The Soviet zone of influence according to the Pact was carved out through tactical operations.&lt;ref name="Roberts 74" /&gt;|group="Note"}}

At the opening of hostilities several Polish cities including Dubno, Łuck and Włodzimierz Wołyński let the Red Army in peacefully, convinced that it was marching on in order to fight the Germans. General [[Juliusz Rómmel]] of the Polish Army issued an unauthorised order to treat them like an ally before it was too late.&lt;ref name="Wywiał-IPN"&gt;{{cite book |url=http://ipn.gov.pl/__data/assets/pdf_file/0003/70275/1-34074.pdf |title=Działania militarne w Wojnie Obronnej po 17 września |trans-title=Military operations after 17 September|publisher=[[Institute of National Remembrance]] |work=Komentarze historyczne, Nr 8–9 (129–130) |date=August 2011 |accessdate=22 December 2014 |author=Przemysław Wywiał |pages=70–78 |format=PDF file, direct download}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet government announced it was acting to protect the [[Ukrainians]] and [[Belarusians]] who lived in the eastern part of Poland, because the Polish state – according to [[Soviet propaganda]] – had collapsed in the face of the Nazi German attack and could no longer guarantee the security of its own citizens.&lt;ref name="SCHULENBURG1" /&gt;&lt;ref name="SCHULENBURG2" /&gt;&lt;ref name="SCHULENBURG3" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Degras 37-45" /&gt; Facing a second front, the Polish government concluded that the defence of the Romanian Bridgehead was no longer feasible and ordered an emergency evacuation of all uniformed troops to then-neutral Romania.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;

==Poland between world wars==
The result of the [[Paris Peace Conference, 1919|Paris Peace Conference (1919)]] did little to decrease the territorial ambitions of parties in the region. [[Józef Piłsudski]] sought to expand the Polish borders as far east as possible in an attempt to create a Polish-led federation to counter any potential imperialist intentions on the part of Russia or Germany.&lt;ref name="Roshwald 37" /&gt; At the same time, the Bolsheviks began to gain the upper hand in the [[Russian Civil War]] and started to advance westward towards the disputed territories with the intent of assisting other Communist movements in Western Europe.&lt;ref name="Davies72 29" /&gt; The border skirmishes of 1919 progressively escalated into the [[Polish–Soviet War]] in 1920.&lt;ref name="Davies 22, 504" /&gt; Following the Polish victory at the [[Battle of Warsaw (1920)|Battle of Warsaw]], the Soviets [[Suing for peace|sued for peace]] and the war ended with an armistice in October 1920.&lt;ref name="Kutrzeba 524, 528" /&gt; The parties signed the formal peace treaty, the [[Peace of Riga]], on 18 March 1921, dividing the disputed territories between Poland and Soviet Russia.&lt;ref name="Davies 376" /&gt; In an action that largely determined the Soviet-Polish border during the [[interwar period]], the Soviets offered the Polish peace delegation territorial concessions in the contested borderland areas, closely resembling the border between the [[Russian Empire]] and the [[Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth]] before the first [[partitions of Poland|partition]] of 1772.&lt;ref name="Davies 504" /&gt; In the aftermath of the peace agreement, Soviet leaders largely abandoned the cause of international revolution and did not return to the concept for approximately 20 years.&lt;ref name="Davies72 xi" /&gt;  The [[Conference of Ambassadors]] and the international community (with the exception of Lithuania) recognized Poland's eastern frontiers in 1923.&lt;ref name="Lukowski" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Gross 3" /&gt;

===Treaty negotiations===
{{Further|Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact|German–Soviet Commercial Agreement (1939)|Polish–British Common Defence Pact}}
[[File:Ribbentrop-Molotov.svg|thumb|right|Planned and actual divisions of Poland, according to the Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact|alt=Map showing the planned and actual divisions of Poland according to the Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact.]]

Germany marched into Prague on 15 March 1939. In mid-April, the Soviet Union, Britain and France began trading diplomatic suggestions regarding a political and military agreement to counter potential further German aggression.&lt;ref name="Watson 698" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Gronowicz 51" /&gt; Poland did not participate in these talks.&lt;ref name="Neilson 275" /&gt; The tripartite discussions focused on possible guarantees to participating countries should German expansionism continue.&lt;ref name="Carley 303-341" /&gt; The Soviets did not trust the British or the French to honour a collective security agreement, because they had already failed to react against the [[Nationalist faction (Spanish Civil War)|Nationalists]] during the [[Spanish Civil War]] and protect Czechoslovakia from dismemberment. The Soviet Union also suspected that Britain and France would seek to remain on the sidelines of any potential Nazi-Soviet conflict.&lt;ref name="Kenéz 129-131" /&gt; In reality however, Stalin had been conducting secret talks with Nazi Germany already since 1936 through his emissaries, and all along a deal with Hitler remained his first diplomatic choice, wrote Robert C. Grogin (author of ''Natural Enemies'').&lt;ref name="Grogin28"&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=qBBcqDludakC&amp;q=Ribbentrop#v=snippet&amp;q=1936%2BRibbentrop&amp;f=false |title=Natural Enemies: The United States and the Soviet Union in the Cold War, 1917–1991 |author=Robert C. Grogin |publisher=Lexington Books |year=2001 |ISBN=0-7391-0160-9 |page=28}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Union sought nothing short of an ironclad guarantee against losing its [[sphere of influence]],&lt;ref name="Watson 695" /&gt; and insisted on stretching the so-called buffer zone from Finland to Romania, in the event of an attack.&lt;ref name="Shaw 119" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Neilson 298" /&gt; The Soviets demanded the right to enter these countries in the event of a security threat.&lt;ref name="Watson 708" /&gt; When the military talks began in mid-August, negotiations quickly stalled over the topic of Soviet troop passage through Poland if the Germans attacked. British and French officials pressured Polish government to agree to the Soviet terms.&lt;ref name="Watson 713" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Shirer 536" /&gt; However, Polish officials bluntly refused to allow Soviet troops in Poland. They believed that once the Red Army entered Poland it might never leave.&lt;ref name="Shirer 537" /&gt; The Soviets suggested that Poland's wishes be ignored, and that the tripartite agreements be concluded despite its objections.&lt;ref name="Neilson 315" /&gt; The British refused to do so because they believed that such a move would push Poland into establishing stronger bilateral relations with Germany.&lt;ref name="Neilson 311" /&gt;

Meanwhile, German officials secretly hinted to Soviet diplomats for months that it could offer better terms for a political agreement than Britain and France.&lt;ref name="Roberts 66-73" /&gt; The Soviet Union began discussions with Nazi Germany regarding the establishment of an economic agreement while concurrently negotiating with those of the tripartite group.&lt;ref name="Roberts 66-73" /&gt; In late July and early August 1939, Soviet and German officials agreed on most of the details for a planned economic agreement, and specifically addressed a potential political agreement.&lt;ref name="Shirer 503" /&gt; On 19 August 1939, German and Soviet officials concluded the [[German–Soviet Commercial Agreement (1939)|1939 German–Soviet Commercial Agreement]], an economic mutual understanding that exchanged Soviet Union raw materials with Germany in exchange for weapons, military technology and civilian machinery. Two days later, the Soviets suspended the [[tripartite military talks]].&lt;ref name="Roberts 66-73" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Shirer 525" /&gt; On 24 August, the Soviet Union and Germany signed the political and military deal that accompanied the trade agreement, the [[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact]]. This pact was an agreement of mutual non-aggression that contained secret protocols dividing the states of [[Northern Europe|northern]] and eastern Europe into German and Soviet spheres of influence. The Soviet sphere initially included [[Latvia]], [[Estonia]] and [[Finland]].{{#tag:ref|On 28 September, the borders were redefined by adding the area between the Vistula and Bug rivers to the German sphere and moving Lithuania into the Soviet sphere.&lt;ref name="Sanford 21" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Weinberg 963" /&gt;|group="Note"}} Germany and the Soviet Union would partition Poland; the areas east of the [[Pisa (river)|Pisa]], [[Narev]], [[Vistula]], and [[San (river)|San]] rivers going to the Soviet Union. The pact provided the Soviets with the chance of taking part in the invasion,&lt;ref name="Davies96 440" /&gt; and offered an opportunity to regain territories ceded in the [[Peace of Riga]] of 1921. The Soviets would enlarge the Ukrainian and Belarusian republics to include the entire eastern half of Poland without the threat of disagreement with Adolf Hitler.&lt;ref name="Dunnigan 132" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Snyder 77" /&gt;

The day after the Germans and Soviets signed the pact, the French and British military delegations urgently requested a meeting with Soviet military negotiator [[Kliment Voroshilov]].&lt;ref name="Shirer 541" /&gt; On 25 August, Voroshilov told them "{{grey|[}}i{{grey|]}}n view of the changed political situation, no useful purpose can be served in continuing the conversation."&lt;ref name="Shirer 541" /&gt; The same day, Britain and Poland signed the [[Anglo-Polish military alliance|British-Polish Pact of Mutual Assistance]].&lt;ref name="Osmańczyk-Mango 231"&gt;[[#Reference-Osmańczyk-Mango|Osmańczyk-Mango]] p. 231&lt;/ref&gt; In this accord, Britain committed itself to the defence of Poland, guaranteeing to preserve Polish independence.&lt;ref name="Osmańczyk-Mango 231" /&gt;

==German invasion of Poland and Soviet preparations==
Hitler tried to dissuade the British and the French from interfering in the upcoming conflict and on 26 August 1939 proposed to make ''[[Wehrmacht]]'' forces available to Britain in the future.&lt;ref name="pledge" /&gt; At midnight on 29 August, German Foreign Minister [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]] handed British Ambassador [[Nevile Henderson]] the list of terms that would allegedly ensure peace in regards to Poland.&lt;ref name="Davies 371-373" /&gt; Under the terms, Poland was to hand over Danzig ([[Gdańsk]]) to Germany, and there was to be a plebiscite ([[referendum]]) in the [[Polish Corridor]] within the year based on residency from 1919 (not after).&lt;ref name="Davies 371-373" /&gt; When the Polish Ambassador [[Józef Lipski|Lipski]] went to see Ribbentrop on 30 August and said that he did not have the power to sign anything of the sort, Ribbentrop dismissed him.&lt;ref name="Mowat 648" /&gt; The Germans announced that Poland had rejected the German offer and negotiations with Poland were finished.&lt;ref name="Henderson 16-18" /&gt; On 31 August, German units posing as Polish troops staged the [[Gleiwitz incident]] near the border city of [[Gliwice|Gleiwitz]].&lt;ref name="Manvell-Fraenkel 76" /&gt; The following morning Hitler ordered hostilities against Poland to start at 04:45 on 1 September.&lt;ref name="Mowat 648" /&gt; The Germany Luftwaffe bombarded cities [[Lwow]] and [[Łuck]].&lt;ref name=strapol&gt;[http://www.hrono.ru/sobyt/1900war/1921zy.php Struggle against Polish occupation of Western Ukraine]. Hrono.ru&lt;/ref&gt; Polish security service carried out arrests among Ukrainian [[intelligentsia]] in Lwow and [[Przemysl]].&lt;ref name=strapol/&gt;
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-S55480, Polen, Parade vor Adolf Hitler.jpg|left|thumb|[[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]] watching German soldiers marching into Poland in September 1939.]]
On 1 September 1939 at 11:00 [[Moscow time]], a counselor of the [[German embassy in Moscow]] [[Gustav Hilger]] arrived to the [[People's Commissariat of Foreign Affairs]] and informed about beginning of the German–Polish War, annexation of [[Free City of Danzig|Danzig]] ([[Gdansk]]) to Germany, and conveyed a request of [[Oberkommando der Luftwaffe#Chiefs of the OKL General Staff|chief of the OKL General Staff]] that the radio station in [[Minsk]] provided some signal support.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39&gt;[http://hrono.ru/sobyt/1900war/1939pol.php The 1939 Polish–Soviet War]. Hrono.ru.&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet side partially satisfied the request.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; Same day on 1 September 1939 an extraordinary session of the [[Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union]] adopted its "Universal Military Duty Act for males aged 17 years and 8 months old", according to which for a year was extended military service of 1937 draft.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; Also, the [[Politburo of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|Politburo]] of the [[Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|CC VKP(b)]] approved the proposal of the [[People's Commissariat of Defense of the Soviet Union|People's Commissariat of Defense]], according to which in the [[Workers’-Peasants’ Red Army|Red Army]] beside 51 ordinary Rifle Divisions it was envisage to have 76 ordinary Rifle Divisions of 6,000, 13 Mountainous Rifle Divisions, and 33 ordinary Rifle Divisions of 3,000.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt;

On 2 September 1939 the [[Army Group North]] carried out a double envelopment of Polish forces ([[Pomorze Army]]) that defended the "[[Polish Corridor]]".&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; The commander of those Polish forces General [[Władysław Bortnowski]] lost communication with own divisions.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; The armored break through of [[Army Group South]] near city of [[Częstochowa]] added to defeat of the Polish [[6th Infantry Division (Poland)|6th Infantry Division]] south of [[Katowice]] where the German 5th Armored Division broke through to [[Oświęcim]] capturing fuel and equipment warehouses.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; To the east German detachments of 18th Army Corps of the [[14th Army (Wehrmacht)|14th Army]] crossed the Polish–Slovak border near [[Dukla Pass]].&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; The [[government of the Soviet Union]] issued its decision № 1355-279сс about approval of "Reorganization plan of the Red Army ground forces on 1939–1940".&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; It was decided to transfer divisions of tertiary deployment to ordinary and to have 173 Rifle Divisions in Red Army.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; It was proposed to increase striking force of infantry nucleus in rifle division, increase number of corps-level artillery and [[reserve of the Supreme High Command]] artillery by transferring it from tertiary to secondary level of deployment.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; By evening of 2 September at the Polish–Soviet border was implemented enhanced security mode.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; Per instruction № 1720 of chief of Border troops of the [[Belorussian Military District]], all border detachments were placed in combat march ready.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt;

The Allied governments declared war on Germany on 3 September but failed to provide any meaningful support.&lt;ref name="Mowat 648-650" /&gt; Despite some Polish successes in minor border battles, German technical, operational and numerical superiority forced the Polish armies to retreat from the borders towards Warsaw and [[Lwów]]. The same day 3 September, new Soviet Ambassador in [[Berlin]] [[:ru:Шкварцев, Алексей Алексеевич|Aleksei Shkvartsev]] handed to [[Reich Chancellor]] [[Adolf Hitler]] letter of credence.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; At the ceremony Shkvartsev and Hitler assured each other on behalf of their countries to fulfill their obligations under the non-aggression agreement.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; The German Embassy in Moscow received a task from [[Minister for Foreign Affairs (Germany)|Minister for Foreign Affairs]] [[Joachim von Ribbentrop]] to probe the intentions of USSR in regards possible entry of the Red Army into Poland.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt;

On 4 September 1939 all German ships in northern Atlantic received an order "to follow to [[Murmansk]], adhering to the most northern course".&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; The same day, [[Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|CC VKP(b)]] and [[government of the Soviet Union]] approved orders of People's Commissar of Defense [[Kliment Voroshilov]] about delay on dismissal of Red Army personnel and young commanders for one month among troops in Leningrad, Moscow, Kalinin, Kharkov, Belorussian and Kiev Special military districts and call for training assembly of Air Defense detachments assigned staff in Leningrad, Kalinin, Belorussian and Kiev Special military districts.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt;

On 5 September 1939 People's Commissar of Foreign Affairs Molotov received German Ambassador von der Schulenburg.&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt; On the question of ambassador in regards to possible entry of Red Army into Poland, Molotov answered that the Soviet government at the right time "will definitely have to... start the specific actions. But we believe that this moment has not yet ripen", and "a haste may ruin things and facilitate the rallying of opponents".&lt;ref name=sov_pol39/&gt;

On 10 September, the Polish commander-in-chief, Marshal [[Edward Rydz-Śmigły]], ordered a [[Withdrawal (military)|general retreat]] to the southeast towards the [[Romanian Bridgehead]].&lt;ref name="Stanley 29" /&gt; Soon after they began their invasion of Poland, the Nazi leaders began urging the Soviets to play their agreed part and attack Poland from the east. Soviet Foreign Minister [[Vyacheslav Molotov]] and German ambassador to Moscow [[Friedrich Werner von der Schulenburg]] exchanged a series of diplomatic messages on the matter but the Soviets nevertheless delayed their invasion of eastern Poland. The Soviets were distracted by crucial events relating to their ongoing [[Soviet-Japanese Border Wars|border disputes]] with Japan. They needed time to mobilize the Red Army and they saw a diplomatic advantage in waiting until Poland had disintegrated before making their move.&lt;ref name="Zaloga 80" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Weinberg 55" /&gt;

On 14 September, with Poland's collapse near, the Soviet press began making ominous statements about Poland.&lt;ref name="gunther1940"&gt;{{cite book |url=https://archive.org/stream/in.ernet.dli.2015.149663/2015.149663.Inside-Europe#page/n15/mode/2up |title=Inside Europe |publisher=Harper &amp; Brothers |author=Gunther, John |location=New York|authorlink=John Gunther|year=1940 |page=xviii}}&lt;/ref&gt; The undeclared war between the [[Soviet Union]] and the [[Empire of Japan]] at the [[Battles of Khalkhin Gol]] (Nomonhan) in the [[Far East]] ended with the [[Vyacheslav Molotov|Molotov]]–[[Hideki Tojo|Tojo]] agreement between the USSR and Japan which was signed on 15 September, with a ceasefire taking effect on 16 September.&lt;ref&gt;Goldman p. 163, 164&lt;/ref&gt;{{r|gunther1940}} On 17 September, Molotov delivered a declaration of war to [[Wacław Grzybowski]], the Polish Ambassador in Moscow:

{{quote|Warsaw, as the capital of Poland, no longer exists. The Polish Government has disintegrated, and no longer shows any sign of life. This means that the Polish State and its Government have, in point of fact, ceased to exist. In the same way, the Agreements concluded between the U.S.S.R. and Poland have ceased to operate. Left to her own devices and bereft of leadership, Poland has become a suitable field for all manner of hazards and surprises, which may constitute a threat to the U.S.S.R. For these reasons the Soviet Government, who has hitherto been neutral, cannot any longer preserve a neutral attitude towards these facts. ... In these circumstances, the Soviet Government have directed the High Command of the Red Army to order troops to cross the frontier and to take under their protection the life and property of the population of Western Ukraine and Western Belarus. &lt;small&gt;— People's Commissar for Foreign Affairs of the U.S.S.R. V. Molotov, September 17, 1939 &lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name="EM-WW2"&gt;Electronic Museum, [https://web.archive.org/web/20120306005914/http://www.electronicmuseum.ca/Poland-WW2/nazi_soviet_friendship/nsf_molotov_note_1-2_eng.html Text of the Soviet communique in English translation.] September 17, 1939, by Vyacheslav M. Molotov; also [[s:ru:Нота правительства СССР, врученная польскому послу в Москве утром 17 сентября 1939 года]] {{in lang|ru}}, [[s:pl:Nota rządu ZSRR z 17.09.1939]] {{in lang|pl}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

Molotov declared on the radio that all treaties between the Soviet Union and Poland were now void, and claimed the Polish government had abandoned its people and effectively ceased to exist.&lt;ref name="Degras 37-45" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Piotrowski 295" /&gt; On the same day, the Red Army crossed the border into Poland.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Zaloga 80" /&gt;

==Soviet invasion of Poland==
In the morning of 17 September 1939, Polish administration was still active on the whole territory of six eastern [[voivodeship]]s, plus on parts of territories of additional five voivodeships; in eastern Poland, schools were opened in mid-September 1939.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rp.pl/artykul/355422.html Zachód okazał się parszywieńki. Interview with Leszek Moczulski, 28-08-2009]&lt;/ref&gt; Polish Army units concentrated their activities in two areas – southern ([[Tomaszów Lubelski]], [[Zamość]], [[Lwów]]), and central ([[Warsaw]], [[Modlin (Nowy Dwór Mazowiecki)|Modlin]], and the [[Bzura]] river). Due to stubborn Polish defense and lack of fuel, the German advance stalled, and the situation stabilized for the areas east of the line [[Augustów]] – [[Grodno]] – [[Białystok]] – [[Kobryń]] – [[Kowel]] – [[Żółkiew]] – Lwów – [[Żydaczów]] – [[Stryi|Stryj]] – [[Turka, Ukraine|Turka]].&lt;ref name="Czesław Grzelak page 242"&gt;Czesław Grzelak, Henryk Stańczyk. ''Kampania polska 1939 roku'', page 242. RYTM Warszawa 2005. {{ISBN|83-7399-169-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; Rail connections were operating in approximately one-third of the territory of the country, and both passenger and cargo traffic was moving on the borders with five neighboring countries (Lithuania, Latvia, Soviet Union, Romania, and Hungary). In [[Pińsk]], assembly of [[PZL.37 Łoś]] planes was going on, in a PZL factory that had been moved from Warsaw.&lt;ref name="Leszek Moczulski 1939, page 879"&gt;Leszek Moczulski, ''Wojna Polska 1939'', page 879. Bellona Warszawa 2009. {{ISBN|978-83-11-11584-2}}&lt;/ref&gt; A [[French Navy]] ship carrying [[Renault R35]] tanks for Poland approached the Romanian port of [[Constanta]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.2wojna.pl/encyklopedia-fr-wb-001.html Encyklopedia Broni (Encyclopedia of Weapons), Renault R-35, R-40, czołg lekki II wojna światowa 1939–1945, → wozy bojowe, Francja]&lt;/ref&gt; Another ship, with artillery equipment, had just left [[Marseilles]]. Altogether, seventeen French ships with materiel were heading towards Romania, carrying fifty tanks, twenty airplanes, and large quantities of ammunition and explosives.&lt;ref name="Czesław Grzelak page 242" /&gt; Several major cities were still in Polish hands, such as Warsaw, Lwów, Wilno, Grodno, Łuck, Tarnopol, and Lublin (captured by the Germans on 18 September). According to [[Leszek Moczulski]], approximately 750,000 soldiers were still in the ranks of Polish Army (Polish historians Czesław Grzelak and Henryk Stańczyk claim that the Polish Army still had 650,000 soldiers).&lt;ref name="Czesław Grzelak page 242" /&gt;)

[[File:Soviet invasion on Poland 1939.jpg|thumb|Soviet invasion of Poland, 1939. Advance of the Red Army troops]]
The Polish Army, although weakened by weeks of fighting, still was a formidable force. As Moczulski wrote, on 17 September 1939, the Polish Army was still bigger than most European armies and strong enough to fight the Wehrmacht for a long time.&lt;ref name="Leszek Moczulski 1939, page 879" /&gt; On the [[Baranowicze]] – [[Łuniniec]] – [[Rivne|Równe]] line, rail transport of troops from the northeastern corner of the country towards the [[Romanian Bridgehead]] was going on day and night (among them were the [[35th Infantry Division (Poland)|35th Reserve Infantry Division]] under Colonel Jarosław Szafran,&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lwow.home.pl/rocznik/obrona39.html Artur Leinwand, OBRONA LWOWA WE WRZEŚNIU 1939 ROKU]&lt;/ref&gt; and the so-called "[[Grodno]] Group" ("Grupa grodzieńska") of Colonel Bohdan Hulewicz), and the second largest battle of the September Campaign – [[Battle of Tomaszów Lubelski]], started on the day of the Soviet invasion. According to Leszek Moczulski, around 250,000 Polish soldiers were fighting in central Poland, 350,000 were getting ready to defend the Romanian Bridgehead, 35,000 were north of [[Polesie]], and 10,000 were fighting on the Baltic coast of Poland, in [[Hel, Poland|Hel]] and [[Gdynia]]. Due to the ongoing battles in the area of Warsaw, [[Modlin Fortress|Modlin]], the [[Bzura]], [[Zamość]], Lwów and Tomaszów Lubelski, most German divisions were ordered to move back towards these locations. The area remaining in control of the Polish authorities was some 140,000 square kilometers – approximately 200 kilometers wide and 950 kilometers long – from the [[Daugava River|Daugava]] to the Carpathian Mountains.&lt;ref name="Czesław Grzelak page 242" /&gt; [[Polish Radio Baranowicze]] and [[Polish Radio Wilno]] stopped broadcasting on 16 September, after having been bombed by the [[Luftwaffe]], but [[Polish Radio Lwów]] and [[Polish Radio Warsaw II]] were still on air as of 17 September.&lt;ref&gt;[Janusz Osica, Andrzej Sowa, and Paweł Wieczorkiewicz. ''1939. Ostatni rok pokoju, pierwszy rok wojny''. Wydawnictwo Zysk i S-ka, Poznań 2009, page 569]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Opposing forces===
{{See also|Polish army order of battle in 1939|Soviet order of battle for invasion of Poland in 1939|Opposing forces in the Polish September Campaign}}
The Red Army entered the eastern regions of Poland with seven [[field army|field armies]], containing between 450,000 and 1,000,000 troops, split between two fronts.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt; [[Comandarm]] 2nd rank [[Mikhail Kovalyov]] led the Red Army in the invasion on the Belarusian Front, while Comandarm 1st rank [[Semyon Timoshenko]] commanded the invasion on the [[Ukrainian Front (1939)|Ukrainian Front]].&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;

Under the Polish [[Plan West]] defensive plan, Poland assumed the Soviet Union would remain neutral during a conflict with Germany. As a result, Polish commanders deployed most of their troops to the west, to face the German invasion. By this time, no more than 20 under-strength battalions, consisting of about 20,000 troopers of the [[Border Protection Corps (Poland)|Border Protection Corps]], defended the eastern border.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Wojsko90" /&gt; When the Red Army invaded Poland on 17 September, the Polish military was in the midst of a fighting retreat towards the Romanian Bridgehead whereupon they would regroup and await British and French relief.

===Military campaign===
[[File:Poland1939 after 14 Sep.jpg|thumb|right|Disposition of all troops following the Soviet invasion|alt=A map showing the disposition of all troops following the Soviet invasion]]

When the Soviet Union invaded, Rydz-Śmigły was initially inclined to order the eastern border forces to resist, but was dissuaded by [[Prime Minister of Poland|Prime Minister]] [[Felicjan Sławoj Składkowski]] and [[President of Poland|President]] [[Ignacy Mościcki]].&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Wojsko90" /&gt; At 04:00 on 17 September, Rydz-Śmigły ordered the Polish troops to fall back, stipulating that they only engage Soviet troops in self-defense.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt; However, the German invasion had severely damaged the Polish communication systems, causing [[command and control]] problems for the Polish forces.&lt;ref name="Gross 17" /&gt; In the resulting confusion, clashes between Polish and Soviet forces occurred along the border.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Wojsko90" /&gt; General [[Wilhelm Orlik-Rückemann]], who took command of the Border Protection Corps on 30 August, received no official directives after his appointment.&lt;ref name="Gross 17-18" /&gt; As a result, he and his subordinates continued to engage Soviet forces proactively, before dissolving the group on 1 October.&lt;ref name="Gross 17-18" /&gt;

The Polish government refused to surrender or negotiate a peace and instead ordered all units to evacuate Poland and reorganize in France.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt; The day after the Soviet invasion started, the Polish government crossed into Romania. Polish units proceeded to manoeuvre towards the Romanian bridgehead area, sustaining German attacks on one flank and occasionally clashing with Soviet troops on the other. In the days following the evacuation order, the Germans defeated the Polish [[Kraków Army]] and [[Lublin Army]] at the [[Battle of Tomaszów Lubelski]].&lt;ref name="Taylor 38" /&gt;
[[File:Spotkanie Sojuszników.jpg|thumb|left|German and Soviet officers shaking hands following the invasion|alt=A photo of a German and a Soviet officer shaking hands at the end of the invasion of Poland.]]

Soviet units often met their German counterparts advancing from the opposite direction. Notable examples of co-operation occurred between the two armies in the field. The ''Wehrmacht'' passed the [[Brest Fortress]] to the Soviet 29th Tank Brigade, which had been seized after the [[Battle of Brześć Litewski]] on 17 September.&lt;ref name="Fischer" /&gt; German General [[Heinz Guderian]] and Soviet Brigadier [[Semyon Krivoshein]] on 22 September held a joint [[parade]] in the town.&lt;ref name="Fischer" /&gt; [[Lwów]] (now [[Lviv]]) surrendered on 22 September, days after the Germans had handed the siege operations over to the Soviets.&lt;ref name="Leinwald" /&gt; Soviet forces had taken [[Vilnius|Wilno]] (now Vilnius) on 19 September after [[Battle of Wilno (1939)|a two-day battle]], and they took [[Grodno]] on 24 September after [[Battle of Grodno (1939)|a four-day battle]]. By 28 September, the Red Army had reached the line formed by the Narew, Western Bug, Vistula and San rivers—the border agreed in advance with the Germans.

Despite a tactical Polish victory on 28 September at the [[Battle of Szack]], the outcome of the larger conflict was never in doubt.&lt;ref name="Interia-Szack" /&gt; Civilian volunteers, [[militia]]s and reorganised retreating units held out against German forces [[Siege of Warsaw (1939)|in the Polish capital]], [[Warsaw]], until 28 September, and the [[Modlin Fortress]], north of Warsaw, surrendered the next day after [[battle of Modlin|an intense sixteen-day battle]]. On 1 October, Soviet troops drove Polish units into the forests in the [[battle of Wytyczno]], one of the last direct confrontations of the campaign.&lt;ref name="Orlik-Rückemann 20" /&gt; Several isolated Polish garrisons managed to hold their positions long after being surrounded, such as those in the [[Volhynia]]n [[Sarny Fortified Area]] which held out until 25 September. The last operational unit of the Polish Army to surrender was General [[Franciszek Kleeberg]]'s [[Independent Operational Group Polesie]]. Kleeberg surrendered on 6 October after the four-day [[Battle of Kock (1939)|Battle of Kock]], effectively ending the September Campaign. On 31 October, [[Vyacheslav Molotov|Molotov]] reported to the [[Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union|Supreme Soviet]]: "A short blow by the German army, and subsequently by the Red Army, was enough for nothing to be left of this bastard ({{lang-ru|ублюдок}}) of the [[Treaty of Versailles]]".&lt;ref name="Moynihan 93" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Tucker 612" /&gt;

===Domestic reaction===
[[File:Tak bulo - tak ye.jpg|thumb|Posters from the Soviet Union showing the bad fate of Ukrainian peasants under Polish yoke and the liberation by the Red Army.]]
[[File:Stamp USSR 1940 historia1.gif|thumb|"Liberation of brotherly people of Western Ukraine and Western Belorussia on 17 September 1939" Post stamps of USSR, 1940.]]

The response of non-ethnic Poles to the situation added a further complication. Many [[Ukraine|Ukrainians]], [[Belarus]]ians and [[Jew]]s welcomed the invading troops.&lt;ref name="Gross 32-33" /&gt; Local Communists gathered people to welcome [[Red Army]] troops in the traditional Slavic way by presenting bread and salt in the eastern suburb of [[Brest, Belarus|Brest]]. For this occasion a sort of [[triumphal arch]] was made of two poles, decked with spruce branches and flowers. A banner, a long strip of red cloth with a slogan in Russian, glorifying the [[USSR]] and welcoming the Red Army, crowned the arch.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.vb.by/article.php?topic=36&amp;article=14200 |script-title=ru:Радость была всеобщая и триумфальная
|author=Юрий Рубашевский. |work=[[Vecherniy Brest]] |date=16 September 2011 |language=ru}}&lt;/ref&gt; The local reaction was mentioned by [[Lev Mekhlis]], who told Stalin that the people of West Ukraine welcomed the Soviets "like true liberators".&lt;ref name="Montefiore 312" /&gt; The [[Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists]] rebelled against the Poles, and communist partisans organized local uprisings, such as that in [[Skidel]].&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;

===International reaction===
{{See also|Western betrayal}}
The reaction of France and Britain to the Soviet invasion and annexation of Eastern Poland was muted, since neither country expected or wanted a confrontation with the Soviet Union at that time.&lt;ref name="Prazmowska 44-45" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Hiden-Lane 148" /&gt; Under the terms of the [[Polish-British Common Defence Pact]] of 25 August 1939, the British had promised assistance if a European power attacked Poland.{{#tag:ref|The "Agreement of Mutual Assistance between the United Kingdom and Poland" (London, 25 August 1939) states in Article 1: "Should one of the Contracting Parties become engaged in hostilities with a European Power in consequence of aggression by the latter against that Contracting Party, the other Contracting Party will at once give the Contracting Party engaged in hostilities all the support and assistance in its power."&lt;ref name="Stachura 125" /&gt;|group="Note"}} A secret protocol of the pact, however, specified that the European power referred to Germany.&lt;ref name="Hiden-Lane 143-144" /&gt; When Polish Ambassador [[Edward Bernard Raczyński|Edward Raczyński]] reminded [[Secretary of State for Foreign and Commonwealth Affairs|Foreign Secretary]] [[Lord Halifax]] of the pact, he was bluntly told that it was Britain's business whether to declare war on the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name="Prazmowska 44-45" /&gt; [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|British Prime Minister]] [[Neville Chamberlain]] considered making a public commitment to restore the Polish state but in the end issued only general condemnations.&lt;ref name="Prazmowska 44-45" /&gt; This stance represented Britain's attempt at balance: its security interests included trade with the Soviets that would support its war effort and the possibility of a future Anglo-Soviet alliance against Germany.&lt;ref name="Hiden-Lane 143-144" /&gt; Public opinion in Britain was divided between expressions of outrage at the invasion and a perception that Soviet claims to the region were reasonable.&lt;ref name="Hiden-Lane 143-144" /&gt;

While the French had made promises to Poland, including the provision of air support, these were not honoured. A [[Franco-Polish Military Alliance]] was signed in 1921 and amended thereafter. The agreements were not strongly supported by the French military leadership, though; the relationship deteriorated during the 1920s and 1930s.&lt;ref name="Hehn 69-70" /&gt; In the French view, the German-Soviet alliance was fragile and overt denunciation of, or action against, the Soviets would not serve either France's or Poland's best interests.&lt;ref name ="Hiden-Lane 148" /&gt; Once the Soviets moved into Poland, the French and the British decided there was nothing they could do for Poland in the short term and began planning for a long-term victory instead. The French had [[Saar Offensive|advanced tentatively into the Saar region in early September]], but after the Polish defeat they retreated behind the [[Maginot Line]] on 4 October.&lt;ref name="Jackson 75" /&gt;
On 1 October 1939, [[Winston Churchill]]—via the radio—stated:
{{quote|... That the Russian armies should stand on this line was clearly necessary for the safety of Russia against the Nazi menace. At any rate, the line is there, and an Eastern Front has been created which Nazi Germany does not dare assail. When Herr von Ribbentrop was summoned to Moscow last week it was to learn the fact, and to accept the fact, that the Nazi designs upon the Baltic States and upon the Ukraine must come to a dead stop.&lt;ref&gt;Winston S. Churchill, ''Blood, Sweat and Tears''. "The First Month of War." [https://books.google.com/books?id=c9uvdT3GRLoC&amp;pg=PA173 P. 173.]&lt;/ref&gt;}}

==Aftermath==
{{Main|Occupation of Poland (1939–1945)}}
{{further|History of Poland (1939–1945)|Polish prisoners of war in Soviet Union (after 1939)}}
[[File:Jeńcy1.jpg|thumb|right|Polish prisoners of war captured by the Red Army during the Soviet invasion of Poland in 1939|alt=A photo of a crowd of marching Polish prisoners of war captured by the Red Army during the Soviet invasion of Poland]]

In October 1939, Molotov reported to the Supreme Soviet that the Soviets had suffered 737 deaths and 1,862 casualties during the campaign, although Polish specialists claim up to 3,000 deaths and 8,000–10,000 wounded.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt; On the Polish side, 3,000–7,000 soldiers died fighting the Red Army, with 230,000–450,000 taken prisoner.&lt;ref name="Wojsko92" /&gt; The Soviets often failed to honour the terms of surrender. In some cases, they promised Polish soldiers their freedom and then arrested them when they laid down their arms.&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;

The Soviet Union had ceased to recognise the Polish state at the start of the invasion. Neither side issued a formal declaration of war; this decision had significant consequences, and Rydz-Smigly would be criticised for it.&lt;ref name="Sanford 22-23, 39" /&gt; The Soviets killed tens of thousands of [[Polish prisoners of war in Soviet Union (after 1939)|Polish prisoners of war]], some during the campaign itself.&lt;ref name="Sanford 23" /&gt; On 24 September, the Soviets killed 42 staff and patients of a Polish military hospital in the village of [[Grabowiec, Zamość County|Grabowiec]], near [[Zamość]].&lt;ref name="Grabowiec" /&gt; The Soviets also executed all the Polish officers they captured after the [[Battle of Szack]], on 28 September 1939.&lt;ref name="Interia-Szack" /&gt; The [[NKVD]] killed 22,000 Polish military personnel and civilians in the [[Katyn massacre]].&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Fischer" /&gt; [[Torture]] was used by the NKVD on a wide scale in various prisons, especially those in small towns.&lt;ref name="Gross 182" /&gt;

[[File:Katyn - decision of massacre p1.jpg|thumb|upright|left|The Soviet document of decision regarding the mass execution of Polish officers ([[Katyn massacre]])|alt=The front page of the Soviet document of decision, with blue writing scrawled across the left-center of the page, authorizing the mass execution of all Polish officers who were prisoners of war in the Soviet Union]]

The Poles and the Soviets re-established diplomatic relations in 1941, following the [[Sikorski–Mayski Agreement]]; but the Soviets broke them off again in 1943 after the Polish government demanded an independent examination of the recently discovered Katyn burial pits ([[Katyn massacre]]).&lt;ref name="Soviet note of 1943" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Sanford 129" /&gt;

On 28 September 1939, the Soviet Union and Germany signed the [[German–Soviet Treaty of Friendship, Cooperation and Demarcation]], changing the secret terms of the [[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact]]. They moved [[Lithuania]] into the Soviet [[sphere of influence]] and shifted the border in Poland to the east, giving Germany more territory.&lt;ref name="PWN_KW_old" /&gt; By this arrangement, often described as a fourth [[partition of Poland]],&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24" /&gt; the Soviet Union secured almost all Polish territory east of the line of the rivers Pisa, Narew, Western Bug and San. This amounted to about 200,000&amp;nbsp;km² of land, inhabited by 13.5 million Polish citizens.&lt;ref name="Gross 17" /&gt; The border created in this agreement roughly corresponded to the [[Curzon Line]] drawn by the British in 1919, a point that would successfully be used by Stalin during negotiations with the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] at the [[Teheran Conference|Teheran]] and [[Yalta Conference]]s.&lt;ref name="Dallas 557" /&gt; The Red Army had originally sown confusion among the locals by claiming that they were arriving to save Poland from the Nazis.&lt;ref name ="Davies96 1001-1003"&gt;[[#Reference-Davies96|Davies (1996)]] pp. 1001–1003&lt;/ref&gt; Their advance surprised Polish communities and their leaders, who had not been advised how to respond to a Soviet invasion. Polish and Jewish citizens may at first have preferred a Soviet regime to a German one.&lt;ref name="Gross 24, 32-33" /&gt; However, the Soviets were quick to impose their ideology on the local ways of life. For instance, the Soviets quickly began confiscating, [[nationalized|nationalising]] and redistributing all private and state-owned Polish property.&lt;ref name="Piotrowski 11" /&gt; During the two years following the annexation, the Soviets also arrested approximately 100,000 Polish citizens.&lt;ref name="Karta" /&gt; Due to a lack of access to secret Soviet archives, for many years after the war the estimates of the number of Polish citizens deported to Siberia from the areas of Eastern Poland, as well as the number who perished under Soviet rule, were largely guesswork.  A wide range of numbers was given in various works, between 350,000 and 1,500,000 for the number deported to Siberia and between 250,000 and 1,000,000 for the number who died, these numbers mostly included civilians.&lt;ref name="Rieber 14, 32-37" /&gt; With the opening of the Soviet secret archives after 1989, the lower range of these estimates has emerged as closer to the truth. In August 2009, on the occasion of the 70th anniversary of the Soviet invasion, the [[Polish Institute of National Remembrance]] announced that its researchers reduced the estimate of the number of people deported to Siberia from one million to 320,000, and estimated that 150,000 Polish citizens perished under Soviet rule during the war.&lt;ref name="Polish experts lower nation's WWII death toll" /&gt;

===Belorussia and Ukraine===
{{further|Territories of Poland annexed by the Soviet Union}}

Of the 13.5 million civilians living in [[Polish areas annexed by the Soviet Union|the newly annexed territories]], according to the last official Polish census the population was over 38% Poles (5.1 million), 37% Ukrainians (4.7 million), 14.5% Belarusians, 8.4% Jews, 0.9% Russians and 0.6% Germans.&lt;ref name="Trela-Mazur 294" /&gt;

On 26 October, [[Elections to the People's Assemblies of Western Ukraine and Western Belarus|elections]] to Belorussian and Ukrainian assemblies were held to give the annexation an appearance of validity.{{#tag:ref| The voters had a choice of only one candidate for each position of deputy; the Communist party commissars then provided the assemblies with resolutions that would push through nationalization of banks and heavy industry and transfers of land to peasant communities.&lt;ref name="Rieber 29-30" /&gt;|group="Note"}} The Belarusians and Ukrainians in Poland had been increasingly alienated by the [[Polonization]] policies of the Polish government and its repression of their [[separatist]] movements, so they felt little loyalty towards the Polish state.&lt;ref name="Stosunki" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Davies02 512-513" /&gt; Not all Belarusians and Ukrainians, however, trusted the Soviet regime.&lt;ref name ="Davies96 1001-1003" /&gt; In practice, the poor generally welcomed the Soviets, and the elites tended to join the opposition, despite supporting the reunification itself.&lt;ref name="Stosunki2"&gt;{{cite journal |language=Polish |first=Marek |last=Wierzbicki |url=http://www.bialorus.pl/index.php?secId=49&amp;docId=60&amp;&amp;Rozdzial=historia |title=Stosunki polsko-białoruskie pod okupacją sowiecką (1939–1941) |journal=Białoruskie Zeszyty Historyczne |publisher=Biełaruski histaryczny zbornik |issue=20 |year=2003 |pages=186–188 |accessdate=16 July 2007 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080623073822/http://www.bialorus.pl/index.php?secId=49&amp;docId=60&amp;&amp;Rozdzial=historia |archivedate=23 June 2008 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Nowak" /&gt; The Soviets quickly introduced [[Sovietization]] policies in Western Belorussia and Western Ukraine, including compulsory [[collectivization]] of the whole region. In the process, they ruthlessly broke up political parties and public associations and imprisoned or executed their leaders as "enemies of the people".&lt;ref name ="Davies96 1001-1003" /&gt; The Soviet authorities also suppressed the [[anti-Polish]] [[Organization of Ukrainian Nationalists]], which had actively resisted the Polish regime since the 1920s; aiming for an independent, undivided Ukrainian state.&lt;ref name="Nowak" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Miner 41-42" /&gt; The unifications of 1939 were nevertheless a decisive event in the history of [[Ukraine]] and [[Belarus]], because they produced the two republics which eventually achieved independence in 1991 after the [[fall of the Soviet Union]].&lt;ref name="Wilson 17" /&gt;

&lt;br /&gt;
==Communist and later censorship==
Soviet [[Censorship in the Soviet Union|censors]] later suppressed many details of the 1939 invasion and its aftermath.&lt;ref name="Kubik 277" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Sanford 214-216" /&gt; From the start The [[Politburo]] called the operation a "liberation campaign", and later Soviet statements and publications never wavered from that line.&lt;ref name="Rieber 29" /&gt; Despite the publication of a recovered copy of the secret protocols of the Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact in the western media, until 1989 it was the official policy of the Soviet Union to deny their existence.&lt;ref name="Biskupski 147" /&gt; Censorship was also applied in the [[People's Republic of Poland]], in order to preserve the image of "Polish-Soviet friendship" which was promoted by the two communist governments. Official policy only allowed accounts of the 1939 campaign that portrayed it as a reunification of the Belarusian and Ukrainian peoples and a liberation of the Polish people from "oligarchic capitalism". The authorities strongly discouraged any further study or teaching of the subject.&lt;ref name="Fischer" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Orlik-Rückemann 20" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Ferro 258" /&gt; Various underground publications addressed the issue, as did other media, such as the 1982 [[protest song]] "''Ballada wrześniowa''{{-"}} by [[Jacek Kaczmarski]].&lt;ref name="Orlik-Rückemann 20" /&gt;&lt;ref name="Kaczmarski" /&gt;

=== Russia ===
In 2009, Russian Prime Minister [[Vladimir Putin]] wrote in the Polish daily ''[[Gazeta Wyborcza]]'' that the [[Molotov–Ribbentrop Pact]] concluded in August 1939 was "immoral".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Kuhrt |first=Natasha |date=2014 |title=Russia and the World: The Internal-External Nexus |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=1QLPBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA23 |location= |publisher=Routledge |page=23 |isbn=1-317-85037-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2015, then President of the Russian Federation, he commented: "In this sense I share the opinion of our culture minister ([[Vladimir Medinsky]] praising the pact as a triumph of Stalin's diplomacy) that this pact had significance for ensuring the security of the USSR".&lt;ref name="YahooMay2015"&gt;{{cite news |date= 10 May 2015|title=Putin defends notorious Nazi-Soviet pact |url=https://www.yahoo.com/news/putin-defends-notorious-nazi-soviet-pact-174156837.html |newspaper=Yahoo News|access-date=3 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 2016 the Russian Supreme Court upheld the decision of a lower court, which had found a blogger, Vladimir Luzgin,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.sky.com/story/how-russia-is-engaged-in-a-battle-for-its-own-history-10691897 |title=How Russia is engaged in a battle for its own history |publisher=Sky News |date=11 December 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; guilty of the "rehabilitation of Nazism" for reposting a text on social media that described the invasion of Poland in 1939 as a joint effort by Nazi Germany and the Soviet Union.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.tol.org/client/article/26273-russia-supreme-court-luzgin-1939-ussr-poland-nazi-germany-molotov-ribbentrop.html |title=Russia's Supreme Court Questions USSR's Role in 1939 Invasion of Poland |first=Azarova |last=Anna |date=2 September 2016 |accessdate=3 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[History of Poland (1939–1945)]]
* [[Germany–Soviet Union relations, 1918–1941]]
* [[Polish Operation of the NKVD|Polish Operation of the NKVD 1937-1938]]
* [[Gestapo–NKVD conferences|Gestapo–NKVD conferences 1939-1940]]
* [[Soviet repressions of Polish citizens (1939–1946)]]
* [[Russia involvement in regime change]]

==References==

===Notes===
{{reflist|group="Note"}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|2|refs=

&lt;ref name="Davies72 xi"&gt;[[#Reference-Davies72|Davies (1972)]] p. xi&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Kaczmarski"&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.kaczmarski.art.pl/tworczosc/wiersze_alfabetycznie/kaczmarskiego/b/ballada_wrzsniowa.php| title=Ballada wrześniowa| first=Jacek| last=Kaczmarski| language=Polish| trans-title=September's tale| accessdate=15 November 2006| url-status=dead| archiveurl=https://archive.is/20121209133244/http://www.kaczmarski.art.pl/tworczosc/wiersze_alfabetycznie/kaczmarskiego/b/ballada_wrzsniowa.php| archivedate=9 December 2012| df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Krivosheev"&gt;Кривошеев Г. Ф., ''Россия и СССР в войнах XX века: потери вооруженных сил. Статистическое исследование'' (Krivosheev G. F., ''Russia and the USSR in the wars of the 20th century: losses of the Armed Forces. A statistical survey'', Greenhill 1997, {{ISBN|1-85367-280-7}}) ''See also:'' {{cite book |first=Grigory Fedot |last=Krivosheev |title=Soviet casualties and combat losses in the twentieth century |location=London |publisher=Greenhill Books |year=1997 |isbn=1-85367-280-7}} Same.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Miner 41-42"&gt;[[#Reference-Miner|Miner]] p. 41-42&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Neilson 275"&gt;[[#Reference-Neilson|Neilson]] p. 275&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="SCHULENBURG1"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://avalon.law.yale.edu/20th_century/ns069.asp| title=The German Ambassador in the Soviet Union, (Schulenburg) to the German Foreign Office No. 317 |publisher=Lillian Goldman Law Library |accessdate=11 June 2009 |work=Avalon project}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Stanley 29"&gt;[[#Reference-Stanley|Stanley]] p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Weinberg 963"&gt;[[#Reference-Weinberg|Weinberg]] p. 963&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Kushner 219"&gt;[[#Reference-Kushner|Kushner]] p.219&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Biskupski 147"&gt;[[#Reference-Biskupski|Biskupski &amp; Wandycz]] p. 147&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Carley 303-341"&gt;[[#Reference-Carley|Carley]] 303–341&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Dallas 557"&gt;[[#Reference-Dallas|Dallas]] p. 557&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Davies 22, 504"&gt;[[#Reference-Davies02|Davies (2002)]] p. 22, 504&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Davies 371-373"&gt;[[#Reference=Davies02|Davies (2002)]] p. 371–373&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Davies 376"&gt;[[#Reference-Davies02|Davies (2002)]] p. 376&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Davies 504"&gt;[[#Reference-Davies02|Davies (2002)]] p. 504&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Davies02 512-513"&gt;[[#Reference-Davies02|Davies (2002)]] pp 512–513.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Davies72 29"&gt;[[#Reference-Davies72|Davies (1972)]] p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Davies96 440"&gt;[[#Reference-Davies96|Davies (1996)]] p. 440&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Degras 37-45"&gt;[[#Reference-Degras|Degras]] pp. 37–45&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Dunnigan 132"&gt;[[#Reference-Dunnigan|Dunnigan]] p. 132&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Ferro 258"&gt;[[#Reference-Ferro|Ferro]] p. 258&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Fischer"&gt;{{cite web |first=Benjamin B. |last=Fischer |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/csi-publications/csi-studies/studies/winter99-00/art6.html |title=The Katyn Controversy: Stalin's Killing Field |work=Studies in Intelligence |date= Winter 1999–2000 |accessdate=16 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Grabowiec"&gt;{{cite web |language=Polish |url=http://www.grabowiec.pl/portal/publikacje/epizod_roztrzelany_szpital.pdf |format=pdf |title=Rozstrzelany Szpital |trans-title=Executed Hospital |publisher=Tygodnik Zamojski |accessdate=28 November 2006 |date=15 September 2004 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070307143816/http://www.grabowiec.pl/portal/publikacje/epizod_roztrzelany_szpital.pdf |archivedate=7 March 2007 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Gronowicz 51"&gt;[[#Reference-Gronowicz|Gronowicz]] p. 51&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Gross 3"&gt;[[#Reference-Gross|Gross]] p. 3&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Gross 17"&gt;[[#Reference-Gross|Gross]] p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Gross 17-18"&gt;[[#Reference-Gross|Gross]] pp. 17–18&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Gross 182"&gt;[[#Reference-Gross|Gross]] p. 182&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Gross 24, 32-33"&gt;[[#Reference-Gross|Gross]] pp. 24, 32–33&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Gross 32-33"&gt;[[#Reference-Gross|Gross]] pp. 32–33&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Hehn 69-70"&gt;[[#Reference-Hehn|Hehn]] pp. 69–70&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Henderson 16-18"&gt;[[#Reference=Henderson|Henderson]] pp. 16–18&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Hiden-Lane 143-144"&gt;[[#Reference-Hiden-Lane|Hiden &amp; Lane]] pp. 143–144&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Hiden-Lane 148"&gt;[[#Reference-Hiden-Lane|Hiden &amp; Lane]] p. 148&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Interia-Szack"&gt;{{cite web |language=Polish|url=http://encyklopedia.interia.pl/haslo?hid=106003 |title=Szack |work=Encyklopedia Interia |accessdate=28 November 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Jackson 75"&gt;[[#Reference-Jackson|Jackson]] p. 75&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Karta"&gt;{{cite web| language=Polish |url= http://www.indeks.karta.org.pl/represje_sowieckie_4.html |title=Represje 1939–41 Aresztowani na Kresach Wschodnich |trans-title=Repressions 1939–41. Arrested on the Eastern Borderlands. |work=Ośrodek Karta |accessdate=15 November 2006 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20061021190059/http://www.indeks.karta.org.pl/represje_sowieckie_4.html |archivedate = 21 October 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Kenéz 129-131"&gt;[[#Reference-Kenéz|Kenéz]] pp. 129–131&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Kitchen 74"&gt;[[#Reference-Kitchen|Kitchen]] p. 74&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Kubik 277"&gt;[[#Reference-Kubik|Kubik]] p. 277&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Kutrzeba 524, 528"&gt;[[#Reference-Kutrzeba|Kutrzeba]] pp. 524, 528&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Leinwald"&gt;{{cite web | author=Artur Leinwand | title=Obrona Lwowa we wrześniu 1939 roku | publisher=Instytut Lwowski | year=1991 | work= | url=http://www.lwow.com.pl/rocznik/obrona39.html | accessdate=16 July 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Lukowski"&gt;{{Cite book|last1= Lukowski |first1= Jerzy |author1-link= Jerzy Lukowski|last2= Zawadzki  |first2= Hubert |year= 2001|title= A Concise History of Poland | location= Cambridge  |publisher= [[Cambridge University Press]]|isbn= 0-521-55917-0 | page=204 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Manvell-Fraenkel 76"&gt;[[#Reference-Manvell-Fraenkel|Manvell-Fraenkel]] p. 76&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Montefiore 312"&gt;[[#Reference-Montefiore|Montefiore]] p 312&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Mowat 648"&gt;[[#Reference-Mowat|Mowat]] p. 648&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Mowat 648-650"&gt;[[#Reference-Mowat|Mowat]] p. 648–650&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Moynihan 93"&gt;[[#Reference-Moynihan|Moynihan]] p. 93&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Neilson 298"&gt;[[#Reference-Neilson|Neilson]] p. 298&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Neilson 311"&gt;[[#Reference-Neilson|Neilson]] p. 311&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Neilson 315"&gt;[[#Reference-Neilson|Neilson]] p. 315&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Nowak"&gt;[[#Reference-Nowak|Nowak]] (online)&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Orlik-Rückemann 20"&gt;[[#Reference-Orlik-Rückemann|Orlik-Rückemann]] p. 20&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="PWN"&gt;{{cite web|language=Polish |url=http://encyklopedia.pwn.pl/haslo.php?id=3949396 |title=Obozy jenieckie żołnierzy polskich |trans-title=Prison camps for Polish soldiers |work=Encyklopedia PWN |accessdate=28 November 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="PWN_KW_old"&gt;{{cite web|language=Polish |url= http://encyklopedia.pwn.pl/33490_1.html |title=Kampania wrześniowa 1939 |trans-title=September Campaign 1939 |work=PWN Encyklopedia |accessdate=16 July 2007 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20060509003357/http://encyklopedia.pwn.pl/33490_1.html |archivedate = 9 May 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Piotrowski 11"&gt;[[#Reference-Piotrowski|Piotrowski]] p. 11&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Piotrowski 295"&gt;[[#Reference-Piotrowski|Piotrowski]] p. 295&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Polish experts lower nation's WWII death toll"&gt;{{cite web|title=Polish experts lower nation's WWII death toll |url=http://www.expatica.com/de/news/german-news/Polish-experts-lower-nation_s-WWII-death-toll--_55843.html |accessdate=4 November 2009 |date=30 July 2009 |publisher=AFP/Expatica}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Prazmowska 44-45"&gt;[[#Reference-Prazmowska|Prazmowska]] pp. 44–45.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Rieber 14, 32-37"&gt;[[#Reference-Rieber|Rieber]] pp. 14, 32–37&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Rieber 29"&gt;[[#Reference-Rieber|Rieber]] p. 29&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Rieber 29-30"&gt;[[#Reference-Rieber|Rieber]] pp. 29–30&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Rieber 30"&gt;[[#Reference-Rieber|Rieber]] p. 30&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Roberts 66-73"&gt;[[#Reference-Roberts|Roberts]] pp. 66–73&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Roberts 74"&gt;[[#Reference-Roberts|Roberts]] p. 74&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Roshwald 37"&gt;[[#Reference-Roshwald|Roshwald]] p. 37&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Rummel 130"&gt;[[#Reference-Rummel|Rummel]] p. 130&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Rummel 132"&gt;[[#Reference-Rummel|Rummel]] p. 132&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="SCHULENBURG2"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://avalon.law.yale.edu/20th_century/ns073.asp |title=The German Ambassador in the Soviet Union, (Schulenburg) to the German Foreign Office No. 371|publisher=Lillian Goldman Law Library |accessdate=11 June 2009 |work=Avalon project}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="SCHULENBURG3"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://avalon.law.yale.edu/20th_century/ns074.asp |title=The German Ambassador in the Soviet Union, (Schulenburg) to the German Foreign Office No. 372 |publisher=Lillian Goldman Law Library |accessdate=11 June 2009 |work=Avalon project}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Sanford 129"&gt;[[#Reference-Sanford|Sanford]] p. 129&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Sanford 20-24"&gt;[[#Reference-Sanford|Sanford]] [https://books.google.com/books?id=tV2AAgAAQBAJ&amp;q=3000%2B7000#v=snippet&amp;q=3000%2B7000&amp;f=false pp. 20–24]&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Sanford 21"&gt;[[#Reference-Sanford|Sanford]] p. 21&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Sanford 214-216"&gt;[[#Reference-Sanford|Sanford]] pp. 214–216&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Sanford 22-23, 39"&gt;[[#Reference-Sanford|Sanford]] pp. 22–23, 39&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Sanford 23"&gt;[[#Reference-Sanford|Sanford]] p. 23&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Shaw 119"&gt;[[#Reference-Shaw|Shaw]] p. 119&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Shirer 503"&gt;[[#Reference=Shirer|Shirer]] p. 503&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Shirer 525"&gt;[[#Reference=Shirer|Shirer]] p. 525&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Shirer 536"&gt;[[#Reference=Shirer|Shirer]] p. 536&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Shirer 537"&gt;[[#Reference-Shirer|Shirer]] p. 537&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Shirer 541"&gt;[[#Reference-Shirer|Shirer]] pp. 541–2&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Snyder 77"&gt;[[#Reference-Snyder|Snyder]] p. 77&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Soviet note of 1943"&gt;{{cite web | date=25 April 1943 |title=Soviet Note of April 25, 1943 |url=http://www.electronicmuseum.ca/Poland-WW2/katyn_memorial_wall/kmw_note.html |accessdate=19 December 2005 |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20050909042329/http://www.electronicmuseum.ca/Poland-WW2/katyn_memorial_wall/kmw_note.html |archivedate = 9 September 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Stachura 125"&gt;[[#Reference-Stachura|Stachura]] p. 125&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Taylor 38"&gt;[[#Reference-Taylor|Taylor]] p. 38.&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Trela-Mazur 294"&gt;[[#Reference-Trela-Mazur|Trela-Mazur]] p. 294&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Tucker 612"&gt;[[#Reference-Tucker|Tucker]] p. 612&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="WIF"&gt;{{cite book |title=Operatsiia Groza, Ili, Oshibka V Tretem Znake: Istoricheskaia Khronika|last=Bunich |first=Igor |authorlink= |year=1994 |publisher=VITA-OBLIK |location= |isbn=5-85976-003-5  |page=88 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Watson 695"&gt;[[#Reference=Watson|Watson]] p. 695&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Watson 695-722"&gt;[[#Reference-Watson|Watson]] p. 695–722&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Watson 698"&gt;[[#Reference=Watson|Watson]] p. 698&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Watson 708"&gt;[[#Reference=Watson|Watson]] p. 708&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Watson 713"&gt;[[#Reference-Watson|Watson]] p. 713&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Weinberg 55"&gt;[[#Reference-Weinberg|Weinberg]] p. 55&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Wettig 47"&gt;[[#Reference-Wettig|Wettig]] p. 47&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Wilson 17"&gt;[[#Reference-Wilson|Wilson]] p. 17&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Wojsko90"&gt;[[#Reference-Topolewski-Polak|Topolewski &amp; Polak]] p. 90&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Wojsko92"&gt;[[#Reference-Topolewski-Polak|Topolewski &amp; Polak]] p. 92&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Zaloga 80"&gt;[[#Reference-Zaloga|Zaloga]] p. 80&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="pledge"&gt;{{cite web |title=Telegram: His Majesty's Ambassador in Berlin – Dept of State 8/25/39 |url=http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/psf/box31/t295s04.html |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20020220043844/http://www.fdrlibrary.marist.edu/psf/box31/t295s04.html |url-status=dead |archive-date=20 February 2002 |publisher=Franklin D. Roosevelt Presidential Library and Museum |accessdate=11 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;!-- Unused citations
&lt;ref name="Levin 31-32"&gt;[[#Reference-Levin|Levin]] pp. 31–32&lt;/ref&gt;

&lt;ref name="Mendelsohn 218"&gt;[[#Reference-Mendelsohn|Mendelsohn]] p. 218&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;
}}

===Bibliography===
{{refbegin|2}}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Biskupski|last1=Biskupski|first1=Mieczyslaw B.|last2=Wandycz| first2= Piotr Stefan|title=Ideology, Politics, and Diplomacy in East Central Europe|publisher=Boydell &amp; Brewer| year=2003|isbn=1-58046-137-9}}
* {{cite journal|ref=Reference-Carley |last1=Carley |first1=Michael Jabara |title=End of the 'Low, Dishonest Decade': Failure of the Anglo–Franco–Soviet Alliance in 1939 |journal=Europe-Asia Studies |year=1993 |volume=45 |issue=2 |pages=303–341|doi=10.1080/09668139308412091}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Dallas |first=Gregor |last=Dallas |title=1945: The War That Never Ended |publisher=Yale University Press |year=2005 |isbn=978-0-300-10980-1 |url=https://archive.org/details/1945warthatnever00dall_1 }}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Davies72|first=Norman |last=Davies |title=White Eagle, Red Star: the Polish-Soviet War, 1919–20 |year=1972 |publisher=St. Martin's Press |location=New York |isbn=0-7126-0694-7}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Davies96 |authorlink=Norman Davies |last=Davies |first=Norman |year= 1996 |title=[[Europe: A History]] |location=Oxford |publisher=[[Oxford University Press]] |isbn= 0-19-820171-0}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Davies02 | last= Davies | first=Norman |title=God's Playground|url=https://archive.org/details/godsplaygroundhi00norm_0 |url-access=registration |year= 2002 |publisher=Columbia University Press | edition=revised |isbn=0-231-12819-3}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Dean |last=Dean |first=Martin |year=2000 |title=Collaboration in the Holocaust: Crimes of the Local Police in Belorussia and Ukraine, 1941–44 |location=Basingstoke | publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |isbn=1-4039-6371-1}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Degras|last=Degras |first=Jane Tabrisky |year=1953 |title=Soviet Documents on Foreign Policy. Volume I: 1917–1941 |location=Oxford |publisher=Oxford University Press}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Dunnigan |last=Dunnigan |first=James F. |year=2004 |title=The World War II Bookshelf: Fifty Must-Read Books |location=New York |publisher=Citadel Press |isbn=0-8065-2609-2}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Ferro |authorlink=Marc Ferro |last=Ferro |first=Marc |year=2003 |title= The Use and Abuse of History: Or How the Past Is Taught to Children |location=London, New York | publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=978-0-415-28592-6}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-FDH |title=Europe and Ethnicity: the First World War and contemporary ethnic conflict |first1=Thomas Grant |last1=Fraser |first2=Seamus |last2=Dunn |first3=Otto |last3=von Habsburg |publisher=Routledge |year=1996 |isbn=0-415-11995-2 |url=https://archive.org/details/europeethnicity00seam }}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Goldstein|last1=Goldstein|first1= |title=Missing |publisher= |isbn=}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Gelven |authorlink=Michael Gelven |last=Gelven |first=Michael |year=1994 |title=War and Existence: A Philosophical Inquiry |location=Pennsylvania |publisher=[[Penn State University Press]] |isbn=0-271-01054-1 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/warexistencephil0000gelv }}
* {{cite book|last=Goldman|first=Stuart D.|title=Nomonhan, 1939; The Red Army's Victory That Shaped World War II|year=2012| publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=978-1-61251-098-9}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Gronowicz |last=Gronowicz |first=Antoni |year=1976 |title=Polish Profiles: The Land, the People, and Their History |location=Westport, [[Connecticut|CT]] |publisher =L. Hill |isbn=0-88208-060-1}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Gross |authorlink=Jan T. Gross |last=Gross |first=Jan Tomasz |year=2002 |title=Revolution from Abroad: The Soviet Conquest of Poland's Western Ukraine and Western Belorussia |location=Princeton, [[New Jersey|NJ]] |publisher=Princeton University Press |isbn= 0-691-09603-1}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Hehn |last=Hehn|first=Paul N. |year=2005|title=A low dishonest decade: the great powers, Eastern Europe, and the economic origins of World War II, 1930–1941| location=| publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group|isbn=978-0-8264-1761-9}}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Henderson|last1=Henderson|first1= |title=Documents concerning German-Polish relations and the outbreak of hostilities between Great Britain and Germany on September 3, 1939 |publisher=Great Britain Foreign Office |year=1939}}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Hiden-Lane |title=The Baltic and the Outbreak of the Second World War| publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |year=2003 |first1=John |last1=Hiden |first2=Thomas |last2 = Lane |isbn=978-0-521-53120-7}}
* {{Citation | last = Hill | first = Alexander | title = The Red Army and the Second World War | publisher = Cambridge University Press | year = 2017 | ISBN = 978-1-107-02079-5}}.
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-House-Seymour |title=What Really Happened at Paris |url=https://archive.org/details/cu31924027876048 |first1= Edward | last1=House |first2=Charles |last2=Seymour |publisher=Scribner|year=1921}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Jackson |authorlink=Julian T. Jackson |last=Jackson |first=Julian |year=2003 |title=The Fall of France: The Nazi Invasion of 1940 |location=Oxford |publisher=Oxford University Press |isbn=0-19-280300-X |url=https://archive.org/details/falloffrancenazi00jack }}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Kenéz |authorlink=Peter Kenéz |last=Kenéz |first=Peter |year=2006 | edition=2nd |title=A History of the Soviet Union from the Beginning to the End |location= Cambridge |publisher=[[Cambridge University Press]] |isbn=978-0-521-86437-4}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Kitchen |title=A World in Flames: A Short History of the Second World War |last=Kitchen |first=Martin |authorlink= |year=1990 |publisher=Longman |location= | isbn=0-582-03408-6}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Kubik |last=Kubik |first=Jan |year=1994 |title=The Power of Symbols Against the Symbols of Power: the Rise of Solidarity and the Fall of State |location=Pennsylvania | publisher=Penn State University Press |isbn=0-271-01084-3}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Kushner |author1=Kushner, Tony |author2=Knox, Katharine  |year=1999 |title=Refugees in an Age of Genocide |location=London, New York |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=0-7146-4783-7}}
* {{cite book|first=S |last=Kutrzeba |contribution=The Struggle for the Frontiers, 1919–1923 |editor-first=William Fiddian |editor-last=Reddaway |title=The Cambridge history of Poland &amp;#124;volume1 | publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |year=1950 | isbn= |pages =512–543|ref=Reference-Kutrzeba}}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Levin| title=The lesser of two evils: Eastern European Jewry under Soviet rule, 1939–1941|publisher=[[Jewish Publication Society]] |first=Dov |last=Levin |year=1995 |isbn=978-0-8276-0518-3}}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Manvell-Fraenkel|last1=Manvell|first1=Roger |last2=Fraenkel |first2= Heinrich |title=Heinrich Himmler: The Sinister Life of the Head of the SS and Gestapo |publisher= Greenhill |location=London |year=2007 |isbn=978-1-60239-178-9}}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Mendelsohn| title=Jews and the Sporting Life: Studies in Contemporary Jewry XXIII|first=Ezra |last= Mendelsohn|publisher=[[Oxford University Press]]|year=2009|isbn=978-0-19-538291-4}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Miner|last=Miner |first=Steven Merritt |year=2003 |title=Stalin's Holy War: Religion, Nationalism, and Alliance Politics, 1941–1945 |location=North Carolina |publisher= UNC Press |isbn=0-8078-2736-3}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Montefiore|last=Montefiore |first=Simon Sebag |year=2003 |title=Stalin: The Court of the Red Tsar|location=New York |publisher=Vintage Books|isbn=1-4000-7678-1}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Mowat |last1=Mowat |first1=Charles Loch |title=Britain between the wars: 1918–1940 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |year=1968 |isbn=0-416-29510-X |url=https://archive.org/details/britainbetweenwa00mowa }}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Moynihan |authorlink=Daniel Patrick Moynihan |last=Moynihan |first= Daniel Patrick |year=1990 |title=On the Law of Nations |url=https://archive.org/details/onlawofnations00dani |url-access=registration |location=Cambridge, [[Massachusetts|MA]] | publisher=[[Harvard University Press]] |isbn=0-674-63575-2}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Neilson |last=Neilson |first=Keith |year=2006 |title=Britain, Soviet Russia and the Collapse of the Versailles Order, 1919–1939 |location=Cambridge |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=978-0-521-85713-0}}
* {{cite journal |ref=Reference-Nowak| authorlink=Andrzej Nowak (historian) | first= Andrzej |last =Nowak|url=http://www.ruf.rice.edu/~sarmatia/197/Nowak.html |title=The Russo-Polish Historical Confrontation |journal=[[Sarmatian Review]] |date=January 1997 |volume=XVII |issue=1 |accessdate=16 July 2007}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Orlik-Rückemann| authorlink=Wilhelm Orlik-Rückemann |last=Orlik-Rückemann |first=Wilhelm |year=1985 |language=Polish |title=Kampania wrześniowa na Polesiu i Wołyniu: 17.IX.1939–1.X.1939 |editor-first=Leopold |editor-last=Jerzewski |location=Warsaw |publisher=Głos}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Piotrowski |last=Piotrowski |first=Tadeusz |year=1998 |title=Poland's Holocaust: Ethnic Strife: Collaboration with Occupying Forces and Genocide in the Second Republic, 1918–1947 |location=Jefferson, [[North Carolina|NC]] |publisher=McFarland &amp; Company |isbn=0-7864-0371-3 |url=https://archive.org/details/polandsholocaust00piot }}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Osmańczyk-Mango|last1=Osmańczyk|first1=Edmund Jan |editor-last=Mango |editor-first=Anthony |title=Encyclopedia of the United Nations and international agreements |volume=1 |edition=3rd |publisher=Routledge |year=2003 |location=New York |isbn=0-415-93921-6}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Prazmowska |authorlink=Anita Prazmowska |last=Prazmowska |first=Anita J. |year=1995 |title=Britain and Poland 1939–1943: The Betrayed Ally |location=Cambridge | publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=0-521-48385-9}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Rieber |last=Rieber |first=Alfred Joseph |year=2000 |title=Forced Migration in Central and Eastern Europe: 1939–1950 |location=London, New York |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=0-7146-5132-X}}
* {{cite journal |ref=Reference-Roberts |last=Roberts |first=Geoffrey |year=1992 |title=The Soviet Decision for a Pact with Nazi Germany |journal=[[Soviet Studies]] |volume=44 |issue=1 |pages=57–78 |doi=10.1080/09668139208411994}}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Roshwald| title=Ethnic Nationalism and the Fall of Empires: Central Europe, the Middle East and Russia, 1914–1923 |first=Aviel |last=Roshwald |authorlink=Aviel Roshwald |publisher=Routledge |year=2001 |isbn=0-415-17893-2}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Rummel |last=Rummel |first=Rudolph Joseph |year=1990 |title=Lethal Politics: Soviet Genocide and Mass Murder Since 1917 |location=New Jersey |publisher=Transaction |isbn=1-56000-887-3}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Ryziński |last1=Ryziński |first1=Kazimierz  |first2=Ryszard |last2= Dalecki |year=1990 |title=Obrona Lwowa w roku 1939 |publisher= Instytut Lwowski |location=Warszawa |isbn=978-83-03-03356-7 |language=Polish}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Sanford |authorlink=George Sanford (scholar) |last=Sanford |first= George |year=2005 |title=Katyn and the Soviet Massacre Of 1940: Truth, Justice And Memory | location=London, New York |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=0-415-33873-5}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Shaw |last=Shaw |first=Louise Grace |year=2003 |title=The British Political Elite and the Soviet Union, 1937–1939 |location=London, New York |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=0-7146-5398-5}}
* {{cite book| ref=Reference-Shirer |last=Shirer|first=William L.|title=The Rise and Fall of the Third Reich: A History of Nazi Germany|publisher=Simon and Schuster|year=1990 |isbn=0-671-72868-7}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Snyder |authorlink=Timothy Snyder |last=Snyder |first=Timothy |year= 2005 |chapter=Covert Polish Missions Across the Soviet Ukrainian Border, 1928–1933 |title=Confini: Costruzioni, Attraversamenti, Rappresentazionicura |editor-first=Silvia |editor-last=Salvatici | location=Soveria Mannelli (Catanzaro) |publisher=Rubbettino |isbn=88-498-1276-0}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Stachura |last=Stachura |first=Peter D. |year=2004 |title=Poland, 1918–1945: An Interpretive and Documentary History of the Second Republic |location=London, New York |publisher=[[Routledge]] |isbn=0-415-34357-7}}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Stanley|last1=Stanley|first1= |title=Missing |publisher= |isbn=}}
* {{cite book|ref=Reference-Sword|last1=Sword|first1=Keith  |year=1991|title=The Soviet Takeover of the Polish Eastern Provinces, 1939–41 |publisher=Palgrave Macmillan |isbn=978-1-349-21381-8}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Taylor |authorlink=A. J. P. Taylor |last=Taylor |first=A. J. P. |year=1975 |title=The Second World War: An Illustrated History |location=London |publisher=Putnam |isbn=0-399-11412-2 |url=https://archive.org/details/secondworldwaran00tayl }}
* {{Cite book |ref=Reference-Topolewski-Polak| language=Polish |url=http://www.dzp.wojsko.pl/dzial/wydawnictwa/zwarte/pdf/EHW_1_2005.pdf | format =pdf |last = Topolewski | first = Stanisław | last2 = Polak | first2= Andrzej |title= 60. rocznica zakończenia II wojny światowej |trans-title=60th anniversary of the end of World War II | series =Edukacja Humanistyczna w Wojsku (Humanist Education in the Army) |publisher=Dom wydawniczy Wojska Polskiego (Publishing House of the Polish Army) |volume=1 |year=2005| accessdate =28 November 2006 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070929020932/http://www.dzp.wojsko.pl/dzial/wydawnictwa/zwarte/pdf/EHW_1_2005.pdf | archivedate= 29 September 2007 |issn=1734-6584 }}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Trela-Mazur |last=Trela-Mazur |first=Elżbieta |authorlink=Elżbieta Trela-Mazur |year=1997 |title=Sowietyzacja oświaty w Małopolsce Wschodniej pod radziecką okupacją 1939–1941 |work=Sovietization of Education in Eastern Lesser Poland During the Soviet Occupation 1939–1941 |editor-first=Włodzimierz |editor-last=Bonusiak |location=Kielce |publisher=Wyższa Szkoła Pedagogiczna im. Jana Kochanowskiego |isbn=978-83-7133-100-8 |language=Polish |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wGq1AAAAIAAJ&amp;focus=searchwithinvolume&amp;q=ponad+38%25 |via=Google Books}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Tucker |authorlink=Robert C. Tucker |last=Tucker |first=Robert C. |year=1992 |title=Stalin in Power: The Revolution from Above, 1929–1941 |location=New York |publisher=Norton |isbn=0-393-30869-3 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/stalininpowerrev00tuck }}
* {{cite journal|ref=Reference-Watson|last=Watson |first=Derek |year=2000 |title=Molotov's Apprenticeship in Foreign Policy: The Triple Alliance Negotiations in 1939 |journal=[[Europe-Asia Studies]]| volume=52 |issue=4 |pages=695–722|doi=10.1080/713663077}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Weinberg |authorlink=Gerhard Weinberg |last=Weinberg |first=Gerhard |year=1994 |title=A World at Arms: A Global History of World War II |location=Cambridge |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=0-521-44317-2 |url=https://archive.org/details/worldatarmsgloba00wein }}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Wilson |authorlink=Andrew Wilson (historian) |last=Wilson |first=Andrew |year=1997 |title=Ukrainian Nationalism in the 1990s: A Minority Faith |location=Cambridge, New York |publisher=Cambridge University Press |isbn=0-521-57457-9}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Wettig |last=Wettig |first=Gerhard |title=Stalin and the Cold War in Europe: the emergence and development of East–West conflict, 1939–1953|publisher=Rowman &amp; Littlefield |location=Lanham |year=2008 |isbn=0-7425-5542-9}}
* {{cite book |ref=Reference-Zaloga |authorlink=Steven Zaloga |last=Zaloga |first=Steven J. |year= 2002 |title=Poland 1939: The Birth of Blitzkrieg |location=Oxford |publisher=Osprey Publishing | isbn=1-84176-408-6}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Soviet invasion of Poland of 1939}}

{{Polish wars and conflicts}}
{{Russian Conflicts}}
{{Soviet zones of occupation}}
{{Joseph Stalin}}
{{Nazi-Soviet relations}}

[[Category:Soviet invasion of Poland| ]]
[[Category:1939 in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1939]]
[[Category:September 1939 events]]
[[Category:October 1939 events]]
[[Category:Military operations involving the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Polish–Russian wars]]
[[Category:Invasion of Poland]]
[[Category:Soviet military occupations]]
[[Category:Stalinism in Poland]]
[[Category:Belarus in World War II]]
[[Category:Western Belorussia (1918–1939)]]</text><sha1>thd4z86ufm9o5l0q7froeqywsbsiyff</sha1></revision></page>