<page><title>Battle of Suomussalmi</title><ns>0</ns><id>187309</id><revision><id>967548977</id><parentid>967335021</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-13T22:15:25Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Pudeo</username><id>1028619</id></contributor><comment>The source gives three numbers, 13,000 - 15,000 and 23,000. So I've changed it to 13,000-23,000. Note that it seems that the Soviet numbers do not state wounded which may be the reason for confusion.</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="9104" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{refimprove|date=January 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Suomussalmi
| partof      = the [[Winter War]]
| image       = Battle suomussalmi.jpg
| image_size  = 300
| caption     =
| date        = 7 December 1939-8 January  1940
| place       = [[Suomussalmi]], [[Finland]]
| result      = Finnish  victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|Finland}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Finland}} [[Hjalmar Siilasvuo]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} {{illm|Ivan Dashichev|ru|Дашичев, Иван Фёдорович}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Alexei Vinogradov]]
| strength1   = T3 regiments and separate battalions&lt;br&gt;11,500
| strength2   = [[9th Army (Soviet Union)|9th Army]]
* 2 divisions
*1 tank brigade 
45,000–55,000
| casualties1 = 750 killed or missing&lt;ref name="Kulju11" /&gt;&lt;br&gt;1,000 wounded&lt;ref name="Kulju11"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], p. 195. The first Finnish reports estimated 600 dead, 162 missing and 1,200 wounded, but later some men died of their wounds.&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = 13,000-23,000 killed or missing&lt;ref&gt;{{in lang|fi|ru}} [http://heninen.net/raatteentie/joukkoviesti/ks2004-2_f.htm Suomalaiset ja venäläiset tutkijat etsivät yhdessä totuutta talvisodasta]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;2,100 captured&lt;br&gt;43 tanks captured&lt;br&gt;71 field-guns captured&lt;br&gt;29 anti-tank guns captured&lt;br&gt;260 trucks captured&lt;br&gt;1,170 horses captured
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Winter War}}
}}

The '''Battle of Suomussalmi''' was a battle fought between [[Finland|Finnish]] and [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] forces in the [[Winter War]]. The action took place from around December 7, 1939, to January 8, 1940. The outcome was a Finnish victory against superior forces. Suomussalmi is considered the clearest, most important, and most significant Finnish victory in the northern half of Finland.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book
 | last1 = Trotter| first1 = William
 | authorlink = William R. Trotter
 | title = A Frozen Hell: The Russo-Finnish Winter War of 1939–1940
 | publisher = [[Algonquin Books]]
 | pages = 171
 | date = January 2000
 | isbn = 1565122496 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In Finland, the battle is still seen today as a symbol of the entire Winter War itself.

==Course of battle==
[[File:Suomussalmi battle from 30 November to 8 December 1939.png|thumb|right|300px|Diagram of the Battle of Suomussalmi from November 30 to December 8, 1939. The Soviet 163rd Division advanced to the town of Suomussalmi.]]

On November 30, 1939, the Soviet [[163rd Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|163rd Rifle Division]] crossed the border between Finland and the [[Soviet Union]] and advanced from the north-east towards the village of [[Suomussalmi]]. The Soviet objective was to advance to the city of [[Oulu]], effectively cutting Finland in half. This sector had only one Finnish [[battalion]] (Er.P 15), which was placed near [[Battle of Raate Road|Raate]], outside Suomussalmi.

Suomussalmi was taken with little resistance on December 7 (only two incomplete companies of covering forces led a holding action between the border and Suomussalmi), but the Finns destroyed the village before this, to deny the Soviets shelter, and withdrew to the opposite shore of lakes Niskanselkä and Haukiperä.

The first extensive fight started on December 8, when Soviet forces began to attack across the frozen lakes to the west. Their attempt failed completely. The second part of Soviet forces led the attack to the northwest on Puolanka, that was defended by the Er.P 16 (lit. 16th detached battalion), that had just arrived. This attempt also failed.

On December 9, the defenders were reinforced with a newly founded regiment (JR 27). Colonel [[Hjalmar Siilasvuo]] was given the command of the Finnish forces and he began immediate counter-measures to regain Suomussalmi. The main forces advanced on Suomussalmi, but failed to take the village, suffering serious losses.

On December 24, Soviet units counterattacked, but failed to break through the surrounding Finnish forces.

Reinforced with two new regiments (JR 64 and JR 65), the Finns again attacked on December 27. This time, they took the village, and the Soviets retreated in panic over the surrounding frozen lakes. A large part of them managed to reach the Russian border along the [[Kiantajärvi]] lake.

During this time, the Soviet [[44th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|44th Rifle Division]] had advanced from the east towards Suomussalmi. It was entrenched on the road between Suomussalmi and Raate and got caught up in the retreat of the other Soviet forces.

Between January 4 and January 8, 1940, the 44th Rifle Division was [[Battle of Raate-Road|divided into isolated groups and destroyed]] by the Finnish troops (in a tactic known as [[Pocket (military)#Motti|motti]]), leaving much heavy equipment for the Finnish troops.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.exile.ru/articles/detail.php?ARTICLE_ID=8430&amp;IBLOCK_ID=35&amp;phrase_id=1428 The Mighty Finn]'' – [[War Nerd]], ''[[the eXile]], Issue 254, December 29, 2006&lt;/ref&gt;

==Outcome==


The battle resulted in a major victory for the Finns. If the [[Soviet Union]] had captured the city of Oulu, the Finns would have had to defend the country on two fronts and an important rail link to Sweden would have been severed. The battle also gave a decisive boost to the morale of the Finnish army.

In addition, Finnish forces on the Raate-Suomussalmi road captured a large amount of military supplies, including tanks (43), field guns (71), trucks (260), horses (1,170), anti-tank guns (29) and other weapons, which were greatly needed by the Finnish army.

[[Alvar Aalto]] sculpted a memorial for the Finnish soldiers who died.&lt;ref&gt;Chilvers, Ian (2004)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Analysis==
The Battle of Suomussalmi is often cited as an example of how a small force, properly led and fighting in familiar terrain, can defeat a vastly numerically superior enemy. Factors which contributed to the Finnish victory included:&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=xILgHyN9riwC&amp;newbks=1&amp;newbks_redir=0&amp;dq=Snow+and+Slaughter+at+Suomussalmi&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s|title=The White Death: The Epic of the Soviet-Finnish Winter War|last=Chew|first=Allen F.|date=1971|publisher=Headquarters, U.S. Marine Corps|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

*Finnish troops having higher mobility due to skis and sleds; in contrast, Soviet heavy equipment confined them to roads.
*The Soviet objective to cut Finland in half across the Oulu region – while appearing reasonable on a map, was inherently unrealistic, as the region was mostly forested marshland, with its road network consisting mainly of logging trails. Mechanized divisions had to rely on these, becoming easy targets for the mobile Finnish ski troops.
*Finnish strategy was flexible and often unorthodox, for example, targeting Soviet [[field kitchen]]s, which [[morale|demoralized]] Soviet soldiers fighting in a sub-Arctic winter.
*Soviet army being poorly equipped, especially with regard to winter camouflage clothing.
*In contrast, Finnish troops' equipment were well suited for warfare in deep snow and freezing temperatures.
*Finnish army had very high morale: they were defending their homes. Soviet troops had only political reasons for their attack, and consequently lost their will to fight soon despite continual efforts by Soviet propagandists.
*Soviet counter-intelligence failures: Finnish troops often intercepted the Soviet communications, which relied heavily on standard phone lines.&lt;ref name=Hughes-Wilson&gt;''Snow and Slaughter at Suomussalmi'' – Hughes-Wilson, John – ''Military History'', January/February 2006, page 50&lt;/ref&gt;
*Simplicity where needed, as the final assault was a simple head-on charge, decreasing the chances of tactical errors. Rough weather also favored comparatively simple plans.

==See also==
*[[Battle of Raate Road]]

==References==
===Citations===
{{Reflist|2}}

===Bibliography ===
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite encyclopedia | editor-first = Ian | editor-last = Chilvers | title = Aalto, Alvar | encyclopedia = The Oxford Dictionary of Art | edition = 3rd | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Oxford, UK | page = 1 | isbn = 0-19-860476-9 | origyear = 1988 | year = 2004}}
* {{Cite book |last1=Kulju |first1=Mika |title= Raatteen tie : Talvisodan pohjoinen sankaritarina |edition= |year=2007 |origyear= |publisher=Ajatus kirjat |location=Helsinki |language=Finnish |isbn=978-951-20-7218-7 |quote= |ref=Kulju2007}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
* [http://www.winterwar.com/Battles/Suomussalmi.htm Battle of Suomussalmi]. by Sami H. E. Korhonen (2006), www.winterwar.com. Texts with plenty of maps. In two parts, the [http://www.winterwar.com/Battles/Suomussalmi2.htm second] part. Retrieved 2014-03-16.{{in lang|en}}

{{Coord|64|53|18|N|28|53|20|E|type:city|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle of Suomussalmi}}
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Winter War|Suomussalmi]]
[[Category:1939 in Finland]]
[[Category:1940 in Finland]]
[[Category:Suomussalmi]]
[[Category:History of Kainuu]]
[[Category:December 1939 events]]
[[Category:January 1940 events]]</text><sha1>5yxs1bspatrzu0zufpbk0pkga0u2gg9</sha1></revision></page>