<page><title>Battle of Raate Road</title><ns>0</ns><id>5467100</id><revision><id>945906276</id><parentid>934667415</parentid><timestamp>2020-03-16T21:35:17Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Pamrel</username><id>35261024</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="13582" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Battle of Raate Road
| partof = the [[Winter War]]
| image = Raate road.jpg
| image_size = 300
| caption = Fragment of the destroyed Soviet column on the road
| date = 1-7 January 1940
| place = Eastern Finland
| result = Finnish victory
| combatant1 = {{flag|Finland}}
| combatant2 = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1 = {{flagicon|Finland}} [[Hjalmar Siilasvuo]]
| commander2 = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Alexei Vinogradov]]
| strength1 = 6,000
| strength2 = 13,962–25,000&lt;ref name="Kulju10a"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], p. 130. Official number of the Soviet [[Stavka]] report.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Officially)&lt;/small&gt;
| casualties1 = 402 killed&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(according to Finnish estimates)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name="Kantakoski2"&gt;[[#Kantakoski1998|Kantakoski 1998]], p. 283: ''310 dead, 92 missing and 618 wounded.''&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = 4,674 casualties &lt;small&gt;(according to the Soviets)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name="Raunio&amp;Kilin153"&gt;[[#Raunio|Raunio &amp; Kilin 2005]], p. 153&lt;/ref&gt;
7,000–9,000 killed&lt;br&gt;1,300 captured&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(according to Finnish estimates)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name="Kulju1"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], p. 229. Modern Finnish estimate.&lt;/ref&gt;
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Winter War}}
}}

The '''Battle of Raate Road''' was a battle fought during the [[Winter War]] between the [[Soviet Union]] and [[Finland]] in January 1940, as a part of the [[Battle of Suomussalmi]].

On December 7, 1939, the Soviet [[163rd Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|163rd Rifle Division]] captured [[Suomussalmi]], but found itself trapped deep inside Finnish territory, and the [[44th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|Soviet 44th Rifle Division]] was sent to aid the 163rd. Over the next week, Colonel [[Hjalmar Siilasvuo]]'s outnumbered 9th Division stopped and decisively defeated the Soviet forces on the Raate-Suomussalmi road.

== Background ==
During the battle of Suomussalmi, the Finns cut the Raate Road on December 11, 1939. The action blocked the second, southern supply route to the Soviet 163rd Rifle Division in the town of Suomussalmi.&lt;ref name="Kulju9a"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; The Finns also cut the first, northern supply route on 13 December, and the Soviets were forced to open a new supply route through [[Kiantajärvi|Lake Kiantajärvi]].&lt;ref name="Kulju10b"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], pp. 82–83&lt;/ref&gt; The 163rd Division was nearly surrounded and suffered major casualties in Suomussalmi. The situation was getting worse, and on 20 December the commander of the 163rd Division, [[Andrei Zelentsov]], asked permission to retreat from Suomussalmi. In response, part of the 44th Division, the 1st Battalion of the 305th Rifle Regiment, and the 3rd Battalion of the 662nd Rifle Regiment, were sent to reinforce the 163rd Division troops near Suomussalmi. Zelentsov's concerns were not understood at [[Red Army]] headquarters, as the entire 44th Division was about to move along the Raate Road.&lt;ref name="Kulju11a"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], p. 83&lt;/ref&gt; The well trained Soviet 81st Mountain Rifles Regiment played a major role in the battle for Suomussalmi.&lt;ref&gt;Campbell p.44&lt;/ref&gt;

Most military historians date the battle of the Raate Road from 1 January to 7 January 1940. The Raate road was a battlefield during the entire Winter War. Before the main battle against the 44th Division, the Finns fought defensive battles against a part of 163rd Division on the Raate Road. Furthermore, some battles were fought on the east side, near the border, on the road during the rest of the Winter War.&lt;ref name="Kulju8"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], p. 125&lt;/ref&gt;

== Battle ==
At the start of the battle, Siilasvuo's 9th Division had already destroyed the Soviet 163rd Division. After that, it received orders to destroy the Soviet 44th Division, which was stopped on the road near [[Haukila]], 12 kilometers from Suomussalmi. The Finnish 9th Division was split in four squadrons, each named after their commanders. The decisive battle was ordered to begin on January 5, 1940, 08:30.

The battles focused on Haukila, where most of the Soviet troops were located and where squadrons "Mandelin" and "Mäkiniemi" attacked. Squadron "Mäkiniemi" had started moving towards Haukila a few days before the official attack. At the same time, the fresh 3rd [[NKVD]] Border Guard Regiment was just arriving to assist the Soviet 44th Division. By the following morning, the Finnish troops held strong blocking positions reinforced with mines at several points in the midst of the Soviet column. During January 6, heavy fighting occurred all along the Raate Road as the Finns continued to break up the enemy forces into smaller pieces. The Soviets attempted to overrun Finnish [[roadblock]]s with armor, losing numerous tanks in frontal attacks, but were unsuccessful. Finally, at 21:30, [[Alexei Vinogradov]] belatedly ordered his division to retreat back to the Soviet border.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Raunio|Raunio &amp; Kilin 2005]], p. 151&lt;/ref&gt;

The despairing Soviet troops began to escape north over [[Lake Kiantajärvi]]. Many soldiers froze to death without proper clothing or supplies. Remnants of Soviet units had already tried to escape to the east, but were blocked by squadron "Kari". Further in the east, squadron "Fagernäs" could not keep a strategic bridge under Finnish control. On January 7, squadron "Fagernäs" recaptured the bridge and before noon all Soviet resistance was suppressed. The mopping-up went on for two days, during which the Finns rounded up hundreds of starving, freezing Soviet soldiers. Other remnants of the 44th Division were forced to withdraw from the area, fleeing through the northern forests pursued by the Finns, finally reaching the border in several small groups.&lt;ref&gt;Sotatieteen laitos: "Talvisodan historia" part 3, p. 291&lt;/ref&gt;

The Finnish army captured a tremendous amount of [[materiel]] in this battle.&lt;ref name="Kulju9b"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], pp. 217–218&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Marching to Raate-road.jpg|thumb|Finnish soldiers on Raate Road]]

{| class="wikitable sortable"
|+ Captured material{{Citation needed|date=January 2012}}
! Finnish statistics!!Soviet statistics
|-
| 4,822 rifles || 4,340 rifles
|-
| 106 machine guns || 97 machine guns
|-
| 190 [[light machine guns]] || 252 light machine guns
|-
| 71 artillery pieces || 55 artillery pieces
|-
| 29 anti-tank guns || 30 anti-tank guns
|-
| 14 [[anti-tank rifles]] || 12 anti-tank rifles
|-
| 43 tanks || 37 tanks
|-
| 10 [[Armored car (military)|armored cars]] ||
|-
| 260 trucks ||
|-
| 20 tractors ||
|-
| 2 cars ||
|-
| 1,170 horses ||
|}

== Casualties ==
[[File:Raattentie T-26.jpg|thumb|Finnish soldiers inspecting an abandoned Soviet [[T-26]] mod. 1933 at Raate. January 1940.]]
For many years, Finnish historians estimated the Soviet losses to be around 17,000 men. The estimation was based on the interrogation of the [[prisoners of war]] captured in early January. Officers of the Soviet 27th Infantry Regiment had given their casualties at 70 percent and the Finns assumed that the strength of the 44th Division was over 20,000 men.&lt;ref name="Kulju2"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], p. 225&lt;/ref&gt; Western historians conformed their figures to Finnish estimations. The Soviets challenged the number of casualties published in the [[Western world]] immediately in January and claimed to have lost no more than 900 men, mostly from [[frostbite]], while inflicting an estimated 2,000 Finn fatalities.&lt;ref name="Kulju3"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], pp. 226–227&lt;/ref&gt; Later Finnish historians conducted further efforts to ascertain the number of Soviet casualties in the battle. The Finns captured over 5,000 rifles, and furthermore, the [[North Finland Group]] replaced 1,200 old rifles with the newer Soviet models. Most recent Finnish studies indicate that the Soviets lost at least 7,000–9,000 men.&lt;ref name="Kulju6"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], p. 229&lt;/ref&gt;

The Finns quickly buried the Soviet dead as the weather warmed during the early spring to reduce the risk of [[epidemic]]s. [[Mass grave]]s were marked on maps and were mounted with a cross or a pole. Later, the maps disappeared. Around [[Easter]], the Soviets made a request that they would like to gather the dead and take them back home. The Finns did not allow Soviet Army officials to cross the border but delivered 300 bodies from near the village of Raate to Soviet officials.&lt;ref name="Kulju4"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], pp. 227–228&lt;/ref&gt; After the [[Continuation War]], the Soviets lost interest in their deceased. The Red Army occupied the Raate Road shortly and gathered wartime debris but left the bodies alone. The fate of the Soviet 44th Division remained unmentioned in [[Soviet historiography]] for decades.&lt;ref name="Kulju5"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], pp. 228–229&lt;/ref&gt;

According to the Russian historian [[Yuri Kilin]], the [[Stavka]] set up a research commission in January 1940 to investigate the number of casualties. The Commission reported 4,674 total casualties: 1,001 dead, 1,430 wounded and 2,243 missing. At the turn of the year, the strength of the division was 13,962 men and by the end of the battle it was at 9,288 men.&lt;ref name="Raunio&amp;Kilin153" /&gt; According to the report, the division was understaffed, because two battalions of the 305th Rifle Regiment were deployed elsewhere. Kilin calculated that some troops returned after the report, so the number of the missing is lower. Later, research by the Ukrainian historian Oleg Bozhko yielded similar numbers as he used the same source.&lt;ref name="Kulju6"/&gt; The Stavka report was published in January 1940, in the middle of the Winter War. The statistics of the report start from 1 January, and by this time the division had already suffered heavy losses for two weeks. The Stavka report did not mention casualties suffered on the Raate Road by other units, along the advancement of the 44th Division.&lt;ref name="Kulju7"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], pp. 230–231&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
Thereafter, the area saw only a few minor skirmishes.

=== Soviet executions ===
The Soviet commander, Vinogradov, and two of his chief officers, Volkov and Pahomov, retreated in the middle of crucial battles. According to the Stavka report, this act had a fatal influence on morale. As they reached the Soviet lines four days later they were [[court-martial]]ed, found guilty and sentenced to death; the executions were carried out immediately. The Stavka itself had made the crucial decisions to keep the 44th Division on the Raate Road after the 163rd had lost Suomussalmi village.&lt;ref name="Kulju12"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], pp. 219–220&lt;/ref&gt;

A Ukrainian veteran of the Raate Road, Sergeant Pyotr Andrevich Morozov, was interviewed in 1991 by the Finnish non-fiction writer Leo Karttimo.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Karttimo1992|Karttimo 1992]]{{page needed|date=August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Morozov the Finns returned prisoners of war, but none of them managed to get back to their homes as the Soviet secret service NKVD executed them all in summer 1940.&lt;ref name="Kulju11b"&gt;[[#Kulju2007|Kulju 2007]], p. 220&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Monuments ===
[[File:The Monument of the Winter War.jpg|thumb|right|The Monument of the Winter War]]
Today, the former battlefield is the site of the [[Monument of the Winter War]] dedicated to all who died in the war on both sides. The memorial includes a field of thousands of stones as symbolic gravestones of the Soviet soldiers who fell in the battle. The Russian monument was installed in September 1994, and the Ukrainians installed their own monument in the spring of 1998.&lt;ref name="Kulju6" /&gt;

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==Sources==
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite book |last1=Kantakoski |first1=Pekka |title= Punaiset panssarit : Puna-armeijan panssarijoukot 1918–1945 |edition= |year=1998 |origyear= |publisher=PS-Elso |location=Hauho |language=Finnish |isbn=951-98057-0-2 |quote= |ref=Kantakoski1998}}
*{{cite book |last1=Kulju |first1=Mika |title= Raatteen tie : Talvisodan pohjoinen sankaritarina |edition= |year=2007 |origyear= |publisher=Ajatus kirjat |location=Helsinki |language=Finnish |isbn=978-951-20-7218-7 |quote= |ref=Kulju2007}}
*{{cite book |last1=Karttimo |first1=Leo |last2=Salminen|first2=K. E.|title=Rannikolta Raatteen tielle : sotaveteraanien haastatteluihin, sotapäiväkirjoihin sekä moniin muihin lähteisiin perustuva teos |edition=|year=1992 |origyear=|publisher=|language=Finnish |isbn=952-90-3809-7|ref=Karttimo1992}}
*{{cite book | author= Sotatieteen laitos | title= Talvisodan historia | year= 1991
|location= Porvoo | publisher= Werner Söderström Osakeyhtiö |language=Finnish
|isbn=951-0-17565-X|ref=TalvisodanHistoria1991 }}
*{{cite book |last1=Raunio |first=Ari |last2=Kilin |first2=Yuri |date=2005 |title=Itsenäisyyden puolustajat: Sodan taisteluja 1. Talvisota |url= |location= |publisher=Weilin+Göös |page= |isbn=951-593-911-9|language=Finnish|ref=Raunio}}
*Winter War 1939-40:Finnish Soldier Versus Soviet Soldier by David Campbell
{{Refend}}

==External links==
*[http://heninen.net/raatteentie/kuvia/vanha_e.htm Gallery of the Soviet and Finnish photographs] The Monument of the Winter War website
*[http://ukrainiancrusade.blogspot.com/2016/11/ukrainian-talvisota-unknown-history-of.html Historic article] Ukrainian Talvisota: Unknown history of a Ukrainian Volunteer Regiment in the Finnish War

{{Coord|64|50|53|N|29|19|35|E|type:event_region:FI|display=title}}

[[Category:1940 in Finland]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Winter War|Raate-Road]]
[[Category:History of Kainuu]]
[[Category:Suomussalmi]]
[[Category:January 1940 events]]</text><sha1>c45wf86nruar0zeu1hgewi7jus5q8ar</sha1></revision></page>