<page><title>Battle of Kollaa</title><ns>0</ns><id>6390869</id><revision><id>955271801</id><parentid>950232290</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-06T21:47:22Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Zarex</username><id>1094964</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="4503" xml:space="preserve">{{Unreferenced|date=November 2008}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Kollaa
| image       = Kollaan-taistelut-maalis-1940.png
| image_size  = 240
| caption     =
| partof      = the [[Winter War]]
| date        = December 7, 1939 – March 13, 1940
| place       = [[Kollaa river]], Finland
| result      = Finnish victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|Finland}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1  = [[Woldemar Hägglund]]&lt;br/&gt;'''Division:'''&lt;br/&gt;[[Lauri Tiainen]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Until 31 January)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[Antero Svensson]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;(From 1 February)&lt;/small&gt;
| commander2  = [[Ivan Khabarov]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Until 13 December)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;[[Grigori Shtern]]&lt;br/&gt;&lt;small&gt;(From 13 December)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br/&gt;'''Division:''' (December)&lt;br/&gt;[[M.S. Yevstigneyev]]&lt;br/&gt;'''Corps:''' (February–March)&lt;br/&gt;[[Dmitri Timofeyevich Kozlov|Dmitri Kozlov]]&lt;br/&gt;[[V.G. Vorontsov]]
| strength1   = 1 division and some small units{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}
| strength2   = 4 divisions, 1 tank brigade{{Citation needed|date=February 2007}}
| casualties1 = 1,500 dead or wounded (estimate)
| casualties2 = 8,000 dead or wounded 
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Winter War}}
}}

'''The Battle of Kollaa''' was fought from December 7, 1939, to March 13, 1940, in Ladoga's Karelia, [[Finland]], as a part of the Soviet-Finnish [[Winter War]].

== Description and outcome ==
Despite having far fewer [[troops]] than the [[Soviet Army|Soviets]], the [[Finnish Army|Finnish forces (12th Division)]] repelled the Red Army because the Soviets were only prepared to proceed along [[road]]s. The Kollaa area had very few roads, all of them guarded by Finnish troops; and the Soviets were not able to proceed cross-country without [[ski]]s.

[[File:Finnish leaders the battle of Kollaa.jpg|thumb|left|Finnish military leaders of the battle of Kollaa.]]
Kollaa is often considered to have been one of the most difficult places to defend during the [[Winter War]]. It has been estimated that the Red Army fired almost 40,000 artillery rounds at the defence line during a single day, whereas the Finnish artillery could fire only 1,000 rounds per day at the very most.{{Citation needed|date=March 2009}}

Although the Finnish 12th Division stopped the Red Army, with both sides suffering heavy losses, the Battle of Kollaa continued until the end of the [[Winter War]]. The Red Army managed to penetrate the Finnish defence line in Kollaa several times, thus pushing the Finns out of their positions, but the Finns systematically counter-attacked to restore the integrity of their defence line. The Finnish defence came close to collapse at the very end of the war; in fact, the Soviets managed to form a 0.5–1.5 kilometre deep fracture point in the Finnish defence line on March 12. As a result, the commander of the 12th Division of the Finnish Army considered abandoning the main defence line at Kollaa. However, as the news from the sector was that the situation was "not yet that alarming", the commander ordered a counter-attack for the defence line to be retaken the following day. As the news of the concluded peace treaty then reached the front, those orders were cancelled and the men were told to hold their current positions until the end of hostilities.

== New expression of Finnish resolve ==
A famous quote from the Battle of Kollaa is [[Major General]] Hägglund's question, "Will Kollaa hold? (''Kestääkö Kollaa?'')", to which [[Lieutenant]] [[Aarne Juutilainen]] replied, "Kollaa will hold (''Kollaa kestää''), unless the orders are to run away."  The simple question and reply have entered Finnish lexicon as an expression of perseverance and resolve in the face of impending difficulty or crisis. The Finnish punk band {{ill|Kollaa Kestää|fi}} uses the name.

== The "White Death" ==
{{Main|Simo Häyhä}}

The legendary Finnish sniper [[Simo Häyhä]], nicknamed the "White Death", served on the Kollaa front. He is credited with only 200 confirmed kills according to Finnish military records.{{Citation needed|date=May 2020}} The true number may amount to 800 kills in total.{{Citation needed|date=May 2020}}

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{coord|62|01|40|N|32|15|20|E|source:nowiki_region:RU|display=title}}

[[Category:Battles and operations of the Winter War|Kollaa]]
[[Category:1939 in Finland]]
[[Category:1940 in Finland]]
[[Category:December 1939 events]]
[[Category:January 1940 events]]
[[Category:February 1940 events]]
[[Category:March 1940 events]]</text><sha1>tbh14ddp8c19gi7v4jfpzb8z8m00jch</sha1></revision></page>