<page><title>Battle of Raseiniai</title><ns>0</ns><id>10944921</id><revision><id>964292520</id><parentid>945942575</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-24T17:21:40Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Renata3</username><id>320236</id></contributor><minor /><comment>fix ref</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="24075" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Raseiniai
| partof      = the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
| image      = File:Battle of Raseiniai Battle Map.jpg
| image_size = 300px
| caption     = Map of the battle
| date        = 23–27 June 1941
| place       = [[Raseiniai]], Lithuania
| result      = German victory
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1  = [[Georg-Hans Reinhardt]]
| commander2  = {{plainlist|
* [[Fyodor Kuznetsov]]
* [[Alexey Kurkin]]
* [[Yegor Solyankin]]{{KIA}}}}
| strength1   = 235–245 tanks{{sfn|Rosado|Bishop|2005|p=66}}{{sfn|Taylor|2003|p=14}}{{ref label|Note|f|f}}
| strength2   = 749 tanks{{sfn|Glantz|2002|p=32}}
| casualties1 = 2/3 of the&lt;br/&gt;(6th Panzer Division and 4th Panzer Group), a few cannons and trucks
| casualties2 = 704 tanks&lt;br/&gt;(crewmen either killed or captured){{sfn|Glantz|2002|p=32}}
| campaignbox =
{{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Campaignbox Barbarossa}}
}}
The '''Battle of Raseiniai''' (23–27 June 1941) was a large tank battle that took place in the early stages of [[Operation Barbarossa]], the German invasion of the Soviet Union. The battle was fought between the elements of the German [[Fourth Panzer Army (Germany)|4th Panzer Group]] and the Soviet [[3rd Mechanized Corps (Soviet Union)|3rd Mechanized Corps]] with the [[12th Mechanised Corps]], in [[Lithuania]], {{convert|75|km|mi|abbr=on}} north-west of [[Kaunas]]. The [[Red Army]] tried to contain and destroy the German troops that had crossed the [[Neman River]] but was unable to prevent them from advancing. 

The result of the battle was the destruction of most of the Soviet armoured forces of the Northwestern Front, which cleared the way for the Germans to attack towards the crossings of the [[Daugava River]] (Western Dvina). The fighting around Raseiniai was one of the main battles of the initial phase of Operation Barbarossa, referred to in Soviet historiography as the [[Border Defensive Battles]] (22–27 June 1941) and formed part of the larger Soviet [[Baltic Operation|Baltic Strategic Defensive Operation]].

==Prelude==
[[Army Group North]], commanded by Field Marshal [[Wilhelm Ritter von Leeb]], and staging in [[East Prussia]] prior to the commencement of the offensive, was the northern of three army groups participating in [[Operation Barbarossa]], the German invasion of the Soviet Union. Army Group North controlled the [[18th Army (Wehrmacht)|18th Army]] and the [[16th Army (Wehrmacht)|16th Army]], along with the [[4th Panzer Group]] (General [[Erich Hoepner]]). The Germans had 20 infantry divisions, three Panzer and three motorized infantry divisions.{{Sfn|Kirchubel|2005|p=26}} Air support was provided by ''[[Luftflotte 1]]'' (1st Air Fleet).{{Sfn|Buttar|2013|p=75}}

The Soviet military administrative control over the [[Baltic republics]] area where the Army Group North would be deployed was exercised by the [[Baltic Military District|Special Baltic Military District]] which after the invasion was renamed into the [[Northwestern Front]] (Colonel General [[Fyodor Kuznetsov]]). The front had the [[8th Army (Soviet Union)|8th]] and [[11th Army (Soviet Union)|11th Armies]] with the [[27th Army (Soviet Union)|27th Armies]] in its second echelon; the Northwestern Front had 28 rifle, 4 tank and 2 motorized divisions.{{Sfn|Kirchubel|2005|p=30}}

On 22 June 1941, the Northwestern Front had two mechanised corps, the [[3rd Mechanised Corps (Soviet Union)|3rd Mechanised Corps]] (Major General [[Alexey Kurkin]]) had 31,975 men{{Sfn|Glantz|1998|p=155}} and 669{{ref label|Note|a|a}} – 672 tanks{{ref label|Note|b|b}} and the [[12th Mechanized Corps (Soviet Union)|12th Mechanized Corps]] (Major General [[Nikolai Shestapolov]]) had 28,832 men{{Sfn|Glantz|1998|p=155}} and 730{{ref label|Note|c|c}} – 749 tanks;{{ref label|Note|d|d}} only BT-7s and T-26 tanks were available.{{ref label|Note|e|e}}

==Battle==

===Initial assault===

[[File:LietuvaRaseiniai.png|thumb|Location map of Lithuania showing Raseiniai]]
The 4th Panzer Group advanced in two spearheads, led by the [[XXXXI Panzer Corps (Germany)|XLI Panzer Corps]] (General [[Georg-Hans Reinhardt]]) and [[LVI Panzer Corps (Germany)|LVI Panzer Corps]] (General [[Erich von Manstein]]). Their objective was to cross the [[Neman River|Neman]] and [[Daugava River|Daugava]], the most difficult natural obstacles in front of the Army Group North and to drive towards [[Leningrad]]. German bombers destroyed many of the signals and communications centers, naval bases and the Soviet airfields from [[Riga]] to [[Kronstadt]]. [[Šiauliai]], [[Vilnius]] and [[Kaunas]] were also bombed. Soviet aircraft had been on one-hour alert but were held on their airfields after the first wave of German bombers passed.{{sfn|Anušauskas|2005|p=162}}

At 9:30 AM on 22 June, Kuznetsov ordered the 3rd and 12th Mechanized corps to take up their counter-attack positions, intending to use them in flanking attacks on the 4th Panzer Group, which had broken through to the river [[Dubysa]] (Dubissa).{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=39}} By noon, the Soviet divisions began to fall back and the German columns then began to swing towards [[Raseiniai]], where Kuznetsov was concentrating his armor for a big counter-attack on the next day. By the evening, Soviet formations had fallen back to the Dubysa. North-west of Kaunas, forward elements of [[LVI Panzer Corps]] reached the Dubysa and seized the vital [[Ariogala]] road viaduct across it.{{Sfn|Buttar|2013|p=78}}

By the end of 22 June, the German armoured spearheads over the Niemen had penetrated {{convert|80|km|mi|abbr=on}}. The next day, Kuznetsov committed his armoured forces to battle. Near Raseiniai, the XLI Panzer Corps was counter-attacked by the Soviet 3rd and 12th Mechanised Corps. The concentration of Soviet armour was detected by the Luftwaffe, which immediately attacked tank columns of the 12th Mechanised Corps south-west of Šiauliai. No Soviet fighters appeared and the Soviet [[23rd Tank Division (Soviet Union)|23rd Tank Division]] sustained particularly severe losses, [[Ju 88]]s from ''Luftflotte 1'' attacking at low level, setting 40 vehicles, including tanks and lorries on fire.{{sfn|Bergstrom|2007|p=23}}

German forces encountered a unit equipped with the Soviet [[Kliment Voroshilov tank|KV]] heavy tanks for the first time. On 23 June, ''[[Kampfgruppe]]'' von Seckendorff of the [[6th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|6th Panzer Division]], consisting of [[114th Panzergrenadier Regiment]] (motorized infantry), ''Aufklärungsabteilung'' 57 (Panzer Reconnaissance [[Battalion]] 57), one company of ''[[Panzerjäger]]'' Battalion 41 and Motorcycle Battalion 6 was overrun by the [[2nd Tank Division (Soviet Union)|2nd Tank Division]] (General [[Yegor Solyankin]]) from the 3rd Mechanised Corps near [[Skaudvilė]].{{sfn|Raus|2003|p=13}}{{ref label|Note|f|f}} The German [[Panzer 35(t)]] tanks and anti-tank weapons were ineffective against the Soviet heavy tanks, some of which were out of ammunition but closed in and destroyed German antitank guns by driving over them.{{sfn|Zaloga|Kinnear|Sarson|1995|pp=17{{endash}}18}}{{sfn|Raus|2003|pp=21{{endash}}25}}{{ref label|Note|g|g}}

The Germans fired at the tracks of the KVs, bombarded them with [[artillery]], anti-aircraft guns or [[Hafthohlladung|sticky bombs]]. A report of the [[1st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|1st Panzer Division]] described the engagement,

{{quote|The [[KV-1 (tank)|KV-1]] and [[KV-2]], which we first met here, were really something! Our companies opened fire at about 800 yards, but it remained ineffective. We moved closer and closer to the enemy, who for his part continued to approach us unconcerned. Very soon we were facing each other at 50 to 100 yards. A fantastic exchange of fire took place without any visible German success. The Russian {{bracket|''[[sic]]'' - Soviet}} tanks continued to advance, and all armour-piercing shells simply bounced off them. Thus we were presently faced with the alarming situation of the Russian tanks driving through the ranks of 1st Panzer Regiment towards our own infantry and our hinterland. Our Panzer Regiment therefore about turned and rumbled back with the KV-1s and KV-2s, roughly in line with them. In the course of that operation we succeeded in immobilizing some of them with special purpose shells at very close range 30 to 60 yards. A counter attack was launched and the Russians  were thrown back. A protective front established and defensive fighting continued.{{sfn|Carrell|1964|pp=23{{endash}}24}}}}

===The lone Soviet tank===

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-209-0091-11, Russland-Nord, russischer Panzer KW-2.jpg|thumb|An abandoned Soviet [[KV-2]] tank left by the roadside inspected by curious German soldiers. One KV-2, in some accounts, held up the entire [[6th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|6th Panzer Division]] for a single day before being finally overwhelmed.{{sfn|Raus|2003|p=33}}]]
A single KV-1 or KV-2 tank (accounts vary) advanced far behind the German lines after attacking a column of German trucks. The tank stopped on a road across soft ground and was engaged by four {{nowrap|50 mm}} anti-tank guns of the 6th Panzer Division's anti-tank battalion. The tank was hit several times but fired back and disabled all four enemy AT guns. A heavy [[88 mm gun]] of the divisional anti-aircraft battalion was moved about {{convert|730|m|yd|abbr=on}} behind the lone Soviet tank but was knocked out by the tank before it could manage to score a hit. During the night, German combat engineers tried to destroy the tank with [[satchel charge]]s but failed despite possibly damaging the vehicle's tracks. Early on the morning of June 25, German tanks fired on the KV from the nearby woodland while another {{nowrap|88 mm}} gun fired at the tank from its rear. Of several shots fired, only two managed to penetrate the tank. German infantry then advanced towards the KV tank and it responded with machine-gun fire against them. Eventually, the tank was knocked out by grenades thrown into the hatches. According to some accounts, the dead crew was recovered and buried by the approaching German soldiers with full military honors, while in other accounts, the crew escaped from their crippled tank during the night.{{Sfn|Buttar|2013|p=85}}

The [[6th Panzer Division]] ''Kampfgruppe'' commander, General [[Erhard Raus]], described it as a [[KV-1]], which was damaged by several shots from an {{nowrap|88 mm}} [[Anti-tank warfare|anti-tank]] gun fired from behind the vehicle, while it was distracted by light Panzer 35(t) tanks from Panzer Battalion 65.{{ref label|Note|h|h}} The KV-1 crew were killed by [[Combat engineering|a pioneer engineer]] unit who pushed [[grenades]] through two holes made by the AT gun while the turret began moving again, with the other five or six shots having not fully penetrated. Apparently, the KV-1 crew had only been stunned by the shots which had entered the turret and were buried nearby with military honors by the German unit.{{Sfn|Raus|2003|pp=32{{endash}}33}}

In 1965, the remains of the crew were exhumed and reburied at the Soviet military cemetery in Raseiniai. According to research by Russian military historian Maksim Kolomiets, the tank may have been from the 3rd Company of the 1st Battalion of the 4th Tank Regiment, itself a part of the 2nd Tank Division. It is impossible to identify the crew because their personal documents were lost after being buried in the woods north of Raseiniai during the retreat, possibly by German troops.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite news|url=http://www.mk.ru/social/2015/04/29/odin-den-iz-zhizni-klimenta-voroshilova.html|title=Один день из жизни "Климента Ворошилова"|last=Dobrovolsky|first=Alexander|date=29 April 2015|work=Moskovsky Komsomolets|language=Russian|trans-title=A Day in the Life of a Kliment Voroshilov|access-date=11 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Conclusion of the battle===

In the south, by 23 June, Lieutenant-General [[Vasili Morozov (general)|Vasily Ivanovich Morozov]], the [[11th Army (Soviet Union)|11th Army commander]], ordered the units falling back to the old fortress town Kaunas on the Niemen to move on to [[Jonava]] some {{convert|30|mi|km|abbr=on|order=flip}} to the north-east. By the evening of 25 June, the Soviet 8th Army was falling back towards Riga and the 11th Army towards Vilnius and the [[Desna River|Desna]], a gap opening in the Soviet front from [[Ukmergė]] to Daugavpils. By 26 June, the 1st Panzer Division and [[36th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|36th Motorised Infantry Division]] of the [[XXXXI Panzer Corps|XLI Panzer Corps]] and following infantry divisions had cut through the rear of the Soviet mechanised corps and linked up. The Soviet 3rd Mechanised Corps had run out of fuel and the 2nd Tank Division was encircled and almost destroyed.{{sfn|Glantz|2002|p=33}} In the encirclement, Solyankin was killed in action.{{Sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=42}} The [[5th Tank Division (Soviet Union)|5th Tank Division]] and [[84th Motorised Division (Soviet Union)|84th Motorised Division]] were severely depleted due to losses in vehicles and personnel.{{sfn|Glantz|1998|p=126}}{{ref label|Note|i|i}} The 12th Mechanized Corps pulled out of the trap but was very short of fuel and ammunition.{{sfn|Glantz|1998|p=128}}{{ref label|Note|j|j}} The Soviet Baltic Fleet was withdrawn from bases in [[Liepāja]], Ventspils and Rīga by 26 June and LVI Panzer Corps dashed for the River Daugava and in a remarkable coup seized bridges near Daugava intact.{{sfn|Glantz|1998|p=133}}

==Aftermath==
The battle is known in Soviet historiography as the Border Defensive Battles (22–27 June 1941), forming part of the larger Soviet [[Baltic Operation|Baltic Strategic Defensive Operation]]. After the battle, the leading formations of LVI Panzer Corps began to enlarge the bridgehead after the seizure of the Dvina bridges and the fall of [[Dvinsk]]. On 25 June, Marshal [[Semyon Timoshenko]] ordered Kuznetsov to organize a defense of the Western Dvina, by deploying the 8th Army on the right bank from Riga to [[Livani]] while the 11th Army defended the Livani–[[Kraslava]] sector. Kuznetsov also used the 27th Army (Major-General [[Nikolai Berzarin]]), moving troops from [[Hiiumaa]] and [[Saaremaa]] islands and Riga to Daugavpils. At the same time the Soviet ([[Stavka]]) released the [[21st Mechanized Corps (Soviet Union)|21st Mechanised Corps]] (Major-General [[Dmitry Lelyushenko]]) with 98 tanks and 129 guns, from the [[Moscow Military District]] to co-operate with the 27th Army.{{sfn|Taylor|2003|p=43}}

At {{nowrap|5:00 a.m.,}} on 28 June, Lelyushenko attempted to destroy the German bridgehead near Daugavpils. Manstein halted on the Dvina but attacked the next day, striking along the Daugavpils–[[Ostrov, Ostrovsky District, Pskov Oblast|Ostrov]] highway. At Riga on the afternoon of 29 June, the Germans crossed the railway bridge over the Dvina. On 30 June, Soviet troops withdrew from the right bank of the river and by 1 July were retreating towards [[Estonia]]. Instead of rushing Leningrad, the panzer divisions were ordered to wait for infantry reinforcements, which took almost a week.{{sfn|Glantz|2005|p=70}}

Kuznetsov was sacked by Timoshenko and Major-General [[Pyotr Sobennikov]], the 8th Army commander, took over the front on 4 July. On 29 June, Timoshenko ordered that if the Northwestern Front had to withdraw from the Daugava, the line of the [[Velikaya River|Velikaya]], was to be held and every effort made to get Soviet troops dug in there. The line at Velikaya fell rapidly on 8 July, with rail and road bridges remaining intact and [[Pskov]] fell on the evening of 9 July. The 11th Army was ordered to move to [[Dno]] but the collapse of the Northwestern Front on the Velikaya and the German sweep to [[Luga River|Luga]] were serious defeats, forcing the 8th Army towards the [[Gulf of Finland]]. The German pause had given time for more troops to be rushed to the [[Siege of Leningrad]], a long and hard battle.{{sfn|Glantz|2005|p=70}}

==References==

=== Footnotes ===
{{refbegin}}
{{notelist}}
* {{note label|Note|a|a}} David Glantz (2010) wrote that 3rd Mechanized Crops had 669 tanks, of which 101 were KV-1s and T-34s, 431 were BT-7s, and the remainder older model T-28 and T-26 tanks.{{Sfn|Glantz|2010|p=36}}
* {{note label|Note|b|b}} Steven Zaloga (2015) wrote that the 3rd Mechanized Crops had 672 tanks, of which were 50 [[T-34]]s and with two divisions consisted of 78 heavy [[KV tank|KV-1s]] tanks.{{Sfn|Zaloga|2015|p=102}}
* {{note label|Note|c|c}} Steven Zaloga (2015) wrote that the 12th Mechanized Crops had 730 tanks available.{{Sfn|Zaloga|2015|p=102}}
* {{note label|Note|d|d}} David Glantz (1998) wrote that the 12th Mechanized Crops had 749 tanks available.{{Sfn|Glantz|1998|p=155}}
* {{note label|Note|e|e}} Robert Forczyk (2014) wrote that the 12th Mechanized Crops had 725 tanks available, of which were 483 T-26 and 242 BT's.{{Sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=30}}
* {{note label|Note|f|f}}On entering the Soviet Union in [[Operation Barbarossa]] the [[6th Panzer Division]] had a total of 235–245 tanks, which consisted of about 47 [[Panzer II]]s, 155 [[Panzer 35(t)]]s, 30 [[Panzer IV]]s, 5 Panzerbef 35(t)s (command tanks) and 8 Panzerbefs.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=6th Panzer Division, Order of Battle of 22 June, 1941 |url=http://www.2ndbn5thmar.com/history/6thPzDiv1941.pdf |publisher= |accessdate=15 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;
* {{note label|Note|g|g}}The tanks were eventually destroyed by [[Artillery battery|batteries]] of [[88 mm gun|88mm flak guns]] and [[Field artillery|100mm artillery guns]] employed in an [[Anti-tank warfare|anti-tank]] role.{{Sfn|Raus|2003|pp=24{{endash}}25}}
* {{note label|Note|h|h}}[[Kampfgruppe]] [[Erhard Raus|Raus]] consisted of Panzer Regiment 11, one [[battalion]] of the 4th [[Motorized infantry]] [[Regiment]], the 2nd [[Battalion]]s of the 76th [[Field artillery|Artillery]] [[Regiment]], one company of [[Combat engineering|Panzer Engineer]] [[Battalion]] 57, one company from [[Panzerjäger]] [[Battalion]] 41, one [[Artillery battery|battery]] of the 2nd [[Battalion]] [[Anti-aircraft warfare|Flak]] [[Regiment]] 411 and Motorcycle [[Battalion]] 6 (afternoon).{{sfn|Raus|2003|p=13}}
* {{note label|Note|i|i}}On 11 July 1941 Colonel P Poluboiarov, [[Northwestern Front]] armoured directorate, reported that the [[3rd Mechanised Corps (Soviet Union)|3rd Mechanised Corps]] had "completely perished" having only 400 men remaining who escaped encirclement with 2nd Tank Division and only 1 [[BT-8|BT-7]] tank. German Sources reported the destruction of more than 200 tanks, including 29 [[KV tank|KV-1s]], 150 guns and hundreds of trucks and other vehicles. The 5th Tank Division was at [[Yelnya]] by 4 July 1941 and consisted of 2,552 men and a total of two [[BT-7]] tanks and four armoured cars. It was destroyed at the [[Battle of Białystok–Minsk]].{{sfn|Glantz|1998|p=126}}
* {{note label|Note|j|j}}Colonel Grinberg temporary commander of the [[12th Mechanized Corps (Soviet Union)|12th Mechanized Corps]] after the death of his corps' original commander Major General Shestopalov, reported on 29 July that the strength of his corps had fallen to under 17,000 men after the first two weeks of combat.{{sfn|Glantz |1998|p=128}}
{{refend}}

=== Citations ===
{{Reflist|20em}}

===Bibliography===
* {{cite book |editor-last=Anušauskas |editor-first=Arvydas|title=Lietuva, 1940–1990 |trans-title=Lithuania, 1940–1990 |year=2005 |publisher= [[Genocide and Resistance Research Centre of Lithuania]] |location=Vilnius |isbn=9986-757-65-7|language=lt|display-editors=etal }}
* {{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=adAMAQAAMAAJ|title=Barbarossa – The Air Battle: July–December 1941|last=Bergstrom|first=Christer|publisher=Ian Allan Publishing|year=2007|isbn=978-1-85780-270-2|location=Shepperton, United Kingdom |via=}}
* {{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=iqudCwAAQBAJ|title=Between Giants: The Battle for the Baltics in World War II|last=Buttar|first=Prit|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=2013|isbn=9781472802873|location=Oxford|pages= |author-link=Prit Buttar|via=}}
* {{Cite book|title=Hitler Moves East, 1941{{endash}}1943|last=Carrell|first=Paul|publisher=Little, Brown|year=1964|location=Boston|oclc=786159838 |author-link=Paul Carell|via=}}
* {{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/?id=-2ptBQAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Tank Warfare on the Eastern Front 1941–1942: Schwerpunkt|last=Forczyk|first=Robert|publisher=Pen &amp; Sword|year=2014|isbn=9781781590089|location=Barnsley, South Yorkshire|pages= |via=}}
* {{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NgJnAAAAMAAJ|title=Stumbling Colossus: The Red Army on the Eve of World War|last=Glantz|first=David M.|publisher=University Press of Kansas|year=1998|isbn=0-7006-0879-6|location=Lawrence, Kansas |author-link=David Glantz|via=}}
* {{Cite book|url=https://archive.org/details/battleforleningr00glan|url-access=registration|title=The Battle for Leningrad 1941–1944|last=Glantz|first=David M.|publisher=University Press of Kansas|year=2002|isbn=0-7006-1208-4|location=Lawrence, Kansas |via=}}
* {{cite book|title=Colossus Reborn: The Red Army at War 1941–1943|last=Glantz|first=David M.|date=2005|publisher=University Press of Kansas|isbn=0-7006-1353-6|location=Lawrence }}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SDfInc6Gb40C|title=Barbarossa Derailed: The Battle for Smolensk 10 July – 10 September 1941. Volume 1: The German Advance, The Encirclement Battle, and the First and Second Soviet Counteroffensives, 10 July-24 August 1941|last=Glantz|first=David M.|date=2010|publisher=Helion &amp; Company|isbn=978-1906033729|location=|pages= |via=}}
* {{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=fLLvCwAAQBAJ|title=Operation Barbarossa 1941 (2): Army Group North|last=Kirchubel|first=Robert|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=2005|isbn=978-1841768571|location=Oxford|pages= |via=}}
* {{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Zyn_AgAAQBAJ|title=Panzer Operations: The Eastern Front Memoir of General Raus, 1941{{endash}}1945|last=Raus|first=Erhard|publisher=Da Capo Press|others=Compiled and Translated by Steven H. Newton|year=2003|isbn=0-306-81247-9|location=Cambridge, Massachusetts |via=|pages=|author-link=Erhard Raus}}
* {{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cDQ1AAAACAAJ|title=German Wehrmacht Panzer Divisions 1939{{endash}}45|last=Rosado|first=Jorge|last2=Bishop|first2=Chris|publisher=Amber Books|year=2005|isbn=1-90468-746-6|location=London|pages= |via=}}
* {{Cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=ECTvAAAAMAAJ|title=Barbarossa to Berlin: A Chronology of the Campaigns on the Eastern Front 1941 to 1945|last=Taylor|first=Brian|publisher=Spellmount|year=2003|isbn=1-862-27206-9|volume=1|location=Staplehurst, Kent, United Kingdom |via=}}
* {{Cite book|title=KV-1 &amp; 2 Heavy Tanks 1939{{endash}}45|last=Zaloga|first=Steven J.|last2=Kinnear|first2=Jim|last3=Sarson|first3=Peter|publisher=Osprey Publishing|year=1995|isbn=1-85532-496-2|location=|pages= |author-link=Steven Zaloga|via=}}
* {{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books/about/Armored_Champion.html?id=Y-O3DAAAQBAJ|title=Armored Champion: The Top Tanks of World War II|last=Zaloga|first=Steven J.|date=2015|publisher=Stackpole Books|isbn=978-0811714372|location=|pages= |via=}}

{{coord|55|21|N|23|17|E|display=title|region:LT_type:event}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Military of Germany
| portal2=Soviet Union
| portal3=World War II
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Raseiniai 1941}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1941]]
[[Category:1941 in Lithuania|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Operation Barbarossa]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:Lithuania in World War II]]
[[Category:Tank battles involving Germany]]
[[Category:Tank battles involving the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:June 1941 events|{{PAGENAME}}]]
[[Category:Tank battles of World War II]]</text><sha1>d7ezqydlqrq958xmt5y40yjs9516cti</sha1></revision></page>