<page><title>Pripyat swamps (punitive operation)</title><ns>0</ns><id>12033567</id><revision><id>929743646</id><parentid>927209225</parentid><timestamp>2019-12-07T23:10:17Z</timestamp><contributor><username>LilHelpa</username><id>8024439</id></contributor><minor /><comment>[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], replaced: the their → their, [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: № → No.</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="9072" xml:space="preserve">'''"Pripyat swamps"''' ({{lang-de|"Pripiatsümpfe"}}), also '''"Pripyat march"''' was the codename of a punitive operation conducted by German forces in July and August 1941. The operation was aimed at the mass murder of the local Jewish population&lt;ref&gt;By the definition of Alexey Litvin, who considers that the previous definition of operation, given by V. Lazyebnikaw and V. Pase, "''operation... against the encircled units of Red Army, partisans and local population''", is overly generalized and so imprecise.&lt;/ref&gt; from the territories of nine [[raion]]s of [[Byelorussian SSR]] and three raions of [[Ukrainian SSR]] in the region of the Pripyat swamps and [[Pripyat River]].

The operation is considered to be the first planned mass extermination operation conducted by [[Nazi Germany]].&lt;ref name=ALitvin/&gt; In the course of the operation, at least 13,788 people were killed in phase one and 3,500 Jewish men were killed in phase two.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=309}} The villages of Dvarets, Khochan', Azyarany, Starazhowtsy and Kremna, were completely destroyed by burning and [[Turaw]] was partially destroyed. The principal means of execution employed was mass shootings, after the local populace had been rounded up. Other methods were also tried, including driving people into the swamps and drowning them, though this was largely ineffective owing to their shallowness.

==History==
The operation was ordered by ''[[Reichsführer-SS]]'' [[Heinrich Himmler]] to be conducted by the [[SS Cavalry Brigade]], as well as the [[Wehrmacht]]'s [[162nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|162nd Infantry Division]] and [[252nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|252nd Infantry Division]]s, under the general command of [[HSSPF]] [[Erich von dem Bach]].&lt;ref name=LazPase/&gt; Beginning on 28 July 1941 and lasting until August,{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=79, 119}} the operation was conducted in two stages, with the second stage beginning on 14 August. There is no data on the SS troops' losses in their reports.&lt;ref name=ALitvin/&gt;

Captured German documents about the operation reached Moscow in January 1942, and were published in the USSR People Commissary (Minister) of Foreign Relations note, issued on 27 April. The note was addressed to all countries with which USSR had maintained diplomatic relations. It is believed that the international publicity and shock caused by this data prompted Nazis to hide or destroy other materials concerned with this operation.&lt;ref name=ALitvin/&gt;

==Beginning of the events==
On 19 July 1941, the [[1st SS Cavalry Regiment|1st]] and [[2nd SS Cavalry Regiment|2nd]] SS Cavalry Regiments were assigned to the general command of [[HSSPF]] [[Erich von dem Bach]] for the action which took place in two stages. The beginning date of the operation is considered 28 July 1941.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=79}} On that day the two SS cavalry regiments were transferred to [[Baranavichy]] for the "systematic combing of the Pripyat swamps".{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=309}}

Shortly thereafter, Himmler ordered the [[SS Cavalry Brigade]] to be formed under the command of [[Hermann Fegelein]] from the 1st and 2nd SS Cavalry Regiments.{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=309}} Also, Himmler ordered von dem Bach to present him with the military plan of the extermination operation.&lt;ref&gt;This plan has not been found, so the information on it has had to be reconstructed. Litvin, 2003&lt;/ref&gt; The "Special order" of Himmler dated 28 July 1941 ordered von dem Bach to harshly exterminate the Pripyat swamps region's population "with disagreeable attitude to Germans"&lt;ref name="turonek-101"&gt;Turonek, p. 101&lt;/ref&gt; — to shoot men, deport women and children, confiscate livestock and food, burn habitations. On the other hand, population "showing agreeable attitude to Germans" was to be "spared" and even to be partially armed.&lt;ref name="turonek-101"/&gt; Himmler's orders for the operation were passed to Fegelein via ''[[SS-Brigadefuhrer]]'' Kurk Knoblauch, who met with him and Bach-Zelewski on 28 July in their new quarters at Liakhovichi in Byelorussia. Fegelein interpreted these orders as follows: Enemy soldiers in uniform were to be taken prisoner, and those found out of uniform were to be shot. Jewish males, with the exception of a few skilled workers such as doctors and leather workers, would be shot.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=80–81}} Fegelein split the territory to be covered into two sections divided by the [[Pripyat River]], with the 1st Regiment taking the northern half and the 2nd Regiment the south.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=81}} The regiments worked their way from east to west through their assigned territory, and filed daily reports on the number of people killed and taken prisoner.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=81}}

Himmler notified Fegelein by telegram on 1 August that the numbers killed so far were too low. A few days later, Himmler issued regimental order no. 42, which called for all male Jews over the age of 14 to be killed. The women and children were to be driven into the swamps and drowned. Thus Fegelein's units were among the first in [[the Holocaust]] to wipe out entire Jewish communities.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=86, 88–89}} As the water in the swamps was too shallow and some areas had no swamps, it proved impractical to drown the women and children, so in the end they were shot as well.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=89–90}}

==The first stage==
The forces of 1st SS Cavalry Regiment moved from [[Baranavichy]] in the direction of [[Lyakhavichy]] — [[Hantsavichy]], [[Baranavichy]] — [[Ivatsevichy]] — [[Byaroza]] — [[Pruzhany]], and "combed" the territory to the south, south-east and south-west reaching the Pripyat River. The forces of 2nd SS Cavalry Regiment moved from [[Lutsk]] in the directions of [[Kamen'-Kashirski]] — [[Drahichyn]] — [[Ivanava]] and [[Sarny]] — [[Luninyets]] — [[Pinsk]], and searched the territory to the south and north of the Pripyat River, until making contact with 1st SS Cavalry Regiment.

Coordinating with the 2nd SS Cavalry Regiment's move, ''[[Einsatzgruppe]]'' B conducted the mass extermination of the Jewish population in Pinsk. Besides that, several elements of the 1st and 2nd SS Cavalry Regiments formed the leading force to block Soviet forces which broke out of the encirclement in the vicinity of [[Slutsk]]—[[Babruysk]] highway on 27 July.&lt;ref name=ALitvin/&gt;

==The second stage==
The forces of the SS Cavalry Brigade moved from the initial line of [[Baranavichy]] — [[Luninyets]] railroad to the east, conducting the "cleansing" of the right and left banks of the Pripyat River keeping south of the highway R-1 ([[Brest, Belarus|Brest]] — [[Slutsk]] — [[Babruysk]]).

In the course of this stage, the 2nd Regiment fought one or two battalions of the Soviet regular and irregular troops on 21 August 1941 near [[Turaw]]. According to the report of 29 August, the brigade's losses were 23 dead and wounded, and the losses of Soviet troops were from 600 to 700 dead and 10 prisoners.

In the course of following days the 1st Regiment combed the region of [[Starobin]] — [[Lyuban, Belarus|Lyuban]] — [[Ptsich]], and the 2nd Regiment advanced to the east of the line of [[Kol'na]] — [[Lyakhavichy]] ([[Knyaz'-Vozyera]]) towards the [[Ptsich River]]. The second stage of the operation ended on either 29 August&lt;ref name=ALitvin&gt;(Litvin 2003)&lt;/ref&gt; or 31 August.&lt;ref name=LazPase&gt;(Lazyebnikaw and Pase)&lt;/ref&gt; Fegelein's final report on the operation, dated 18 September, states that they killed 14,178 Jews, 1,001 partisans, and 699 Red Army soldiers with losses of 17 dead, 36 wounded, and 3 missing.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|pp=119–120}}{{sfn|Miller|2006|p=310}}  The historian Henning Pieper estimates the actual number of Jews killed was closer to 23,700.{{sfn|Pieper|2015|p=120}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
* (Lazyebnikaw and Pase) Лазебнікаў В. С., Пасэ У. С. Прыпяцкія балоты // Belarusian Soviet Encyclopedia, V.8. p.&amp;nbsp;604.
* (Litvin 2003) Литвин Алексей. Убийцы // Советская Белоруссия No.226 (21892), 3.12.2003. — [http://www.sb.by/article.php?articleID=33062 Newspaper's archive in the net].
* {{cite book | last = Miller | first = Michael | year = 2006 | title = Leaders of the SS and German Police, Vol. 1 | publisher = R. James Bender | location = San Jose, CA | isbn = 978-9-3297-0037-2 | ref = harv }}
*{{cite book | last = Pieper | first = Henning | year = 2015 | title = Fegelein's Horsemen and Genocidal Warfare: The SS Cavalry Brigade in the Soviet Union | publisher = Palgrave Macmillan | location = Houndmills, Basingstoke, Hampshire | isbn = 978-1-137-45631-1 | ref = harv }}
* (Turonek) Jerzy Turonek. Białoruś pod okupacją niemiecką. Warszawa—Wrocław: WERS, 1989. 186 p., ill.

{{Holocaust Ukraine}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Pripyat swamps 1941}}
[[Category:The Holocaust]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Belarus]]
[[Category:The Holocaust in Ukraine]]
[[Category:Anti-partisan operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Mass murder in 1941]]</text><sha1>k53jtpa2q2kp0xgi09qqw27v5oj0ldq</sha1></revision></page>