<page><title>Siege of Odessa (1941)</title><ns>0</ns><id>4768077</id><revision><id>966134856</id><parentid>954537202</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-05T08:10:53Z</timestamp><contributor><username>CommonsDelinker</username><id>2304267</id></contributor><comment>Removing [[:c:File:Lyudmila_Pavlichenko,_before_title.png|Lyudmila_Pavlichenko,_before_title.png]], it has been deleted from Commons by [[:c:User:Túrelio|Túrelio]] because: Can be undeleted in 2063.</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="21178" xml:space="preserve">{{Redirects|Siege of Odessa|the naval battle at Odessa in 1914|Battle of Odessa (1914)}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{More footnotes|date=June 2011}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Siege of Odessa
| partof      = the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = File:Romanian troops in odessa WWII.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = Romanian troops in Odessa after the siege
| date        = 8 August – 16 October 1941 (2 months, and 8 days)
| place       = [[Odessa]] region, [[Ukrainian SSR]], [[Soviet Union]]
| result      = Axis victory, subsequent [[1941 Odessa massacre]]
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Romania}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}&lt;br/&gt;'''Aerial support:'''&lt;br&gt;{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1  = 
{{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} [[Ion Antonescu]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} [[Alexandru Ioanițiu]]{{KIA}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} [[Iosif Iacobici]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} [[Nicolae Ciupercă]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Erich von Manstein]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Georgiy Sofronov]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Ivan Yefimovich Petrov|Ivan Petrov]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|naval}} [[Gavriil Zhukov]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|naval}} [[Filipp Oktyabrskiy]] 
| units1      = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} [[Fourth Army (Romania)|4th Army]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[11th Army (Wehrmacht)|11th Army]]
| units2      = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[9th Army (Soviet Union)|9th Independent Army]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Separate Coastal Army]]
| strength1= 160,000 men (initially)&lt;ref&gt;Axworthy (1995), p. 50.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;340,223 men (total)
| strength2= 34,500 men (initial)&lt;ref name=glantz&gt;Glantz (1995), p. 293&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;240 artillery pieces&lt;br&gt;120,000+ men (total)
| casualties1 = 92,545 overall&lt;br/&gt;17,729 dead&lt;br/&gt;63,345 wounded&lt;br/&gt;11,471 missing&lt;br/&gt;19 tanks&lt;br/&gt;90 artillery pieces&lt;br/&gt;20 aircraft&lt;ref name="worldwar2.ro"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.worldwar2.ro/operatii/?article=7|title=
The Battle of Odessa - 1941|publisher=WorldWar2.ro}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = '''Low estimate:''' 41,268 overall&lt;ref name=glantz/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;16,578 dead/missing&lt;br/&gt;24,690 wounded&lt;br/&gt;1 armored train&lt;br/&gt;151 aircraft&lt;br/&gt;'''High estimate:''' 60,000 overall&lt;ref name=Axworthy&gt;Axworthy, Mark. Third Axis Fourth Ally: Romanian Armed Forces in the European War, 1941–1945. p. 58.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''Naval losses to Romanian forces:'''&lt;br&gt;1 destroyer possibly damaged&lt;br&gt;1 armed merchantman captured
| campaignbox = 
{{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Campaignbox Barbarossa}}
{{Romanian military actions in World War II}}
}}
The '''Siege of Odessa''', known to the Soviets as the '''Defence of Odessa''', lasted from 8 August until 16 October 1941, during the early phase of [[Operation Barbarossa]], the [[Axis powers|Axis]] invasion of the [[Soviet Union]] during [[World War II]].

[[Odessa]] was a port on the [[Black Sea]] in the [[Ukrainian SSR]]. On 22 June 1941, the Axis powers invaded the Soviet Union. In August, Odessa became a target of the Romanian [[4th Army (Romania)|4th Army]] and elements of the German [[11th Army (Wehrmacht)|11th Army]].  Due to the heavy resistance of the Soviet [[9th Army (Soviet Union)|9th Independent Army]] and the rapidly formed [[Separate Coastal Army]], supported by the [[Black Sea Fleet]], it took the Axis forces 73 days of [[siege]] and four assaults to take the city. Romanian forces suffered 93,000 casualties, against Red Army casualties estimated to be between 41,000 and 60,000.&lt;ref name=Axworthy /&gt;

==Prelude==
On 27 July 1941, [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]] sent a letter to General [[Ion Antonescu]] in which he recognised the Romanian administration of the territory between the [[Dniester]] and the [[Southern Bug|Bug river]]s. The [[Romanian Third Army]] had already crossed the Dniester on 17 July. Lieutenant-general [[Nicolae Ciupercă]]'s [[Fourth Army (Romania)|Fourth Army]] advanced over the river on 3 August, with the 5th Corps, comprising the 15th Infantry Division and 1st Cavalry Brigade, joined by the [[1st Armored Division (Romania)|1st Armored Division]]. On 8 August, the Romanian General Staff issued the Operative Directive No. 31 instructing the 4th Army to occupy Odessa off the march. It was thought that the city garrison, which was heavily outnumbered, would surrender quickly.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

Odessa was heavily fortified by three defensive lines and, thanks to the presence of the [[Soviet Black Sea Fleet]], could not be completely surrounded. The first line was 80&amp;nbsp;km long and situated 25–30&amp;nbsp;km from the city. The second and main line of defense was situated 6–8&amp;nbsp;km from the city and was about 30&amp;nbsp;km long. The third and last line of defense was organized inside the city itself. The forces that initially manned the fortifications were made up of the [[25th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|25th]] and [[95th Rifle Division|95th Rifle Divisions]], the [[2nd Cavalry Division (Soviet Union)|2nd Cavalry Division]], the [[421st Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|421st Rifle Division]], the 54th Rifle Regiment and an [[NKVD]] Regiment. The Red Army had 34,500 men and 240 artillery pieces in the area. Air support was provided by the 69th Fighter Aviation Regiment, two seaplane squadrons and one bomber squadron. Later, other fighters joined the defenders, as did an [[Ilyushin Il-2|Il-2]] squadron.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

==Battle==
The defense of Odessa lasted 73 days, from 5 August to 16 October 1941. On 10 August, in the sector of the 3rd Corps, the bulk of the 7th Infantry Division reached [[Elssas]], while the 1st Guard Division arrived on the alignment [[Kuchurhan, Rozdilna Raion|Strassburg]] – [[Petra Evdokievka]]. In the sector of the 5th Corps, the 1st Armored Division broke through Odessa's first line of defense. That evening, the Romanian division reached the second line of defense. The 1st Cavalry Brigade took [[Severinovca]] and joined the 1st Armored Division. At the same time, the 10th Dorobanți Regiment overran the Soviet forces at [[Lozova|Lozovaya]]. The 4th Army gradually closed the circle around Odessa, but the offensive was temporarily stopped by Antonescu on 13 August to strengthen the line west of the [[Hadjibey bank]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

The offensive resumed on 16 August, as Romanian troops attacked along the entire line, capturing Odessa's water reservoirs on 17 August. The Soviet forces put up a stubborn resistance, launching repeated counter-attacks, inflicting and taking heavy casualties. The [[Royal Romanian Air Force]] actively supported the ground troops, disrupting Soviet naval traffic to and from Odessa, and also destroying an armored train on 20 August.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

[[File:Odessa Soviet artilery.JPG|thumb|left|A Soviet gun crew during the siege.]]
By 24 August, despite constant attacks, the Romanians were bogged down in front of the Soviets' main line of defense. The 4th Army had already suffered 27,307 casualties, including 5,329 killed in action. Nevertheless, the Soviets were also weakened, and thanks to the capture of Kubanka, Romanian heavy artillery now threatened the port of Odessa. Over the next three days, there was a lull in the fighting.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

On 28 August, the Romanians resumed their offensive, reinforced by a German assault battalion and ten heavy artillery battalions. The [[4th Army Corps (Romania)|4th]], 11th and [[1st Army Corps (Romania)|1st Army Corps]] advanced towards Gnileakovo and Vakarzhany, only to be pushed back in some areas by a strong Soviet counterattack the following day. On 30 August the Romanians retook the initiative, but gained very little ground. Hitler and the German High Command noted that 'Antonescu [was] using at Odessa the tactics of the First World War,' crudely depending upon infantry to make unsupported frontal attacks against Soviet trench line defenses.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Kiev 1941|last = Stahel|first = David|publisher = Cambridge University Press|year = 2012|isbn = 978-1-107-01459-6|location = New York City|pages = 136–37}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviets temporarily retook Kubanka but were driven back by nightfall. Soviet troops in Vakarzhany were encircled and continued to fight until 3 September, when combined German and Romanian infantry successfully stormed the village.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

On 3 September, General Ciupercă submitted a memoir to by-now Marshal Antonescu, highlighting the poor condition of the front-line divisions, which were exhausted after nearly a month of continuous fighting. He proposed a reorganization of six divisions (the 3rd, 6th, 7th, 14th, 21st Infantry and Guard Divisions), which would be split into 2 corps and supported by 8 heavy artillery battalions. These units would then attack in a single area to break through the Soviet line. The memoir however, was rejected by both Antonescu and Brigadier-General [[Alexandru Ioaniţiu]], chief of the [[Romanian General Staff]], who argued that an attack in a single direction would leave the rest of the Romanian line too exposed. Marshal Antonescu subsequently issued a new directive calling for attacks between Tatarka and Dalnik, and Gniliavko and Dalnik, to be made by the 11th and 3rd Corps, respectively. Ioaniţiu forwarded a note to Major-General [[Arthur Hauffe]], chief of the German military mission to Romania, informing him of the situation at Odessa and requesting assistance in the form of aircraft and several pioneer battalions. Although the Royal Romanian Air Force enjoyed some success against the Soviets ground and air forces, it was ill-equipped for anti-shipping raids, and the Soviets were being steadily reinforced and resupplied via the Navy.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}


Meanwhile, the Romanian offensive was halted to wait for reinforcements. A German detachment led by Lieutenant-General [[René von Courbier]] and comprising one infantry regiment, one assault pioneer regiment and two artillery regiments arrived. Concurrently, the Soviets also received 15,000 men and ammunition. On 9 September, Ciupercă was replaced by Lieutenant-General Iosif Iacobici, who was expressly ordered to follow the General Staff's directives without question. The offensive resumed on 12 September, but was again stopped temporarily on September 14 as Romanian and German artillery units were running low on ammunition. Two [[Vânători de munte|Vânători]] battalions were encircled by Red Army troops near the Hadjibey bank, but were eventually relieved despite Soviet efforts to annihilate them.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

On the night of 15 September, Soviet troops broke contact with the Romanian 1st Corps and retreated toward the southeast. On 16 September, the 1st Corps took the heights northwest of Gross-Liebenthal. Romanian troops also occupied the area south of the Sukhoy bank. Over 3,000 Soviet soldiers were captured, but these losses were replaced by the [[157th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|157th Rifle Division]], with a strength of 12,600 troops. Also, 18 Soviet companies were brought in from [[Novorossiysk]]. Partisan fighting continued, however, in the [[Odessa Catacombs|city's catacombs]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

The expected Soviet counteroffensive which was meant to break the siege came during the night of 21/22 September 1941, and it was the climax of the battle for Odessa. Red Army troops established a bridgehead at [[Chebanka]], threatening the Romanian 4th Army's weaker right flank. Before the Soviets could attack, a large formation of 94 Romanian aircraft (32 bombers and 62 fighters) supported by 23 Italian aircraft attacked the Red Army troops as they advanced North. During the ensuing aerial battle, which lasted ten hours, numerous bombing and strafing attacks were carried out against the Soviet bridgehead, as well as numerous dogfights with the Soviet Air Force. The bridgehead was pulverized, with eventually all Soviet troops withdrawing from the area during the night of 4/5 October. Axis air forces destroyed over 20 Soviet aircraft (nine or ten of them during air battles) while losing one Romanian fighter during air combat plus four more either shot down by Soviet flak or destroyed on the ground. One Italian Savoia-Marchetti bomber was also lost.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=4PgwCKQQP1gC&amp;pg=PA165&amp;dq=chebanka+grigorievka&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiui_KIoLDcAhVG2qQKHYFyBfQQ6AEIKjAA#v=onepage&amp;q=chebanka%20grigorievka&amp;f=false Frank Joseph, ''The Axis Air Forces: Flying in Support of the German Luftwaffe'', ABC-CLIO, 2011, p. 165]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=spgeDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA21&amp;dq=chebanka+grigorievka&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjVr_yoobDcAhVDzaQKHW6rCP0Q6AEIMDAB#v=onepage&amp;q=chebanka%20grigorievka&amp;f=false Dénes Bérnad, ''Rumanian Aces of World War 2'', Bloomsbury Publishing, 2012, p. 21]&lt;/ref&gt;

With the advance of Axis forces into the Soviet Union, [[Stavka|STAVKA]] decided to evacuate the defenders of Odessa. On the night of 14–15 October 1941, the Black Sea Fleet evacuated the garrison to [[Siege of Sevastopol (1941–1942)|Sevastopol]] where most of the units were later destroyed in the bitter fighting that took place there during [[Siege of Sevastopol (1941–42)|the Defence of Sevastopol]]. The Black Sea Fleet also managed to evacuate 350,000 soldiers and civilians.&lt;ref name="worldwar2.ro"/&gt;

==Naval warfare==
[[File:Heinkel he 114 san diego air and space museum 2.jpg|thumb|Romanian Heinkel He 114 seaplane]]
In support of the land offensive, the [[Romanian Navy]] dispatched [[motor torpedo boat]]s to the [[Operation München#Fighting in Southern Bessarabia|recently occupied]] port of [[Vylkove]] (Vâlcov in Romanian). During the night of 18 September, the motor torpedo boats [[NMS Viscolul|NMS ''Viscolul'']] and [[NMS Vijelia|NMS ''Vijelia'']] attacked a Soviet convoy south of Odessa, each boat launching her two torpedoes at the closest enemy destroyer. Three of the four torpedoes missed. The fourth torpedo struck and damaged the Soviet destroyer, but failed to detonate.&lt;ref&gt;Jipa Rotaru, Ioan Damaschin, ''Glorie și dramă: Marina Regală Română, 1940-1945'', Ion Cristoiu Publishing, 2000, pp. 74-75 (in Romanian)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jipa Rotaru, Octavian Burcin, Vladimir Zodian, ''Mareșalul Ion Antonescu: Am făcut "războiul sfânt" împotriva bolșevismului: Campania anului 1941'', p. 180 (in Romanian)&lt;/ref&gt; It was one of the few actions the Romanian Navy undertook to support the siege, generally limiting itself to patrols of the submarine ''[[NMS Delfinul|Delfinul]]''. No Western source could be found to confirm this claim.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

On 20 August, ''Delfinul'' fought the only submarine vs submarine engagement of the siege. At 12:08 pm, the Soviet [[Soviet M-class submarine|M-class]] submarine ''M-33'' launched a torpedo at her, which missed. ''Delfinul'' swiftly counterattacked with her twin 13&amp;nbsp;mm machine gun, causing the Soviet submarine to submerge and retreat.&lt;ref&gt;Antony Preston, ''Warship 2001-2002'', Conway Maritime Press, 2001. p. 73&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Asociația Națională a Veteranilor de Război, ''Veteranii pe drumul omoarei și jertfei (1941-1945): de la Nistru la Marea de Azov, Volume 3'', Vasile Cârlova Publishing, 1997, p. 517&lt;/ref&gt;

During the October evacuation, [[Heinkel He 114]] seaplanes of the Romanian Naval Aviation captured a Soviet armed merchantman.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=4PgwCKQQP1gC&amp;pg=PA166&amp;dq=CANT+Z.501+Romania&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjoyq_M_ZncAhUBJlAKHfCZCL8Q6AEIKDAA#v=onepage&amp;q=CANT%20Z.501%20Romania&amp;f=false Frank Joseph, ''The Axis Air Forces: Flying in Support of the German Luftwaffe'', ABC-CLIO, 2011, p. 166]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
The operations at Odessa highlighted significant weaknesses in the Romanian Army, leading both military and political leaders in the country to call for a discontinuation of military operations against the Soviet Union.&lt;ref&gt;Axworthy, page 59&lt;/ref&gt; Antonescu ignored such objections, regarding continued participation and eventual victory on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] as necessary for the restoration of Romania's territorial integrity.&lt;ref&gt;Axworthy, page 49&lt;/ref&gt;

Casualties suffered during the Siege of Odessa were:

* Romanian
** 17,729 dead, 63,345 wounded, and 11,471 missing
* Soviet
** 16,578 dead or missing, and 24,690 wounded (Glantz)
** 60,000 dead, wounded or missing (Axworthy)&lt;ref name=Axworthy /&gt;

The Romanian victory at Odessa represented the most significant victory ever achieved independently by an [[Axis Powers#Subsequent signatories of the Tripartite Pact|Axis satellite]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=wm_YDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA1422&amp;dq=romanian+tanks+chisinau&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwjLvJLxvKncAhXJYVAKHcRTDeUQ6AEILjAB#v=onepage&amp;q=dumitrache&amp;f=false Spencer C. Tucker, ''World War II: The Definitive Encyclopedia and Document Collection (5 volumes)'', ABC-CLIO, 2016, p. 1422]&lt;/ref&gt;

The recapture of Bessarabia and Northern Bukovina in [[Operation München]] and the subsequent victory at Odessa led to a partial demobilization of the Romanian army, which was reduced in size from nearly 900,000 personnel on 1 October to 465,000 on 1 January 1942. Politically, the presence of Romanian troops in Odessa and the establishment of the [[Transnistria Governorate]] led to a deterioration of Romania's international situation, with the British declaring war on Romania on 6 December, and on 12 December Romania declared war on the United States in solidarity with Germany and Japan.&lt;ref&gt;Axworthy, page 73&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commemoration==
[[File:Odessa_(timbre_soviétique).jpg|thumb|upright|Postage stamp of the USSR 1965 “[[Hero City]] Odessa 1941–-1945”]]
Odessa was one of the first four Soviet cities to be awarded the title of "[[Hero City]]" in 1945, the others being [[Siege of Leningrad|Leningrad]], [[Battle of Stalingrad|Stalingrad]], and [[Siege of Sevastopol (1941–42)|Sevastopol]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Dowling |first1=Timothy C. |title=Russia at War: From the Mongol Conquest to Afghanistan, Chechnya, and Beyond |date=2014 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |isbn=9781598849486 |pages=343-344}}&lt;/ref&gt; Museum of the Heroic Defense of Odessa (411th Coastal Battery Memorial) was opened on the day of the 30th anniversary of the victory over Nazi Germany, 9 May 1975.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Museum of Heroic Defense of Odessa(411th Battery) |url=http://www.odessatourism.org/en/do/museums/muzej_geroicheskoj_oborony_odessy_411_ja_batareja |website=odessatourism.org |accessdate=20 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Close by is also the [[Museum of Partisan Glory]] in the [[Odessa Catacombs]]. The underground museum commemorates the partisan movement in the Odessa region.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Museum of Partisan Glory (catacombs) |url=http://www.odessatourism.org/en/do/museums/muzej_partizanskoj_slavy_katakomby |website=odessatourism.org}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Transnistria Governorate]]

==Notes==
&lt;references/&gt;

==References==
* {{cite book|title = Third Axis Fourth Ally: Romanian Armed Forces in the European War, 1941–1945|author1 = Axworthy, Mark|author2 = Scafes, Cornel|author3 = Craciunoiu, Cristian |publisher = Arms &amp; Armour Press |place=London|year = 1995|isbn = 1-85409-267-7}}
*Glantz, David M. &amp; House, Jonathan (1995), ''When Titans Clashed: How the Red Army Stopped Hitler'', Lawrence, Kansas: University Press of Kansas, {{ISBN|0-7006-0899-0}}

==External links==
*[http://www.worldwar2.ro/operatii/?article=7 The Battle of Odessa - 1941], WorldWar2.ro
*[http://www.odessatourism.org/en/do/museums/muzej_partizanskoj_slavy_katakomby Museum of Partisan Glory], Odessa Tourism official web site
* [http://www.odessatourism.org/en/do/museums/muzej_geroicheskoj_oborony_odessy_411_ja_batareja Museum of the Heroic Defence of Odessa (411th Coastal Battery Memorial)], Odessa Tourism official web site
* [http://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/eleanor-roosevelt-and-the-soviet-sniper-23585278/?no-ist Eleanor Roosevelt and the Soviet Sniper], ''Smithsonian Magazine''
{{coord missing|Ukraine}}

[[Category:History of Odessa|Siege]]
[[Category:Sieges involving Romania|Odessa]]
[[Category:Sieges involving Ukraine|Odessa (1941), Battle of]]
[[Category:1941 in Ukraine|Odessa (1941), Battle of]]
[[Category:Military history of Romania during World War II|Odessa (1941), Battle of]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of the European theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Romania–Soviet Union relations]]
[[Category:Operation Barbarossa|Odessa (1941), Battle of]]
[[Category:Sieges involving Germany|Odessa (1941)]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:1941 in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Sieges of World War II|Odessa 1941]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations of World War II|O]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Romania]]
[[Category:August 1941 events]]
[[Category:September 1941 events]]
[[Category:October 1941 events]]</text><sha1>kyrf638mpft5e7s4y2kpw6ysyf0zto1</sha1></revision></page>