<page><title>Bombing of Tallinn in World War II</title><ns>0</ns><id>11137635</id><revision><id>942692668</id><parentid>915696788</parentid><timestamp>2020-02-26T06:50:23Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Estopedist1</username><id>13892613</id></contributor><comment>requested image + wikifying</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="11162" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Bombing of Tallinn during the Second World War}}
{{Campaignbox Estonia 1944}}

[[File:TLA_1465_1_973_Varemetes_Harju_tänav,_vasakul_Kuld_Lõvi_varemed_1944.jpg|thumb|The old town of Tallinn after being bombed by the Soviet Air Forces in March 1944]]
[[File:Estonia threatre after bombing.jpg|thumb|[[Estonia Theatre]] after bombing by the Soviet Air Forces in March 1944]]
[[File:TLA 1465 1 5557 põlev vaekoda 9 10 märts 1944.jpg|thumb|Burning building {{lang-et|vaekoda}}]]

The German [[Luftwaffe]] and Soviet [[Long Range Aviation]] bombed the [[Estonia]]n capital [[Tallinn]] several times during [[World War II]]. The first instance was during the [[Estonia in World War II#Summer War|Summer War]] of 1941 (part of [[Operation Barbarossa|Operation ''Barbarossa'']]). A number of bombing missions followed in 1942–43.

The largest of the bombings occurred in March 1944 in connection with the [[Battle of Narva (1944)|Battle of Narva]] and is known as '''March bombing''' ({{lang-et|märtsipommitamine}}). After Soviet saboteurs had deliberately disabled the water supply, over a thousand incendiary bombs set the defenceless town on fire, killed 757 people, of whom 586 were civilians and 75 prisoners of war, wounded 659, and left over 20,000 people without shelter in the spring thaw.

The Soviet bombings left a legacy of anti-Soviet resentment and resistance, as personified in the slogan ''Varemeist tõuseb kättemaks!'', or "Vengeance Will Rise from the Ruins!", which was also used as a slogan by an Estonian division of the Nazi ''[[Waffen-SS]].''

== Luftwaffe raids in 1941 ==
The Soviet Union took control of Latvia, Lithuania, and [[Estonia in World War II|Estonia]] in 1940 gaining control over the naval bases in the Baltic Sea, including [[Tallinn]].&lt;ref name="The Soviet Dunkirk: The Tallinn Offensive"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://warfarehistorynetwork.com/daily/wwii/the-soviet-dunkirk-the-tallinn-offensive/|title=The Soviet Dunkirk: The Tallinn Offensive|website=warfarehistorynetwork.com|language=en|access-date=2018-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; The German invasion quickly progressed eastward towards the Baltic states where they began to destroy Soviet naval bases.&lt;ref name="The Soviet Dunkirk: The Tallinn Offensive" /&gt; By August 1941, the Soviet’s most westward naval base was in Tallinn, making it a main target for the German forces.&lt;ref name="The Soviet Dunkirk: The Tallinn Offensive" /&gt; Luftwaffe commenced bombing of Tallinn from the first days of the war in June, and this intensified in August due to the Soviet attempts to evacuate the city's residents, elements of the [[Baltic Fleet]], formations of the [[8th Army (Soviet Union)|8th Army]], and industrial assets important for war production. The Soviet forces lost control of Estonia in the summer of 1941, when the Germans began to gradually occupy the country.&lt;ref name="Estonia"&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/article.php?ModuleId=10005448|title=Estonia|website=www.ushmm.org|language=en|access-date=2018-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

== Soviet Air Forces raids, 1942–43 ==
Tallinn was bombed on several occasions during May and September, 1942. During 1943, several bombing missions were performed by the [[Soviet Air Forces]] on Tallinn in February, March, May, August, and September.  With German forces now occupying Estonia's capital Tallinn, the Soviet air force began bombing the city which it formerly controlled.&lt;ref name="Estonia" /&gt;

== Soviet Air Forces raids in 1944 ==
In February 1944, Germans began storing provisions, supply depots, and reserve units for the front lines in Estonia.&lt;ref name="Estonica.org - Bombing of Tallinn in March 1944"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.estonica.org/en/Bombing_of_Tallinn_in_March_1944/|title=Estonica.org – Bombing of Tallinn in March 1944|website=www.estonica.org|language=en|access-date=2018-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt; Tallinn's harbor became a main terminal for the Germans' transportation of goods that were supplying the front lines.&lt;ref name="Estonica.org - Bombing of Tallinn in March 1944" /&gt; Due to the increase of German activity in Tallinn, the Soviet air force began targeting the city for bombings in an effort to debilitate Germany.&lt;ref name="Estonica.org - Bombing of Tallinn in March 1944" /&gt; 

The heaviest of the air assaults was on 9 March. A week before, the Mayor of Tallinn had given an order to the city dwellers to leave the town, but the evacuation failed, as the extent of the attack was beyond the expectations of the local people and Army Group North. The first attack, from 6:30 – 9:00&amp;nbsp;pm, saw 300 aircraft drop 3068 bombs, 1725 explosive and 1300 incendiary.&lt;ref name="tules"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Kivimäe, Jüri |author2=Kõiv, Lea |title= Tallinn tules. Dokumente ja materjale Tallinna pommitamisest 9/10. märtsil 1944. (Tallinn on Fire. Documents and materials on the bombing of Tallinn 9/10 March 1944.)|language=Estonian|publisher= Tallinn City Archives|year= 1997}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="hiio"&gt;{{cite book|author=Toomas Hiio|year=2006|pages=1035–1094|chapter=Combat in Estonia in 1944|editor1=Toomas Hiio |editor2=Meelis Maripuu |editor3=Indrek Paavle |title=Estonia 1940–1945: Reports of the [[Estonian International Commission for the Investigation of Crimes Against Humanity]]|location=Tallinn}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Estonica.org - Bombing of Tallinn in March 1944" /&gt; Bombers hit the capital again at 2 a.m. for an additional hour and a half.&lt;ref name="Estonica.org - Bombing of Tallinn in March 1944" /&gt; The fire brigades were scarce on water, as Soviet [[saboteurs]] had blown up the city pumping station before the air raid. A large part of the wooden suburbs went up in flames, and the city centre suffered major damage. In all, about twenty percent of the buildings in Tallinn were burnt to the ground.&lt;ref name="Estonica.org - Bombing of Tallinn in March 1944" /&gt;

Military damage was minor, with a few military installations and supply stores destroyed. The major military loss was the burning of a million litres of fuel in the fuel depot. Of the enterprises with some military importance, the "Luther" plywood factory and the ''Urania-Werke''-run cable factory were destroyed. Most of the bombs fell on the dwellings and public buildings, including the [[Estonia Theatre]], [[St. Nicholas' Church, Tallinn|St. Nicholas Church]], the city synagogue, four cinemas, and the Tallinn City Archives.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.tallinn.ee/eng/archives/History|title=History of the Tallinn City Archives |author=Tallinn City Archives |date=20 April 2012 |accessdate=26 April 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

According to the official report, 757 people were killed, of whom 586 were civilians, 50 were military personnel, and 121 were prisoners-of-war. 213 had serious injuries, 446 had minor injuries. Amongst the injured were 65 military servicemen and 75 prisoners-of-war. Later, more victims were found, with the number of deaths estimated at up to 800.&lt;ref name="hiio" /&gt; More than 20,000 people were left without a shelter in the spring thaw, while the military objects were almost untouched.&lt;ref name="tules" /&gt;&lt;ref name="white"&gt;{{cite book|page=18|author1=Enn Sarv|author2=Peep Varju|lastauthoramp=yes|chapter=Survey of Occupation Regimes|url=http://www.just.ee/orb.aw/class=file/action=preview/id=12709/TheWhiteBook.pdf|format=PDF|title=The White Book: Losses inflicted on the Estonian nation by occupation regimes. 1940–1991|year=2005|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130114130824/http://www.just.ee/orb.aw/class%3Dfile/action%3Dpreview/id%3D12709/TheWhiteBook.pdf|archivedate=2013-01-14}}&lt;/ref&gt; Immediately after the bombing raid [[Flying Regiment 4, Finnish Air Force|Finnish air force bombers]] followed returning Soviet bombers to three [[military airbase]]s near [[Leningrad]] and bombed them.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url =http://www.iltasanomat.fi/kotimaa/art-2000001142673.html | title =Lentorykmentti 4:n pommikoneet nousivat vihollisen siivelle | last =Jaakkonen | first =Pasi | date =2016-03-25 | website =Ilta-Sanomat | publisher =Sanoma Media | access-date =2016-06-07 | language=Finnish}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the attack, about twenty-five Soviet airplanes were shot down in Tallinn with an additional ten destroyed by the ''Ilmavoimat'' later the same night.&lt;ref name="Estonica.org - Bombing of Tallinn in March 1944" /&gt;

Despite the high number of civilian casualties and low damage to military and strategic installations, sources disagree on whether the Soviet bombing raids were conducted primarily in order to destroy the morale of local civilians opposed to a return of Soviet occupation forces.&lt;ref name="Estonica.org - Bombing of Tallinn in March 1944" /&gt;&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=white/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2&gt;{{cite book |pages=32–59|chapter=Battles in Estonia in 1944|title=Estonia in World War II |last=Laar |first=Mart |year=2005 |publisher=Grenader| authorlink=Mart Laar|location=Tallinn}}&lt;/ref&gt; Regardless of Soviet intentions, the high civilian casualty toll of the raids significantly increased the hostility of the Estonian public towards the Soviet army. On 27 February, a Soviet air raid had hit children playing in the school yard of [[Luunja Parish]], killing four. The date of their burial was turned into a national memorial day, accompanied by the poem "''Uus Herodes''" ("Modern [[Massacre of the Innocents|Herod]]") published by [[Henrik Visnapuu]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|publisher =Eesti Sõna|title=Uus Herodes|author=Henrik Visnapuu|date=5 March 1944|language=Estonian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=laar&gt;{{cite book|author=Mart Laar|title=Sinimäed 1944: II maailmasõja lahingud Kirde-Eestis (Sinimäed Hills 1944: Battles of II World War in Northeast Estonia|publisher= Tallinn: Varrak|year= 2006|language=Estonian}}&lt;/ref&gt; More Estonians felt an urge to fight against the Soviet advance.&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;A.Aasmaa (1999). Tagasivaateid.(Looking Back. In Estonian) In: Mart Tamberg (Comp.). Eesti mehed sõjatules. EVTÜ, Saku&lt;/ref&gt; A slogan:&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;{{quote|''Varemeist tõuseb kättemaks!'' (Vengeance Will Rise from the Ruins!)}} was written on the ruins of the Estonia Theatre. The slogan became the title of the newspaper of the [[20th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Estonian)]].&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;

The last Soviet Air Forces bombing raid on Tallinn was commenced the night before 22 September 1944. The Soviet Union annexed Estonia as one of its republics for a second time in September 1944.&lt;ref name="Estonia" /&gt;

== Memorials ==
The last ruins—along the Harju Street in the Old Town—served as a memorial to the victims of the raid; but the ruins were filled in 2007 and a park built over them after careful archaeological work.{{cn|date=March 2019}}

== References ==
{{reflist}}

{{WWII city bombing}}

{{authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tallinn Bombing}}
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Eastern Front of World War II]]
[[Category:World War II aerial operations and battles of the Eastern Front]]
[[Category:Military history of Estonia during World War II]]
[[Category:1944 in Estonia]]
[[Category:History of Tallinn]]
[[Category:20th century in Tallinn]]
[[Category:Estonia–Germany military relations]]</text><sha1>fvlvpn7j2p7gjnzh8tll9cn788536sf</sha1></revision></page>