<page><title>Nevsky Pyatachok</title><ns>0</ns><id>15453429</id><revision><id>875104130</id><parentid>800430247</parentid><timestamp>2018-12-23T20:58:53Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>217.165.68.246</ip></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="6211" xml:space="preserve">[[Image:Nevsky pyatachok Kirovsk.jpg|thumb|250px|Memorial at the battlefield of Nevsky Pyatachok]]
'''Nevsky Pyatachok''' ({{lang-ru|Не́вский пятачо́к}}) is the name of the Neva Bridgehead 50&amp;nbsp;km east south-east of [[St. Petersburg|Leningrad]] and 15&amp;nbsp;km south of [[Shlisselburg]]. It was the site of one of the most critical and costly campaigns during the [[Siege of Leningrad]] from September 1941 until May 1943 to reopen land communications with the city during the German siege.

The Russian word ''pyatachok'' means a five-[[Ruble|kopeck]] coin, or (by way of a metaphor) a very small area.

==Campaign for the land communications==

The area between Shlisselburg and the bend of the [[Neva]] to the south represented the land link between the Soviet-controlled territory and the city defence perimeter. The Red Army objective was to retain this narrow stretch of the shore and prevent German forces from completing the blockade, thus allowing transports to reach the population in besieged Leningrad with food, medication and other supplies.

The area was first defended by the Red Army's [[Krasnogvardeisk Fortified Region]], the [[55th Army (Soviet Union)|55th]] and the [[48th Army (Soviet Union)|48th Armies]] which included the 45th Guards, 115th, 86th, 168th, 10th Rifle Divisions, 1st NKVD Rifle Division and 4th Separate Naval Infantry Brigade.&lt;ref&gt;Степан Кашурко, "Независимая газета", ''Эпопея "Невского пятачка"'' 2003-03-14 [http://nvo.ng.ru/history/2003-03-14/5_epopee.html]&lt;/ref&gt; On 7 September 1941, the German [[20th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|20th Motorised Division]] was able to force the elements of the 48th Army out of Shlisselburg, setting the stage for a more than two-year struggle by the Red Army to reopen land communications with Leningrad.&lt;ref&gt;p.32, Glantz&lt;/ref&gt;

Initially, the Germans secured the area. On September 20, 1941,a small group of Soviet soldiers under Captain Vasily Dubik managed to cross the river using fishing boats and homemade rafts and establish the bridgehead, but they failed to enlarge it. The Germans managed to eliminate the bridgehead by April 29, 1942, but it was re-established on September 26, 1942.

The battle for Nevsky Pyatachok extended from January 1942 to May 1943.

In 1942, the area was a scene of heavy fighting for the German [[XXVIII Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXVIII Army Corps]] which, from October 1942, was under constant assault by the [[67th Army (Soviet Union)|67th Army]].&lt;ref&gt;p.126, Glantz&lt;/ref&gt;

Eventually, [[Leonid Govorov]] proposed two operations to the [[Stavka]], called the Shlisselburg Operation and the Uritsk Operation, which became the basis of the planning for [[Operation Iskra]]. The intention was for the [[2nd Shock Army]] of the [[Volkhov Front]] and the 67th Army of the [[Leningrad Front]] to destroy the German troops in the Shlisselburg - Siniavino sector, thereby restoring the land communications and raising the siege. They were supported in this by the [[13th Air Army (Soviet Union)|13th Air Army]] and some units of the [[Long Range Aviation]].&lt;ref&gt;pp.128-129, Glantz&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the south-eastern perimeter of the siege was temporarily penetrated, Soviet forces only managed to open a 10–12&amp;nbsp;km wide corridor, meaning all traffic passed under the fire of German guns. German casualties for the duration of the struggle for the bridgehead, estimated to be 1&amp;nbsp;km by 1.5&amp;nbsp;km in area, were some 160,000 (combat and combat-related).&lt;ref name="p.149, Glantz"&gt;p.149, Glantz&lt;/ref&gt;

These, and other operations conducted until 10 May 1943, resulted in Red Army casualties estimated at 260,000 in this sector of the front.&lt;ref name="p.149, Glantz"/&gt;

==After World War II==
[[Image:NevskyPyatachokTrenches.jpg|thumb|250px|Remnants of World War II Russian trenches in the Nevsky Pyatachok.]]
After the war, a tradition began in which the children of Leningrad schools took summer trips to the area to search for the remains of the many who died there. Official burial ceremonies were then held commemorating the dead whose remains were recovered. The terrain still contains unidentifiable skeletal remains.

==National memorial==
Today, the battlefield of Nevsky Pyatachok is a well-known national and historic landmark in Russia. A memorial was built as part of the "[[Green Belt of Glory]]" commemorating the heroic resistance during the siege of Leningrad.

The words on the memorial belong to [[Robert Rozhdestvensky]] and can be literally translated as:

"You,

Those who are alive,

Should know

That this land

We didn't want to leave

And never left.

We were fighting to the bitter end

By the dark [[Neva]].

We have perished

For you to live."

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
* The siege of Leningrad. By Alan Wykes. Ballantines Illustrated History of WWII, 3rd edition, 1972.
* Scorched earth. Leningrad: Tragedy of a City. (pages 205 - 208) By [[Paul Carell]]. [[Schiffer Publishing|Schiffer Military History]], 1994. {{ISBN|0-88740-598-3}}
* Military-Topographic Directorate, maps No. 194, 196, Officer's Atlas. General Staff USSR. 1947. Атлас Офицера. Генеральный штаб вооруженных сил ССР. М., Военно-топографическоее управление,- 1947. Листы 194, 196
*Glantz, David, Leningrad, city under siege 1941-1944, Grange Books, Kent, 2001

== External links ==
* [http://www.ido.edu.ru/ffec/hist/h8.html] Map of German advance
* [http://victory.tass-online.ru/data/Photos/Photo/175.JPEG] Map of the advance on Leningrad and relief; Blue are the German and allied Finnish troops. The Soviets are red.

{{coord|59|50|37|N|30|57|12|E|region:RU_type:landmark|display=title}}

[[Category:Geography of Leningrad Oblast]]
[[Category:Sieges involving Germany|Leningrad]]
[[Category:Sieges involving the Soviet Union|Leningrad]]
[[Category:History of Saint Petersburg]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1941]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Eastern Front of World War II|Leningrad]]
[[Category:Tourist attractions in Leningrad Oblast]]
[[Category:Monuments and memorials in Russia]]
[[Category:Alexander Nevsky|Pyatachok]]</text><sha1>e2iekuema156ujh8zjwnuj79txknrlz</sha1></revision></page>