<page><title>First Battle of Kharkov</title><ns>0</ns><id>9396487</id><revision><id>954891525</id><parentid>954891228</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-04T20:47:27Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Grondorn</username><id>31741747</id></contributor><comment>Undid revision 954855820 by [[Special:Contributions/Bulgaria1991|Bulgaria1991]] ([[User talk:Bulgaria1991|talk]])</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="19711" xml:space="preserve">{{Expert needed|Military history|date=March 2010}}
{{Use American English|date=December 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2013}}

{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = '''First Battle of Kharkov'''
| partof      = the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = Bundesarchiv Bild 183-L20582, Charkow, Strassenkämpfe.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = [[Germany|German]] infantry and armored vehicles battle [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] defenders on the streets of [[Kharkov]]
| place       = [[Kharkiv#German occupation|Kharkov]], [[Ukrainian SSR]], [[Soviet Union]]
| date        = 20–24 October 1941
| result      = German victory
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Erwin Vierow]]&lt;br /&gt; {{Flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Anton Dostler]]&lt;!---&lt;br /&gt;{{Flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Josef Brauner von Haydringen]]&lt;br /&gt; {{Flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Kurt von Barisani]]---&gt;
| commander2  = {{Flagicon|Soviet Union}} [[Viktor Tsyganov]]
| strength1   = Two divisions&lt;br /&gt;1 Sturmgeschütz-Abteilung&lt;br /&gt;10,000–30,000 men (est.)&lt;br /&gt;12 [[StuG III]]
| strength2   = One division&lt;ref&gt;According to Glantz 2001, p. 247-248, the strength of the weakened Southwestern Front on 30 September was 147,110 men, mostly survivors from the battle of Kiev. Reïnforcements sent after this date include several NKVD divisions and brigades fighting as regular ground units.&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties1 = unknown
| casualties2 = unknown, but&lt;ref&gt;According to Glantz 2001, p. 248, the losses of the Southwestern Front from 30 September to 30 November numbered 96,509 men, including 75,720 irrecoverable (dead, missing or captured) and 20,789 sick and wounded.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;probably higher
| campaignbox =
{{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Campaignbox Barbarossa}}
}}

The '''1st Battle of Kharkov''', so named by [[Wilhelm Keitel]],&lt;ref&gt;see The memoirs of Field-Marshal Keitel. Edited with an introduction and epilogue by Walter Gorlitz. Translated by [[David Irving]], William Kimber, London (1965)&lt;/ref&gt; was the 1941 battle for the city of [[Kharkiv#German occupation|Kharkiv]] (''[[Kharkiv|Kharkov in Russian]]''&lt;ref name=name&gt;Kharkov is the Russian language name of the city (Kharkiv the Ukrainian one); both Russian and Ukrainian were official languages in the Soviet Union (Source:[https://books.google.com/books?id=Nn3xDTiL0PQC&amp;pg=PA1&amp;dq=official+languages+Soviet+Union&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;cd=6#v=onepage&amp;q=%22official%20language%22&amp;f=false Language Policy in the Soviet Union by L.A. Grenoble] &amp; [https://books.google.com/books?id=qmN95fFocsMC&amp;pg=PA848&amp;dq=Russian+name+Kharkov+Kharkiv&amp;hl=nl&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=pk4mUbnjKKyY0QXir4C4CA&amp;ved=0CDQQ6AEwADgK#v=onepage&amp;q=Russian%20name%20Kharkov%20Kharkiv&amp;f=false Eastern Europe and the Commonwealth of Independent States] by [[Routledge]])&lt;/ref&gt;) ([[Ukrainian SSR]]) during the final phase of [[Operation Barbarossa]] between the German [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|6th Army]] of [[Army Group South]] and the Soviet [[Southwestern Front (Soviet Union)|Southwestern Front]]. The Soviet [[38th Army (Soviet Union)|38th Army]] was ordered to defend the city while its factories were dismantled for relocation farther east.

The German 6th Army needed to take the city in order to close the widening gap to the German  [[17th Army (Wehrmacht)|17th Army]]. By 20 October the Germans had reached the western edge of the city, it was taken by the [[57th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|57th Infantry Division]] by 24 October. At that time, however, most of Kharkiv's industrial equipment had been evacuated or rendered useless by the Soviet authorities.

==Importance of Kharkiv==

===Kharkiv's railroad system===
In the autumn of 1941, Kharkiv was considered one of the Soviets' most important strategic bases for railroad and airline connections. It not only connected the east-west and north-south parts of Ukraine, but also several central regions of the USSR including the [[Crimea]], the [[Caucasus]], the [[Dnieper]] region, and [[Donbas]].{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

===Military importance===
Kharkiv was one of the largest industrial centers of the Soviet Union. One of its greatest contributions was the Soviet [[T-34 tank]] that was both designed and developed at the [[Kharkov Tractor Factory|Kharkiv Tractor Factory]]. It was considered to be the most powerful tank plant in the country. Other factories that were located in the city included the Kharkiv Aircraft Plant, Kharkiv Plant of the [[NKVD]] (FED), and the Kharkiv Turbine Plant. Military products that were in Kharkiv before the battle started included: tanks, [[Su-2]], [[artillery tractor]]s, [[82-PM-41|82 mm mortars]], [[sub-machine guns]], ammunition, and other military equipment.
The main objective for the German troops was to capture the railroad and military factories, thus they desperately tried to keep the industrial area of Kharkiv intact. [[Adolf Hitler]] himself stressed the importance of those military plants stating: "… The second in importance is south of Russia, particularly the [[Donets Basin]], ranging from the Kharkiv region. There is the whole basis of [the] Russian economy; if the area is mastered then it would inevitably lead to the collapse of the entire Russian (sic - Soviet) economy…&lt;ref&gt;[http://memorial.kharkov.ua/history Memoir of Kharkiv’s History]&lt;/ref&gt;"

===Population of Kharkiv===
Kharkiv was one of the most populated Soviet cities during [[World War II]]. It was rated at 901,000 people on 1 May 1941. In September 1941 the population skyrocketed to 1.5 million people, due to numerous evacuees from other cities. After multiple attacks and many deaths, the population of Kharkiv decreased to 180 – 190,000, which was the size after the retaking of the city in August 1943.&lt;ref&gt;[http://vecherniy.kharkov.ua/news/14899/ Kharkiv News ]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Before the battle==

===The aftermath of Kiev===

[[File:Map Operation Typhoon.jpg|thumb|German advances, 26 August – 5 December 1941]]
After the [[Battle of Kiev (1941)|Battle of Kiev]], [[Army Group Center]] was ordered to redeploy its forces for the [[Battle of Moscow|attack on Moscow]], and so the [[2nd Panzer Group]] turned north towards [[Bryansk]] and [[Kursk]]. [[Army Group South]], and in particular [[Walther von Reichenau]]'s [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|6th Army]] and [[Carl-Heinrich von Stülpnagel]]'s [[17th Army (Wehrmacht)|17th Army]] took the place of the panzer divisions. The main offensive formation of Army Group South, [[Paul Ludwig Ewald von Kleist]]'s [[1st Panzer Group]], was in the meantime ordered south for a drive to [[Rostov-on-Don]] and the [[Caucasus|Caucasian]] oilfields, following [[Führer Directives|Führer Directive No. 35]]. The burden of processing Kiev's 600,000 [[prisoners of war]] (POWs) fell upon the 6th and 17th Armies, so while the 1st Panzer Group secured the German victory in the [[Battle of Melitopol]], these two armies spent the next three weeks regrouping.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

[[Stavka]] (Soviet High Command), needed to stabilize its southern flank and poured reinforcements into the area between Kursk and Rostov, at the expense of its forces in front of [[Moscow]].&lt;ref&gt;Glantz 2001, p. 140.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Southwestern Front (Soviet Union)|Southwestern Front]], which had been destroyed during the battle of Kiev, was re-established under the command of Marshal [[Semyon Timoshenko]], one of the more capable [[Red Army]] commanders. The [[6th Army (Soviet Union)|6th]], [[21st Army (Soviet Union)|21st]], [[38th Army (Soviet Union)|38th]] and [[40th Army (Soviet Union)|40th]] [[List of Soviet armies|Armies]] were reconstituted almost from scratch.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

===Approaching Kharkiv===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-B16174, Charkow, Sowjetische Sandsackstellung.jpg|thumb|Soviet bunkers used in the defense of Kharkiv]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-L20721, Charkow, deutscher Einmarsch.jpg|thumb|The German Army enters downtown Kharkiv]]
With the Battle of Moscow under way, the Germans had to protect their flanks, and on 6 October von Reichenau advanced through [[Sumy]] and [[Okhtyrka]] in the direction of [[Belgorod]] and Kharkiv. On the same day, the 17th Army commenced its offensive from [[Poltava]] towards [[Lozova]] and [[Izyum]] to protect the lengthening flank of the [[1st Panzer Army]] (formerly the 1st Panzer Group). The 6th Army ([[Rodion Malinovsky]]) and 38th Army ([[Viktor Tsiganov]]) failed to conduct a coordinated defense and were beaten back. In the lead up to the [[Battle of Moscow]], the Red Army suffered a big defeat at [[Vyazma]] and Bryansk, with 700,000 casualties. The few reserves available were desperately needed to defend the Soviet capital, not the Southwestern Front. With no reserves to plug the breach, the [[Stavka]] was forced fall back to [[Voronezh]] to prevent the collapse of the southern flank.&lt;ref&gt;Glantz 2001, p. 151-152.&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the main objectives of the German Army before winter fell were to capture Leningrad, Moscow and the approaches to the Caucasian oilfields, Kharkiv was an important secondary objective. Besides the need to protect the flanks of its motorized spearheads, the German Army high command, ''[[Oberkommando des Heeres]]'' (OKH), also saw the importance of Kharkiv as an industrial center and railroad hub. Capturing the city meant that the Southwestern and [[Southern Front (Soviet Union)|Southern Front]] had to fall back on [[Voronezh]] and [[Stalingrad]] as their major transport hubs. When, in the second week of October, the rainy season of the [[Rasputitsa]] (the 'mud' season) and the poor logistics in the area between the [[Dnepr]] and the front, (all the bridges had collapsed during combat and ice threatened the pontoons), caused the offensive to stall.&lt;ref&gt;Margry 2001, p. 5&lt;/ref&gt; Hitler allocated resources from the 17th Army to the 6th Army to ensure the capture of Kharkiv. This, however, weakened the 17th Army's effort to protect the flank of the 1st Panzer Army and contributed to the German defeat at the [[Battle of Rostov (1941)|Battle of Rostov]].&lt;ref&gt;Kirchubel 2003, p. 76.&lt;/ref&gt; After 17 October, night frost improved the roads, but snow storms and the cold started to hamper the Germans, who were insufficiently equipped for winter operations (the German Army had planned that ''Barbarossa'' would be over before winter fell).{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

==Course of the battle==

===Preparing to take the city===
The task of assaulting Kharkiv itself was given to the ''LV. Armeekorps'' commanded by [[General of the Infantry (Germany)|''General der Infanterie'']] [[Erwin Vierow]]. This corps had at its disposal the ''101. Leichte-Division'', commanded by ''[[Generalleutnant]]'' [[Josef Brauner von Haydringen]] and coming in from the north, the [[57th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|''57. Infanterie-Division'']], commanded by ''[[Generalmajor]]'' [[Anton Dostler]] and coming in from the south, and the [[100th Light Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|''100. Leichte-Division'']], which did not take part in the battle. ''Sturmgeschütz-Abteilung 197'', commanded by ''[[Hauptmann]]'' [[Kurt von Barisani]] had two of its three batteries attached to the ''57. Infanterie-Division'' to provide close fire support during the assault.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

For the defense of Kharkiv, the [[216th Rifle Division]] had been reformed there after its destruction at Kiev. It received little to no support from other divisions or from higher command formations, because the 38th Army was in the process of a strategic retreat and the defense of Kharkiv was only necessary as long as its factory equipment had not been completely evacuated.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-B13548, Charkow, Einmarsch deutsche Truppen.jpg|thumb|German troops enter Kharkiv from the west, crossing the main railroad running through the city on the viaduct of Sverdlov Street.&lt;ref&gt;Margry 2001, p.6&lt;/ref&gt;]]

===Battles on the western edge of the city (20–23 October)===

====57th Infantry Division plus a Panzer Brigade====

====101st Light Division====
By 21 October the 101st Light Division had reached a line about six kilometers west of Kharkiv. The 228th Light Regiment spearheaded the division, its 1st and 3rd [[battalion]]s taking up defensive positions on the front, with the 2nd battalion in reserve. On 22 October the regiment was ordered to conduct [[reconnaissance]] to determine the enemy's strength. That same day at noon the regiment was attacked by a Soviet infantry battalion supported by tanks. The attack was repulsed and two tanks were disabled. That night the recon information was transmitted by radio to the Division HQ. The 216th Rifle Division had occupied the western edge of the city, with machine gun nests, mortar pits and minefields in place.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

For the attack, the 3rd battalion (the regiment's right flank), was reinforced with two guns from the division's artillery, The 85th Artillery Regiment, a company of engineers and an [[8.8 cm Flak 18/36/37/41|88 mm anti-aircraft gun]]. The 2nd battalion received the same reinforcements, but without the AA gun. The 1st battalion acted as the regimental reserve. The first battalion of the 229th Light Regiment would protect the left flank of the 228th. The attack hour was set at noon, in conjunction with the 57th Infantry Division.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

At 11:00 hours, a liaison was established between the 85th Artillery and the 228th Light Regiments. The artillery was not ready at the time designated, so the attack had to be postponed. In the meantime the anti-tank company, who had been stuck in the mud at the rear, finally arrived at the front and was ordered to assign one [[3.7 cm Pak 36|37 mm AT-gun]] [[platoon]] to every frontline battalion. At 14:25, the artillery was ready and the attack hour was set at 15:00.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

===Assault on the city (23–24 October)===
The evacuation of industrial enterprises started before the Germans had a chance to attack. By 20 October 1941 it was virtually completed. Three-hundred and twenty trains were sent with the equipment from 70 major factories. Kharkiv was taken by von Reichenau's 6th Army, on 24 October 1941.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

==Occupation of Kharkiv==
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-B13132, Charkow, Sturmgeschütz und Schützenpanzer.jpg|thumb|German armored vehicles in Kharkiv]]
[[File:1941oct25SumskayaStreetOccupation.jpg|thumb|right|[[Sumskaya street]] in Kharkiv, 25 October 1941]]

The city was subject to its first occupation during the war, which lasted until 16 February 1943. The city never became part of [[Reichskommissariat Ukraine|''Reichskommissariat'' Ukraine]] because of its proximity to the front. The staff of the ''LV Army Corps'' acted as the occupational authority, using 57.ID as an occupation force. ''Generalmajor'' Anton Dostler was ''Stadtkommandant'' until 13 December, when he was succeeded by ''Generalleutnant'' [[Alfred von Puttkamer]], and Kharkiv was transferred to the ''[[Heeresgebiet]]'' of the ''6th Armee'' and put under the joint authority of the ''Stadtkommandant'' and ''Field Command 757''.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

German troops acting under the authority of the ''Reichenau-Befehl'' of 10 October (effectively an order to kill anybody associated with [[communism]]) terrorized the population that was left after the battle. Many of the Soviet commanders' corpses were hung off balconies to strike fear into the remaining population. Many people began to flee, causing chaos.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

In the early hours of 14 November, multiple buildings in the city center were blown up by time-fuses left by the retreating Red Army. Casualties included the commander (''Generalleutnant'' [[Georg Braun (general)|Georg Braun]]) and staff of the [[68th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|''68th Infantry Division'']]. The Germans arrested some 200 civilians (mostly Jews) and hanged them from the balconies of large buildings. Another 1,000 were taken as hostages and interned in the Hotel International on [[Freedom Square, Kharkiv|Dzerzhinsky Square]]. All of these [[War crimes of the Wehrmacht|war crimes]] were committed by frontline [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|''Heer'']] commanders, and not by [[SS]] troops.&lt;ref&gt;Margry 2001, p. 8&lt;/ref&gt;

On 14 December, the ''Stadtkommandant'' ordered the Jewish population to be concentrated in a hut settlement near the Kharkiv Tractor Factory. In two days, 20,000 Jews were gathered there. ''Sonderkommando'' 4a, commanded by ''SS-Standartenführer'' [[Paul Blobel]], of ''[[Einsatzgruppe]]'' [[Einsatzkommando#Einsatzgruppe C|C]] started shooting the first of them in December, then continuing to kill them throughout January in a [[Nazi gas van|gas van]]. This was a modified truck that fitted 50 people in it; the van drove around the city and slowly killed the people that were trapped in it with [[carbon monoxide]] that was emitted from the vehicle itself and channeled into an airtight compartment. The victims died by a combination of [[carbon monoxide poisoning]] and [[suffocation]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.history.org.ua/JournALL/journal/1999/6/8.pdf Ukrainian Historical Journal]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Margry 2001, p. 8-9&lt;/ref&gt;

The German Army [[Hunger Plan|confiscated large quantities of food]] to be used by its troops, creating acute shortages in the Ukraine. By January 1942 around one-third of the city's 300,000 remaining inhabitants suffered from starvation. Many would die in the cold winter months.&lt;ref&gt;Margry 2001, p. 9&lt;/ref&gt;

As a result of the battles in Kharkiv, the city was left in ruins. Dozens of architectural monuments were destroyed and numerous artistic treasures taken. One of the Soviet Unions's best known authors, [[Aleksey Nikolayevich Tolstoy]] wrote: "I saw Kharkiv. As if it were [[Rome]] in the 5th century. A huge cemetery…"{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

==See also==
* [[Second Battle of Kharkov]]
* [[Third Battle of Kharkov]]

==References and footnotes==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
* {{Cite web | last = Chen | first = Peter | title = First Battle of Kharkov | work = World War II Database | date = 2004–2007 | url = http://ww2db.com/battle_spec.php?battle_id=58 | accessdate = 2007-02-08}}
* Glantz, David M. (2001). ''Before Stalingrad'', Tempus Publishing Ltd. {{ISBN|0-7524-2692-3}}
* [http://vecherniy.kharkov.ua/news/14899/ Kharkov News]
* Kiessling, Hannes (2007–2011). [http://www.57id.de/index.php?title=Bericht_%C3%BCber_die_Einnahme_von_Charkow Bericht über die Einnahme von Charkow], ''57.Infanterie-Division''. Retrieved 14-08-2011
* Kirchubel, Robert (2003). ''Operation Barbarossa 1941: Army Group South'', Praeger Publishers. {{ISBN|0-275-98282-3}}
* Margry, Karel (February 2001). "Kharkov", ''After The Battle'', Issue 112, p.&amp;nbsp;3–45
* [http://memorial.kharkov.ua/history Memoir of Kharkov’s History]
* [http://www.history.org.ua/JournALL/journal/1999/6/8.pdf Ukrainian Historical Journal]

==External links==
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Military of Germany
| portal2=Soviet Union
| portal3=World War II
| commons=y
| commons-search=First Battle of Kharkov
}}

{{Coord missing|Ukraine}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kharkov, 1st Battle Of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1941]]
[[Category:1941 in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Battles of Kharkov]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:Operation Barbarossa]]
[[Category:October 1941 events]]</text><sha1>rnk0m10cfr4t3ei95pbqq1vedljquaa</sha1></revision></page>