<page><title>Battle of the Kerch Peninsula</title><ns>0</ns><id>7541477</id><revision><id>962060247</id><parentid>954726470</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-11T21:55:39Z</timestamp><contributor><username>TiltuM</username><id>25848390</id></contributor><comment>See cited sources</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="72729" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|1941 battle in the Crimea}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Battle of the Kerch Peninsula
|partof = the [[Crimean campaign]] during the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
|image = Bombardowanie przez lotnictwo niemieckie miasta Kercz (2-832).jpg
|image_size = 300px
|caption = German bombs fall on the Kerch Peninsula, May 1942
|date = 26 December 1941 – 19 May 1942&lt;br /&gt;({{Age in years, months, weeks and days|month1=12|day1=26|year1=1941|month2=05|day2=19|year2=1942}})
|place = [[Crimean Peninsula]], [[Russian SFSR]], [[Soviet Union]]
|result = Axis victory
|combatant1 = {{flag|Nazi Germany|name=Germany}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of Romania.svg}} [[Romania]]&lt;br&gt;
|combatant2 = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
|commander1 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Erich von Manstein]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Wolfram Freiherr von Richthofen|W. F. von Richthofen]]
|commander2 = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Dimitri Kozlov]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Lev Mekhlis]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|naval}} [[Filipp Oktyabrsky]]
|units1 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[11th Army (Wehrmacht)|11th Army]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[8th Air Corps (Germany)|8th Air Corps]]
|units2 = [[Caucasus Front (Soviet Union)|Caucasus Front]]{{efn|The front started as the [[Transcaucasian Front]], which became the [[Caucasus Front (Soviet Union)|Caucasus Front]] on 30 December 1941, and which the independent [[Crimean Front]] split from on 28 January 1942|name="FrontName"}}&lt;br&gt;[[Crimean Front]]
*[[44th Army (Soviet Union)|44th Army]]
*[[47th Army]]
*[[51st Army (Russia)|51st Army]]
[[Separate Coastal Army]]&lt;br/&gt;Air Force of the Crimean Front&lt;br/&gt;[[Black Sea Fleet]]
|strength1 = 8 May 1942:&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}}&lt;br/&gt;232,549 men (2 May){{sfn|Isaev|2016|p=626}}&lt;br/&gt;200 tanks{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=168}}&lt;br/&gt;57 assault guns{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=163}}&lt;br/&gt;800+ aircraft{{sfn|Hooton|2016|p=116}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon image|Flag of Romania.svg}}&lt;br/&gt;95,000 men (2 May){{sfn|Isaev|2016|p=626}}
|strength2 = 8 May 1942:&lt;br/&gt;249,800 men{{sfn|Krivosheev|1997|p=108}}&lt;br/&gt;238 tanks{{sfn|Isaev|2016|p=638}}&lt;br/&gt;404 aircraft (Air Force of the Crimean Front){{sfn|Hooton|2016|p=116}}
|casualties1 = 38,362
{{Collapsible list
|title = Breakdown
|'''Kerch losses:'''
----
'''21 December – 31 December:'''&lt;br /&gt;6,654 men&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ww2stats.com/cas_ger_okh_dec41.html |title=Heeresarzt 10-Day Casualty Reports per Army/Army Group, 1941|accessdate=19 March 2018 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130525020822/http://ww2stats.com/cas_ger_okh_dec41.html |archivedate=25 May 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
:1,108 killed
:5,287 wounded
:259 missing
----
'''January 1942 – April 1942:'''&lt;br /&gt;24,120 men{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=127}}
----
'''8 May 1942 – 19 May 1942:'''&lt;br /&gt;7,588 men{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=171}}
:1,703 killed or captured
:5,885 wounded
8–12 tanks destroyed{{sfn|Forczyk|2008|p=36}}{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=171}}&lt;br /&gt;3 assault guns destroyed{{sfn|Forczyk|2008|p=36}}&lt;br /&gt;9 artillery pieces destroyed{{sfn|Forczyk|2008|p=36}}&lt;br /&gt;37 aircraft destroyed{{sfn|Hooton|2016|p=117}}
}}
|casualties2 = 570,601
{{Collapsible list
|title = Breakdown
|'''Kerch losses:'''
----
'''26 December – 2 January:'''&lt;br /&gt;41,935 men{{sfn|Krivosheev|1997|p=122}}
:32,453 killed or captured
:9,482 wounded or sick
----
'''1 January 1942 – 30 April 1942:'''&lt;br /&gt;352,000 men{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=165|loc=115,630 in January, 98,523 in February, 74,125 in March and 63,722 in April}}{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=127}}
----
'''8 May 1942 – 19 May 1942:'''&lt;br /&gt;176,566 men{{sfn|Krivosheev|1997|p=108}}
:162,282 killed or captured
:14,284 wounded or sick
258 tanks destroyed&lt;br /&gt;1,133 guns lost&lt;br /&gt;417 aircraft destroyed (315 from Air Force of the Crimean Front){{sfn|Hooton|2016|p=117}}
}}
|campaignbox=
}}
{{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Campaignbox Crimea and Caucasus}}
{{Romanian military actions in World War II}}
The '''Battle of the Kerch Peninsula''', which commenced with the Soviet '''Kerch-Feodosia Landing Operation''' ({{lang-ru|Керченско-Феодосийская десантная операция}}, ''Kerchensko-Feodosiyskaya desantnaya operatsiya'') and ended with the German '''Operation [[Bustard]] Hunt''' ({{lang-de|Unternehmen Trappenjagd}}), was a World War II battle between [[Erich von Manstein]]'s [[Nazi Germany|German]] and [[Kingdom of Romania|Romanian]] [[11th Army (Wehrmacht)|11th Army]] and the [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] [[Crimean Front]] forces in the [[Kerch Peninsula]], in the eastern part of the [[Crimean Peninsula]]. It began on 26 December 1941 with an [[amphibious warfare|amphibious]] [[landing operation]] by two Soviet [[Field army|armies]] intended to break the [[Siege of Sevastopol (1941–42)|Siege of Sevastopol]]. Axis forces first contained the Soviet [[beachhead]] throughout the winter and [[air interdiction|interdicted]] its naval supply lines through aerial bombing. From January through April, the Crimean Front launched repeated offensives against the 11th Army, all of which failed with heavy losses. The [[Red Army]] lost 352,000 men in the attacks, while the Axis suffered 24,120 casualties. Superior German artillery firepower was largely responsible for the Soviet debacle.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=163}}

On 8 May 1942, the Axis struck with great force in a major [[counteroffensive]] codenamed ''Trappenjagd'' which concluded by around 19 May 1942 with the liquidation of the Soviet defending forces. Manstein used a large concentration of airpower, heavily armed [[infantry]] divisions, concentrated [[artillery]] bombardments and amphibious assaults to [[breakthrough (military)|break through]] the Soviet front in its southern portion in 210 minutes, swing north with the [[22nd Panzer Division]] to encircle the Soviet [[51st Army (Russia)|51st Army]] on 10 May and annihilate it on 11 May. The remnants of the [[44th Army (Soviet Union)|44th]] and [[47th Army|47th Armies]] were pursued to [[Kerch]], where the last pockets of organized Soviet resistance were eradicated through German aerial and artillery [[firepower]] by 19 May. The decisive element in the German victory was the campaign of [[airstrikes]] against the Crimean Front by [[Wolfram von Richthofen]]'s 800 aircraft-strong ''[[8th Air Corps (Germany)|VIII. Fliegerkorps]]'', which flew an average of 1,500 [[sortie]]s per day in support of ''Trappenjagd'' and constantly attacked Soviet field positions, [[Armoured warfare|armored]] units, troop [[Column (formation)|column]]s, [[medical evacuation]] ships, airfields, and supply lines.{{sfn|Melvin|2010|p=268}} German bombers used up to 6,000 canisters of [[Butterfly Bomb|SD-2]] anti-personnel [[cluster munition]]s to kill masses of fleeing Soviet infantrymen.

Manstein's outnumbered 11th Army suffered 7,588 casualties, while the Crimean Front lost 176,566 men, 258 tanks, 1,133 artillery pieces and 315 aircraft in three armies comprising twenty-one [[division (military)|division]]s.{{sfn|Erickson|1975|p=347}} Total Soviet casualties during the five month-long battle amounted to 570,000 men, while Axis losses were 38,000. ''Trappenjagd'' was one of the battles immediately preceding the German summer offensive ([[Case Blue]]). Its successful conclusion allowed the Axis to concentrate their forces on Sevastopol, which was conquered within six weeks. The Kerch Peninsula was used as a launching pad by German forces to cross the [[Kerch Strait]] on 2 September 1942 during [[Operation Blücher]] II, a part of the German [[Battle of the Caucasus|drive]] to capture the [[Caucasus]] oilfields.

==Prelude==
[[File:Zdobycie przez wojska niemieckie miasta Kercz (2-830).jpg|thumb|right|German soldiers in Kerch, November 1941.]]
On 8 December 1941, ''[[Stavka]]'', the [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] [[Commander-in-chief|supreme command]], ordered [[General-Lieutenant]] [[Dmitry Timofeyevich Kozlov|Dmitry Kozlov]]'s [[Transcaucasian Front]] to begin planning for a major [[military operation|operation]] to cross the Kerch Strait and link up with the Soviet [[Separate Coastal Army]] holed up in [[Sevastopol]], thereby liberating the Crimea from the Germans.{{sfn|Glantz|House|1995|p=94}}{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=92}} The ambitious operation, the first major [[amphibious operation]] in Soviet history, was founded upon Soviet dictator [[Joseph Stalin]]'s belief in the German [[Wehrmacht]]'s imminent collapse.{{sfn|Melvin|2010|p=257}}{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=92}} The plan was drawn up by the Transcaucasian Front's [[chief of staff]] [[General-Major]] [[Fyodor Tolbukhin]].{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=92}}

Tolbukhin's plan was too complicated for the [[Red Army]]'s and [[Soviet Navy]]'s abilities.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=93}} It was based on multiple small [[Landing operation|landings]] at separate locations at separate times instead of one large, simultaneous landing.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=93}} Five [[Maritime transport|transport]] groups from [[Rear-Admiral]] [[Sergey Gorshkov]]'s [[Azov Flotilla]] would land 7,500 soldiers from the [[224th Rifle Division]] and [[302nd Mountain Rifle Division]] of the [[51st Army (Russia)|51st Army]] on eight isolated beaches north and south of Kerch.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=93}} After the Germans were [[military deception|distracted]] by this, the [[44th Army (Soviet Union)|44th Army]] would land at [[Feodosiya]] in the German rear.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=93}} [[Naval gunfire support]] would be provided by the [[Black Sea Fleet]].{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=93}} The [[Soviet Air Forces]], would contribute air cover from the [[Taman Peninsula]].{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=93}} The Soviets had the men and troop transports on hand but were compelled to use [[fishing trawler]]s for the actual landings due to the lack of [[landing craft]], had little experience with large-scale [[joint operations]] and were impeded by the stormy winter weather.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=93}}

A German [[Messerschmitt Bf 110]] [[reconnaissance]] aircraft noted the buildup of Soviet naval forces and reported it to [[Generalleutnant|Lieutenant General]] [[Hans Graf von Sponeck]]'s [[XXXXII Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXXXII Army Corps]] [[headquarters]].{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=93}} Sponeck issued a general alert for enemy amphibious landings in the Kerch Peninsula.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=93}} The mass of Sponeck's units had been transferred for the assault on Sevastopol and he had only the [[46th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|46th Infantry Division]] under Lieutenant General [[Kurt Himer]] who had assumed his command on 17 December, two [[coastal artillery]] [[battalion]]s equipped with obsolete World War I artillery pieces, a [[pioneer (military)|combat engineer]] [[regiment]] and a ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' [[anti-aircraft]] battalion.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|pp=93–94}} The 46th [[Infantry]] [[Division (military)|Division]], mostly up to strength, was woefully overextended holding down the entire Kerch Peninsula against potential Soviet landings.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=94}} Sponeck's only [[Military reserve|backup]] was the [[Kingdom of Romania|Romanian]] 8th [[Cavalry]] [[Brigade]] near [[Alushta]].{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=94}}

On the evening of 25 December 1941, the Soviet 224th Rifle Division and [[83rd Naval Infantry Brigade]] were packed into small craft on the Taman Peninsula and began to pass the Kerch Strait.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=94}}

==Battle==
===Kerch landing, 26 December – 28 December===
[[File:Керченская десантная операция.jpg|thumb|Map of the Soviet [[amphibious operation|amphibious]] offensive 26 December 1941 – 2 January 1942 (in Russian).]]
[[File:Bundesarchiv N 1603 Bild-097, Russland, Kertsch, Schiffe im Hafen.jpg|thumb|[[Cargo ship]] in German-controlled Kerch harbor in the winter of 1941.]]
Group 2 disembarked at Cape Khroni to the northeast of Kerch.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=94}} It consisted of the [[gunboat]] ''Don'', the transports ''Krasny Flot'' and ''Pyenay'', a [[tugboat]], two motor [[barge]]s that carried three [[T-26]] [[light tank]]s and a few artillery pieces, and 16 fishing trawlers.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=94}} [[Whaleboat]]s were substituted for landing craft, resulting in tediously slow landings and the drowning of men and equipment.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=94}} 697 men from the 2nd Battalion of the 160th Rifle Regiment landed at Cape Khroni by 0630 hours on 26 December and many drowned in the waves or were incapacitated by [[hypothermia]].{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=94}} Another [[rifle]] battalion landed at Khroni later that day with a [[platoon]] of T-26 [[tank]]s and [[light artillery]] pieces.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=95}} At Cape Zyuk, 290 troops got ashore in six hours but a few vessels foundered on the rocky beach. At Cape Tarhan only 18 soldiers got to the beach out of Group 3's landing force of 1,000 men due to a lack of whaleboats. West of Cape Khroni at Bulganak Bay the Azov flotilla landed 1,452 men, three T-26 tanks, two 76mm [[howitzer]]s and two 45mm [[anti-tank gun]]s. Two more landings at Kazantip Point and Yenikale were aborted due to stormy weather. By noon, the Red Army had 3,000 lightly armed men ashore north of Kerch in five separate [[beachhead]]s.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=96}} German resistance was minimal at first, but by 1050 hours [[He 111]] [[medium bomber]]s and [[Junkers Ju 87|Ju 87 ''Stuka'']] [[dive bomber]]s began attacking the Soviet landing forces. The cargo ship ''Voroshilov'' at Cape Tarhan was bombed and sunk with 450 troops aboard. One vessel with 100 men from Group 2 was bombed and sank off Cape Zyuk.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=96}} Lacking radios, the lightly-armed and half-frozen Soviet formations north of Kerch moved only one kilometer inland before stopping and [[field fortification|digging in]] for German [[counterattacks]]. The Soviet regimental [[Military commander|commander]]s, with little to no communications link to headquarters, decided to wait for planned reinforcements that were delayed for three days due to the unfavorable winter weather and never arrived to help them.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=96}}

The 302nd Mountain Rifle Division landed at Kamysh Burun south of Kerch and ran into extremely effective German resistance. Two German battalions from [[Colonel]] [[Ernst Maisel]]'s 42nd Infantry Regiment held perfect defensive positions on high ground that dominated the sand beaches. The landing at 0500 hours was stopped by an onslaught of German [[MG 34]] [[machine gun]], [[mortar (weapon)|mortar]] and light-artillery fire that prevented the whaleboats and fishing trawlers from advancing to the shore.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=97}} The 2nd Battalion of the 42nd Infantry Regiment devastated a Soviet landing at Eltigen. A Soviet [[naval infantry]] [[company (military unit)|company]] landed at Stary Karantin but was annihilated by a counterattack from [[Major (rank)|Major]] Karl Kraft's 1st Battalion/42nd Infantry. The second wave landed at 0700 hours and was also thrown back. Soviet troops seized the [[Dock (maritime)|dock]]s at Kamysh Burun, allowing the third wave to land there and create a foothold by afternoon. The ''Luftwaffe'' sank several ships offshore and only 2,175 troops out of the 5,200-strong Kamysh Burun landing force got ashore.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=97}}

[[File:Hans Graf von Sponeck.jpg|thumb|upright=0.8|[[Lieutenant General|''Generalleutnant'']] [[Hans Graf von Sponeck]].]]

Lieutenant General Kurt Himer was aware of the Soviet landings by 0610 hours but was uncertain where the Soviet point of main effort was due to the disunited nature of the Soviet forces. He ordered Colonel Friedrich Schmidt's 72nd Infantry Regiment to wipe out the Soviet force at Cape Khroni but lacked the troops to deal with the Bulganak Bay and Cape Zyuk formations. Himer improvised by ordering a headquarters company, 3rd Battalion/97th Infantry Regiment and an [[artillery battery]] of [[10.5 cm leFH 18|10.5 cm]] howitzers to tackle the Cape Zyuk landing. By midnight, infantry regiment (IR) 97 had its 1st and 3rd Battalions and two artillery batteries in position for a counterattack the next day.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=97}} At 1350 hours on 26 December, IR 72 reported that a captured Soviet officer from Cape Khroni had revealed the extent of the Soviet plan – to land 25,000 troops at Kerch. Himer acted decisively and decided to bring up 2nd Battalion/IR 97 from Feodosia as well to crush the Cape Zyuk force with IR 97's full strength. IR 42 would contain the Kamysh Burun landings until the northern Soviet forces were destroyed. A mixed alarm unit consisting of infantry, artillery and combat engineers would deal with the Bulganak Bay landing. Army Corps commander Lieutenant General Sponeck requested permission to use the Romanian 8th Cavalry Brigade to reinforce Himer.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=98}}

The counterattack against Zyuk was launched only at 1300 hours on 27 December due to the muddy roads. The beachhead was flat and devoid of [[flora]], offering no cover for either side. The Soviet 2nd Battalion/83rd Naval Infantry Brigade spotted the German deployment and launched an immediate attack with three T-26 tanks and several infantry companies. A [[3.7 cm Pak 36]] anti-tank gun fired 42 [[Shell (projectile)|rounds]] and knocked out all three Soviet tanks. Several German bombers showed up to support the German infantry and helped drive the Soviet naval infantry back to its beachhead but the Germans delayed their main attack until the next day.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=99}} At dawn, the two deployed infantry battalions of IR 97 attacked the Soviet position, supported by two 10.5&amp;nbsp;cm howitzers. A combat engineer company blocked the Soviet escape route to the east. The Soviet defensive position was hopelessly exposed. Six [[He 111]] bombers and a few ''Stukas'' bombed the Soviet troops. The Soviet defenses were smashed and by 1200 hours the Germans reached the beach. A number of Soviet troops fought on while waist-deep in the water. Their resistance fell apart by evening. 458 were captured and {{circa|300}} killed. Infantry Regiment 97 lost only 40 men killed or wounded in two days of destroying the Soviet beachhead at Cape Zyuk.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=99}} The Soviet beachhead at Cape Khroni was also wiped out by IR 72 on 28 December, with only 12 men swimming to safety. Himer's division took 1,700 prisoners and only the 1,000-strong Soviet force at Bulganak Bay remained, along with the Kamysh Burun beachhead as well as isolated pockets of Soviet resistance inland.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=99}}

===Feodosia landing, 29 December – 2 January===
[[File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-F016213-0015, Krim, Feodosija, Hans v. Ahlfen mit Offizieren.jpg|thumb|left|[[Lieutenant Colonel|''Oberstleutnant'']] [[Hans von Ahlfen]] with another officer near Feodosia in May 1942.]]
Feodosia, a mid-sized town with a pre-war population of 28,000, was lightly defended by two coastal artillery battalions and 800 combat engineers under the command of [[Lieutenant Colonel|''Oberstleutnant'']] [[Hans von Ahlfen]], which were refitting from the assault on Sevastopol.{{sfn|Melvin|2010|p=258}} The artillery units had 17 obsolete World War I-era German and [[Czechoslovakia|Czech]] 15&amp;nbsp;cm and four 10&amp;nbsp;cm howitzers. The engineers had only small arms.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=100}} A [[Boom (navigational barrier)|boom]] at the harbor entrance was supposed to deny the enemy access but had been left open due to negligence. The Romanian 3rd Rosiori [[Motorized infantry|motorized]] cavalry regiment was in reserve near Feodosia. Two more Romanian mountain infantry and cavalry brigades were halfway toward Kerch to crush the Soviet landings there.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=100}}

The 44th Army began loading up men and equipment at 1300 hours on 28 December into an invasion fleet at [[Novorossiysk]], which consisted of two [[light cruiser]]s, eight [[destroyer]]s, 14 transports and dozens of small craft. At 1730, the [[advance guard]] consisting of the [[Soviet cruiser Krasnyi Kavkaz|Soviet cruiser ''Krasnyi Kavkaz'']], the [[Fidonisy-class destroyer]]s ''[[Soviet destroyer Shaumyan|Shaumyan]]'', ''[[Soviet monitor Zhelezniakov|Zhelezniakov]]'', and ''[[Soviet destroyer Nezamozhnik|Nezamozhnik]]'' and [[patrol boat]]s and [[minesweeper]]s steamed towards Feodosia in relatively favorable weather permitting speeds of 16 knots. The destroyer ''Sposobnyi'' struck a [[naval mine]] and sank with 200 casualties. The Soviet troops were exposed to freezing weather and suffered from hypothermia and seasickness. Two Soviet [[submarine]]s waited above the surface at Feodosiya harbor to mark the port entrance with lights.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=99}} At 0350 hours on 29 December, the Soviet destroyers ''Shaumyan'' and ''Zhelezniakov'' showed up at Feodosia, fired star shells for illumination and followed up with a 13-minute barrage on the German defenses.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=100}} Four [[MO-class small guard ship]]s carrying 60 naval infantrymen secured the lighthouse at the harbor [[Mole (architecture)|mole]]. The naval infantrymen, led by [[Lieutenant]] Arkady F. Aydinov, captured two 3.7&amp;nbsp;cm Pak anti-tank guns and launched [[Pyrotechnic colorant|green]] flares to signal the all-clear for the follow-up forces. The German II./AR 54 gunners engaged the Soviet patrol boats without hitting them. Beginning at 0426 hours, the destroyer ''Shaumyan'' inserted a company of naval infantrymen in 20 minutes into the harbor. The destroyers ''Zhelezniakov'' and ''Nyezamozhnik'' landed more reinforcements soon after. ''Shaumyan'' was damaged by German artillery fire.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=101}}

[[File:KrasnyyKavkaz1930s3.jpg|thumb|Soviet [[cruiser]] ''[[Soviet cruiser Krasnyi Kavkaz|Krasnyi Kavkaz]]'']]
At 0500 hours, the cruiser ''Krasnyi Kavkaz'' began unloading 1,853 soldiers from the 633rd Rifle Regiment of the [[157th Rifle Division]] at the mole. The Germans concentrated all of their fire on the cruiser, hitting it 17 times and setting its No. 2 [[gun turret]] on fire. ''Krasnyi Kavkaz'' responded with its 180&amp;nbsp;mm batteries, landed its troops in three hours and then departed the harbor. The ''Luftwaffe'' arrived above the battlefield and sank a minesweeper and a patrol boat in the morning, but missed its chance to stop the main force from landing. By 0730, the Soviets were in full control of the port and began landing artillery and vehicles. The Soviets fought their way through the town and by 1000 hours the Germans fled after a brief fight. In a quickly executed operation, the Soviets landed 4,500 troops in the morning and parts of three divisions were ashore by the end of the day.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=101}} Sponeck immediately ordered the Romanian 8th Cavalry Brigade and 4th Mountain Brigade to turn around and form defensive positions around the Soviet bridgehead at Feodosia. He requested permission from [[11th Army (Wehrmacht)|11th Army]] commander ''[[General of Infantry|General der Infanterie]]'' [[Erich von Manstein]] to withdraw the 46th Infantry Division from Kerch to avoid its encirclement but Manstein refused, ordering Sponeck to throw the enemy back into the sea with the help of reinforcements in the form of ''Gruppe'' Hitzfeld from the [[73rd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|73rd Infantry Division]] and the entire [[170th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|170th Infantry Division]], which would crush the Soviet landing force at Feodosia.{{sfn|Melvin|2010|p=258}}{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=102}} Sponeck then disobeyed orders, cut off contact with 11th Army headquarters and at 0830 hours on 29 December, ordered the 46th Infantry Division to retreat west from Kerch to avoid encirclement. Sponeck's order was highly controversial. There were insufficient German forces at Feodosia to stop further Soviet advances, but there were 20,000 Romanian troops in the vicinity and strong German reinforcements on the way. Two Romanian brigades launched a counterattack on 30 December, but were defeated in large part due to their insufficient air and artillery support.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=102}}

The 46th Infantry Division retreated 120 kilometers through a snowstorm in two days from 30–31 December. A number of vehicles were abandoned due to a lack of fuel. Moving from Feodosia, the Soviet 63rd Mountain Infantry Division established a [[roadblock]] by the morning of 31 December and after a brief fight, the 46th took a detour cross country through a narrow 10-kilometer gap between the lead Soviet elements and the [[Sea of Azov]]. The 46th avoided encirclement, but suffered moderate equipment losses and light personnel casualties. It established a new defensive line to the east of [[Kirovske, Crimea|Islam Terek]]. On 31 December, 250 Soviet [[paratrooper]]s jumped from 16 [[TB-3]] bombers to close the gap between the Red Army and the Sea of Azov. The bombers were unsuitable for [[airborne operation]]s and the Soviet paratroopers were too dispersed for decisive action. They caused a degree of worry at XXXXII Corps headquarters due to the darkness which concealed the limited nature of the operation. Sponeck was relieved of his command on 29 December for [[insubordination]] and [[court-martial]]ed in Germany three weeks later.{{sfn|Melvin|2010|p=258}} He was replaced by [[72nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|72nd Infantry Division]] commander ''General der Infanterie'' [[Franz Mattenklott]].{{sfn|Melvin|2010|p=258}} [[Army Group South]] commander-in-chief ''[[Colonel general|Generaloberst]]'' [[Walther von Reichenau]] ordered that, "because of its slack reaction to the Russian landing on the Kerch Peninsula, as well as its precipitate withdrawal from the Peninsula, I hereby declare 46. Infanterie-Division forfeit of soldierly honor. [[Military awards and decorations|Decorations]] and promotions are in abeyance until countermanded."{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=104}} 302nd Mountain Division attacked from its Kamysh Burun bridgehead to capture Kerch on 31 December after 46th Infantry Division's retreat. The 51st Army had four rifle divisions ashore and liberated the eastern Kerch Peninsula on 1 January.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=103}}{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=107}}

By 1 January XXXXII Army Corps had a defensive line 20 kilometers west of Feodosia. Gruppe Hitzfeld, led by [[Otto Hitzfeld]], arrived with IR 213 from the 73rd Infantry Division, an artillery battalion, an anti-tank gun battalion (''[[Panzerjäger]]-Abteilung 173''), four [[StuG III]] [[assault gun]]s and an anti-aircraft detachment. The Soviet [[236th Rifle Division]] attacked the Romanian 4th Mountain Brigade and gained ground. The Soviets advanced only 10 kilometers in three days after landing at Feodosia on 29 December. Their failure to cut off the 46th Infantry Division and destroy the Romanian brigades was criticized by Manstein as a missed Soviet opportunity to destroy the entire 11th Army.{{sfn|Melvin|2010|p=258}} On 1 January the 44th Army had 23,000 troops ashore in three rifle divisions but this was insufficient for sustained offensive operations against Manstein.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=107}} A Soviet infantry-[[Armoured warfare|armored]] attack on the XXXXII headquarters at Islam-Terek failed after 16 T-26 tanks were knocked out by the fresh ''Panzerjäger-Abteilung 173''.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=103}} By 2 January, the follow-up effects of the Soviet success at Feodosia fizzled out and the 44th Army's combat operations degenerated into a static defense.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=107}}

The Soviet landings prevented the fall of Sevastopol and seized the initiative.{{sfn|Forczyk|2008|p=13}} They did not succeed in their main objective of relieving Sevastopol.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=122}} Casualties were high. The Soviet forces involved in the Kerch-Feodosia landing operation from 26 December 1941 through 2 January 1942 lost 41,935 men, including 32,453 killed or captured and 9,482 wounded or sick.{{sfn|Krivosheev|1997|p=122}}

===German counterattack, 15 January – 20 January===
[[File:Crimean Front commander Lt Gen Dmitry Kozlov.jpg|thumb|Lieutenant General Dmitry Kozlov commanded the Crimean Front during the battle]]
The 51st Army moved with extreme slowness from Kerch, reaching the Parpach Narrows on 5 January but deploying only two rifle divisions in its forward elements on 12 January. It conducted no offensive action against the 46th Infantry Division aside from minor [[static warfare]] raiding.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=108}} The Axis response was far quicker. Mattenklott's XXXXII Corps received the 170th and [[132nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|132nd Infantry Division]]s as reinforcements along with two battalions from the 72nd Infantry Division, {{circa|5}} StuG III assault guns and the Romanian 18th Infantry Division. Its task was to hold the line against the 51st Army. Manstein also diverted the [[XXX Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXX Corps]] under ''Generalmajor'' [[Maximilian Fretter-Pico]] from the siege of Sevastopol to lead a counteroffensive composed of four Axis divisions that were in place by 13 January. The objective was to recapture Feodosia and throw the 44th Army off balance. ''Luftwaffe'' reinforcements poured in to meet Manstein's demand for air support and a new Special Staff Crimea was created under the command [[Robert Ritter von Greim]] to lead operations in the peninsula.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=108}} Kozlov's Transcaucasian Front (which had now become the [[Caucasus Front (Soviet Union)|Caucasus Front]]) leadership did not believe the Axis were strong enough to mount an attack and did not order his two armies to dig in. Prior to his planned main offensive, he landed 226 soldiers on board the destroyer ''Sposobnyi'' 40 kilometers southwest of Feodosia as a diversion but succeeded in drawing off only one company of ''Panzerjäger'' to contain it – which Kozlov translated as weakness.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=109}}

On 16 January, Kozlov landed the 226th Rifle Regiment behind German lines at [[Sudak]]. Supported by the battleship [[Russian battleship Sevastopol (1911)|''Parizhskaya Kommuna'']], the cruiser [[Soviet cruiser Krasnyi Krym|''Krasnyi Krym'']] and four destroyers, the Soviets quickly dispersed the small Romanian [[garrison]] in the town with naval gunfire. After wading ashore, the Soviet regiment sat tight and entrenched itself. Manstein correctly saw the operation as a distraction and sent only a token watch force to keep the Soviets occupied.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=110}} The Soviet landing force at Sudak initially resisted the counterattacks of two Romanian infantry battalions. The Germans used their [[airpower]] and artillery to reduce the Soviet force through [[attrition warfare]]. The 226th Rifle Regiment had no supporting artillery, anti-tank armament or mortars and could not fight back.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=164}} Kozlov sent more troops to Sudak from 24 through 26 January to bring the total number of troops landed to 4,264. XXX Corps deployed more reinforcements to crush the Soviet units and by 28 January the battle was over. 2,000 Soviet troops were killed at Sudak, another 876 prisoners were taken and executed, 350–500 joined [[partisan (military)|partisan]] groups, while the rest laid low in the [[wilderness]]. Fretter-Pico tasked a Romanian [[mountain infantry]] battalion with mopping up operations, which continued for five months until June.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=112}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1995-082-19, Otto Hitzfeld.jpg|thumb|''[[Oberst]]'' [[Otto Hitzfeld]] led the attack that recaptured Feodosia. He was awarded the [[Knight's Cross of the Iron Cross]] on 17 January 1942 and is seen wearing it on this 25 February 1942 photo.]]

The Soviet 236th Rifle Division's forward security zone was 20 kilometers west of Feodosia and the [[main line of resistance]] ran atop a major ridge 15 kilometers from the town. At daybreak on 15 January, He 111 medium bombers and Stuka dive bombers began attacking the Soviet positions on the ridge and were preceded by a quick artillery preparation. German bombers located the 44th Army headquarters, destroyed it and severely wounded its commander, throwing the Soviet leadership into chaos. Otto Hitzfeld's IR 213 attacked, supported by two battalions from the 46th Infantry Division (ID) and three StuG IIIs. The Germans achieved complete surprise and swiftly overran the Soviet positions. The StuGs knocked out two T-26 tanks but lost one of their own to a Soviet 76.2&amp;nbsp;mm anti-tank gun. The ridge-line west of Feodosia was in German hands by afternoon, along with a dominant position over the 44th Army. In the north, 46 ID and the Romanian 8th Cavalry Brigade launched distraction attacks against 51st Army and succeeded in drawing the majority of the Soviet reserves into an irrelevant sector. Fretter-Pico's XXX Corps lost 500 men killed, wounded and missing in its 15 January attack against the 236th Rifle Division. In exchange, five German infantry battalions backed up by powerful air support and several assault guns crushed a Soviet division and established an ascendancy over the 44th Army.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=109}}

The German counteroffensive continued on 16 January. Fretter-Pico reinforced Hitzfeld with more battalions as the Soviet 63rd Mountain and 236th Rifle Divisions lost ground and were pushed into narrow, isolated sectors close to the sea. In the afternoon, the 132nd Infantry Division began deploying for an attack into Feodosia. The ''Luftwaffe'' bombed the Red Army at Feodosia with impunity. The Soviets mistakenly located the German main point of effort at [[Vladislavovka railway station|Vladislavovka]] to the north of Feodosia and launched a battalion-sized armored-infantry counterattack there. They were stopped in their tracks by ''Sturmgeschütz-Abteilung 190'' StuG IIIs, which knocked out 16 T-26 tanks.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=110}} 32 ID assaulted Feodosia at dawn on 17 January. The Red Army troops in the town fought on through heavy street combat but were badly hampered by constant ''Stuka'' attacks as well as German artillery and machine gun fire. Impenetrable black smoke clouds formed above the burning buildings. Owing to ceaseless German airstrikes, a Black Sea Fleet evacuation of the trapped 236th Rifle Division failed. The formation was destroyed and 5,300 prisoners were taken by Fretter-Pico's men on 17 January. Its commanding officer escaped but was convicted and executed by a Soviet [[military tribunal]] three weeks later.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=111}}

XXX Corps' attack intensified on 19 January as the remaining two divisions of the 44th Army were pursued along the Black Sea coast, unraveling the Soviet forward positions to the north. On 20 January, the XXXXII and XXX Corps reached the Parpach Narrows, greatly shortening the front-line. Kozlov was thrown into a panic and predicted the Soviet landing force's complete destruction. The Soviets paid the price for their slow westward deployment from Kerch, as they lacked the reserves to throw back this new and potent German threat. Soviet generals complained about the impassable roads, although this did not stop the German 46th Infantry Division from executing a fast march over the same terrain in late December. Both sides began to construct defensive positions reinforced by [[dugout (military)|dugout]]s, trenches and [[barbed wire]]. XXX Corps defeated the 44th Army in five days, threw two Soviet armies on the defensive, killed an estimated 6,700 Soviet troops, destroyed 85 tanks and took 10,000 prisoners and 177 guns for the cost of 995 casualties, of which 243 were killed or missing.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=112}}{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=123}} The Caucasus Front, having lost 115,630 men in January, was too shaken and weakened by Manstein's rapid counter-stroke and the ''Luftwaffe's'' anti-shipping campaign to mount large-scale offensive operations for more than a month.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=119}}{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=165}} The Germans lacked armor and sufficient air units to exploit their victory to the hilt.{{sfn|Melvin|2010|p=259}}

===Battle of the Parpach Narrows, 27 February – 11 April===
''Stavka'' reinforced the Caucasus Front Front with nine rifle divisions. Soviet engineers built an ice road across the frozen Kerch Strait, enabling 96,618 men, 23,903 horses and 6,519 motor vehicles to reinforce the Kerch peninsula forces. The [[47th Army]] was deployed to the area, initially with only two rifle divisions.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=119}} The ''Stavka'' created the [[Crimean Front]] under, with Kozlov as its commander, on 28 January, with the 44th, 47th and 51st Armies belonging to it organically and the Separate Coastal Army and Black Sea Fleet falling under its operational command.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=122}}{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=119}} Kozlov had little command experience beyond the regimental level and his staff was as inept.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=119}} ''Stavka'' representative [[Lev Mekhlis]] arrived at the Crimean Front HQ in late January and introduced his own ideas into the planning stage.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=144}} Stalin and Mekhlis wanted to liberate the Crimea with an offensive on 13 February, but the Soviet forces were unequal to the task.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=148}}{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=119}} Soviet troops lacked food and three 76mm artillery regiments had no ammunition at all.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=122}} The backward nature of the Kerch peninsula's road network, the muddy roads and the ''Luftwaffe's'' bombing campaign against ports and Soviet cargo shipping prevented a sufficient [[logistics|logistical]] buildup and made Stalin's demand unrealistic.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=121}} On 27 February Kozlov finally had available for his operation the required 93,804 troops, 1,195 guns and mortars, 125 anti-tank guns, 194 tanks and 200 aircraft.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=149}} These forces were assembled in nine rifle divisions at the front along with numerous tank brigades containing T-26, [[T-34]] and 36 [[KV-1 tank]]s. The Soviets were far from ready.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=151}} Their tanks and aircraft lacked fuel supplies, many weapons did not work, the Soviet artillery had not organized a fire system, communications between Kozlov's HQ and the Crimean Front armies were repeatedly cut off and engineers had not constructed field works of any kind.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|pp=151–152}} Under pressure from Stalin, Kozlov started his attack anyway.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=121}}

====First Offensive, 27 February – 3 March====
The 51st Army planned to attack in the north on 27 February across a flat, 80-square kilometer plain dotted only by a handful of small villages. The Germans fortified the villages of Tulumchak, Korpech’, and Koi-Asan. The German 46th and 132nd Infantry Divisions held the XXXXII Corps front along with the Romanian 18th Infantry Division. Gruppe Hitzfeld waited in reserve. The Axis defensive preparations were extensive and in accordance with German tactical doctrine. Reinforced German [[strongpoint]]s had all-around defenses, neutralizing the effects of simultaneous Soviet frontal and flank attacks, and the Germans created a system of engineering works permeated with augmented artillery fires.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=156}} Mattenklott made the mistake of putting the Romanian 18th Infantry Regiment into a difficult and exposed position in a salient on the northern part of the line. The Soviet planners, led by Tolbukhin, failed to account for the warm weather that turned the terrain into a sea of mud.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=121}}

51st Army's offensive kicked off at 0630 hours on 27 February with a 230-gun artillery preparation of which most were light 76&amp;nbsp;mm guns and only 30 were heavy 122&amp;nbsp;mm guns.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=121}} The fortified German strongpoints were largely unharmed by the light [[high-explosive]] rounds.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=121}} German artillery responded with its own fire and the Soviets lacked the counter-battery capabilities to suppress them.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=122}} The open terrain provided no cover for the Red Army soldiers, who were systematically killed and wounded in great numbers by incessant German artillery strikes.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=163}} The heavy Soviet KV-1s sank into the mud and could not get forward.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=163}} Vehicles were also stuck and Soviet artillery shells had to be carried by hand.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=163}} Confused Soviet soldiers trampled their comrades to death in the mud.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=163}}

The German strongpoint at Tulumchak was overrun by T-26 tanks and infantry, although seven tanks were lost to German [[Teller mine]]s; and the Romanian 18th Infantry Regiment was routed.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=122}} A German artillery battalion in support of the Romanians lost all 18 of its 10.5&amp;nbsp;cm leFH howitzers and 14 3.7&amp;nbsp;cm PaK guns.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=122}} Kozlov's push was supported by 100 Air Force of the Crimean Front [[sortie]]s that day, while the Luftwaffe flew only three sorties in the area.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=122}} After a five-kilometer Soviet penetration, Gruppe Hitzfeld sealed off the attack with artillery, anti-tank and machine-gun fire.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=122}}{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=154}} Strongpoint Korpech’ remained in German hands and subjected the attacking Soviets to withering machine gun and mortar fire.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=122}} Kozlov added the [[77th Mountain Rifle Division]] into the right-wing attack at the plain, while Mattenklott redeployed Hitzfeld's IR 213 and I./IR 105 to help out the Romanians.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=122}} Hitzfeld attacked on 28 February and took back a part of the lost ground.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=122}} The Romanians proved brittle and 100 were captured as the 77th Mountain Rifle Division made a small penetration and captured Kiet hamlet, threatening to outflank all of 11th Army.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}} Hitzfeld counterattacked and retook Kiet, stabilizing the line.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}} The Soviet attack against the Romanians continued on 1 March until it was stopped by the arrival of the German 170th Infantry Division.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}} The rest of the Soviet effort slackened.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}} The 44th Army's weak attacks failed to tie down all German troops opposite it and could not prevent reinforcements from moving to the threatened north.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}} The Soviets lost 40 tanks in three days from 27 February – 1 March.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}} Soviet naval bombardments of Feodosia and [[Yalta]] achieved little, as did a small and quickly withdrawn landing at [[Alushta]] on 1 March.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}}

The German strongpoint at Koi-Asan, held by IR 42 and 72 in the junction between XXXXII and XXX Corps was the pivot of Manstein's defense and its control allowed the Germans to feed reserves into the north with little difficulty.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}} Kozlov directed two rifle divisions, three tank brigades and a tank battalion to take the village on 2 March.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}} German [[Anti-tank obstacles|obstacles]] slowed down the Soviet tanks, turning them into easy targets for German anti-tank units and artillery.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}} The Luftwaffe made its presence felt with 40 ''Stuka'' sorties on the overcrowded Soviet tank masses.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}} The Soviets admitted to losing 93 tanks in one day.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=123}} Their gains were comparatively minor: four Czech-made German howitzers were destroyed and the Soviet Air Forces bombed and destroyed a 23-ton ammunition dump at Vladislavovka.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=124}} The Soviets called off their attack on 3 March.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=124}} Kozlov's big push failed and from 27 February he suffered extremely heavy losses of infantry and tanks, including 28 KV-1s.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=124}} He had gained an exposed salient, which he could hold only with light forces due to its lack of cover.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=124}}

====Second Offensive, 13 March – 15 March====
[[File:Walki uliczne w mieście na Krymie (2-840).jpg|thumb|German soldiers during street fighting in the Crimea, March 1942.]]
Kozlov blamed the weather for his failure, while Mekhlis decided the fault lay with Tolbukhin's inept planning and had him fired.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=124}}{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=161}} Stalin ordered the second offensive to proceed in ten days.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=124}} The Soviet planning staffs saw Koi-Asan as the priority target and decided to mass 51st Army's striking power against it.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=124}} The 44th Army would launch a significant feint attack on the 132nd Infantry Division along the coast.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=124}} Kozlov had 224 tanks, but on Mekhlis' recommendation he decided to share them between the rifle divisions instead of massing them in a strike force.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=124}} Stalin reinforced the Air Force of the Crimean Front to 581 aircraft by early March, though they were largely obsolete models.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=124}} The Germans laid down 2,000 Teller mines near the Koi-Asan position and Manstein concentrated assault guns for its defense.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=124}}

The Soviets attacked at 0900 hours on 13 March with three rifle divisions that were quickly cut to pieces in the boggy terrain. The supporting Red Army tanks were easily destroyed by StuG IIIs and anti-tank guns. Lieutenant Johann Spielmann's StuG III destroyed 14 T-34s in one day while Fritz Schrödel's StuG III destroyed eight Soviet tanks, of which two were KV-1s. Soviet tank losses were large, with 157 tanks destroyed in three days. The [[56th Tank Brigade]] lost 88 tanks.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=125}} The Soviet attempt to capture Koi-Asan failed yet again but the fighting had been bitter.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=124}} The German 46th Infantry Division repulsed at least 10 Soviet attacks during the three day offensive.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=124}} On 24 March, strongpoint Korpech’ fell to the 51st Army after the Soviet infantry suffered heavy losses. The Crimean Front had fired off most of its artillery ammunition and could not proceed further despite its limited success. II./[[Jagdgeschwader 77|JG 77]], a German fighter wing, arrived in the Crimea after refitting and began to weaken Soviet air superiority. The 60-ton ammunition dump at Vladislavovka was again blown up by Soviet bombers.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=125}}

====German counterattack, 20 March====
The [[22nd Panzer Division]] was a fresh German [[Panzer division|armored division]] and was tasked by Manstein with the recapture of Korpech’. The division was not yet fully equipped with its supporting elements and its tanks were mostly obsolete Czech-built [[Panzer 38(t)]]s. Its attack at 0600 hours on 20 March in dense fog ran headlong into an offensive buildup of Soviet armor and went badly wrong. One of the division's battalions had to stop after meeting a [[minefield]], while another lost cohesion in the fog. The Soviet [[55th Tank Brigade]] blocked the road to Korpech’ with a battalion of T-26s and four KV-1s. A battalion of Regiment 204 lost 40% of its tanks destroyed or damaged after running into a concentration of Soviet 45&amp;nbsp;mm anti-tank guns. After three hours the German attack was called off. 22nd Panzer lost 32 of 142 tanks destroyed or damaged, including 17 Panzer 38(t), nine [[Panzer II]] and six [[Panzer IV]].{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=126}} Manstein conceded he had prematurely committed an inexperienced, half-deployed division into an all-out assault but pointed out that an immediate counterattack was necessary as his army was in danger of losing its critical defensive positions. Also, the division did succeed in disrupting the Soviet attack preparations.{{sfn|Melvin|2010|p=262}}{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=124}}

====Third Offensive, 26 March====
Kozlov's third drive on Koi-Asan began after a week of replacements, restocking and reinforcements; it was a smaller operation conducted by the [[390th Rifle Division]] and 143rd Rifle Brigade of the 51st Army, supported by two T-26 companies, six KVs, and three T-34s from the 39th and 40th Tank Brigades and the 229th Separate Tank Battalion. It failed on the first day after immense losses and quickly died down.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=126}} As a result of these operations, the 51st Army suffered losses of 9,852 killed, 4,959 missing, and 23,799 wounded for a total of more than 39,000 casualties between 10 and 31 March.{{sfn|Isaev|2016|p=566}}

====Fourth Offensive, 9 April – 11 April====
Mounting ''Luftwaffe'' air superiority began to tell as Kerch port came under heavy and sustained German air attack, constraining the buildup of Soviet armor and artillery. Mekhlis demanded that massed tank attacks be made against the unbroken German lines.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=126}} Manstein received more reinforcements in the form of the [[28th Jäger Division (Wehrmacht)|28th Light Infantry Division]], which was equipped with the new, easily concealed, low-silhouette [[2.8 cm sPzB 41]] light anti-tank gun.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=124}} One of its soldiers, ''[[Obergefreiter]]'' Emanuel Czernik, destroyed seven T-26s and one [[BT tank]] in one day with the weapon. Manstein estimated the Soviet attack strength as six to eight rifle divisions and 160 tanks.{{sfn|Melvin|2010|p=263}} After three days of heavy losses, Kozlov called off his fourth and as it turned out, final offensive.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=163}} He withdrew back to his February starting positions by 15 April.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=163}} The Crimean Front was now heavily weighted toward its right flank – 51st Army – leaving the 44th Army on the left depleted and the 47th Army in reserve a ghost command.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=127}}

Kozlov's four major offensives from 27 February through 11 April were all defeated by Manstein's 11th Army with heavy Soviet losses. From 1 January to 30 April, Kozlov's Crimean Front, including the forces at Sevastopol, lost 352,000 men of which 236,370 were lost from February through April in the Parpach Narrows fighting.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=164}}{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=127}} The Front's losses were the second-heaviest of any Soviet Front during the period.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=164}} The offensives cost the Crimean Front 40% of its manpower, 52% of its tanks and 25% of its artillery.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=163}} Axis 11th Army casualties from January to April 1942 were far fewer at 24,120 men.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=127}} The result was an unbalanced loss ratio of 14–1. Insufficient artillery and air support and ignorance of the German defenses were singled out by Soviet critics as the causes of the failure.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=163}} The Crimean Front had been all but destroyed as a combat-effective formation and would be completely routed from the peninsula in May.{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=164}} For four months, Manstein had conducted a successful defense on two fronts at once. The spring thaw arrived in early May, and both sides prepared for the battle that would decide the campaign.{{sfn|Forczyk|2008|p=14}}

===Luftwaffe anti-shipping operations===

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-452-0985-36, Russland, Generäle Löhr und W. v. Richthofen.jpg|thumb|right|[[Alexander Löhr]], commander of ''[[Luftflotte 4]]'' (left) and [[Wolfram von Richthofen]], commander of ''[[8th Air Corps (Germany)|VIII. Fliegerkorps]]'' in February 1942.]]
To slow the Soviet build-up, [[Alexander Löhr]]'s [[Luftflotte 4|''Luftflotte'' 4]] was sent to the region to interdict shipping. The 7,500-[[tonnage|ton]] transport ''Emba'' was severely damaged on 29 January, but the ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' failed to prevent the transport of 100,000 men and hundreds of artillery pieces to Kerch between 20 January and 11 February. At Sevastopol, 764 tons of fuel and 1700 tons of supplies arrived at the port. On 13 February, the cruiser ''[[Soviet cruiser Komintern|Komintern]]'' and destroyer ''Shaumyan'' brought in 1,034 soldiers and 200 tons of supplies. The cruiser ''[[Soviet cruiser Krasnyi Krym|Krasnyi Krym]]'' and destroyer ''Dzerzhinskiy'' brought in a further 1,075 men on 14 February. The next day, the minesweeper ''T410'' brought in 650 and evacuated 152. On 17 February, the transport ''Byelostok'' brought in 871 men. The [[Black Sea Fleet]] regularly shelled German positions on the coast. The ''Luftwaffe'' increased its pressure, dispatching [[KG 27]], [[KG 55]], and [[KG 100]] to bomb the ports at [[Anapa]], [[Tuapse]], and [[Novorossiysk]] on the Caucasian Black Sea coast. On 20 February, the 1,900-ton transport ''Kommunist'' was sunk by KG 100.{{sfn|Bergström|2007|p=27}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-F016217-0010A, Russland, Feldflugplatz mit zwei Flugzeugen Ju 52.jpg|thumb|German [[airfield]] in the [[Kerch Peninsula]] with two [[Junkers Ju 52]] [[Military transport aircraft|transports]], May 1942]]
Meanwhile, the ''Luftwaffe'' had flown in the specialist [[torpedo bomber]] unit [[KG 26]]. On 1/2 March 1942, it damaged the 2,434-ton steamer ''Fabritsius'' so severely that it was written off. The 4,629-ton oil tanker ''Kuybyshev'' was damaged on 3 March south of Kerch, which deprived the Soviets of much fuel. It was withdrawn to the port of Novorossiysk where it was crippled by [[Junkers Ju 88|Ju 88]]s of KG 51 on 13 March. On 18 March, [[KG 51]] Ju 88s sank the 3,689-ton transport ''Georgiy Dimitrov''. Further damage was done on 23 March when nine Ju 88s of KG 51 sank the minelayers ''Ostrovskiy'' and ''GS-13'' and a motor torpedo boat in Tuapse harbour. They also damaged two submarines (''S-33'' and ''D-5''). That evening, [[He 111]]s of KG 27 claimed one 5,000-ton and two 2,000-ton ships sunk. Soviet records recorded the sinking of the 2,960-ton steamer ''V. Chapayev'', with the loss of 16 crew and 86 soldiers.&amp;nbsp;{{Proper name|KG 51}} returned to Tuapse on 24 March and sank the transports ''Yalta'' and ''Neva''. On 2 April, the ''Kuybyshev'' was intercepted and sunk. So great was the loss of shipping that Soviet land forces were ordered to cease all offensive operations to conserve supplies. In the eight-week air offensive, from early February to the end of March, the Black Sea Transport Fleet had been reduced from 43,200 tons of shipping to 27,400 tons. Six transports had been lost and six were under repair. On 17 April, the 4,125-ton steamer ''Svanetiya''&lt;!--Forczyk has "Svanetia"  --&gt; was sunk by KG 26 during an attempt to supply Sevastopol. Approximately 535 men were lost. On 19 April, the tanker ''I. Stalin'' was damaged along with three other transports. On 21 April, [[KG 55]] damaged the minesweeper ''Komintern'' and sank a transport ship. By this time the Black Sea Fleet's ability to supply the Soviet forces in Sevastopol was severely curtailed.{{sfn|Bergström|2007|p=28}}

===Operation Bustard Hunt, 8 May – 19 May===
[[File:Radzieckie umocnienia i zasieki na półwyspie Kercz (2-831).jpg|thumb|Soviet fortifications and barbed wire on the Kerch Peninsula, May 1942]]
The Germans launched Operation ''Trappenjagd'' on 8 May 1942. ("Trappenjagd" is a German compound noun meaning "[[bustard]] hunt".) Prior to the offensive, the ''Luftwaffe'' succeeded in applying severe pressure to the Soviet supply lines. By late April food and other resources were virtually exhausted. Everything, including firewood had to be brought in by sea. The ''Stavka'' asked Stalin to consider the evacuation of the Kerch region. Stalin refused, and on 21 April ordered preparations for an offensive to retake the Crimea. On 6 May, he changed his mind and issued Order No. 170357, which ordered all forces to assume a defensive posture. He also refused to send more reinforcements. Mixed in with this order, was a limited offensive operation against German lines to improve the defenders' tactical positions. Instead of preparing for a defense against the impending German offensive, the Soviets were preparing for an attack.{{sfn|Bergström|2007|pp=31–33}}

For the defence of the peninsula, the Soviets had three armies; the 51st, protecting the north, had three rifle, two tank brigades and eight rifle divisions, while the 44th Army in the south had five rifle divisions and two tank brigades. The [[47th Army]], with four rifle and one cavalry division, was kept in reserve. The Air Force of the Crimean Front deployed 404 aircraft.{{sfn|Hooton|2016|p=116}} Kozlov did not expect a major attack as he outnumbered the Germans two to one. Moreover, on the southern front, he had swampy terrain which made it an unfavorable place for offensive operations. Although the Soviets constructed an anti-tank ditch that ran the entire length of the Parpach Narrows and had three lines of defense, the infantry units were deployed in one line at the front, with the tanks and cavalry in reserve.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=162}} Kozlov failed to deploy his troops into a well-prepared defense-in-depth.{{sfn|Forczyk|2008|p=35}}

[[File:Gen. Erich von Manstein na froncie pod Kerczem na Ukrainie. (2-678).jpg|thumb|Manstein at the frontline in the Kerch Peninsula, May 1942.]]

The German offensive had no option but to [[breakthrough (military)|break through]] the Soviet lines in the south head-on and then swing north with armored and motorized units to encircle the 51st Army. To do this, it needed exceptionally strong air support. [[8th Air Corps (Germany)|''Fliegerkorps'' VIII]] under the command of [[Wolfram Freiherr von Richthofen]] was sent to support the assault. The unit was the best equipped [[close air support]] corps in the ''Luftwaffe''. To bolster its strength, it was given the experienced KG 55 medium bomber wing.{{sfn|Brookes|2003|p=80}} Richthofen had 20 ''Gruppen'' comprising 740 aircraft and a number of seaplanes. Two ''Kampfgruppen'' were also made available by the [[4th Air Corps (Germany)|4th Air Corps]] of General [[Kurt Pflugbeil]].{{sfn|Hooton|2016|p=116}} The corps operated from newly-built [[airfield]]s as Richthofen had the airfield system expanded to reduce bomber sortie times. He was also fascinated and delighted by the 2 kilogram [[Butterfly Bomb|SD-2]] anti-personnel [[cluster bomb]]s and had more than 6,000 canisters of them delivered by the end of April.{{sfn|Hooton|2016|p=116}} By 8 May, he had 800 aircraft under his command in the Crimea and Soviet air superiority in the area had collapsed.{{sfn|Hooton|2016|p=116}} The limited Soviet air reconnaissance failed to spot this buildup.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=162}}

To maximize surprise, Manstein selected the swampy terrain held by the 44th Army as his main attack sector. Fretter-Pico's XXX Corps would breach the Soviet lines, allowing the 22nd Panzer Division to run riot through the gaps. Improved tactics for breaking through heavily defended enemy lines were utilised, built on the integration of infantry assault groups, assault guns, combat engineers, ''Panzerjäger'' and flak units. Fretter-Pico received 57 StuG IIIs, 12 of which had the new [[7.5 cm KwK 40]] gun, two batteries of [[8.8 cm Flak 18/36/37/41|8.8 cm Flak]] and ample combat engineer support. Only one German infantry division and the Romanians were in the north, while the rest were under Fretter-Pico's command.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=163}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-F016223-0024, Russland, Krim, Panzer IV im Einsatz.jpg|thumb|left|German [[Panzer IV]] tank and infantry in battle on the [[Kerch Peninsula]] in May 1942.]]

''Trappenjagd'' began at 04:15 on 8 May.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=164}} ''Fliegerkorps'' VIII operating under ''Luftflotte'' 4, began operations against lines of communication and against Soviet airfields. Within hours, Ju 87s of StG 77 had knocked out the Soviet 44th Army's critical communications and mortally wounded the 51st Army's commander. The airfields were destroyed and 57 of the 401 Soviet aircraft in the area were shot down in 2,100 German sorties. With the army's Headquarters knocked out, the Soviets could not organise a counter offensive and the 44th Army collapsed into a retreat when Manstein launched the ground attack.{{sfn|Bergström|2007|pp=31–33}} Manstein had five infantry divisions, the 22nd Panzer Division, and two and a half Romanian divisions against 19 Soviet divisions and four armoured brigades at Kerch. The 902nd Assault Boat Command of the 436th Regiment, 132nd German Infantry Division, landed behind the Soviet lines and helped unbuckle the Soviet second lines.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=166}} The Soviet Black Sea Fleet failed to stop the German seaborne attack. The German artillery bombardment, which included four ''Nebelwerfer'' rocket batteries, lasted only 10 minutes, and within 210 minutes of the assault being launched, the second defensive line of the 44th Army was broken.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|pp=164–165}} ''Stukas'', [[Henschel Hs 129]]s, [[Ju 88]]s and He 111s raked the Soviet positions, paving a smooth road for the German ground forces. Soviet field fortifications were neutralized by ''Fliegerkorps'' VIII's [[close air support]] and [[air interdiction]] capabilities. The 44th Army's 157th and [[404th Rifle Division]]s were mauled and paralyzed in their movements by the ''Stuka''s and Hs 129s.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=166}} In one incident, 24 counterattacking Soviet tanks were destroyed on sight by StuG IIIs for the loss of only one German assault gun.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=166}} The 56th Tank Brigade and 126th Separate Tank Battalion launched a counterattack with 98 tanks, including seven KV-1 against the 28th Light Infantry Division. ''Stukas'' and Hs 129 Bs showed up and destroyed the attacking Soviet tanks. An estimated 48 Soviet tanks were knocked out, including all seven KV-1.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=166}} On the first day, XXX Corps, attacking with the 28th, 50th and 132nd Divisions broke through in the south. At a cost of 104 killed and 284 wounded, they captured 4,514 Soviet soldiers.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=166}} The German engineers partially bridged the anti-tank obstacles on 8 May to prepare the way for the 22nd Panzer Division. Kozlov did not appreciate the significance of the German breakthrough and failed to release reserves for a counter-attack.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=166}}

[[File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-F016217-0015A, Krim, Panzerjäger Marder 2.2.jpg|thumb|right|[[Marder III]] [[tank destroyer]] mounting a captured 76.2mm Russian anti tank gun, deploying for an attack on the Kerch Peninsula in May 1942]]

On 9 May, the German engineers finished breaching the anti-tank ditch and Manstein committed the 22nd ''Panzer'' Division, which swung north and trapped the 51st Army against the [[Sea of Azov]] on mid-day 10 May.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=168}} Confused Soviet counterattacks near [[Arma-Eli]] were blasted apart by German close air support and infantry-armor teams. The remaining combat-capable Soviet armor was eliminated by German airpower on 9 May and 25 Soviet aircraft were shot down by German [[Bf 109]] fighters.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=166}} Richthofen's air units flew 1,700 sorties on 9 May and claimed 52 Soviet aircraft shot down for the loss of 2 of their own. A rainstorm gave the Soviets a brief respite on the evening of 9 May, but when it cleared the next morning, ''Fliegerkorps'' VIII destroyed the remaining isolated Soviet tanks, including 11 KV-1.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=167}} Soviet morale and organisation collapsed, and a stampede to the rear areas began. Once this happened, the eight divisions of the 51st Army surrendered on 11 May, releasing XXX Corps to pursue the fragments of retreating Soviet forces to [[Marfovka]], barely eight miles from Kerch.{{sfn|Forczyk|2008|p=36}} The motorized ''ad-hoc'' Groddeck brigade reached the Marfovka airfield in the afternoon and destroyed 35 fighters on the ground.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=167}} ''Fliegerkorps'' VIII's air supremacy peaked on 12 May, when it conducted 1,500 sorties without significant Soviet opposition and was free to bomb the fleeing Soviet columns, resistance nests and Kerch harbour.{{sfn|Hayward|1998|p=83}} Richthofen burned Kerch to the ground by dropping 1,780 bombs on it on 12 May.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=168}} That day, Richthofen was ordered to send the bulk of his combat units to support the [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|German 6th Army]] at the [[Second Battle of Kharkov]]. The number of flown missions was reduced accordingly; from 1,500 to 2,000 sorties per day prior to the redeployment to between 300 and 800 to the end of the Kerch operation.{{sfn|Hayward|1998|p=84}}  Richthofen described his bombing operations during ''Trappenjagd'' as 'concentrated air support, the likes of which has never existed'.{{sfn|Hooton|2016|p=116}}

[[File:Kercz - fotografia lotnicza. (2-833).jpg|thumb|Aerial photograph of Kerch, May 1942.]]

The speed of the advance was rapid. The 132nd Infantry Division overran several airfields, capturing 30 Soviet aircraft on the ground. On 10 May, ''Fliegerkorps'' VIII launched KG 55's He 111s against the Soviet forces. The large and slow He 111s made easy targets for ground fire, and eight were lost but the anti-personnel bombs ([[Butterfly Bomb|SD-2]]) were devastating to Soviet infantry. German bombers also attacked shipping evacuating personnel from Kerch. Three transports with 900 wounded aboard were sunk, along with a gunboat, six patrol boats and other small craft.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=168}} The 1,048-[[tonnage|ton]]  ''Chernomorets'' was sunk the same day.{{sfn|Bergström|2007|pp=34–35}} By this time, the air battle was won by the Luftwaffe. Despite the withdrawal of a number of ''Geschwader'' to support the 6th Army at the Second Battle of Kharkov, the ''Luftwaffe'' had destroyed Soviet aerial opposition and enabled the German Army to make deep penetrations, capturing 29,000 Soviet men, 220 guns and around 170 tanks.{{sfn|Brookes|2003|p=80}} Kerch fell on 15 May.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=169}} The ''Luftwaffe'' assisted the final defeat of Soviet ground forces on 20 May, when the last pocket of Soviet resistance south of Kerch was destroyed.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=170}}

==Aftermath==
Manstein destroyed three Soviet armies, wiping out nine Soviet divisions and reduced nine more to ineffective remnants.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=171}} Although forced to return several ''Luftwaffe'' units and the 22nd ''Panzer'' Division for [[Case Blue]], he could now concentrate his forces for an attack on Sevastopol.{{sfn|Forczyk|2008|p=36}}

===Analysis===
[[File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-F016237-0022A, Krim, russische Soldaten bei Gefangennahme.jpg|thumb|right|Five Soviet soldiers march to captivity on the Kerch Peninsula in May 1942. Three German tanks are visible on the background.]]
Manstein executed a successful [[combined-arms]] offensive, concentrating armored mobility as well as artillery and aerial firepower to annihilate a Soviet grouping twice his strength. The Soviets failed to conduct a defense-in-depth, allowing the Germans to puncture their lines on the first day of the offensive and defeat their counterattacks. Three Soviet armies either surrendered within four days, or were heavily mauled by Richthofen's ''VIII. Fliegerkorps'' while retreating.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=171}}

===Casualties===
In the 11 days of Operation Bustard Hunt, ''Fliegerkorps'' VIII lost 37 aircraft.{{sfn|Hooton|2016|p=117}} At the same time, the Air Force of the Crimean Front lost 417 aircraft.{{sfn|Hooton|2016|p=117}} Between 37,000–116,045 Soviet soldiers were evacuated by sea, of which 20% were wounded. An estimated 162,282 were left behind, killed or captured. 28,000 Soviet troops were killed and 147,000–170,000 taken prisoner, but according to Swedish historian Christer Bergström the prisoners included a large number of civilians.{{sfn|Bergström|2007|pp=31–33}}{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=171}} German casualties amounted to only 7,588 men in XXX and XLII Corps, including 1,703 killed or missing.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=171}} They expended 6230 tons of ammunition, losing nine artillery pieces, three assault guns and 8–12 tanks.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=171}}

Several groups of Soviet survivors refused to surrender and [[Defense of the Adzhimushkay quarry|fought on]] for many months, hiding in the catacombs of the quarries. Many of these soldiers were occupying the caves along with many civilians, who had fled the city of Kerch.{{sfn|Forczyk|2014|p=171}} The Germans also deployed [[Chemical warfare|poison gas]] against the survivors, thus furthering the casualties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Bellamy |first1=Chris |title=Absolute War: Soviet Russia in the Second World War |date=2008 |publisher=Knopf}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Citations==
{{notelist}}
{{Reflist|20em}}

==Bibliography==
{{Refbegin|35em}}
*{{cite book|last=Brookes|first=Andrew|title=Air War Over Russia|location = Shepperton, United Kingdom|publisher=Ian Allan Publishing|year=2003|isbn=978-0-7110-2890-6|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book|last=Bergström|first=Christer|title=Stalingrad – The Air Battle: 1942 through January 1943|publisher=Midland Publishing|location=Hinckley|year=2007| isbn=978-1-85780-276-4|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book
 | last = Erickson
 | first = John
 | authorlink = John Erickson (historian)
 | title = The Road to Stalingrad: Stalin's War With Germany
 | publisher = Yale University Press
 | year = 1975
 | location = New Haven, Connecticut
 | isbn = 978-0-300-07812-1
 | ref = harv
 | url-access = registration
 | url = https://archive.org/details/stalinswarwithge00eric
 }}
*{{cite book |last=Forczyk |first=Robert |title=Sevastopol 1942: Von Manstein's Triumph |publisher=Osprey|location=Oxford  |year=2008 |isbn=978-1-84603-221-9 |ref=harv }}
*{{cite book |last=Forczyk |first=Robert |title=Where the Iron Crosses Grow: The Crimea 1941–44 |publisher=Osprey|location=Oxford  |year=2014 |isbn=978-1472816788 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book
 | last1 = Glantz
 | first1 = David M.
 | authorlink1 = David Glantz
 | last2 = House
 | first2 = Jonathan
 | authorlink2 = Jonathan House
 | title = When Titans Clashed: How the Red Army Stopped Hitler
 | publisher = Kansas University Press
 | year = 1995
 | location = Lawrence, Kansas
 | isbn = 978-0-7006-0717-4
 | ref=harv}}
* {{cite journal|last1=Glantz|first1=David M.|title=Forgotten Battles of the German-Soviet War (1941-45), Part 6: The Winter Campaign (5 December 1941 – April 1942): The Crimean Counteroffensive and Reflections|journal=Journal of Slavic Military Studies|date=March 2001|volume=14|issue=1|pp=121–170|ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last=Hayward |first=J. | authorlink = Joel Hayward |title=Stopped At Stalingrad: The Luftwaffe and Hitler's Defeat in the East, 1942–1943 |publisher=[[University Press of Kansas]]|location=[[Lawrence, Kansas]]|year=1998 |isbn=978-0-7006-1146-1 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Hooton |first=E.R. |title=War over the Steppes: The air campaigns on the Eastern Front 1941–45 |publisher=Osprey|location=Oxford |year=2016 |isbn=978-1-47281562-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Krivosheev | first = Grigoriy| authorlink = Grigoriy Krivosheyev| title = Soviet Casualties and Combat Losses in the Twentieth Century| location = London| publisher = Greenhill Books| year = 1997| isbn = 978-1-85367-280-4| ref = harv}}
* {{cite book | last = Isaev | first = Alexei|display-authors=etal | year = 2016 |location = Moscow |publisher = Yauza/Eksmo |ref = harv|title = Битва за Крым 1941–1944&amp;nbsp;гг. |language = Russian |trans-title = Battle for Crimea 1941–1944 |isbn = 978-5-699-92485-1|edition = EPUB}}
* {{cite book | last = Melvin | first = Mungo | authorlink = Mungo Melvin | title = Manstein: Hitler's Greatest General | year = 2010 | publisher = Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson | location = London | isbn = 978-0-297-84561-4 | ref = harv}}
{{Refend}}

===Further reading===
{{Refbegin|35em}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Hayward|first1=Joel S. A.|title=The German Use of Air Power at Kharkov, May 1942|journal=Air Power History|date=Summer 1997|volume=44|issue=2|url=http://www.joelhayward.org/JH-Air%20Power%20History.pdf}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Hayward|first1=Joel S. A.|title=Von Richthofen's 'Giant fire-magic': The Luftwaffe's Contribution to the Battle of Kerch, 1942|journal=The Journal of Slavic Military Studies|date=June 1997|volume=10|issue=2|pages=97–124|doi=10.1080/13518049708430293|url=https://archive.org/stream/JoelHaywardvonRichthofensgiantFire-magicTheLuftwaffes/JoelHaywardRichthofen1#page/n0/mode/2up}}
*[[E.R. Hooton|Hooton, E.R.]]. ''Eagle in Flames: The Fall of the Luftwaffe''. Arms &amp; Armour Press. 1997. {{ISBN|1-86019-995-X}}
{{Refend}}

{{Coord missing|Ukraine}}

{{authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kerch Peninsula, Battle Of The}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:Crimea in World War II|Battle]]
[[Category:Kerch Peninsula|Battle]]
[[Category:1942 in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations involving Germany|Kerch Peninsula]]</text><sha1>2za1e5ix00gebwgd3n5uhpak9cxaimy</sha1></revision></page>