<page><title>Demyansk Pocket</title><ns>0</ns><id>2398404</id><revision><id>964191496</id><parentid>962262781</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-24T02:36:21Z</timestamp><contributor><username>JJMC89 bot III</username><id>35936988</id></contributor><minor /><comment>Moving [[:Category:Airbridge]] to [[:Category:Airbridge (logistics)]] per [[Wikipedia:Categories for discussion/Speedy]]</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="14850" xml:space="preserve">{{More footnotes|date=October 2008}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Demyansk Pocket
|partof=the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
|image= Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-003-3445-33, Russland, Lufttransport mit Junkers Ju 52.jpg
|image_size= 300px
|date=8 February – 20 May 1942
|place=[[Demyansk]], [[Russian SSR]], [[Soviet Union]]
|result= German defensive victory{{sfn|Glantz|2001|p=31}}
|combatant1={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|combatant2={{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
|commander1=[[Walter von Brockdorff-Ahlefeldt]]&lt;br&gt; [[Walther von Seydlitz-Kurzbach]]
|commander2=[[Pavel Kurochkin]]
|units1=[[16th Army (Wehrmacht)|16th Army]]
|units2=[[Northwestern Front]]
|strength1=100,000 &lt;small&gt;(initially)&lt;/small&gt;{{sfn|Hayward|1997|p=24}}{{sfn|Beevor|1999|p=43}}&lt;br&gt;31,000 &lt;small&gt;(reinforcements)&lt;/small&gt;
|strength2=400,000 &lt;small&gt;(initially)&lt;/small&gt;
|casualties1=11,777 killed&lt;br&gt;40,000 wounded&lt;br&gt;2,739 missing&lt;br&gt;265 aircraft destroyed&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''Total''':&lt;br&gt;55,000&lt;ref name="http://ww2stats.com/cas_ger_okh_dec42.html"&gt;{{cite web|url= http://ww2stats.com/cas_ger_okh_dec42.html |title=OKH Casualty Data December 1942 |accessdate=2015-03-24 |url-status=dead |archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20151228032412/http://ww2stats.com/cas_ger_okh_dec42.html |archivedate=2015-12-28 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2=88,908 killed &amp; missing&lt;br&gt;156,603 wounded&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''Total''':&lt;br&gt;245,500&lt;ref name="http://lib.ru/MEMUARY/1939-1945/KRIWOSHEEW/poteri.txt"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://lib.ru/MEMUARY/1939-1945/KRIWOSHEEW/poteri.txt |title=Г.Ф.Кривошеев (под редакцией). Россия и СССР в войнах XX века: Потери вооруженных сил|website=Lib.ru |date= |accessdate=2017-06-23}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| coordinates = |57|39|N|32|28|E|
| map_type = European Russia
| map_size = 200
| map_caption = Location of Demyansk within modern European Russia
}}
{{Campaignbox_Axis-Soviet_War}}
{{Campaignbox Leningrad and Baltics 1941-1944}}

The '''Demyansk Pocket''' ({{lang-de|Kessel von Demjansk|links=no}}; {{lang-ru|Демя́нский котёл|links=no}}) was the name given to the pocket of German troops encircled by the [[Red Army]] around [[Demyansk]], south of [[Leningrad]], during World War II on the Eastern Front. The pocket existed mainly from 8 February to 21 April 1942. A much smaller force was surrounded in the [[Kholm Pocket]] at the town of [[Kholm, Kholmsky District, Novgorod Oblast|Kholm]], about {{convert|100|km|mi|abbr=on}} to the southwest. Both resulted from the German retreat following their defeat during the [[Battle of Moscow]].

The successful defence of Demyansk, achieved through the use of an [[Airbridge (logistics)|airbridge]], was a significant development in modern warfare. Its success was a major contributor to the decision by the [[Oberkommando des Heeres|Army High Command]] to try the same tactic during the [[Battle of Stalingrad]] where it failed to save the 6th Army under Paulus.

==Encirclement==
The encirclement began as the Demyansk Offensive Operation, the first phase being carried out from 7 January-20 May 1942 on the initiative of General Lieutenant [[Pavel Kurochkin]], commander of [[Northwestern Front]]. The intention was to sever the link between the German Demyansk positions, and the [[Staraya Russa]] railway that formed the lines of communication of the German [[16th Army (Wehrmacht)|16th Army]]. However, owing to the very difficult wooded and swampy terrain, and heavy snow cover, the initial advance by the Front was very modest against stubborn opposition.

On 8 January, the [[Rzhev–Vyazma Strategic Offensive]] was launched by the Red Army. This incorporated the previous Front's planning into the [[Toropets–Kholm Offensive]] Operation between 9 January and 6 February 1942 which formed the southern [[pincer movement|pincer]] of the attack that, beginning the second phase of the northern pincer Demyansk Offensive Operation between 7 January and 20 May, which encircled the German 16th Army's (Generaloberst [[Ernst Busch (field marshal)|Ernst Busch]]) [[II Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|II Army Corps]], and parts of the [[X Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|X Army Corps]] during winter 1941/1942.

German forces inside the pocket consisted of :
;[[X Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|X Army Corps]] (General [[Christian Hansen (general)|Christian Hansen]]) 
*[[30th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|30th Infantry Division]] (Generalleutnant [[Kurt von Tippelskirch]])
*[[290th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|290th Infantry Division]] (Generalleutnant [[Theodor von Wrede]])
*[[SS Division Totenkopf]] (Obergruppenführer [[Theodor Eicke]])
;[[II Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|II Army Corps]] (General [[Walter von Brockdorff-Ahlefeldt]])
*[[12th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|12th Infantry Division]] (Oberst [[Karl Hernekamp]])
*[[32nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|32nd Infantry Division]] (Generalmajor [[Wilhelm Bohnstedt]])
*[[123rd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|123rd Infantry Division]] (Generalmajor [[Erwin Rauch]])
; auxiliary units
* units of [[Police Regiment North]]
* units of the [[Reich Labour Service]]
* units of [[organisation Todt]]
for a total of about 90,000 German troops and around 10,000 auxiliaries. Their commander was General [[Walter von Brockdorff-Ahlefeldt]], commander of the II Army Corps.

==Northwestern Front offensives==
[[Image:Demjansk Einkesselung.png|thumb|Offensive of the Red Army south of Lake Ilmen, 7 January–21 February 1942.]]

The intent of the Northwestern Front offensive was to encircle the entire northern flank of the 16th Army's forces, of which the 2nd Army Corps was only a small part, and the Soviet command was desperate to keep the Front moving even after this success. The first thrust was made by the [[11th Army (Soviet Union)|11th Army]], [[1st Shock Army]] and the [[1st Guards Rifle Corps|1st]] and [[2nd Guards Rifle Corps]] released for the operation from Stavka reserve. A second thrust was executed on 12 February by the [[3rd Shock Army|3rd]] and [[4th Shock Army|4th Shock Armies]] of the [[Kalinin Front]], with the additional plan of directly attacking the encircled German forces by inserting two airborne brigades to support the advance of the [[34th Army (Soviet Union)|34th Army]].{{sfn|Rutherford|2008|p=359}} The front soon settled as the Soviet offensive petered out due to difficult terrain and bad weather.

After being assured that the pocket could be supplied with its daily requirement of {{convert|300|ST|t|lk=on|abbr=on}} of supplies{{sfn|Hayward|1997|p=24}} by [[Luftflotte 1]], Hitler ordered that the surrounded divisions hold their positions until relieved. The pocket contained two viable airfields at Demyansk and [[Peski]] capable of receiving transport aircraft. From the middle of February, the weather improved significantly, and while there was still considerable snow on the ground at this time, resupply operations were generally very successful due to inactivity of the [[Soviet Air Forces|VVS]] in the area.{{sfn|Hayward|1997|p=24}} However, the operation did use up all of Luftflotte 1's transport capability, as well as elements of its bomber force.

Over the winter and spring, the Northwestern Front launched a number of attacks on the "Ramushevo corridor" that formed the tenuous link between Demyansk and Staraya Russa but was unable to reduce the pocket.

==Breakout==

On 21 March 1942, German forces under the command of General [[Walther von Seydlitz-Kurzbach]] attempted to manoeuvre through the "Ramushevo corridor". Soviet resistance on the Lovat River delayed II Corps' attack until April 14. Over the next several weeks, this corridor was widened. A [[Kampfgruppe|battle group]] was able to break the siege on 22 April, but the fighting had taken a heavy toll.{{sfn|Rutherford|2008|p=365}} Out of the approximately 100,000 men originally in the pocket, there were 3,335 lost and over 10,000 wounded.

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1972-042-42, Russland, Kesselschlacht von Demjansk.jpg|thumb|German forces near Demyansk, 21 March 1942.]]

Between the forming of the pocket in early February to the abandonment of Demyansk in May, the two pockets (including [[Kholm, Kholmsky District, Novgorod Oblast|Kholm]]) received {{convert|65000|ST|t|abbr=on}} of supplies (both through ground and aerial delivery), 31,000 replacement troops, and 36,000 wounded were evacuated. The supplies were delivered through over 100 flights of [[Junkers Ju 52]] transport aircraft per day.{{sfn|Beevor|1999|p=43}} The cost was significant: the Luftwaffe lost 265 aircraft, including 106 [[Junkers Ju 52]], 17 [[Heinkel He 111]] and two [[Junkers Ju 86]] aircraft. In addition, 387 airmen were lost.{{sfn|Bergstrom|2007|p=23}} [[Richard Overy]] argues that the Demyansk airlift was a [[Pyrrhic victory]], citing the loss of over 200 aircraft and their crew "when annual production of transports was running at only 500; and all to save 90,000 German soldiers, 64,000 of whom were either killed, wounded or too sick for service" by the airlift's end.{{sfn|Overy|1980|p=414}}

Fighting in the area continued until 28 February 1943. The Soviet forces did not retake Demyansk until 1 March 1943, with the organized withdrawal of the German troops.

== Effect of the Demyansk airlift operation ==
The success of the Luftwaffe convinced Reich Marschall  [[Hermann Göring]] and Hitler that they could conduct effective airlift operations on the Eastern front.{{sfn|Bergstrom|2007|p=23}} Furthermore, it "determined Hitler in his belief that encircled troops should automatically hold on to their territory.{{sfn|Beevor|1999|pp=43-44}}

After the German [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|6th Army]] was [[Operation Uranus|encircled]] in the Battle of Stalingrad, Göring convinced Hitler to resupply the besieged forces by airlift until a [[Operation Winter Storm|relief effort]] could reach them;{{sfn|Beevor|2012|p=286}} however, the sheer scale of the effort required in Stalingrad (calculated at 750 tons per day) greatly exceeded the Luftwaffe's now-depleted capacities.{{sfn|Hayward|1997|pp=24-26}} The Stalingrad airlift effort ultimately failed to deliver sufficient supplies, and the Germans estimated that they lost 488 transports, as well as 1,000 personnel, to the now-strengthened Soviet Air Forces.{{sfn|Beevor|1999|pp=292, 398}} Despite the Stalingrad airlift, the German 6th Army, counting 300,000 soldiers trapped in the city, had to surrender in February 1943, due to their degrading physical condition, as the supplies with food, new troops, weapons and ammunition was not sufficient to defeat the Soviet troops at Stalingrad. At the time of the surrender, the German [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|6th Army]] lost 100,000 soldiers at Stalingrad, counting from November 1942 until February 1943.

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Sources==
*{{cite book|last1=Beevor|first1=Antony|title=Stalingrad|date=1999|publisher=Penguin Books|location=London|isbn=9780140249859|ref=harv|url=https://archive.org/details/stalingrad00anth}}
*{{cite book|last = Beevor|first = Antony|title = The Second World War|publisher = Back Bay Books|location = New York|year = 2012|isbn = 978-0-316-02374-0|ref = harv|url = https://archive.org/details/secondworldwar00beev}}
*{{cite book|last1=Bergstrom|first1=Christer|title=Stalingrad: The Air Battle: 1942-January 1943|date=2007|publisher=Chevron/Ian Allan|location=London|isbn=978-1-85780-276-4|ref=harv}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20080224022418/http://victory.mil.ru/lib/books/h/nwf/index.html Сборник. На Северо-Западном фронте — М.: «Наука», 1969 (Вторая Мировая война в исследованиях, воспоминаниях, документах) Институт военной истории Министерства Обороны СССР; под редакцией и с предисловием члена-корреспондента АН СССР генерал-лейтенанта П. А. Жилина; cоставил и подготовил сборник кандидат военных наук, доцент, полковник Ф. Н. Утенков; научно-техническая работа проведена подполковником В. С. Кислинским.]
*{{cite journal|last1=Glantz|first1=David|title=The Ghosts of Demiansk: In Memory of the Soldiers of the Soviet 1st Airborne Corps|journal=Journal of Military History|date=October 1992|volume=56|issue=4|pages=617–650|doi=10.2307/1986164|jstor=1986164|ref=harv}}
*{{cite web|last1=Glantz|first1=David|title=The Soviet-German War 1941-1945: Myths and Realities: A Survey Essay|url=http://sti.clemson.edu/publications-mainmenu-38/commentaries-mainmenu-211/cat_view/33-strom-thurmond-institute/153-sti-publications-by-subject-area/158-history|website=Strom Thurmond Institute|date=2001|accessdate=2 May 2016|ref=harv|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20170722130850/http://sti.clemson.edu/publications-mainmenu-38/commentaries-mainmenu-211/cat_view/33-strom-thurmond-institute/153-sti-publications-by-subject-area/158-history|archive-date=22 July 2017|url-status=dead}}
*Group of authors, ''A collection. On the North-Western Front'', Moscow, Science (pub.), 1969 (Second World War in research, memoirs, documents), Institute of military history of Ministry of Defence of USSR, edited and with foreword by member-correspondent AN SSR, General-lieutenant P.A. Zhilin; compiled and prepared for publication by candidate of military sciences, dozent, Colonel F.N. Utenkov, scientific-technical work undertaken by Sub-colonel V.S. Kislinsky.
*{{cite journal|last1=Hayward|first1=Joel|title=Stalingrad: An Examination of Hitler's Decision to Airlift|journal=Airpower Journal|date=Spring 1997|volume=11|issue=1|pages=21–37|url=http://www.joelhayward.org/An-Examination-of-.pdf|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Overy|first1=Richard|title=Hitler and Air Strategy|journal=Journal of Contemporary History|date=July 1980|volume=15|issue=3|pages=405–421|jstor=260411|ref=harv}}
*{{cite journal|last1=Rutherford|first1=Jeff|title=Life and Death in the Demiansk Pocket: The 123rd Infantry Division in Combat and Occupation|journal=Central European History|date=2008|volume=41|issue=3|doi=10.1017/S0008938908000551|jstor=20457366|ref=harv}}

{{coord|57.6500|N|32.4667|E|source:wikidata-and-enwiki-cat-tree_region:DE|display=title}}
{{Authority control}}
{{Subject bar
| portal1=Military of Germany
| portal2=Soviet Union
| portal3=World War II
| commons=y
| commons-search=Battle of Demiansk
}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:Encirclements in World War II]]
[[Category:History of Novgorod Oblast]]
[[Category:Airbridge (logistics)|Demyansk]]</text><sha1>pdp5d25m0bhvt0qknkuzlz413yqxqjb</sha1></revision></page>