<page><title>Operation Braunschweig</title><ns>0</ns><id>17942346</id><revision><id>921694496</id><parentid>914900237</parentid><timestamp>2019-10-17T08:55:35Z</timestamp><contributor><username>BrownHairedGirl</username><id>754619</id></contributor><minor /><comment>replace links to deleted portals: [[Portal:Fascism]] → [[Portal:Politics]]</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="4087" xml:space="preserve">{{Campaignbox Operation Blue to 3rd Kharkov}}
'''Operation Braunschweig''' (''Brunswick''), named after [[Braunschweig]], was the German summer offensive that began on 28 June 1942. The operation was initially named ''[[Fall Blau]]'' (Case Blue), which is the common name used for the whole offensive. The name was changed from ''Blau'' to ''Braunschweig'' on 30 June.&lt;ref&gt;Schramm, 1942, Teilband 2, S. 60&lt;/ref&gt; The plans following the original Case Blue (originally named ''Blue I'' and ''Blue II'') were renamed to [[Operation Clausewitz (1942)|Operation Clausewitz]] and [[Operation Dampfhammer]]. ''Clausewitz'' detailed the beginning of the operations of [[Army Group A]] in July 1942, ''Dampfhammer'' the follow-up operations in July 1942.&lt;ref&gt;Schramm, 1942, Teilband 2, S. 1330&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Führer Directive]] No. 45, dated 23 July 1942, [[Adolf Hitler]]&lt;ref&gt;Schramm, 1942, Teilband 1, S. 520&lt;/ref&gt; outlined new goals for Operation ''Braunschweig''. The German forces were to advance towards the [[Caucasus]] ([[Operation Edelweiss]]) and Stalingrad ([[Operation Fischreiher]]).&lt;ref&gt;Schramm, 1942, Teilband 2, S. 1420&lt;/ref&gt;

Hitler had personally intervened in the plans for this operation, and ordered a split in [[Army Group South]]. This division of Army Group South had caused alarm in the General Staff, and Hitler was warned repeatedly about the dangers this division entailed.  Complaints from the field caused Hitler to dismiss and replace the Commander of Army Group South, [[Fedor von Bock|Field Marshal Fedor von Bock]] on July 15. Later studies confirmed this split to be one of the main causes for the eventual demise of the [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|German 6th Army]] in Stalingrad. Hitler persisted in this division of Army Group South for strategic reasons: acquiring the oilfields in the Caucasus region and cutting Soviet supply transports along the [[Volga]] through Stalingrad.

On July 23, 1942 Hitler met with Chief of staff Lutze and SA Obergruppenführer Jüttner at the Werwolf headquarters. They discussed several events but the key discussion surrounded Directive Number 45, which was a continuance of Operation Braunschweig. In this meeting Hitler stated several directives that, “[[Army Group A]] take the Caucasus and Baku (Operation Edelweiss), while [[Army Group B]] was supposed to conquer Stalingrad and, if possible, Astrakhan (Operation Heron – Fischreiher because of the fish in the Volga River). [[Army Group North]] was instructed to conquer Leningrad (Operation Fireworks because of artillery fire).”).”&lt;ref&gt;* Domarus, Max. Speeches and proclamations, 1932-1945. Wauconda, Il: Bolchazy-Carducci Publishers Inc., 2004.&lt;/ref&gt;

The directive said:
:“In a campaign of little more than three weeks, the ultimate goal I had set the south wing of the eastern front have already been accomplished. Only some rather weak enemy forces belonging to the armies of [[Semyon Timoshenko]] have managed to escape the envelopment and reach the bank of the Southern Don. These will presumably receive reinforcements from the Caucasus area.
:Currently the enemy is massing another army group in the Stalingrad area, where stiff resistance is to be expected.”&lt;ref&gt;* Domarus, Max. Speeches and proclamations, 1932-1945. Wauconda, Il: Bolchazy-Carducci Publishers Inc., 2004.(page 2654)&lt;/ref&gt;
The directives went on to explain just what each individual army should do in the upcoming assault.

== Bibliography ==
* Domarus, Max. Speeches and proclamations, 1932-1945. Wauconda, Il: Bolchazy-Carducci Publishers Inc., 2004.
* {{cite book|title = Kriegstagebuch des Oberkommandos der Wehrmacht, 1940–1945 Teilband II|author =  Schramm, Percy Ernst|publisher = Bernard &amp; Graefe Verlag für Wehrwesen|place = Bonn|year = 1963}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Subject bar
| portal1=Military of Germany
| portal2=Germany|portal20=Politics| portal3=Soviet Union
| portal4=World War II
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Braunschweig, Operation}}
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]</text><sha1>3x33822zb5ax9o4e95wglnsekb1dpqf</sha1></revision></page>