<page><title>Operation Mars</title><ns>0</ns><id>7213145</id><revision><id>966652417</id><parentid>964889361</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-08T10:34:05Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>2A02:C7D:6BD6:9900:3C69:F3BD:EFC9:F9F3</ip></contributor><comment>/* Soviet plans */ Fixed typo</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="18501" xml:space="preserve">{{About|the Soviet offensive operation in the Second World War|the German offensive in the First World War|Spring Offensive|the Portuguese military offensive|Operation Mars (Portugal)}}
{{more footnotes|date=April 2009}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2018}}

{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Operation Mars
| partof = the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
| image = Operation mars schema.JPG
| image_size = 300px
| caption = 
| date = 25 November – 20 December 1942
| place = [[Rzhev]] and [[Velikie Luki]] salients, [[Russian SFSR]]
| result = German victory 
* Soviet operational failure
| combatant1 = {{flagcountry|USSR|1936}}
| combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1 = {{flagicon|USSR|1936}} [[Georgy Zhukov]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|USSR|1936}} [[Ivan Konev]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|USSR|1936}} [[Maksim Purkayev]] 
| commander2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Walter Model]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Günther von Kluge]]
| strength1 = 702,923 personnel,&lt;br /&gt;1,718 tanks&lt;ref name="militera.lib.ru"/&gt;
| strength2 = 3 combined corps&lt;br /&gt;(with 13 infantry divisions&lt;br /&gt;and 2 paratrooper divisions)&lt;br /&gt;2 panzer corps&lt;br /&gt;(5 panzer divisions,&lt;br /&gt;3 motorized divisions)&lt;br /&gt;1,615 tanks&lt;ref name="militera.lib.ru"&gt;[http://militera.lib.ru/h/isaev_av6/08.html Исаев, Алексей Валерьевич. Когда внезапности уже не было. История ВОВ, которую мы не знали. — М.: Яуза, Эксмо, 2006. (Alexey Valeryevich Isayev. When the sudden element was lost – History of World War II, the facts that we do not know. Yauza &amp; Penguin Books. Moskva. 2006. Part II: 1942 Autumn-Winter Offensive. Sector 2: Operation Mars)]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Total forces:&lt;br /&gt;~ 350,000 troops.
| casualties1 = '''Isayev''':&lt;br /&gt;70,373 irrecoverable&lt;br /&gt;145,301 sanitary&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"&gt;Гриф секретности снят: Потери Вооруженных Сил СССР в войнах, боевых действиях и военных конфликтах: Стат. исслед./ Г. Ф. Кривошеев, В. М. Андроников, П. Д. Буриков. — М.: Воениздат, 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'''Glantz''':&lt;br /&gt;100,000 killed&lt;br /&gt;235,000 wounded&lt;br /&gt;1,600 tanks{{sfn|Glantz|1999|p=308}}
| casualties2 = '''Grossmann''': 40,000 casualties&lt;ref name="Grossmann H. Rzhew 1980"&gt;[http://militera.lib.ru/h/grossman/index.html Гроссманн Хорст. Ржев — краеугольный камень Восточного фронта. — Ржев: «Ржевская правда», 1996. German name: Grossmann H. Rzhew: Eckpfeiler der Ostfront. — Friedberg : Podzun-Pallas-Verlag, 1980.]&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Campaignbox Rzhev}}
{{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}

'''Operation Mars''' (Russian: Операция «Марс»), also known as the '''Second Rzhev-Sychevka Offensive Operation''' (Russian: Вторая Ржевско-Сычёвская наступательная операция), was the codename for an offensive launched by [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] forces against [[Nazi Germany|German]] forces during [[World War II]]. It took place between 25 November and 20 December 1942 around the [[Rzhev]] [[Salients, re-entrants and pockets|salient]] in the vicinity of [[Moscow]].

The offensive was a joint operation of the [[Soviet Western Front]] and [[Kalinin Front]] co-ordinated by [[Georgy Zhukov]]. The offensive was one in a series of particularly-bloody engagements that are collectively known in Soviet and Russian histories as the '''[[Battles of Rzhev]]''', which occurred near [[Rzhev]], [[Sychyovka, Sychyovsky District, Smolensk Oblast|Sychevka]] and [[Vyazma]] between January 1942 and March 1943. The battles became known as the "Rzhev meat grinder" ("Ржевская мясорубка") for their huge losses, particularly on the Soviet side. For many years, they were relegated to a footnote in [[Soviet military history]].

== Soviet plans ==
[[File:RIAN archive 87961 Collective farmers from the Moscow suburbs handing over tanks to Soviet servicemen.jpg|thumb|right|Soviet collective farmers hand over [[KV-1S]] tanks to their crews.]]

In Operation Mars, which was planned to start in late October, forces of the Kalinin and the Western Fronts would encircle and destroy the powerful [[German Ninth Army]] in the Rzhev salient. The basic plan of the offensive was to launch multiple co-ordinated thrusts from all sides of the salient, resulting in the destruction of the Ninth Army. The offensive would also tie down German units and prevent them from being moved south.{{sfn|Beevor|2012|p=369}}

The [[Kalinin Front|Kalinin]] and [[Western Front (Soviet Union)|Western Front]]s were directed by Stalin and Zhukov "to crush the Rzhev-Sychovka-Olenino-Bely enemy grouping."  The Western Front was to "take Sychovka no later than the 15th December." The Kalinin Front's [[39th Army (Soviet Union)|39th]] and [[22nd Army (Soviet Union)|22nd]] armies were to take [[Olenino, Tver Oblast|Olenino]] by 16 December and Bely by 20 December.&lt;ref name=GeorgyZhukov/&gt;{{rp|121–122,129–130}}

Operation Mars was to be followed soon afterward by Operation Jupiter, which was to commence two to three weeks later. The Western Front's powerful [[5th Army (Soviet Union)|5th]] and [[33rd Army (Soviet Union)|33rd]] armies, supported by [[3rd Guards Tank Army]], would attack along the Moscow-Vyazma highway axis, link up with the victorious Mars force, and envelop and destroy all German forces east of Smolensk. Once resistance around Vyazma was neutralized, the [[9th Tank Corps |9th]] and [[10th Tank Corps]] and the 3rd Tank Army would then penetrate deeper into the rear of [[Army Group Centre]].{{cn|date=July 2019}}

== Launch of offensive ==
The offensive was launched in the early hours of 25 November 1942. It got off to a bad start, as fog and snowy weather grounded the planned air support. It also greatly reduced the effect of the massive artillery barrages preceding the main attacks by making it impossible for the forward artillery observers to adjust fire and observe the results.
The northern thrust made little progress. The eastern attack across the frozen Vazuza river slowly ground forward. The two western thrusts made deeper penetrations, especially around the key town of [[Bely, Tver Oblast|Belyi]].
Still, the progress was nowhere near what the Soviets expected.

The German defenders fought stubbornly, clinging to their strong-points, which were often centered on many of the small villages dotting the area. In some cases, the German strong points remained manned for a time after the Soviets advanced past them, creating more problems for the Red Army in their rear areas. Despite repeated, persistent Soviet attacks, German small-arms fire and pre-planned artillery concentrations cut down the attacking Soviet infantry. Soviet tanks were picked off by [[anti-tank gun]]s and the few German tanks, as well as in close combat with infantry.

{{quote box | width = 22em | quote = One part of a small wood... had been a battlefield; the trees blasted by shells and mines looked like stakes driven in at random. The earth was criss-crossed by trenches; dugouts bulged like blisters... The deep roar of guns and the furious barks of mortars were deafening.{{sfn|Beevor|2012|pp=370-371}}| source = —[[Ilya Ehrenburg]]}}

The relative lack of initial success compounded the Soviet problems. The minor penetrations and the resulting small bridgeheads made it difficult to bring forward reinforcements and follow-up forces, especially artillery so critical for reducing the German strong points. The Germans reacted by shifting units within the salient against the points of the Soviet advance and pinching off their spearheads. With limited reserves and reinforcement unlikely due to Soviet offensives elsewhere, the Ninth Army was placed under great pressure.

Eventually the shifting of German forces, coupled with Soviet losses and supply difficulties, allowed the German forces to gain the upper hand. Their lines held, and they retook much of the lost ground. The German counterattacks against the Belyi (western) and the Vazuza (eastern) Soviet thrusts resulted in several thousand Soviet soldiers being trapped behind German lines. A few of them managed to break through to Soviet lines, some after fighting in the German rear for weeks. The trapped Soviets had to leave almost all of their vehicles and heavy weapons behind. Though the Germans were not able to remove Soviet forces from the Luchesa valley in the northwest of the salient, that was of little significance because the Soviets there were unable to press their attack through the difficult terrain.

== Outcome ==
"The Western Front failed to penetrate enemy defences," according to Zhukov.  The Germans were able to hit the flank of the Kalinin Front and trapped [[Major General]] MD Solomatin's Mechanized Corps for three days before they were relieved.&lt;ref name=GeorgyZhukov/&gt;{{rp|131}}

Operation Mars was a military failure, and the Soviets were unable to accomplish any of their objectives. However, in the aftermath of Operation Mars the commander of Army Group Centre, ''[[Generalfeldmarschall]]'' [[Günther von Kluge]], recommended the Germans abandon the salient to economize on manpower and to assume more defensible positions. [[Adolf Hitler]] refused. His denial of a major withdrawal in the winter of 1941–1942 had ultimately stabilized the [[German Army]] when it was on the edge of a collapse. Subsequently, he was less willing to heed the advice of his commanders. In addition, he was unwilling to give up any ground he had won and saw usefulness in retaining the salient as a starting point for a future thrust upon Moscow. However, in the spring of 1943, his desire to move back onto the offensive made him more receptive to withdrawing forces from the salient to free up manpower for operations elsewhere. A staged withdrawal was begun at the beginning of March 1943. By 23 March, the withdrawal was complete.

Historian A. V. Isayev has pointed out that together with influences on other sectors during the winter of 1942–1943, Operation Mars had an effect upon the strategic situation in 1943. In the plan for the large [[Operation Citadel|offensive at Kursk]] in July 1943, the German Ninth Army was located in the southern area of the [[Oryol|Orel]] salient. It delivered the assault upon the Kursk salient from the north. However, losses suffered at Rzhev during Operation Mars resulted in the Ninth Army being short of forces, particularly infantry formations, and it could not muster enough force to fulfill its task.{{sfn|Glantz|1999}}

==Assessment==
In the final assessment, Operation Mars was a failure for the Soviet forces.&lt;ref&gt;О провале операции пишут А. Исаев, В. Бешанов, Д. Гланц.&lt;/ref&gt; However, the unintentional result of the battle were losses to the reserves of [[Army Group Center]], which reduced the German forces that could be redirected against the more successful Soviet operations against [[Army Group South]] in the [[Battle of Stalingrad]]. About this matter, German [[Colonel General]] [[Kurt von Tippelskirch]] commented:

{{quote|In order to confine the German forces in every sector of the front and prevent the large reinforcement to the critical sectors, and in order to strengthen their [i.e., the Soviet] position in the places which were suitable for future offensives in the following winter, the Russians renewed their offensives in the central sector. Their main efforts focused on Rzhev and [[Velikye Luki|Velikye Luky]]. Therefore, our three [[panzer division]]s and several [[infantry division]]s – which were planned to be used in the southern sectors – had to be kept here to close gaps in the front and to retake lost territories. This was the only method for us to stop the enemy breakthrough.|Kurt von Tippelskirch&lt;ref&gt;[http://militera.lib.ru/h/tippelskirch/07.html Типпельскирх К. История Второй мировой войны. СПб.:Полигон; М.:АСТ,1999 /(Tippelskirch K., Geschichte des Zweiten Weltkrieges. — Bonn, 1954, Chapter VII] {{in lang|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

An area of controversy is whether the operation was intended as a major offensive or was really intended to simply divert German attention and resources from [[Stalingrad]] to prevent the relief of their [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|Sixth Army]]. The Soviet forces concentrated for Operation Mars were much larger than the ones used in [[Operation Uranus]] at Stalingrad.&lt;ref name="mars"&gt;[http://nvo.ng.ru/history/2005-12-02/5_mars.html Георгий Глебович Колыванов. «Марс», оказавшийся в тени «Урана» (Georgy Glebovich Kolyvanov. "Mars" in the shadow of "Uranus". Article published in the "Independent" 2 December 2005)]&lt;/ref&gt; Military historian [[David M. Glantz]] believes that Operation Mars was the main Soviet offensive and that the narrative that it was intended as a "diversion attack" was a propaganda effort on the part of the Soviet government. He termed Operation Mars as the "greatest defeat of Marshal Zhukov".

{{quote|In the unlikely event that Zhukov was correct and Mars was really a diversion, there has never been one so ambitious, so large, so clumsily executed, or so costly.|David M. Glantz}}

The [[United Kingdom|British]] historian [[Antony Beevor]] disagrees with Glantz by citing that Zhukov spent less time planning Mars than Uranus, and that the Soviet artillery shell allocation was much smaller for Mars than for Uranus. Operation Uranus received "2.5 to 4.5 ammunition loads [per gun]... compared with less than one in Operation Mars."{{sfn|Beevor|2012|p=370}} In addition, the Russian historian [[Makhmut Akhmetovich Gareyev]], citing [[Stavka]] orders, asserted that the goal of Operation Mars was to tie down German forces in the Rzhev sector, preventing them from reinforcing Stalingrad. Thus, it ensured the success of Uranus and the Soviet offensives in the south.&lt;ref&gt;[http://mil.ru/files/10_2003.pdf M. A. Гареев. Операция «Марс» и современные «марсиане»] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20100401041659/http://mil.ru/files/10_2003.pdf |date=2010-04-01 }} // Военно-исторический журнал № 10, 2003.]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to [[Pavel Anatoliyevich Sudoplatov]], Soviet intelligence intentionally leaked the plan of Operation Mars to the Germans as part of a series of deceptive "radio games" named "Monastery" (''Монастырь''). One of the "Monastery" operations was intended to lure the German attention to the Rzhev sector. During the intelligence operation, the Soviet [[double agent]] [[Aleksandr Petrovich Demyanov]] (code name "Heine") sent information about a large-scale Soviet offensive in the Rzhev area to make the Germans believe that the next main blow by the [[Red Army]] would occur in the central sector. Aside from the Soviet intelligence agency, only [[Joseph Stalin]] knew about this "Monastery" operation.&lt;ref name="Pavel Pavel Anatolyevich Sudoplatov 1950"&gt;[http://militera.lib.ru/memo/russian/sudoplatov_pa/06.html Судоплатов, Павел Анатольевич. Спецоперации. Лубянка и Кремль 1930–1950 годы. — М.: ОЛМА-ПРЕСС, 1997.] {{in lang|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.fsb.ru/fsb/history/author/single.htm!id%3D10318112@fsbPublication.html Lyutmila Obchinikova. Secret activities at center of Moskva.] at official website of [[Federal Security Service (Russia)|FSB]]. 18-1-2002 {{in lang|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://nvo.ng.ru/spforces/2005-04-22/7_radiogame.html Andrey Tyurin, Vladimir Makarov et al. The fight between Lyublyanka and Abwehr – The "Monastery" radio game. Newspaper "Independence". 22-4-2005.] {{in lang|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=WGjUd5htjagC&amp;pg=PA108&amp;dq=%D0%BE%D0%BF%D0%B5%D1%80%D0%B0%D1%86%D0%B8%D1%8F+%D0%BC%D0%BE%D0%BD%D0%B0%D1%81%D1%82%D1%8B%D1%80%D1%8C&amp;hl=ru&amp;ei=lIxTTNbqF5SSjAfJ6IDEBA&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=9&amp;ved=0CFAQ6AEwCA#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false Eduard Prokopyevich Sharapov. Eltigen incidcent and the punishment blade of Stalin – The person of special goal. Neva Publisher. Sainkt Petersburg. 2003.] {{in lang|ru}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Zhukov concluded the main reason the Soviet forces were unable to destroy the Rzhev salient "was underestimation of the rugged terrain" and "the shortage of supporting armour, artillery, mortars, and aircraft to pierce the enemy defences." He also did not expect the Germans to bring "up considerable reinforcements to this sector from other Fronts."&lt;ref name=GeorgyZhukov&gt;{{Cite book |last=Zhukov |first=Georgy |title=Marshal of Victory, Volume II |publisher=Pen and Sword Books Ltd. |year=1974 |ISBN=9781781592915 |pages=131–132}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Casualties==
* Soviet: 
**'''Isayev''':&lt;br&gt;70,373 irrecoverable&lt;br&gt;145,301 sanitary&lt;ref name="ReferenceA"/&gt;
**'''Glantz''':&lt;br&gt;100,000 killed&lt;br&gt; 235,000 wounded&lt;br&gt;1,600 tanks{{sfn|Glantz|1999|p=308}}
* German: 40,000 casualties&lt;ref name="Grossmann H. Rzhew 1980"/&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* {{cite book|last1=Beevor|first1=Antony|title=The Second World War|date=2012|publisher=Back Bay Books|location=New York|isbn=978-0-316-02375-7|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|title=Zhukov’s Greatest Defeat: The Red Army’s Epic Disaster in Operation Mars, 1942|last=|first=|date=1999|publisher=University Press of Kansas|year=|isbn=0-7006-0944-X|location=Lawrence|pages=|ref=harv|via=|last1=Glantz|first1=David M.}}
* {{cite book|last1=Krisvosheev|first1=G. F.|title=Soviet Casualties and Combat Losses in the Twentieth Century|date=1997|publisher=Stackpole Books|location=Mechanicsburg|isbn=978-1853672804}}

==External links==
* [http://www.battlefield.ru/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=163&amp;Itemid=88 Counterpoint To Stalingrad: Operation Mars]
* [http://www.armchairgeneral.com/rkkaww2/battles/mars42.htm Operation "Mars" – The Second Offensive in Rzhev Vicinities. November–December 1942]

{{coord missing|Russia}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War|Mars]]
[[Category:Strategic operations of the Red Army in World War II|Mars]]
[[Category:World War II aerial operations and battles of the Eastern Front|Mars]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany|Mars]]</text><sha1>j2241pviou7yvlx3k55h8q0hhyid3c3</sha1></revision></page>