<page><title>Operation Little Saturn</title><ns>0</ns><id>1634379</id><revision><id>955186784</id><parentid>955186701</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-06T12:18:41Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Brufnus</username><id>7031078</id></contributor><comment>/* Background */typo</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="19019" xml:space="preserve">{{infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Operation Little Saturn
| partof      = the [[Battle of Stalingrad]] during the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]
| image       = Eastern Front 1942-11 to 1943-03.png
| image_size  = 300
| caption     = Soviet advances during Operations [[Operation Uranus|Uranus]], [[Operation Mars|Mars]] and Saturn.
| date        = 12 December 1942 – 18 February 1943
| place       = Northern [[Caucasus]] and the [[Donets Basin]]
| coordinates = 
| map_type    = 
| latitude    = 
| longitude   = 
| map_size    = 
| map_marksize =
| map_caption = 
| map_label   = 
| territory   = 
| result      = Soviet tactical victory
| status      = 
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Kingdom of Italy|Italy]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Hungary (1920–46)}} [[Kingdom of Hungary (1920–46)|Hungary]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} [[Kingdom of Romania|Romania]]
| combatant2  = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Soviet Union]]
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Adolf Hitler]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Erich von Manstein]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Erhard Raus]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Paul Ludwig Ewald von Kleist|Edwald von Kleist]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Italo Gariboldi]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Hungary (1920–46)}} [[Gusztáv Jány]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} [[Petre Dumitrescu]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Joseph Stalin]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Fyodor Isidorovich Kuznetsov|Fyodor Kuznetsov]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Dmitri Danilovich Lelyushenko|Dmitri Lelyushenko]]&lt;br&gt; {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Vasily Gerasimenko]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Filipp Golikov]]
| units1      =
| units2      =
| strength1   = 
| strength2   = 
| casualties1 = 
| casualties2 = 
| notes       = 
| campaignbox =
}}
{{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}{{Campaignbox Operation Blue to 3rd Kharkov}}
{{Romanian military actions in World War II}}
'''Operation Saturn''', revised as '''Operation Little Saturn''', was a [[Red Army]] operation on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]] that led to battles in the [[North Caucasus]] and [[Donets Basin]] regions of the [[Soviet Union]] from December 1942 to February 1943.

The success of [[Operation Uranus]], launched on 19 November 1942, had trapped 250,000–300,000 troops of General [[Friedrich Paulus]]' [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|German 6th Army]] and parts of General Hoth’s [[4th Panzer Army]] in [[Stalingrad]]. To exploit this victory, the Soviet general staff planned a winter campaign of continuous and highly ambitious offensive operations, codenamed "Saturn". Later [[Joseph Stalin]] reduced his ambitious plans to a relatively small campaign codenamed "Operation Little Saturn". The offensive succeeded in smashing Germany's Italian and Hungarian allies, applied pressure on the over stretched German forces in Eastern Ukraine and prevented further German advances to the relief of the entrapped forces at Stalingrad. Despite these victories, the Soviets themselves became over extended, setting up the stages for the German offensives of the [[Third Battle of Kharkov]] and the [[Battle of Kursk]].

==Background==

On 17 May 1942, German Army Groups [[Army Group A|A]] and [[Army Group B|B]] launched a counteroffensive against advancing Soviet armies around the city of [[Kharkiv|Kharkov]], resulting in the [[Second Battle of Kharkov]];&lt;ref&gt;Glantz (1997), p. 116&lt;/ref&gt; this would ultimately be expanded on 28 June into [[Case Blue]], which aimed the capture of the Caucasus oil fields.&lt;ref&gt;Glantz (1997), p. 117&lt;/ref&gt; By 6 July, General [[Hermann Hoth]]'s [[4th Panzer Army|Fourth Panzer Army]] had taken the city of Voronezh, threatening to collapse the [[Red Army]]'s resistance.&lt;ref&gt;Cooper (1978), pp. 415–416&lt;/ref&gt; By early August, General [[Paul Ludwig Ewald von Kleist]]'s [[1st Panzer Army|First Panzer Army]] had reached the oil center of [[Maykop]], {{convert|500|km|mi}} south of the city of [[Rostov]],&lt;ref&gt;McCarthy &amp; Syron (2002), p. 132&lt;/ref&gt; which had been taken by the Fourth Panzer Army on 23 July.&lt;ref&gt;Erickson (1975), p. 362&lt;/ref&gt; The rapid German advance threatened to cut the Soviet Union off from its southern territories, while also threatening to cut the lend-lease supply lines from Persia.&lt;ref&gt;Beevor (1998), p. 84&lt;/ref&gt; However, the offensive began to peter out, as the offensive's supply train struggled to keep up with the advance and spearhead units began to run low on fuel and manpower;&lt;ref&gt;Glantz (1997), pp. 119–120&lt;/ref&gt; for example, some panzer divisions were down to 54 tanks.&lt;ref&gt;Glantz (1997), p. 120&lt;/ref&gt;
Eventually, the German focus shifted towards Stalingrad in an attempt to cut off supply shippings on the Volga river. The fall of Stalin’s namesake city would also mean a psychological boost for the Germans and, vice versa, a blow to the Soviets.
However, after months of brutal fighting in which more than 90% of the city had been conquered by the Germans, the city would eventually deplete the German forces - the 6th Army and units from 4th Panzer Army - in their unsuccessful and exhausting attempt to expel the remainder of the Soviet defences.
Both sides suffered enormous casualties during this battle, but, most importantly for the final outcome, the Germans severely depleted their forces, made them strip their flanks ever increasingly, leaving these in the hands of overstretched and poorly equipped Italian, Hungarian, and Romanian Allies. 
The dangerous situation that evolved, while addressed several times by worried German Generals, were ignored and, thus, had set the circumstances for the ultimate disaster for the Germans and their Allies.   

===Operation Uranus===
{{main|Operation Uranus}}
Operation Uranus was the codename of the [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] strategic operation in World War II which led to the encirclement of the German [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|Sixth Army]], [[Romanian Armies in the Battle of Stalingrad|Third and Fourth Romanian]] armies, and portions of the German [[4th Panzer Army|Fourth Panzer Army]]. The operation formed part of the ongoing [[Battle of Stalingrad]], and was aimed at destroying German forces in and around Stalingrad. Planning for Operation Uranus had commenced as early as September 1942, and was developed simultaneously with plans to envelop and destroy German [[Army Group Centre|Army Group Center]] and German forces in the Caucasus. The Red Army took advantage of the fact that German forces in the southern Soviet Union were overstretched around [[Stalingrad]], using weaker Romanian armies to guard their flanks; the offensive's starting points were established along the section of the front directly opposite Romanian forces. These Axis armies were deployed in open positions on the steppe and lacked heavy equipment to deal with Soviet armor.

===German attempt to relieve Stalingrad===
{{main|Operation Winter Storm}}
Operation Winter Storm (''Unternehmen Wintergewitter''), undertaken between 12–23 December 1942, was the German [[4th Panzer Army|Fourth Panzer Army]]'s attempt to relieve encircled Axis forces during the [[Battle of Stalingrad]]. In late November, the [[Red Army]] completed [[Operation Uranus]], which resulted in the encirclement of Axis personnel in and around the city of [[Volgograd|Stalingrad]]. German forces within the Stalingrad Pocket and directly outside were reorganized under [[Army Group Don]], under the command of Field Marshal [[Erich von Manstein]]. As the Red Army continued to build strength, in an effort to allocate as many resources as possible to the eventual launch of the planned Operation Saturn, which aimed to isolate [[Army Group A]] from the rest of the [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|German Army]], the [[Luftwaffe]] had begun an attempt to supply German forces in Stalingrad through an air bridge. However, as the Luftwaffe proved incapable of carrying out its mission and it became more obvious that a successful breakout could only occur if it was launched as early as possible, Manstein decided to plan and launch a dedicated relief effort.

==Soviet counter-offensive: Operation Little Saturn==

After the defeat of the Romanian Army around Stalingrad and the successful encirclement of the German Sixth Army, Stalin started a counter-offensive nicknamed "Operation Little Saturn" in order to enlarge the area controlled by the Soviet Army in eastern Ukraine to [[Kharkov]] and [[Rostov]].

[[Zhukov]] states the South-Western Front was assigned a mission in which the 1st and 3rd Guard armies and the 5th Tank Army "were to strike out in the general direction of [[Morozovsk]] and destroy the enemy grouping in that sector." They would be supported by the 6th Army of the [[Voronezh Front]].&lt;ref name=GeorgyZhukov&gt;{{Cite book |last=Zhukov |first=Georgy |title=Marshal of Victory, Volume II |publisher=Pen and Sword Books Ltd. |year=1974 |ISBN=9781781592915 |page=129,134–135}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===First stage: December 1942===

The first stage &amp;mdash; an attempt to cut off the German [[Army Group A]] in the Caucasus &amp;mdash; had to be rapidly revised when General [[Erich von Manstein]] launched [[Operation Wintergewitter|Operation Winter Storm]] on 12 December in an attempt to relieve the trapped armies at Stalingrad. While General [[Rodion Malinovsky]]'s [[Soviet Second Guards Army|Soviet 2nd Guards Army]] blocked the German advance on Stalingrad, the modified plan ''Operation Little Saturn'' was launched on 16 December.
[[File:Operazione Piccolo Saturno.jpg|thumb|250px|right|Soviet forces during Operation Little Saturn in December 1942]]
This operation consisted of a pincer movement which threatened to cut off the relieving forces. General [[Fyodor Isidorovich Kuznetsov]]'s [[Soviet First Guards Army|1st Guards Army]] and General [[Dmitri Danilovich Lelyushenko]]'s [[Soviet Third Guards Army|3rd Guards Army]] attacked from the north, encircling 130,000 soldiers of the [[Italian Army in Russia|Italian 8th Army]] on the [[Don River, Russia|Don]] and advancing to [[Millerovo]]. The Italians resisted the Soviet attack for nearly two weeks, although outnumbered 9 to 1 in some sectors, but with huge losses. Manstein sent the 6th Panzer Division to the Italians' aid: of the 130,000 encircled troops, only 45,000 survived after bloody fighting to join the Panzers at Chertkovo on 17 January.

To the south the advance of General Gerasimenko's 28th Army threatened to encircle the 1st Panzer Army and General Trufanov's 51st Army attacked the relief column directly. In a daring raid, by 24 December tanks of the [[24th Tank Corps]] had reached [[Tatsinskaya Raid|Tatskinskaya]], the air base closest to Stalingrad from which the Luftwaffe had been supplying the besieged troops. The Soviet tanks drove through snowstorms onto the airfield and roamed about for hours, destroying the German transport planes at their leisure.

With the relief column under threat of encirclement, Manstein had no choice but to retreat back to [[Kotelnikovo]] on 29 December, leaving the encircled Germans at Stalingrad to their fate. Of the 200,000 - 250,000 soldiers encircled 90,000 survived to be taken prisoner. Only 5,000 lived to return to Germany. The limited scope of the Soviet offensive also gave General [[Paul Ludwig Ewald von Kleist|Ewald von Kleist]] time to withdraw his [[Army Group A]] in the direction of the [[Kuban]], with the exception of [[1st Panzer Army]] which joined [[Army Group Don]] via [[Rostov-on-Don|Rostov]].

===Second stage: January 1943===
{{main|Ostrogozhsk–Rossosh Offensive}}

The second stage of operations opened on 13 January 1943 with an attack by four armies of General Golikov's Voronezh Front that encircled and destroyed the [[Hungarian Second Army]] near Svoboda on the Don. As a consequence the Hungarian Second Army, as most other Axis armies in the Army Group B, ceased to represent a meaningful fighting force (indeed the German Sixth Army, encircled in Stalingrad, was destroyed on February 2, 1943)

The Italian 8th Army's [[Alpini]] Corps, consisting of Alpine Divisions [[3 Alpine Division Julia|3rd Julia]], [[2 Alpine Division Tridentina|2nd Tridentina]] and [[4 Alpine Division Cuneense|4th Cuneense]] and the [[156th Infantry Division Vicenza|156th ''Vicenza'']] Infantry Division to their rear, were at this point largely unaffected by the Soviet offensive on their right flank. But on January 13, 1943, the Soviets launched their second stage of Operation Saturn, where four armies of Soviet General [[Filipp Golikov]]'s [[Voronezh Front]] attacked, encircled, and destroyed the [[Hungarian Second Army]] near Svoboda on the Don to the northwest of the Italians. The Soviets then attacked and pushed back the remaining units of the German 24th Army Corps on the Alpini left flank and contemporarily attacked the Alpini themselves. 
[[File:Ripiegamentoalpinigennaio43.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Route of the Alpini toward Nikolaievka]]

The Alpini held the front, but within three days the Soviets advanced {{convert|200|km|mi|-1|sp=us}} to the left and right of the Alpini, who were thus encircled and forced to try to escape a siege (like the one of German sixth Army in Stalingrad).

Although the Alpini corps was ordered to hold the front at all costs, preparations for a general retreat began on January 15. On the evening of January 17, the commanding officer of the corps General Gabriele Nasci finally ordered the full retreat, which was fully carried out on January 19.

At this point the Julia and Cuneense divisions were already heavily decimated and only the Tridentina division was still capable of conducting effective combat operations ([[Battle of Nikolayevka]], January 25–27).

By February first the Alpini reached the [[Kharkov]] area, where the Axis forces successfully organized a line of defense. But they did pay a high price in the Soviet Union. The [[4 Alpine Division Cuneense]] was annihilated. Only about one tenth of the [[3 Alpine Division Julia]] survived (approximately 1200 survivors of 15000 troops deployed) and only about one third of the [[2 Alpine Division Tridentina]] survived 
(approximately 4250 survivors of 15000 troops deployed).

=== Voronezh-Kastornensk operation ===
{{main|Voronezh-Kastornensk operation}}

An attack on the German 2nd Army further north threatened to bring about an encirclement; although the German 2nd Army managed to escape, it was forced to retreat and by 5 February troops of the Voronezh Front were approaching Kursk and Kharkov.

==See also==
* [[Italian participation in the Eastern Front]]
* [[Italian Army in Russia|ARMIR]]
* [[Romanian Armies in the Battle of Stalingrad]]
* [[Second Army (Hungary)|Hungarian Army in Operation Little Saturn]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|3}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
*{{cite book |last       = Beevor
 |first      = Antony
 |authorlink = Anthony Beevor
 |title      = Stalingrad: The Fateful Siege: 1942−1943
 |publisher  = Penguin Putnam Inc.
 |year       = 1998
 |location   = Harmondsworth, United Kingdom
 |isbn       = 0-670-87095-1
 |url        = https://archive.org/details/stalingrad00beev
}}
*{{cite journal
| last      = Bell
| first     = Kelly
| title     = Struggle for Stalin's Skies
| journal   = WWII History: Russian Front
| issue    = Special Issue 
| publisher = Sovereign Media
| location  = Herndon, Virginia
| date      = Fall 2006
| id        = 1539-5456}}
*{{cite book
| last      = Clark
| first     = Alan
| title     = Barbarossa: The Russian-German Conflict, 1941-1945
| publisher = William Morrow
| year      = 1965
| location  = New York City, New York
| isbn      = 0-688-04268-6}}
*{{cite book
| last      = Cooper
| first     = Matthew
| title     = The German Army 1933-1945
| publisher = Scarborough House
| year      = 1978
| location  = Lanham, Maryland
| isbn      = 0-8128-8519-8}}
*{{cite book
| last      = Erickson
| first     = John
| title     = The Road to Berlin: Stalin's War with Germany
| publisher = Yale University Press
| year      = 1983
| location  = 
| isbn      = 0-300-07813-7}}
*{{cite book
| last      = Erickson
| first      = John
| title      = The Road to Stalingrad: Stalin's War With Germany
| publisher      = Yale University Press
| year      = 1975
| location      = 
| isbn      = 0-300-07812-9
| url      = https://archive.org/details/stalinswarwithge00eric
}}
*{{cite journal
| last      = Glantz
| first     = David M.
| title     = Soviet Military Strategy During the Second Period of War (November 1942–December 1943): A Reappraisal
| journal   = The Journal of Military History
| volume    = 60
| issue     = 1
| pages     = 35
| publisher = Society for Military History
| date      = January 1996
| doi=10.2307/2944451}}
*{{cite book
| last      = Glantz
| first     = David M.
|author2=[[Jonathan House]]
| title     = When Titans Clashed: How the Red Army Stopped Hitler
| publisher = Kansas University Press
| year      = 1995
| location  = Lawrence, Kansas
| isbn      = 0-7006-0717-X}}
*{{cite book
| last      = Heiber
| first     = Helmut
|author2=[[David Glantz|David M. Glantz]]
| title     = Hitler and his Generals: Military Conferences 1942 - 1945
| publisher = Enigma Books
| year      = 2003
| location  = New York City, New York
| isbn      = 1-929631-09-X}}
*{{cite book |last       = McCarthy
 |first      = Peter
 |author2    = Mike Syryon
 |title      = Panzerkieg: The Rise and Fall of Hitler's Tank Divisions
 |publisher  = Carroll &amp; Graf
 |year       = 2002
 |location   = New York City, New York
 |isbn       = 0-7867-1009-8
 |url-access = registration
 |url        = https://archive.org/details/panzerkriegrisef0000mcca
}}
*{{cite journal
| last      = McTaggart
| first     = Pat
| title     = Soviet Circle of Iron
| journal   = WWII History: Russian Front
| issue    = Special Issue 
| publisher = Sovereign Media
| location  = Herndon, Virginia
| date      = Fall 2006
| id        = 1539-5456}}
*{{cite book
| last      = Raus
| first     = Erhard
| title     = Panzers on the Eastern Front: General Erhard Raus and his Panzer Divisions in Russia 1941–1945
| publisher = Military Book Club
| year      = 2002
| location  = Mechanicsburg, PA
| isbn      = 0-7394-2644-3}}
*{{cite book
| last      = von Manstein
| first     = Erich
| title     = [[Verlorene Siege|Lost Victories]]
| publisher = Zenith Press
| year      = 1982
| location  = St. Paul, MN
| isbn      = 0-7603-2054-3}}
{{refend}}

{{coord missing|Russia}}

{{Battle of Stalingrad |Operations}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Little Saturn, Operation}}
[[Category:Battle of Stalingrad]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War|Little Saturn]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany|Little Saturn]]
[[Category:Strategic operations of the Red Army in World War II|Little Saturn]]
[[Category:December 1942 events]]
[[Category:January 1943 events]]
[[Category:February 1943 events]]</text><sha1>k8ottpaa7ci8p77cisl1a6vfepzlq7g</sha1></revision></page>