<page><title>Battle of Nikolayevka</title><ns>0</ns><id>14528165</id><revision><id>964775371</id><parentid>947142149</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-27T14:25:58Z</timestamp><contributor><username>SiBr4</username><id>16981284</id></contributor><minor /><comment>/* top */Updated Hungary flag variant</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="4920" xml:space="preserve">{{more citations needed|date=January 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Nikolayevka
| partof      = the [[Battle of Stalingrad]] during the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = Ripiegamentoalpinigennaio43.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = Alpini route toward Nikolaievka, from the Don river
| date        = January 13–26, 1943 (including prelude)
| place       = [[Livenka, Belgorod Oblast|Nikolayevka]], [[Belgorod Oblast]], [[Russian SFSR]], [[Soviet Union]]
| result      = Axis breakout
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Kingdom of Italy|Italy]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Hungary|1920}} [[Kingdom of Hungary|Hungary]]
| combatant2  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Giulio Martinat]]{{KIA}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Luigi Reverberi]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Fyodor Isidorovich Kuznetsov|Fyodor Kuznetsov]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Dmitri Danilovich Lelyushenko|Dmitri Lelyushenko]]
| strength1   = 8–9,000 {{Citation needed|date=February 2011}}
| strength2   = 6,000 infantry (plus [[Soviet partisans]]) {{Citation needed|date=May 2012}}
| casualties1 = Unknown
| casualties2 = Unknown
}}
{{Campaignbox Operation Blue to 3rd Kharkov}}

The '''Battle of Nikolayevka''' was the breakout of Italian forces in January 1943, as a small part of the larger [[Battle of Stalingrad]]. The breakout involved a corps of the [[Italian war in Soviet Union, 1941–1943#The Italian 8th Army or Armata Italiana in Russia|Italian 8th Army's]] near the village of Nikolayevka (now [[Livenka, Belgorod Oblast]], in Russia).

==The breakout==
The Italian 8th Army's [[Alpini]] (Mountain) Corps, consisting of the [[3 Alpine Division Julia|3rd Julia]], [[2 Alpine Division Tridentina|2nd Tridentina]] and [[4 Alpine Division Cuneense|4th Cuneense]] divisions and the [[156th Infantry Division Vicenza|156th Vicenza]] Infantry Division to their rear, were at this point largely unaffected by the Soviet offensive on their right flank. On January 13, 1943, the Red Army launched the second stage of Operation Saturn. Four armies of General [[Filipp Golikov]]'s [[Voronezh Front]] attacked, encircled, and destroyed the [[Hungarian Second Army]] near [[Svoboda, Voronezh Oblast|Svoboda]] on the Don to the northwest of the Italians and pushed back the remaining units of the German 24th Army Corps on the Alpini left flank, thus encircling the Italian Corps.

On the evening of January 17, the commanding officer of the corps General [[Gabriele Nasci]] ordered a full retreat. At this point only the Tridentina division was still capable of conducting effective combat operations. The 40,000-strong mass of stragglers—Alpini and Italians from other commands, plus German and Hungarian Hussars (Light Cavalry) —formed two columns that followed the Tridentina division which, supported by a handful of German armoured vehicles, led the way westwards to the Axis lines.

On the morning of January 26, the spearheads of the Tridentina reached the hamlet of Nikolayevka, occupied by a Soviet division, which repulsed Alpini's attack. General [[Luigi Reverberi]], commander of the Tridentina division, led the final assault. As the 4,000 Alpini advanced, all remaining soldiers of the columns fell in and the Soviet formation, facing a [[human wave attack]] by many of the 40,000 Axis troops, abandoned the village. The Corps' Chief of Staff General [[Giulio Martinat]] was killed at the head of his troops on 26 January.

The retreat of the Alpini was no longer contested by Soviet forces and on February 1 the remnants of the Corps reached Axis lines. The Italians suffered heavy losses in the breakout: the Cuneense division had been destroyed; one tenth of the Division Julia survived (approximately 1,200 of 15,000 troops deployed) and one third of the Division Tridentina survived (approximately 4,250 of 15,000 troops deployed).

==Aftermath==

The battle has become an important point of reference for the [[Alpini]] and their fighting spirit. The Alpini Association also supports social programs in the city.

==See also==
*[[Italian Army in Russia]]
*[[Italian participation in the Eastern Front]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* Hamilton, H. ''Sacrifice on the Steppe.'' Casemate, 2011 (English)

{{coord missing|Belgorod Oblast}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nikolayevka}}
[[Category:Battle of Stalingrad]]
[[Category:Battles involving Italy]]
[[Category:Battles involving Hungary]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1943]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Hungary]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:1943 in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Alpini|Battle of Nikolayevka]]
[[Category:January 1943 events]]</text><sha1>evvtdxf56zfxnc539ev9lq1uzmbjvcw</sha1></revision></page>