<page><title>Battle of the Dnieper</title><ns>0</ns><id>4846267</id><revision><id>953051342</id><parentid>949933696</parentid><timestamp>2020-04-25T13:05:46Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Kges1901</username><id>21685244</id></contributor><comment>/* Soviet organisation */ link</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="31475" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|WWII battle}}
{{refimprove|date=May 2016}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of the Dnieper
| partof      = the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = Map of dnieper battle grand.jpg
| image_size  = 300
| caption     = Map of the battle of the Dnieper and linked operations
| date        = 26 August 1943 – 23 December 1943&lt;br /&gt;({{Age in years, months, weeks and days|month1=08|day1=26|year1=1943|month2=12|day2=23|year2=1943}})
| place       = [[Dnieper River]], [[Soviet Union]]
| territory   = [[Red Army|Soviets]] reclaim [[left-bank Ukraine]], including the city of [[Kiev]] and [[Donets basin]]
| result      = Soviet victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Kingdom of Romania}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Georgy Zhukov]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Aleksandr Vasilevsky]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Nikolai Vatutin]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Ivan Konev]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Rodion Malinovsky]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Fyodor Tolbukhin]]&lt;br/&gt;{{nowrap|{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]]}}
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Erich von Manstein]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Paul Ludwig Ewald von Kleist|Ewald von Kleist]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Günther von Kluge]]
| units1      = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[1st Ukrainian Front]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[2nd Ukrainian Front]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[3rd Ukrainian Front]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[4th Ukrainian Front]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[1st Belorussian Front]]
| units2      = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Army Group South]] 
* [[1st Panzer Army]]
* [[4th Panzer Army]]
* [[8th Army (Wehrmacht)|8th Army]]
{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Army Group A]]                                            
* [[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|6th Army]]
{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Army Group Center]]
* [[2nd Army (Wehrmacht)|2nd Army]]
| strength1   = '''26 August:'''&lt;br/&gt;2,633,000 men (1,450,000 reinforcements){{sfn|Frieser|Schmider|Schönherr|Schreiber|2007|p=343}}&lt;br/&gt;51,200 guns and mortars{{sfn|Frieser|Schmider|Schönherr|Schreiber|2007|p=343}}&lt;br/&gt;2,400 tanks and assault guns{{sfn|Frieser|Schmider|Schönherr|Schreiber|2007|p=343}}&lt;br/&gt;2,850 combat aircraft{{sfn|Frieser|Schmider|Schönherr|Schreiber|2007|p=343}}
| strength2   = Unknown
| casualties1 = Krivosheev: 1,285,977 men&lt;ref&gt;[http://lib.ru/MEMUARY/.../1939-1945/KRIWOSHEEW/poteri.txt ]&lt;/ref&gt;
:348,815 killed or missing
:937,162 wounded or sick
Frieser:
1,687,164 men{{sfn|Frieser|Schmider|Schönherr|Schreiber|2007|p=379}}
:417,323 killed or missing
:1,269,841 wounded or sick
| casualties2 = 281,407 men (21 August – 20 December)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ww2stats.com/cas_ger_okh_dec43.html |title=Archived copy |accessdate=10 December 2017 |url-status = dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130525020822/http://ww2stats.com/cas_ger_okh_dec43.html |archivedate=25 May 2013 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Forczyk: 372,000+ men&lt;ref&gt;Forczyk, Robert. The Dnepr 1943: Hitler's Eastern Rampart Crumbles. Osprey Publishing 2016, p. 91&lt;/ref&gt;
 

| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Romanian military actions in World War II}}
}}

The '''Battle of the Dnieper''' was a [[military campaign]] that took place in 1943 on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]. It was one of the largest operations in World War II, involving almost 4,000,000 troops at a time stretched on a {{convert|1400|km|mi}} long front. During its four-month duration, the eastern bank of the [[Dnieper River|Dnieper]] was recovered from [[Nazi Germany|German]] forces by five of the [[Red Army]]'s [[Front (military formation)|fronts]], which conducted several assault river crossings to establish several [[lodgement]]s on the western bank. Subsequently, [[Kiev]] was liberated in the [[Battle of Kiev (1943)|Battle of Kiev]].

2,438 Red Army soldiers were awarded the [[Hero of the Soviet Union]] which was more than had been awarded previously since the award's establishment and never again were there so many laureates.{{citation needed|date=April 2017}}
{{TOC limit}}

== Strategic situation ==
Following the [[Battle of Kursk]], the Wehrmacht{{'}}s [[German Army (Wehrmacht)|''Heer'']] and supporting ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' forces in the southern Soviet Union were on the defensive in the southern Ukraine. By mid-August, [[Adolf Hitler]] understood that the forthcoming Soviet offensive could not be contained on the open steppe and ordered construction of a series of fortifications along the line of the Dnieper river.

On the Soviet side, [[Joseph Stalin]] was determined to launch a major offensive in Ukraine. The main thrust of the offensive was in a southwesterly direction; the northern flank being largely stabilized, the southern flank rested on the [[Sea of Azov]].

== Planning ==
=== Soviet planning ===
{{multiple image
 | align     = right
 | direction = vertical
 | width     = 120
 | image1    = Konstanty Rokossowski, 1945.jpg
 | caption1  = Central Front [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]]
 | image2    = Николай Ватутин, 1943 год.jpg
 | caption2  = Voronezh Front [[Nikolai Fyodorovich Vatutin|Nikolai Vatutin]]
 | image3    = IS Konev 01.jpg
 | caption3  = Steppe Front [[Ivan Konev]]
 | image4    = Rodion Malinovsky 1.jpg
 | caption4  = Southwestern Front [[Rodion Malinovsky]]
 | image5    =
 | caption5  = Southern Front [[Fyodor Tolbukhin]]
}}
{{Unreferenced section|date=April 2017}}
The operation began on 26 August 1943. Divisions started to move on a 1,400-kilometer front that stretched between [[Smolensk]] and the Sea of Azov. Overall, the operation would be executed by 36 Combined Arms, four Tank and five Air Armies. 2,650,000 personnel were brought into the ranks for this massive operation. The operation would use 51,000 guns and mortars, 2,400 tanks and 2,850 planes.

The Dnieper is the third largest river in [[Europe]], behind only the [[Volga]] and the [[Danube]]. In its lower part, its width can easily reach three kilometres, and being dammed in several places made it even larger. Moreover, its western shore&amp;mdash;the one still to be retaken&amp;mdash;was much higher and steeper than the eastern, complicating the offensive even further. In addition, the opposite shore was transformed into a vast complex of defenses and [[fortification]]s held by the ''Wehrmacht''.

Faced with such a situation, the Soviet commanders had two options. The first would be to give themselves time to regroup their forces, find a weak point or two to exploit (not necessarily in the lower part of the Dnieper), stage a [[breakthrough (military)|breakthrough]] and encircle the German defenders far in the rear, rendering the defence line unsupplied and next to useless (very much like the German [[Panzer]]s bypassed the [[Maginot line]] in 1940). This option was supported by Marshal [[Georgy Zhukov|Zhukov]] and Deputy Chief of Staff [[Aleksei Antonov|A. I. Antonov]], who considered the substantial losses after the fierce [[battle of Kursk]]. The second option would be to stage a massive assault without waiting, and force the Dnieper on a broad front. This option left no additional time for the German defenders, but would lead to much larger casualties than would a successful deep operation breakthrough. This second option was backed by Stalin due to the concern that the German "scorched earth" policy might devastate this region if the Red Army did not advance fast enough.

[[Stavka#Stavka of the RKKA during World War II|Stavka]] (the Soviet high command) chose the second option. Instead of deep penetration and encirclement, the Soviet intended to make full use of partisan activities to intervene and disrupt Germany's supply route so that the Germans could not effectively send reinforcements or take away Soviet industrial facilities in the region. Stavka also paid high attention to the possible scorched earth activities of German forces with a view to preventing them by a rapid advance.

The assault was staged on a 300-kilometer front almost simultaneously. All available means of transport were to be used to transport the attackers to the opposite shore, including small fishing boats and improvised rafts of barrels and trees (like the one in the photograph). The preparation of the crossing equipment was further complicated by the German scorched earth strategy with the total destruction of all boats and raft building material in the area. The crucial issue would obviously be heavy equipment. Without it, the [[bridgehead]]s would not stand for long.

==== Soviet organisation ====
* [[Central Front (Soviet Union)|Central Front]] (known as the [[1st Belorussian Front|Belorussian Front]] after 20 October 1943), commanded by [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]] and accounted for 579,600 soldiers (took no part in the Dnieper battle after 3 October)
** [[2nd Tank Army]], led by [[Alexey Rodin (general)|Aleksei Rodin]] / [[Semyon Bogdanov]] &lt;small&gt;(since September)&lt;/small&gt;
** [[9th Tank Corps (Soviet Union)|9th Tank Corps]], led by Hryhoriy Rudchenko (KIA), Boris Bakharov
** [[60th Army (Soviet Union)|60th Army]], led by [[Ivan Chernyakhovsky]]
** [[13th Army (Soviet Union)|13th Army]], led by [[Nikolay Pukhov]]
** [[65th Army (Soviet Union)|65th Army]], led by [[Pavel Batov]]
** [[61st Army (Soviet Union)|61st Army]], led by [[Pavel Alexeyevich Belov|Pavel Belov]]
** [[48th Army (Soviet Union)|48th Army]], led by [[Prokofy Romanenko]]
** [[70th Army (Soviet Union)|70th Army]], led by [[Ivan Galanin]] / Vladimir Sharapov &lt;small&gt;(September - October)&lt;/small&gt; / [[Aleksei Aleksandrovich Grechkin|Aleksei Grechkin]] &lt;small&gt;(since October)&lt;/small&gt;
** [[16th Air Army]], led by [[Sergei Rudenko (general)|Sergei Rudenko]]
* [[Voronezh Front]] (known as the [[1st Ukrainian Front]] after 20 October 1943), commanded by [[Nikolai Fyodorovich Vatutin|Nikolai Vatutin]] and accounted for 665,500 soldiers
**[[3rd Guards Tank Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Guards Tank Army]], led by [[Pavel Rybalko]]
** [[1st Tank Army]], led by [[Mikhail Katukov]]
** [[4th Guards Tank Corps]], led by Pavel Poluboyarov
** 1st Guard Cavalry Corps, led by [[Viktor Kirillovich Baranov|Viktor Baranov]]
** [[5th Guards Army]], led by [[Aleksey Semenovich Zhadov|Aleksei Zhadov]]
** [[4th Guards Army]], led by [[Grigory Kulik]] / Aleksei Zygin (KIA) / Ivan Galanin
** [[6th Guards Army]], led by [[Ivan Chistyakov]]
** [[38th Army (Soviet Union)|38th Army]], led by [[Nikandr Chibisov]] / [[Kirill Moskalenko]] &lt;small&gt;(since October)&lt;/small&gt;
** [[47th Army]], led by Pavel Korzun / [[Filipp Zhmachenko]] &lt;small&gt;(September - October)&lt;/small&gt; / Vitaliy Polenov &lt;small&gt;(since October)&lt;/small&gt;
** [[27th Army (Soviet Union)|27th Army]], led by [[Sergei Trofimenko]]
** [[52nd Army (Soviet Union)|52nd Army]], led by [[Konstantin Koroteev]]
** [[2nd Air Army]], led by [[Stepan Krasovsky]]
* [[Steppe Front]] (known as the [[2nd Ukrainian Front]] after 20 October 1943), commanded by [[Ivan Konev]]
* [[Southwestern Front (Soviet Union)|Southwestern Front]] (known as the [[3rd Ukrainian Front]] after 20 October 1943), commanded by [[Rodion Malinovsky]]
* [[Southern Front (Soviet Union)|Southern Front]] (known as the [[4th Ukrainian Front]] after 20 October 1943), commanded by [[Fyodor Tolbukhin]]

=== German planning ===
{{Main|Panther-Wotan line}}
{{multiple image
 | align     = right
 | direction = vertical
 | width     = 120
 | image1    = Bundesarchiv Bild 183-H01757, Erich von Manstein.jpg
 | caption1  = Army Group South [[Erich von Manstein]]
 | image2    = Paul Ludwig Ewald von Kleist.jpg
 | caption2  = Army Group A [[Paul Ludwig Ewald von Kleist|Ewald von Kleist]]
}}
The order to construct the Dnieper defence complex, known as "Eastern Wall", was issued on 11 August 1943 and began to be immediately executed.

Fortifications were erected along the length of the Dnieper. However, there was no hope of completing such an extensive defensive line in the short time available. Therefore, the completion of the "Eastern Wall" was not uniform in its density and depth of fortifications. Instead, they were concentrated in areas where a Soviet assault-crossing were most likely to be attempted, such as near [[Kremenchuk]], [[Zaporizhia]] and [[Nikopol, Ukraine|Nikopol]].

Additionally, on 7 September 1943, the SS forces and the Wehrmacht received orders to implement a [[scorched earth]] policy, by stripping the areas they had to abandon of anything that could be used by the Soviet war effort.

==== German organisation ====
* [[Luftflotte 2]] &lt;small&gt;(selected units)&lt;/small&gt; - [[Wolfram Freiherr von Richthofen]]
* (in Ukraine) [[Army Group South]] - [[Erich von Manstein]]
**[[4th Panzer Army]] - [[Hermann Hoth]]
**[[1st Panzer Army]] - [[Eberhard von Mackensen]]
**[[8th Army (Wehrmacht)|8th Army]] - [[Otto Wohler]]
**[[6th Army (Wehrmacht)|6th Army]] - [[Karl-Adolf Hollidt]] (transferred to Army Group A control)
**[[Luftflotte 4]] - [[Wolfram Freiherr von Richthofen]] / [[Otto Deßloch]] &lt;small&gt;(since September)&lt;/small&gt;
* (in Crimea) [[Army Group A]] - [[Paul Ludwig Ewald von Kleist|Ewald von Kleist]]
* [[Army Group Center]] - [[Günther von Kluge]]
**[[2nd Army (Wehrmacht)|2nd Army]] - [[Walter Weiß]] (took no part in the Dnieper battle after 3 October)

== Description of the strategic operation ==

=== Initial attack ===
[[File:Hitlerdnieper.jpg|thumb|German soldiers manning defensive positions on the Dnieper]]
Despite a great superiority in numbers, the offensive was by no means easy. German opposition was ferocious and the fighting raged for every town and city. The ''Wehrmacht'' made extensive use of rear guards, leaving some troops in each city and on each hill, slowing the Soviet offensive.

=== Progress of the offensive ===
[[File:Crossing the Dnieper.png|thumb|[[Soviet Union|Soviet]] soldiers crossing the [[Dnieper River|Dnieper]] on improvised [[raft]]s]]
Three weeks after the start of the offensive, and despite heavy losses on the Soviet side, it became clear that the Germans could not hope to contain the Soviet offensive in the flat, open terrain of the steppes, where the Red Army's numerical strength would prevail. Manstein asked for as many as 12 new divisions in the hope of containing the Soviet offensive – but German reserves were perilously thin.

On 15 September 1943, Hitler ordered Army Group South to retreat to the Dnieper defence line. The battle for [[Poltava]] was especially bitter. The city was heavily fortified and its garrison well prepared. After a few inconclusive days that greatly slowed down the Soviet offensive, Marshal Konev decided to bypass the city and rush towards the Dnieper. After two days of violent [[urban warfare]], the Poltava garrison was overcome. Towards the end of September 1943, Soviet forces reached the lower part of the Dnieper.

=== Dnieper airborne operation ===
[[File:Ivan Chernyakhovsky 2.jpg|thumb|[[Ivan Chernyakhovsky]] and other members of his military council on the eve of the Battle of the Dnieper, 1943]]
(The following is, largely, a synopsis of an account by Glantz&lt;ref&gt;The History of Soviet Airborne Forces, Chapter 8, Across The Dnieper (September 1943), by David M. Glantz, Cass, 1994.  [https://books.google.com/books?id=7hb7BsoNDIoC&amp;pg=PA262&amp;source=gbs_toc_r&amp;cad=0_0&amp;sig=iFLZoVa3Y4TOTd6rABWAyVdy7RA (portions online)]&lt;/ref&gt; with support from an account by Staskov.&lt;ref&gt;1943 Dnepr airborne operation: lessons and conclusions Military Thought, July 2003, by Nikolai Viktorovich Staskov. [http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0JAP/is_4_12/ai_112321381/pg_1  (online)]  See ref at [[Army (Soviet Army)]] under 40th Army entry.&lt;/ref&gt;){{Verify source|date=April 2017}}

Stavka detached the [[Central Front (Soviet Union)|Central Front]]'s [[3rd Guards Tank Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Tank Army]] to the [[Voronezh Front]] to race the weakening Germans to the Dnieper, to save the wheat crop from the German scorched earth policy, and to achieve strategic or operational river [[bridgehead]]s before a German defence could stabilize there. The 3rd Tank Army, plunging headlong, reached the river on the night of 21–22 September and, on the 23rd, Soviet infantry forces crossed by swimming and by using makeshift rafts to secure small, fragile bridgeheads, opposed only by 120 German Cherkassy flak academy NCO candidates and the hard-pressed 19th Panzer Division Reconnaissance Battalion.  Those forces were the only Germans within 60&amp;nbsp;km of the Dnieper loop. Only a heavy German air attack and a lack of bridging equipment kept Soviet heavy weaponry from crossing and expanding the bridgehead.

The Soviets, sensing a critical juncture, ordered a hasty airborne corps assault to increase the size of the bridgehead before the Germans could counterattack. On the 21st, the Voronezh Front's 1st, 3rd and 5th Guards [[Russian Airborne Troops|Airborne]] Brigades got the urgent call to secure, on the 23rd, a bridgehead perimeter 15 to 20&amp;nbsp;km wide and 30&amp;nbsp;km deep on the Dnieper loop between Kaniv and Rzhishchev, while Front elements forced the river.

The arrival of personnel at the airfields was slow, necessitating, on the 23rd, a one-day delay and omission of 1st Brigade from the plan; consequent mission changes caused near chaos in command channels. Mission change orders finally got down to company commanders, on the 24th, just 15 minutes before their units, not yet provisioned with spades, anti-tank mines, or ponchos for the autumn night frosts, assembled on airfields.  Owing to the weather, not all assigned aircraft had arrived at airfields on time (if at all).  Further, most flight safety officers disallowed maximum loading of their aircraft. Given fewer aircraft (and lower than expected capacities), the master loading plan, ruined, was abandoned. Many radios and supplies got left behind. In the best case, it would take three lifts to deliver the two brigades. Units (still arriving by the over-taxed rail system), were loaded piecemeal onto returned aircraft, which were slow to refuel owing to the less-than-expected capacities of fuel trucks. Meanwhile, already-arrived troops changed planes, seeking earlier flights.  Urgency and the fuel shortage prevented aerial assembly aloft. Most aircraft, as soon as they were loaded and fueled, flew in single file, instead of line abreast, to the dropping points.  Assault waves became as intermingled as the units they carried.

As corps elements made their flights, troops (half of whom had never jumped, except from training towers) were briefed on drop zones, assembly areas and objectives only poorly understood by platoon commanders still studying new orders. Meanwhile, Soviet aerial photography, suspended for several days by bad weather, had missed the strong reinforcement of the area, early that afternoon. Non-combat cargo pilots ferrying 3rd Brigade through drizzle expected no resistance beyond river pickets but, instead, were met by anti-aircraft fire and starshells from the [[19th Panzer Division]] (only coincidentally transiting the drop zone, and just one of six divisions and other formations ordered, on the 21st, to fill the gap in front of the 3rd Tank Army). Lead aircraft, disgorging [[paratrooper]]s over Dubari at 1930, came under fire from elements of the 73rd Panzer Grenadier Regiment and division staff of 19th Panzer Division. Some paratroops began returning fire and throwing grenades even before landing; trailing aircraft accelerated, climbed and evaded, dropping wide. Through the night, some pilots avoided starshell-lit drop points entirely, and 13 aircraft returned to airfields without having dropped at all. Intending a 10 by 14&amp;nbsp;km drop over largely undefended terrain, the Soviets instead achieved a 30 by 90&amp;nbsp;km drop over the fastest mobile elements of two German corps.

On the ground, the Germans used white parachutes as beacons to hunt down and kill disorganized groups and to gather and destroy airdropped supplies. Supply bonfires, glowing embers, and multi-color starshells illuminated the battlefield. Captured documents gave the Germans enough knowledge of Soviet objectives to arrive at most of them before the disorganized paratroops.

Back at the Soviet airfields, the fuel shortage allowed only 298 of 500 planned sorties, leaving corps anti-tank guns and 2,017 paratroops undelivered. Of 4,575 men dropped (seventy percent of the planned number, and just 1,525 from 5th Brigade), some 2,300 eventually assembled into 43 ad-hoc groups, with missions abandoned as hopeless, and spent most of their time seeking supplies not yet destroyed by the Germans. Others joined with the nine [[Soviet partisans|partisan]] groups operating in the area. About 230 made it over (or out of) the Dnieper to Front units (or were originally dropped there). Most of the rest were almost casually captured that first night or killed the next day (although, on that first night, the 3rd Co, 73rd Panzer Grenadier Regiment, suffered heavy losses while annihilating about 150 paratroopers near Grushevo, some 3&amp;nbsp;km west of Dubari).

The Germans underestimated that 1,500 to 2,000 had dropped; they recorded 901 paratroops captured and killed in the first 24 hours. Thereafter, they largely ignored the Soviet paratroopers, to counterattack and truncate the Dnieper bridgeheads. The Germans deemed their anti-paratrooper operations completed by the 26th, although a modicum of opportunistic actions against garrisons, rail lines, and columns were conducted by remnants up to early November. For a lack of manpower to clear all areas, forests of the region would remain a minor threat.

The Germans called the operation a fundamentally sound idea ruined by the dilettantism of planners lacking expert knowledge (but praised individual paratroops for their tenacity, bayonet skills and deft use of broken ground in the sparsely wooded northern region). Stavka deemed this second (and, ultimately, last) corps drop a complete failure; lessons they knew they had already learned from their winter offensive corps drop at Viazma had not stuck.  They would never trust themselves to try it again.

Soviet 5th Guards Airborne Brigade commander Sidorchuk, withdrawing to the forests south, eventually amassed a brigade-size command, half paratroops, half partisans; he obtained air supply, and assisted the 2nd Ukrainian Front over the Dnieper near Cherkassy to finally link up with Front forces on 15 November. After 13 more days combat, the airborne element was evacuated, ending a harrowing two months. More than sixty percent never returned.

=== Assault-crossing the Dnieper ===
[[File:Dayosh Kiev.jpg|thumb|Soviet soldiers preparing rafts to cross the Dnieper (the sign reads "Onwards to Kiev!")]]

The first bridgehead on the Dnieper's western shore was established on 22 September 1943 at the confluence of the Dnieper and [[Pripyat River|Pripyat]] rivers, in the northern part of the front. On 24 September, another bridgehead was created near [[Kamianske|Dniprodzerzhynsk]], another on 25 September near [[Dnipropetrovsk]] and yet another on 28 September near [[Kremenchuk]]. By the end of the month, 23 bridgeheads were created on the western side, some of them 10 kilometers wide and 1-2 kilometres deep.

The crossing of the Dnieper was extremely difficult. Soldiers used every available floating device to cross the river, under heavy German fire and taking heavy losses. Once across, Soviet troops had to dig themselves into the clay ravines composing the Dnieper's western bank.

=== Securing the lodgements ===
[[File:Dnieper Forcing Offensive.jpg|thumb|Soviet soldiers attacking on a lodgement in October 1943]]
German troops soon launched heavy [[counterattack]]s on almost every bridgehead, hoping to annihilate them before heavy equipment could be transported across the river.

For instance, the Borodaevsk lodgement, mentioned by Marshal [[Konev]] in his memoirs, came under heavy armored attack and air assault. Bombers attacked both the lodgement and the reinforcements crossing the river. Konev complained at once about a lack of organization of Soviet air support, set up air patrols to prevent bombers from approaching the lodgements and ordered forward more artillery to counter tank attacks from the opposite shore. When Soviet aviation became more organized and hundreds of guns and [[Katyusha rocket launcher]]s began firing, the situation started to improve and the bridgehead was eventually preserved.

Such battles were commonplace on every lodgement. Although all the lodgements were held, losses were terrible – at the beginning of October, most divisions were at only 25 to 50% of their nominal strength.

=== Lower Dnieper Offensive ===
By mid-October, the forces accumulated on the lower Dnieper bridgeheads were strong enough to stage a first massive attack to definitely secure the river's western shore in the southern part of the front. Therefore, a vigorous attack was staged on the [[Kremenchuk]]-[[Dnipropetrovsk]] line. Simultaneously, a major diversion was conducted in the south to draw German forces away both from the Lower Dnieper and from Kiev.

At the end of the offensive, Soviet forces controlled a bridgehead 300 kilometers wide and up to 80 kilometers deep in some places. In the south, the Crimea was now cut off from the rest of the German forces. Any hope of stopping the Red Army on the Dnieper's east bank was lost.

== Outcomes ==
The Battle of the Dnieper was another defeat for a ''Wehrmacht'' that required it to restabilize the front further West. The Red Army, which Hitler hoped to contain at the Dnieper, forced the ''Wehrmacht''{{'}}s defences. Kiev was recaptured and German troops lacked the forces to annihilate Soviet troops on the Lower Dnieper bridgeheads. The west bank was still in German hands for the most part, but both sides knew that it would not last for long.

Additionally, the Battle of the Dnieper demonstrated the strength of the Soviet partisan movement. The "[[rail war]]" operation staged during September and October 1943 struck German logistics very hard, creating heavy supply issues.

Incidentally, between 28 November and 1 December 1943 the [[Teheran conference]] was held between [[Winston Churchill]], [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]], and Stalin. The Battle of the Dnieper, along with other major offensives staged in 1943, certainly gave Stalin a dominant position for negotiating with his Allies.

The Soviet success during this battle created the conditions for the follow-up [[Dnieper–Carpathian Offensive|Dnieper-Carpathian Offensive]] on the [[right-bank Ukraine]], which was launched on 24 December 1943 from a bridgehead west of [[Kiev]] that was secured during this battle.&lt;ref&gt;Грылев А.Н. Днепр-Карпаты-Крым. Освобождение Правобережной Украины и Крыма в 1944 году. Москва: Наука, 1970, p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; The offensive brought the Red Army from the [[Dnieper]] all the way to [[Galicia (Eastern Europe)|Galicia]] ([[Poland]]), [[Carpathian Mountains]] and [[Romania]], with [[Army Group South]] being split into two parts- north and south of Carpathians.

==Soviet operational phases==

From a Soviet operational point of view, the battle was broken down into a number of different phases and offensives.

The first phase of the battle :
*[[Chernigov-Poltava Strategic Offensive]]  26 August 1943 – 30 September 1943 (Central, Voronezh and Steppe fronts)
:[[Chernigov-Pripyet Offensive]] 26 August – 30 September 1943
:[[Sumy-Priluki Offensive]] 26 August – 30 September 1943
:[[Poltava-Kremenchug Offensive]] 26 August – 30 September 1943
*[[Donbass Strategic Offensive (August 1943)|Donbass Strategic Offensive]]  13 August – 22 September 1943 (Southwestern and Southern fronts)
*[[Dnieper airborne assault]] 24 September - 24 November 1943

The second phase of the operation includes :
*[[Lower Dnieper Offensive]] 26 September – 20 December 1943
:[[Melitopol Offensive]] 26 September – 5 November 1943
:[[Zaporizhia Offensive]] 10–14 October 1943
:[[Kremenchug-Pyatikhatki Offensive]] 15 October – 3 November 1943
:[[Dnepropetrovsk Offensive]] 23 October – 23 December 1943
:[[Krivoi Rog Offensive]] 14–21 November 1943
:[[Apostolovo Offensive]] 14 November – 23 December 1943
:[[Nikopol Offensive]] 14 November – 31 December 1943
:[[Aleksandriia-Znamenka Offensive]] 22 November – 9 December 1943
:[[Krivoi Rog Offensive]] 10–19 December 1943
* Kiev Strategic Offensive Operation (October) (1–24 October 1943)
:Chernobyl-Radomysl Offensive Operation (1–4 October 1943)
:Chernobyl-Gornostaipol Defensive Operation (3–8 October 1943)
:Lyutezh Offensive Operation (11–24 October 1943)
:Bukrin Offensive Operation (12–15 October 1943)
:Bukrin Offensive Operation (21–24 October 1943)
*[[Battle of Kiev (1943)|Kiev Strategic Offensive]]  3–13 November 1943
:Rauss' November 1943 counterattack
*[[Battle of Kiev (1943)|Kiev Strategic Defensive]]  13 November – 22 December 1943

==References==
===Citations===
{{reflist}}

===Bibliography===
{{More footnotes|date=February 2008}}
* {{cite book
 | last1 = Frieser
 | first1 = Karl-Heinz
 | author-link1 = Karl-Heinz Frieser
 | first2 =Klaus 
 | last2 = Schmider
 | first3 =Klaus 
 | last3 = Schönherr
 | first4 = Gerhard 
 | last4 = Schreiber
 | first5 = Kristián 
 | last5 = Ungváry
 | author-link5 = Krisztián Ungváry
 | first6 =Bernd 
 | last6=Wegner
 | work = [[Das Deutsche Reich und der Zweite Weltkrieg]] [Germany and the Second World War]
 | volume = VIII
 | title = Die Ostfront 1943/44 – Der Krieg im Osten und an den Nebenfronten
 | trans-title = The Eastern Front 1943–1944: The War in the East and on the Neighbouring Fronts
 | publisher = Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt 
 | location = München
 | year = 2007
 | isbn = 978-3-421-06235-2
 | language = German
 | ref = harv
 }}
* David M. Glantz, [[Jonathan House|Jonathan M. House]], ''When Titans Clashed: How the Red Army stopped Hitler'', University Press of Kansas, 1995
* Nikolai Shefov, ''Russian fights'', Lib. Military History, Moscow, 2002
* ''History of Great Patriotic War'', 1941 — 1945. Moscow, 1963
* [[John Erickson (historian)|John Erickson]], ''Barbarossa: The Axis and the Allies'', Edinburgh University Press, 1994
*Harrison, Richard. (2018) ''The Battle of the Dnepr: The Red Army's Forcing of the East Wall, September–December 1943''. Helion and Company. {{ISBN|978-1912174171}}
* Marshal [[Konev]], ''Notes of a front commander'', Science, Moscow, 1972.
* [[Erich von Manstein]], ''Lost Victories'', Moscow, 1957.

{{coord missing|Ukraine}}
{{World War II}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2017}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1943|the Dnieper]]
[[Category:1943 in Ukraine]]
[[Category:Strategic operations of the Red Army in World War II|the Dnieper]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Czechoslovakia|Dnieper]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Soviet Union|Dnieper]]
[[Category:1943 in the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War|the Dnieper]]
[[Category:World War II aerial operations and battles of the Eastern Front|the Dnieper]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany|Dnieper]]</text><sha1>gu6t0wvao1p3ef7fyniyqtll857iw5j</sha1></revision></page>