<page><title>Zhitomir–Berdichev Offensive</title><ns>0</ns><id>19661777</id><revision><id>933200609</id><parentid>819848361</parentid><timestamp>2019-12-30T15:05:13Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Tai3chinirv7ana</username><id>32580938</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="5996" xml:space="preserve">{{Campaignbox Dnieper–Carpathian Offensive}}
The '''[[Zhytomyr]]–[[Berdychiv]] Offensive'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Red storm over the Balkans: the failed Soviet invasion of Romania, spring 1944 |last=Glantz |first=David |authorlink=David Glantz |coauthors= |year=2007 |publisher=University Press of Kansas |location= |isbn=0-7006-1465-6 |pages=3, 8, 58 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=9vNmAAAAMAAJ|accessdate=}}&lt;/ref&gt; operation ({{lang-uk|Житомирсько-Бердичівська наступальна операція}}) was a part of the [[strategic offensive]] of the Red Army in the right-bank (western) [[Ukrainian SSR]], the [[Dnieper–Carpathian Offensive]]. The [[Offensive (military)|offensive]] operation was conducted by the forces of the [[1st Ukrainian Front]] commanded by General of Army [[Nikolai Fyodorovich Vatutin|Nikolai Vatutin]] during [[World War II]], from 24 December  through to 14 January 1944.

The task was to defeat the opposing German [[4th Panzer Army]] of [[Army Group South]] and advance to the [[Southern Bug]] river while preventing new attempts by the enemy to recapture [[Kiev]]. After an opening  attack across a 300 kilometer front, Soviet troops advanced from 80 to 200&amp;nbsp;km and nearly liberated all of the [[Kiev oblast|Kiev]] and [[Zhytomyr Oblast]] regions, along with the regions of the [[Vinnytsia Oblast|Vinnytsa]] and [[Rivne Oblast]]s. The 1st Ukrainian Front gained a position north of the main German forces of Army Group South. The German forces retained the western shore of the [[Dnieper]] in the [[Kaniv]] region.
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-090-3911-07, Russland, Kolonne von Panzer IV.jpg|thumb|170px|left|A panzer group checks its position]]
[[File:Zitomir 43-44.jpg|thumb|right|Soviet T-34 tanks await orders to move forward]]

Manstein brought the [[1st Panzer Army]] up to join the 4th Panzer Army in launching a series of counterattacks against the flanks of the extended Soviet forces. These counterattacks, conducted over the following three weeks, succeeded in creating a series of loosely held pockets, and the Germans began to stabilize their front. The German counterattacks inflicted considerable losses in men and material upon the Red Army, and a cohesive defensive position eventually was restored. However the Soviet's held a great number of forces in reserve, and the success von Manstein achieved could not last.

In addition to the Soviet formations and units, the [[Czechoslovak military units on Eastern front|1st Czechoslovak Brigade]] also participated in the operation.

As a result of the [[Battle of Kiev (1943)|Kiev Strategic Offensive]] operation late in 1943, troops of the 1st Ukrainian Front under Vatutin took a large bridgehead on the right bank of the Dnieper in the Kiev region that “overhung” the enemy group of the troops in the south-western Ukraine. In an attempt to reduce the bridgehead and to retake Kiev, German forces counter-attacked in the region south of [[Zhytomyr]]. The attempt to retake Kiev failed during the [[Battle of Kiev (1943)|Kiev Strategic Defensive]].

All told, in the course of the operation, the Soviets achieved notable success. Having advanced to a depth of 80 to 200 km, they almost completely cleared the German forces from the [[Kiev Oblast|Kiev]] and [[Zhytomyr Oblast|Zhytomyr]] regions, a number of districts of the [[Vinnytsia Oblast|Vinnitsa]] and [[Rivne Oblast|Rovno]] regions.&lt;ref name="auto5"&gt;Грылев А.Н. Днепр-Карпаты-Крым. Освобождение Правобережной Украины и Крыма в 1944 году. Москва: Наука, 1970, p. 46&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviets now dangerously hanged from the north over Army Group South, while the [[27th Army (Soviet Union)|27th]] and [[40th Army (Soviet Union)|40th]] Armies had deeply enveloped the German troops that continued to hold the right bank of the [[Dnieper]] in the area of Kanev. This created the conditions for the subsequent [[Battle of the Korsun–Cherkassy Pocket|Korsun-Schevchenkovsky Operation]].

The blow of the 1st Ukrainian Front was struck at the most sensitive place of Army Group South - its northern flank, which threatened to cut off its main forces from the paths leading to Germany. The [[1st Panzer Army|1st]] and [[4th Panzer Army|4th]] Panzer Armies operating in the front line had suffered serious losses- the 143rd and 147th Reserve Infantry Divisions were disbanded, the [[68th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|68th Infantry Division]] due to heavy losses was withdrawn from the front-line and sent to Poland for extensive refits, while [[8th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|8th Panzer Division]], [[20th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|20th Panzer-Grenadier Division]], [[112th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|112th]], [[291st Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|291st]] and 340th Infantry Divisions were halved in strength.&lt;ref name="auto5" /&gt; All told, 8 Wehrmacht divisions were either destroyed or halved in strength.

To close the gaps in their defense and to stop the Soviet offensive on this sector, the Germans had to urgently transfer 12 divisions of the [[1st Panzer Army]] from the southern Ukraine to this area. The reserves turned out to be almost completely spent, which affected the further course of operations. To parry the subsequent attacks of the Soviet troops, the German command was forced to deploy troops from [[Western Europe]], as well as from [[Romania]], [[Hungary]], [[Yugoslavia]].&lt;ref name="auto5" /&gt;

==Notes and references==
{{reflist}}

{{clear}} &lt;!-- The clr tag prevents the picture from running into the next section. Please keep it at the bottom of this section. --&gt;

==See also==
* [[Eastern Front (World War II)]]
* [[Timeline of the Eastern Front of World War II]]

{{coord missing|Ukraine}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Zhitomir-Berdichev Offensive}}
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]


{{WWII-battle-stub}}</text><sha1>4n49or86kxcxebqitqwrghyraa5z9c0</sha1></revision></page>