<page><title>Leningrad–Novgorod Offensive</title><ns>0</ns><id>19882395</id><revision><id>955939745</id><parentid>955907729</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-10T16:54:57Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Filiep</username><id>1065306</id></contributor><comment>/* Novgorod–Luga Offensive : 14 January — 15 February 1944 */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="18010" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Leningrad–Novgorod Offensive
| partof      = the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = RIAN archive 764 A battle in the outskirts.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = Soviet machine-gunners near Detskoye Selo railway station in [[Pushkin, Saint Petersburg|Pushkin]], January&amp;nbsp;21
| date        = January&amp;nbsp;14 – March&amp;nbsp;1, 1944
| place       = Southern [[Leningrad Oblast|Leningrad region]], [[Novgorod Oblast|Novgorod]], [[Pskov Oblast|Pskov]]&lt;ref&gt;Most of modern [[Novgorod Oblast]] and parts of [[Pskov Oblast]] belonged to Leningrad Oblast at the time.&lt;/ref&gt; and [[Narva]]
| result      = Soviet victory
* [[Siege of Leningrad]] is lifted.
| territory   = Recapture of the region by Soviets 
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]
| combatant2  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Georg von Küchler]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Until February&amp;nbsp;1)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Walter Model]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(From February&amp;nbsp;1)&lt;/small&gt;
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Kirill Meretskov]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Leonid Govorov]]
| units1      = [[Army Group North]]: &lt;br&gt;44 infantry divisions &lt;br&gt;{{sfn|Glantz|2002|p=329}}
| units2      = [[Leningrad Front]]&lt;br&gt;[[Volkhov Front]]&lt;br&gt;[[2nd Baltic Front]]&lt;br&gt;[[Baltic Fleet]]:&lt;br&gt;57 divisions
| strength1   = 500,000 men&lt;br&gt;2,389 artillery pieces&lt;br&gt;146 tanks&lt;br&gt;140 aircraft{{sfn|Glantz|2002|p=329}}
| strength2   = 822,000 men&lt;br&gt;4,600 artillery pieces&lt;br&gt;550 tanks&lt;br&gt;653 aircraft{{sfn|Glantz|2002|p=329}}
| casualties1 = 24,739 dead and missing&lt;ref name="ww2stats.com"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://ww2stats.com/cas_ger_okh_dec44.html |title=Heeresarzt 10-Day Casualty Reports per Army/Army Group, 1944 |work=Human Losses in World War II |url-status=usurped |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20121029022744/http://ww2stats.com/cas_ger_okh_dec44.html |archive-date=2012-10-29 |publisher=German Statistics and Documents }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;46,912 wounded&lt;ref name="ww2stats.com"/&gt; &lt;br&gt;'''Total:''' 71,651 casualties (per German military medical reports)&lt;ref name="ww2stats.com"/&gt;
| casualties2 = 76,686 dead and missing,&lt;br&gt; 237,267 wounded{{sfn|Glantz|House|1995|p=298}}&lt;br&gt;'''Total:''' 313,953 casualties{{sfn|Glantz|House|1995|p=298}}
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Campaignbox Leningrad and Baltics 1941-1944}}
{{Campaignbox Leningrad–Novgorod Offensive}}
{{Campaignbox Stalin's ten blows}}
}}
[[File:Eastern Front 1943-08 to 1944-12.png|thumb|right|Soviet gains, mid-1943 to end of 1944]]

The '''Leningrad–Novgorod strategic offensive''' was a strategic offensive during World War II. It was launched by the [[Red Army]] on {{date|1944-1-14|mdy}} with an attack on the German [[Army Group North]] by the Soviet [[Volkhov Front|Volkhov]] and [[Leningrad Front|Leningrad]] fronts, along with part of the [[Bryansk Front|2nd Baltic]] Front,&lt;ref name="siege"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.secondworldwarhistory.com/siege-of-leningrad.asp|title=Siege of Leningrad|publisher=Second World War History Online|accessdate={{date|2011-2-27|mdy}}}}&lt;/ref&gt; with a goal of fully lifting the [[Siege of Leningrad]]. Approximately two weeks later, the Red Army regained control of the [[Moscow – Saint Petersburg Railway|Moscow–Leningrad railway]], and on {{date|1944-1-26|mdy}} [[Joseph Stalin]] declared that the Siege of Leningrad was lifted, and that German forces were expelled from the [[Leningrad Oblast]].&lt;ref name=knigapoter315&gt;Krivosheev, Grigori et al., p.&amp;nbsp;315&lt;/ref&gt; The lifting of the 900-day-long blockade was celebrated in [[Leningrad]] on that day with a 324-gun salute.&lt;ref name=siege/&gt; The strategic offensive ended a month later on 1 March, when Stavka ordered the troops of the Leningrad Front to a [[Narva Offensive (1–4&amp;nbsp;March 1944)|follow-on operation]] across the [[Battle of Narva (1944)|Narva River]], while the 2nd Baltic was to defend the territory it gained in pursuit of the German [[XVI Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XVI Army Corps]].&lt;ref name=knigapoter317&gt;Krivosheev, Grigori et al., p.&amp;nbsp;317&lt;/ref&gt;

The Germans had suffered nearly 72,000 casualties, lost 85 artillery pieces ranging in caliber from 15&amp;nbsp;cm to 40&amp;nbsp;cm, and were pushed back between 60 and 100 kilometers from Leningrad to the [[Luga River]].&lt;ref name=grechko/&gt;
&lt;!--
==Order of battle==
The operation involved three fronts: The [[Leningrad Front]], the [[Bryansk Front|Second Baltic Front]] and the [[Volkhov Front]]. The total Soviet strength was 1,241,000 men, 10,070 guns, 385 tanks and 370 planes plus the Soviet [[Baltic Fleet]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Absolute War: Soviet Russia in the Second World War |last=Bellamy |first=Chris |year=2007 |publisher=Macmillan |location= |isbn=978-0-333-78022-0 |pages= |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=S2BoAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=%22Leningrad-Novgorod+Strategic+Offensive%22&amp;dq=&amp;pgis=1 }}&lt;/ref&gt;
--&gt;

==Background==
After [[Operation Barbarossa]], German troops had encircled Leningrad, and the [[Siege of Leningrad]] began. Several operations had been designed by the Soviet commanders in the area to liberate the outskirts of Leningrad from the Germans. In the fall of 1943, preparations had begun to design another plan to retake the outskirts of Leningrad from the Germans, after the only partially successful [[Operation Iskra]] in January of that year which had followed the failed [[Sinyavino Offensive (1942)|Sinyavino Offensive]] of late 1942. The first staff meeting was held on {{date|1943-9-9|mdy}}, two years and a day after the beginning of the siege.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury560&gt;Salisbury, p.&amp;nbsp;560&lt;/ref&gt; Two plans, Neva&amp;nbsp;I and Neva&amp;nbsp;II, were conceived. Neva I was to be implemented if the Germans, pressured on different fronts, withdrew their forces from Leningrad on their own accord to reinforce the pressured areas. Both [[Stavka]] and Leningrad believed this was possible.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury560/&gt; Neva&amp;nbsp;II, therefore, would be implemented if the Germans did not withdraw from Leningrad within the coming months.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury560/&gt; The offensive would be three-pronged, driving from the [[Oranienbaum Bridgehead|foothold at Oranienbaum]] that had been captured earlier that year, the [[Pulkovo Heights]] and from the fortifications around [[Novgorod]].&lt;ref name=Sailsbury560/&gt; The offensive was planned to start in the winter, when sufficient numbers of troops and artillery could be moved across the ice without incident.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury560/&gt;

==Preparations==

===Soviet===
The Baltic Fleet had been assigned the task of transporting the Second Shock Army under the command of [[Ivan Fedyuninsky]] over Lake Ladoga to Oranienbaum. From {{date|1943-11-5|mdy}} onwards, the Fleet transported 30,000 troops, 47 tanks, 400 artillery pieces, 1,400 trucks and 10,000 tons of ammunition and supplies from the wharves at the Leningrad factories, Kanat and the naval base at [[Lisy Nos]] to Oranienbaum.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury561/&gt; After Lake Ladoga froze, another 22,000 men, 800 trucks, 140 tanks and 380 guns were sent overland to the jump-off point.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury561&gt;Salisbury, p.&amp;nbsp;561&lt;/ref&gt; When the shipments were complete, the artillery was positioned along the entire length of the Leningrad, Second Baltic and Volkhov fronts at a concentration of 200 guns per kilometer, including 21,600 standard artillery pieces, 1,500 Katyusha rocket guns, and 600 anti-aircraft guns.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury561/&gt; 1,500 planes were also obtained from the Baltic Fleet and from installations around Leningrad.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury561/&gt;{{sfn|Гречанюк |Дмитриев |Корниенко |1990}} The total number of Soviet personnel prepared for action was 1,241,000, against the 741,000 German troops.&lt;ref&gt;Salisbury, p.&amp;nbsp;561–562&lt;/ref&gt; A final meeting took place on January&amp;nbsp;11 in [[Smolny]].&lt;ref name=Sailsbury562/&gt; General Govorov, the top Soviet commander on the Leningrad Front, had listed his priorities. In order to open up southeastward and eastward main railroad lines from Leningrad, Soviet troops would have to occupy [[Gatchina]], from which they could retake [[Mga]], the minor city and rail station whose capture in 1941 had closed the last railroad route into Leningrad. Govorov positioned his troops accordingly.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury562/&gt;

===German===
[[Image:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-244-2321-34, Ostfront-Süd, Panzer V (Panther).jpg|thumb|Panther on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]], 1944.]]
The situation of the German Army Group North at the end of 1943 had deteriorated to a critical point. The [[Blue Division]] and three German divisions had been withdrawn by October, while the Army Group had acquired sixty miles of additional frontage from [[Army Group Center]] during the same period. As replacements, Field Marshal [[Georg von Küchler]] received the Spanish [[Blue Legion]] and three divisions of SS troops. In such a weakened state, the Army Group staff planned a new position to its rear that would shorten the front lines by twenty-five percent and remove the Soviet threats posed in many salients on the current lines. The plan ''Operation Blue'' called for a January withdrawal of over 150&amp;nbsp;miles to the natural defensive barrier formed by the [[Narva River|Narva]] and [[Velikaya River]]s and Lakes [[Peipus]] and [[Pskov Lake|Pskov]]. This position, the so-called "[[Panther Line]]", was buttressed by fortifications that had been constructed since September. The retreat would be carried out in stages, using intermediate defensive positions, the most important of which was the Rollbahn Line formed on the [[October Railway]] running through [[Tosno]], [[Lyuban, Russia|Lyuban]] and [[Chudovo, Chudovsky District, Novgorod Oblast|Chudovo]]. There the two most exposed Army Corps, the XXVI and [[XXXVIII Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXVIII]], would regroup and catch their breath before proceeding farther back to their positions in the Panther Line.&lt;ref name=anabasis/&gt;

The fate of Army Group North turned for the worse in the new year, for [[Hitler]] rejected all proposals for an early withdrawal into the "Panther" position, insisting that the Soviet forces be kept as far as possible from Germany and that they be forced to pay dearly for each meter of ground. Finally, Hitler transferred three more first-rate infantry divisions out of Army Group North to reinforce [[Erich von Manstein]]'s [[Army Group South]] as it reeled back from the [[Dnieper River]] under continuous Soviet assault. Field Marshal von Küchler now held an extremely precarious position, and could only await events on the Leningrad and Volkhov Fronts with great pessimism.&lt;ref name=anabasis&gt;Kenneth W. Estes [http://www.gutenberg-e.org/esk01/esk05.html A European Anabasis — Western European Volunteers in the German Army and SS, 1940-1945. Chapter 5. "Despair and Fanaticism, 1944-45"] [[Columbia University Press]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Combat activity==

===Krasnoye Selo–Ropsha Offensive: 14–31 January 1944 ===
{{Main|Krasnoye Selo–Ropsha Offensive}}
In the late hours of {{date|1944-1-13|mdy}}, long-range bombers from the Baltic Fleet attacked the main German command points on the defensive line. On January&amp;nbsp;14, troops from both the Oranienbaum foothold and Volkhov Front attacked, followed the next day by troops of the [[42nd Army (Soviet Union)|42nd Army]] under the command of [[Ivan Maslennikov]] from the Pulkovo Heights.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury562/&gt; An artillery barrage was launched all along the front, laying down 220,000 shells onto the German lines.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury564/&gt; Fog inhibited major progress for the first few days, although the Second Shock Army and 42nd Army advanced two miles on a seven-mile front while in combat with the [[9th Luftwaffe Field Division (Germany)|9th]] and [[10th Luftwaffe Field Division (Germany)|10th]] [[Luftwaffe Field Division]]s,&lt;ref name=Sailsbury562&gt;Salisbury, p.&amp;nbsp;562&lt;/ref&gt; and the Volkhov Front pushed the Germans back about three miles.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury564&gt;Salisbury, p.&amp;nbsp;564&lt;/ref&gt; It thawed on the 16th, and the Second Shock Army managed to move forward 23&amp;nbsp;kilometers.&lt;ref name=grechko&gt;{{cite book|author=A.A. Grechko|title=Geschichte des Zweiten Weltkrieges (History of World War II. In German)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Sailsbury565&gt;Salisbury, p.&amp;nbsp;565&lt;/ref&gt; On the 19th, the Second Shock Army captured Ropsha and the 63rd Guards Rifle Division, part of the 42nd Army, drove the Germans out of [[Krasnoye Selo]]. By January&amp;nbsp;26, German troops had been pushed 100&amp;nbsp;kilometers away from the city, and the [[Moscow – Saint Petersburg Railway|Moscow–Leningrad Railroad]] line had been opened.&lt;ref name=Sailsbury566/&gt; The next day, Stalin declared the city to have been relieved, and Leningrad celebrated with a red, white and blue salute from 324 [[Katyusha rocket launcher|Katyusha]] rocket launchers and artillery pieces at 8&amp;nbsp;pm,&lt;ref name=Sailsbury566&gt;Salisbury, p.&amp;nbsp;566&lt;/ref&gt; which was inconceivable during the siege due to [[blackout (wartime)|blackout]].

===Novgorod–Luga Offensive : 14 January — 15 February 1944 ===
{{Main|Novgorod–Luga Offensive}}
On 14 January Soviet troops of the [[Volkhov Front]] launched an offensive from the [[Novgorod]] area towards [[Luga, Leningrad Oblast|Luga]] against a part of the [[18th Army (Wehrmacht)|18th German Army]]. The aim was freeing the [[October Railway]] and encircling, together with the troops of the [[Leningrad Front]], the main forces of the 18th Army in the Luga region.

The offensive did not develop as rapidly as planned before the operation. The German 18th Army suffered a heavy defeat, but still wasn't destroyed and retained a significant part of its combat potential, which prevented the Soviet troops in the spring of 1944 to break through the [[Panther–Wotan line]] and begin the liberation of the Baltics.
One of the reasons for this development was the lack of coordination between the [[2nd Baltic Front]] and the [[Volkhov Front]], which allowed the German command to move significant forces from the 16th Army to the Luga area.

By February 15, the troops of the Volkhov Front, as well as the 42nd and 67th Army of the Leningrad Front, reached [[Lake Peipus]], having pushed the enemy 50-120 kilometers to the West. In total 779 cities and settlements were liberated, including Novgorod, Luga, [[Batetsky (rural locality)|Batetsky]], Oredezh, [[Mga]], [[Tosno]], [[Lyuban (town), Leningrad Oblast|Lyuban]] and [[Chudovo, Chudovsky District, Novgorod Oblast|Chudovo]].
The restoration of control over the strategically important railways, especially Kirov and October, was of great importance.

===Staraya Russa – Novorzhev Offensive : 18 February - 1 March 1944 ===
{{Main|Staraya Russa-Novorzhev Offensive}}
On 18 February, Soviet troops of the [[2nd Baltic Front]], carried out this operation in cooperation with part of the [[Leningrad Front]] against the [[16th Army (Wehrmacht)|German 16th Army]] of Army Group "North" with the aim of liberating the area southwest of [[Lake Ilmen]] and creating the conditions for further offensives.
As a result of the operation, the Soviet troops, pursuing the retreating enemy, advanced up to 180 kilometers to the West, liberating many cities and towns, including [[Staraya Russa]], [[Novorzhev]], [[Dno]] and [[Pustoshka, Pustoshkinsky District, Pskov Oblast|Putoshka]].

===Kingisepp–Gdov Offensive : 1 February - 1 March 1944 ===
{{Main|Kingisepp–Gdov Offensive}}

=== Overview ===

{| Class="wikitable" style="text-align: center"
|-
| style="width:25px;"|[[File:Leningradsko Novgorodskaya operatsya 1944 1 polozhenie storon.jpg|center|300px]]
| style="width:25px;"|[[File:Leningradsko Novgorodskaya operatsya 1944 2 boi 14-31-01-44.jpg|center|300px]]
| style="width:25px;"|[[File:Leningradsko Novgorodskaya operatsya 1944 3 boi 1-15-2-44.jpg|center|300px]]
|-
|Position of the armies before the operation and plan of attack
|Operations between 14-31 January 1944.
|Operations between 1-15 February 1944
|}

==Aftermath==
{{Main|Battle of Narva (1944)}}

==References==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{cite book |ref=harv
 | last= Glantz | first= David M. | author-link=David Glantz
 | last2= House | first2= Jonathan M. | author2-link=Jonathan House
 | title=When Titans Clashed. How the Red Army Stopped Hitler
 | publisher=University Press of Kansas | year=1995 | isbn=0-7006-2120-2
}}
* {{cite book | ref= harv | last= Glantz | first= David M. | author-link= David Glantz | title= The Battle for Leningrad 1941–1944 | publisher= University Press of Kansas | year= 2002 | isbn= 0-7006-1208-4 | url-access= registration | url= https://archive.org/details/battleforleningr00glan }}
*{{cite book |ref=harv
 | last=Salisbury | first=Harrison Evans | authorlink=Harrison Salisbury
 | year=1969 | title=The 900 Days: The Siege of Leningrad
 | publisher=Da Capo Press | isbn= 0-306-81298-3}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv
 | last=Гречанюк | first=Н.М. | last2=Дмитриев | first2=В.И.
 | last3=Корниенко | first3=А.И.
 | year=1990 | title=Дважды, Краснознаменный Балтийский Флот (Baltic Fleet)
 | publisher=Воениздат}}
* {{cite book |ref=harv
 | last=Кривошеев | first=Григорий |last2=Андроников |first2=Владимир |last3=Буриков |first3=Петр
 | title=Россия и СССР в войнах XX века: Книга Потерь
 | publisher=Вече | location=Moscow, Russia | date=2010-03-25}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Leningrad-Novgorod Offensive}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Strategic operations of the Red Army in World War II]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:1944 in Russia]]
[[Category:January 1944 events]]
[[Category:February 1944 events]]
[[Category:March 1944 events]]</text><sha1>jk8h5mv6swejmdbtzz5a0urtp1w0rsf</sha1></revision></page>