<page><title>Battle of Narva (1944)</title><ns>0</ns><id>1932659</id><revision><id>963778774</id><parentid>963563598</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-21T18:55:41Z</timestamp><contributor><username>BHGbot</username><id>5737366</id></contributor><minor /><comment>[[WP:BHGbot 6]] ([[User:BHGbot/6/List 5|List 5]]): eponymous category first, per [[MOS:CATORDER]]; [[WP:GENFIXES]]</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="52994" xml:space="preserve">{{For|other Battles of Narva|Battle of Narva (disambiguation){{!}}Battle of Narva}}
{{short description|Battle of World War II}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Narva
|image= Narva 1944.jpg
|image_size= 300
|caption= Soldiers defending the Estonian bank of the [[Narva River]], with the fortress of [[Ivangorod]] on the opposite side
|partof= the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
|coordinates={{Coord|59|23|N|28|12|E|region:EE_type:event|display=inline,title}}
|place=[[Narva]], [[Estonia]]
|date=2 February – 10 August 1944
|result= German defensive victory
|combatant1={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]
* [[File:Estonian Division.jpg|23px]] [[20th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Estonian)|Estonian conscript]], [[Estonian Auxiliary Police|auxiliary police]] and border guard forces
|combatant2={{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Soviet Union]]
|commander1={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Johannes Frießner]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Felix Steiner]]
|commander2= {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Leonid Govorov]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Ivan Fedyuninsky]]
|units1=
* [[III SS (Germanic) Panzer Corps]]
* XXVI Army Corps
* XXXXIII Army Corps
* Eastern sector, coastal defence
|units2=
* [[2nd Shock Army]]
* [[8th Army (Soviet Union)|8th Army]]
* [[59th Army (Soviet Union)|59th Army]]
* [[8th Estonian Rifle Corps]]
* 14th Rifle Corps
|strength1=123,541 personnel&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;32 tanks&lt;ref name=laar&gt;{{cite book|author=Mart Laar|title=Sinimäed 1944: II maailmasõja lahingud Kirde-Eestis (Sinimäed Hills 1944: Battles of World War II in Northeast Estonia)|publisher= Tallinn: Varrak|year= 2006|language=Estonian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;137 aircraft&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;
|strength2=200,000 personnel&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;&lt;ref name=walter&gt;{{cite web|url=http://historicaltextarchive.com/sections.php?op=viewarticle&amp;artid=383|author=Hannes Walter|publisher=Historical Text Archive|location=Mississippi|title=Estonia in World War II|access-date=21 October 2008|archive-url=https://archive.is/20120523231619/http://historicaltextarchive.com/sections.php?op=viewarticle&amp;artid=383|archive-date=23 May 2012|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;2500 guns&lt;br /&gt;125 tanks&lt;ref name=paulman/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;800 aircraft&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;
|casualties1= 14,000 dead or missing&lt;br /&gt;54,000 wounded or sick&lt;br /&gt;'''68,000 casualties'''&lt;ref name="doyle"&gt;{{cite book|last=Doyle|first=Peter|title=World War II in Numbers|year=2013|publisher=A &amp; C Black|isbn=9781408188194|page=105}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2= 100,000 dead or missing&lt;br /&gt;380,000 wounded or sick{{refn|[[Mart Laar]] in his book ''Sinimäed 1944: II maailmasõja lahingud Kirde-Eestis'' has presented an indirect account of Soviet casualties for the battles. According to the data of the [[Stavka]], the total casualties of the Leningrad Front in 1944 were 665,827 men, 145,102 of them dead or missing. The share of the battles around Narva is unknown but considering the length of the operation, Laar accounts roughly half of the documented 56,564 dead or missing and the 170,876 wounded or sick in the [[Leningrad-Novgorod Offensive]] for the Battle of Narva. This is in accordance with the estimation of F. Paulman, stating in his ''Ot Narvy do Syrve'' that the 2nd Shock Army lost over 30,000 troops at the Narva bridgeheads during February. Deducting the losses in the operations of the Leningrad-Novgorod Offensive conducted elsewhere, the casualties in the [[Vyborg–Petrozavodsk Offensive|battles in Finland]] and in the [[Baltic Offensive (1944)|Baltic Offensive]], Laar totals the numbers of Soviet losses in the Battle of Narva at approximately 100,000 dead or missing and 380,000 wounded or sick. The "cost of nearly 500,000 men" is confirmed in the book ''Battle in the Baltics 1944–1945'' by I. Baxter.|group=nb}}&lt;br /&gt;300 tanks&lt;br /&gt;230 aircraft&lt;ref name=laar&gt;{{cite book|author=Mart Laar|title=Sinimäed 1944: II maailmasõja lahingud Kirde-Eestis (Sinimäed Hills 1944: Battles of World War II in Northeast Estonia)|publisher= Tallinn: Varrak|year= 2006|language=Estonian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'''480,000 casualties'''&lt;ref name="doyle"/&gt;
|notes={{Reflist|group="nb"}}
}}
{{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Campaignbox Leningrad and Baltics 1941-1944}}
{{Campaignbox Estonia 1944}}

The '''Battle of Narva'''{{refn|Estonian: ''Narva lahing''; German: ''Schlacht bei Narva''; Russian: ''Битва за Нарву''|group=nb}} was a military campaign between the German Army Detachment "Narwa" and the Soviet [[Leningrad Front]] fought for possession of the strategically important [[Ida-Viru|Narva Isthmus]] on 2 February – 10 August 1944 during [[World War II]].

The campaign took place in the northern section of the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] and consisted of two major phases: the [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead]] (February to July 1944)&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=McTaggart |first=Pat |chapter=The Battle of Narva, 1944 |editor-last=Command Magazine |pages=294, 296, 297, 299, 302, 305, 307 |title=Hitler's army: the evolution and structure of German forces |publisher=Combined Books |date=2003 |location=Cambridge, MA}}&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Battle of Tannenberg Line]] (July–August 1944).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=McTaggart |first=Pat |chapter=The Battle of Narva, 1944 |editor-last=Command Magazine |page=306 |title=Hitler's army: the evolution and structure of German forces |publisher=Combined Books |date=2003 |location=Cambridge, MA}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet [[Kingisepp–Gdov Offensive]] and Narva Offensives ([[Narva Offensive (15–28 February 1944)|15–28 February]], [[Narva Offensive (1–4 March 1944)|1–4 March]] and [[Narva Offensive (18–24 March 1944)|18–24 March]]) were part of the [[Strategic operations of the Red Army in World War II#Winter Spring campaign of 1944 (1 January – 31 May)|Red Army Winter Spring Campaign of 1944]].&lt;ref name=glantz2/&gt; Following [[Joseph Stalin]]'s "Broad Front" strategy, these battles coincided with the [[Dnieper–Carpathian Offensive]] (December 1943 – April 1944) and the [[Lvov–Sandomierz Offensive]] (July–August 1944).&lt;ref name=glantz2/&gt; A number of foreign volunteers and local [[20 SS|Estonian conscripts]] participated in the battle as part of the German forces. By giving its support to the [[Hague Conventions (1899 and 1907)|illegal]] German conscription call, the underground [[National Committee of the Republic of Estonia]] had hoped to recreate a national army and restore the independence of the country.&lt;ref name=misiunas&gt;Romuald J. Misiunas, Rein Taagepera [https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=FJejwedGesMC The Baltic States, Years of Dependence, 1940–1980]. p. 66. University of California Press, 1983&lt;/ref&gt;

As a continuation of the [[Leningrad–Novgorod Offensive]] of January 1944, the Soviet Estonian operation pushed the front westward to the [[Narva River]], aiming to destroy "Narwa" and to thrust deep into Estonia. The Soviet units established a number of [[bridgehead]]s on the western bank of the river in February while the Germans maintained a bridgehead on the eastern bank. Subsequent attempts failed to expand their toehold. German counterattacks annihilated the bridgeheads to the north of Narva and reduced the bridgehead south of the town, stabilizing the front until July 1944. The Soviet [[Narva Offensive (July 1944)]] led to the capture of the city after the German troops retreated to their prepared Tannenberg Defence Line in the [[Sinimäed Hills]] 16 kilometres from Narva. In the ensuing Battle of Tannenberg Line, the German army group held its ground. Stalin's main strategic goal—a quick recovery of Estonia as a base for air and seaborne attacks [[Continuation War|against Finland]] and an invasion of [[East Prussia]]—was not achieved. As a result of the tough defence of the German forces the Soviet war effort in the [[Baltic Sea]] region was hampered for seven and a half months.&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

==Background==
===Terrain===
Terrain played a significant role in operations around Narva. The elevation above sea level rarely rises above 100 meters in the area and the land is cut by numerous waterways, including the Narva and [[Plyussa River|Plyussa]] Rivers. The bulk of the land in the region is forested and large swamps inundate areas of low elevation. The effect of the terrain on operations was one of channelization; because of the swamps, only certain areas were suitable for large-scale troop movement.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

[[File:Narva terrain.png|thumb|300px|left|The terrain of the Narva Isthmus is dominated by water and forests.]]
On a strategic scale, a natural choke point was present between the northern shore of [[Lake Peipus]] and the [[Gulf of Finland]]. The 45 kilometre wide strip of land was entirely bisected by the Narva River and had large areas of wilderness. The primary transportation routes, the Narva–[[Tallinn]] highway and railway, ran on an east-west axis near and parallel to the coastline. There were no other east-west transportation routes capable of sustaining troop movement on a large scale in the region.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

===Preceding actions===
{{Main|Krasnoye Selo–Ropsha Offensive}}
On 14 January 1944, the Leningrad Front launched the Krasnoye Selo–Ropsha Offensive, aimed at forcing the German [[18th Army (Wehrmacht)|18th Army]] back from its positions near [[Lomonosov, Russia|Oranienbaum]]. On the third day of the offensive, the Soviets broke through German lines and pushed westward.&lt;ref name=anabasis&gt;Kenneth W. Estes. [http://www.gutenberg-e.org/esk01/esk05.html A European Anabasis – Western European Volunteers in the German Army and SS, 1940–1945. Chapter 5. "Despair and Fanaticism, 1944–45"] [[Columbia University Press]]&lt;/ref&gt; The Army Group North evacuated the civilian population of Narva.&lt;ref name=florence&gt;{{cite news|title=Strange Guerilla Army Hampers Nazi Defence of Baltic|location=Florence, Alabama|newspaper=Times Daily|date=10 February 1944|author=Robert Sturdevant}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Soviet aims===
By 1944 it was fairly routine practice for [[Stavka]] to assign its operating fronts new and more ambitious missions while the Soviet Armed Forces were conducting major offensive operations. The rationale was that relentless pressure might trigger a German collapse. For the 1943/1944 winter campaign, Stalin ordered the Red Army to conduct major offensives along the entire Soviet-German front in a continuation of the 'Broad Front' strategy he had pursued since the beginning of the war. This was applied in consonance with his long-standing rationale that, if the Red Army applied pressure along the entire front, German defences were likely to break in at least one section. The Soviet winter campaign included major assaults across the entire expanse the front in the [[Dnieper–Carpathian Offensive|Ukraine]], [[Belorussia]] and against the German [[Panther Line]] in the region of the [[Baltic Sea]].&lt;ref name=glantz2&gt;{{cite book|author=[[David M. Glantz]]|location=Glemson, South Carolina|url=http://sti.clemson.edu/index.php?option=com_docman&amp;task=doc_download&amp;gid=189&amp;Itemid=310|publisher=Strom Thurmond Institute of Government and Public Affairs, Clemson University|year=2001|title=The Soviet-German War 1941–1945: Myths and Realities}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Breaking through the Narva Isthmus situated between the Gulf of Finland and Lake Peipus was of major strategic importance to the Soviet Armed Forces. The success of the Estonian operation would have provided an unobstructed lane to advance along the coast to Tallinn, forcing the German Army Group North to escape from Estonia for fear of getting cornered. For the [[Baltic Fleet]] trapped in an eastern bay of the Gulf of Finland, Tallinn was the closest exit to the Baltic Sea.&lt;ref name=hiio&gt;{{cite book|author=Toomas Hiio|year=2006|pages=1035–1094|chapter=Combat in Estonia in 1944|editor1=Toomas Hiio |editor2=Meelis Maripuu |editor3=Indrek Paavle |title=Estonia 1940–1945: Reports of the [[Estonian International Commission for the Investigation of Crimes Against Humanity]]|location=Tallinn}}&lt;/ref&gt; The ejection of the Army Group North from Estonia would have made Finland subject to air and amphibious attacks originating from Estonian bases. The prospect of an invasion of [[East Prussia]] through Estonia&lt;ref name=krivo&gt;{{cite book|title=Битва за Нарву, февраль-сентябрь 1944 год (The Battle for Narva, February–September 1944)|author=Евгений Кривошеев|author2= Николай Костин|language=Russian|chapter=I. Sraženie dlinoj v polgoda (Half a year of combat)|pages=9–87|location=Tallinn|publisher=Eesti raamat|year=1984}}&lt;/ref&gt; appealed even more to Stavka, as it could bring German resistance to a standstill.&lt;ref name=desjat/&gt; With the participation of [[Leonid Govorov]], commander of the Leningrad Front, and [[Vladimir Tributz]], commander of the Baltic Fleet, a scheme was prepared to destroy the Army Group North.&lt;ref name=desjat/&gt;&lt;ref name=fed&gt;{{cite book|title=Поднятые по тревоге (Risen by Agitation)|author=Иван Иванович Федюнинский|url=http://militera.lib.ru/memo/russian/fedyuninsky/08.html|publisher=Воениздат, Moscow|year=1961 |language=Russian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stalin ordered the capture of Narva at all costs no later than 17 February:&lt;ref name=glantz/&gt;
:"It is mandatory that our forces seize Narva no later than 17 February 1944. This is required both for military as well as political reasons. It is the most important thing right now. I demand that you undertake all necessary measures to liberate Narva no later than the period indicated. (signed) I. Stalin"

After the failure of the Leningrad Front, Stalin gave a new order on 22 February: to break through the "Narwa" defence, give a shock at [[Pärnu]], eliminate the German forces in Estonia, direct two armies at Southeast Estonia, keep going through [[Latvia]] and open the road to East Prussia and [[Central Europe]]. On the same day, the Soviet Union presented Finland with peace conditions.&lt;ref name=glantz&gt;{{cite book|author=David M. Glantz|title=The Battle for Leningrad: 1941–1944|publisher=University Press of Kansas|location=Lawrence|year=2002|isbn=0-7006-1208-4|url=https://archive.org/details/battleforleningr00glan}}&lt;/ref&gt; While Finland regarded the terms as unacceptable, the war waging around them appeared dangerous enough to keep negotiating. To influence Finland, Stalin needed to take Estonia.&lt;ref name=krivo/&gt; His wish was an order to the commanders of the Leningrad Front, with their heads at stake.&lt;ref name=laar2&gt;{{cite book |pages=32–59|chapter=Battles in Estonia in 1944|title=Estonia in World War II |last=Laar |first=Mart |year=2005 |publisher=Grenader| authorlink=Mart Laar|location=Tallinn}}&lt;/ref&gt; After reinforcements, the Narva front acquired the highest concentration of forces at any point on the Eastern Front in March 1944.&lt;ref name=lentsman&gt;{{cite book|author=L. Lentsman|year=1977|title= Eesti rahvas Suures Isamaasõjas (Estonian People in Great Patriotic War)|publisher= Eesti Raamat|location= Tallinn|language= Estonian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Soviet deployments===
[[File:Narva area.png|thumb|Situation around Narva, March 1944.]]
Three Soviet armies were deployed at the maximum concentration of forces in March 1944. The 2nd Shock Army was placed north of Narva, the 59th Army was positioned south of Narva and the [[8th Army (Soviet Army)|8th Army]] south of the 59th Army along the 50&amp;nbsp;km long Narva River stretching down to Lake Peipus. Detailed information on the size of the Soviet forces at the Narva front during the Winter-Spring campaign has not been published by any sources. It is impossible to give an overview on the Soviet strength until the Red Army archival information is made available to non-Russian investigators or published.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; Estonian historian Hannes Walter has estimated the number of Soviet troops in the Battle of Narva at 205,000,&lt;ref name=walter/&gt; which is in accordance with the number of divisions multiplied by the assumed sizes of the divisions presented by the Estonian historian [[Mart Laar]].&lt;ref name=laar/&gt; The order of battle of the Leningrad Front as of 1 March 1944:&lt;ref&gt;[http://tashv.nm.ru/BoevojSostavSA/1944/19440301.html Боевой состав Советской Армии на 1 марта 1944 г.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080514124834/http://tashv.nm.ru/BoevojSostavSA/1944/19440301.html |date=14 May 2008 }} (Order of battle of the Soviet Army on 1 March 1944)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[2nd Shock Army]] – ''Lieutenant General Ivan Fedyuninsky''
** [[43rd Rifle Corps]] – ''Major General Anatoli Andreyev''
** [[109th Rifle Corps]] – ''Major General Ivan Alferov''
** [[124th Rifle Corps]] – ''Major General Voldemar Damberg''
* [[8th Army (Soviet Union)|8th Army]] – ''Lieutenant General Filip Starikov''
** [[6th Rifle Corps]] – ''Major General Semyon Mikulski''
** [[112th Rifle Corps]] – ''Major General Filip Solovev''
* 59th Army – ''Lieutenant General Ivan Korovnikov''
** [[117th Rifle Corps]] – ''Major General Vasili Trubachev''
** [[122nd Rifle Corps]] – ''Major General Panteleimon Zaitsev''

Separate detachments:
* [[8th Estonian Rifle Corps]] – ''Lieutenant General Lembit Pärn''&lt;ref&gt;8th &amp; 14th Rifle Corps may have been under the 42nd Army, but the source above does not list it as such.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[14th Rifle Corps]] – ''Major General Pavel Artyushenko''
* [[124th Rifle Division]] – ''Colonel Mikhail Papchenko''
* [[30th Guards Rifle Corps]] – ''Lieutenant General Nikolai Simonyak''
* 46th, 260th and 261st Separate Guards Heavy Tank and 1902nd Separate Self-propelled Artillery regiments&lt;ref&gt;Операция "Нева-2" http://www.rkka.ru/memory/baranov/6.htm chapter 6, Baranov, V.I., Armour and people, from a collection "Tankers in the combat for Leningrad"Lenizdat, 1987  (Баранов Виктор Ильич, Броня и люди, из сборника "Танкисты в сражении за Ленинград". Лениздат, 1987)&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[3rd Breakthrough Artillery Corps]] – ''Major General N. N. Zhdanov''
* [[3rd Guards Tank Corps]] – ''Major General I. A. Vovchenko''

At the start of the [[Narva Offensive (July 1944)]], the Leningrad Front deployed 136,830 troops,&lt;ref name=losses&gt;{{cite book|url=http://lib.ru/MEMUARY/1939-1945/KRIWOSHEEW/poteri.txt#w06.htm-_Toc536603390|author= G.F.Krivosheev|title=Soviet casualties and combat losses in the twentieth century|year=1997|location=London|publisher=Greenhill Books}}&lt;/ref&gt; 150 tanks, 2,500 assault guns and 800+ aircraft.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;

===German and Finnish aims===
{{Further|Continuation War}}
The [[Oberkommando des Heeres]] believed it was crucial to stabilize the front on the Narva River. A Soviet breakthrough here would have meant the loss of the northern coast of Estonia and with it loss of control of the Gulf of Finland, giving the Soviet Baltic Fleet access to the Baltic Sea.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; A breakthrough by the fleet would have threatened German control of the entire Baltic Sea and the shipment of [[iron ore]] imports from Sweden. The loss of Narva would have meant fuel derived from the adjacent [[Kohtla-Järve]] [[oil shale]] deposits (32 kilometers west of Narva on the coast) would be denied to the German war machine.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; As Colonel General [[Georg Lindemann]] said in his daily order to the 11th Infantry Division:&lt;ref&gt;Gruppen-Befehl für den Küstenschutz. (Detachment Orders to the Coastal Defence. In German). 9 February 1944. Berlin Archives MA RH24-54/122&lt;/ref&gt;{{quote|We are standing on the border of our native land. Every step backwards will carry the war through the air and water to Germany.}}

As Finland was negotiating with the Soviet Union for peace, the Oberkommando des Heeres paid attention to the Narva front, using every means to convince the [[Chief of Defence (Finland)|Finnish Defence Command]] that their defence was going to hold. The German command informed their Finnish colleagues in detail about the events on the Narva front while a delegation of the Finnish Defence Command visited Narva in spring 1944.&lt;ref name="laar"/&gt; Besides being a narrow corridor well suited for defence, the terrain in the area of Narva was dominated by forests and swamps. Directly behind the Narva River lay the city itself, ideally positioned as a bastion from which defending forces could influence combat to both the north and south of the city along the river valley.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

This position was the northern segment of the German [[Panther Line]] and it was where [[Generalfeldmarschall]] [[Georg von Küchler]] in charge of the Army Group wanted to set up his defence. Hitler initially refused and replaced von Küchler with Generalfeldmarschall [[Walter Model]] as the commander of the Army Group North.&lt;ref name=anabasis/&gt; Model agreed with von Küchler, and as one of Hitler's favourites he also was allowed more freedom. Using this freedom to his advantage, Model managed to fall back and begin establishing a line along the Narva River with a strong bridgehead on the eastern bank in [[Ivangorod]]. This appeased Hitler and followed the German standard operating procedure for defending a river line.&lt;ref name=anabasis/&gt; On 1 February 1944, the High Command of Army Group North tasked the Sponheimer Group (renamed Army Detachment "Narwa" on 23 February) to defend the segment of the Panther Line at the isthmus between the Gulf of Finland and Lake Peipus at all costs.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; Stalin presented Finland with his peace terms on 8 February 1944, after the initial Soviet success. With the tactical victories of "Narwa" from mid-February to April, Finland terminated the negotiations on 18 April 1944.&lt;ref name="EIHC"&gt;{{cite book|year=2006|pages=1191–1237|chapter=Chronology of events in 1939–1945|editor=Toomas Hiio |editor2=Meelis Maripuu |editor3=Indrek Paavle |title=Estonia 1940–1945: Reports of the Estonian International Commission for the Investigation of Crimes Against Humanity|location=Tallinn}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;

===Aims of the Estonian resistance movement===
[[File:RiigiTeataja20091944.jpg|thumb|200px|The 18 September 1944 proclamation of the [[Government of Estonia]] in [[Riigi Teataja]] ([[Government gazette]])]]
{{Further|National Committee of the Republic of Estonia}}
During the course of the [[occupation of Estonia by Nazi Germany]], Estonian expectations of regaining their independence began to diminish. Pursuant to the [[Constitution of Estonia]], formally still in force, Estonian politicians formed an underground National Committee of the Republic of Estonia which convened on 14 February 1944. As [[President of Estonia|President]] [[Konstantin Päts]] was currently imprisoned by the Soviet authorities, the acting head of state according to the Constitution was the former Prime Minister [[Jüri Uluots]]. The German-appointed [[Occupation of Estonia by Nazi Germany#Estonian Self-Administration|Estonian Self-Administration]] had previously attempted several unsuccessful general mobilisation calls, which were illegal under the [[Hague Conventions (1899 and 1907)]] and opposed by Uluots.&lt;ref name=white/&gt;&lt;ref name="mälksoo3"&gt;{{cite book|year=2006|author=Lauri Mälksoo|pages=1095–1106|chapter=The Government of Otto Tief and Attempt to Restore the Independence of Estonia in 1944: A Legal Appraisal.| title=Toomas Hiio, Meelis Maripuu, Indrek Paavle (Eds.). Estonia 1940–1945: Reports of the Estonian International Commission for the Investigation of Crimes Against Humanity|location=Tallinn}}&lt;/ref&gt; In February 1944 when the Leningrad Front reached the vicinity of Narva and the Soviet return became a real threat, Uluots switched his stand on the German draft. In a radio speech on 7 February, Uluots reasoned that armed Estonians could become useful against both Germans and Soviets. He also hinted that Estonian troops on Estonian soil would have: "... a significance much wider than what I could and would be able to disclose here."&lt;ref&gt;Taagepera pp. 70&lt;/ref&gt; Along with other Estonian politicians, Uluots saw resistance against the Soviet Armed Forces as a means of preventing the restoration of Soviet power and restoring Estonia's independence once the war was over.&lt;ref name=vm&gt;{{cite web |url=http://web-test.vm.ee/estonia/kat_509/pea_172/4738.html |publisher=Estonian Ministry of Foreign Affairs |title=Year 1944 in Estonian History |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090414115122/http://web-test.vm.ee/estonia/kat_509/pea_172/4738.html |archivedate=14 April 2009 |df=dmy }}&lt;/ref&gt; The conscription call was received with popular support and the mobilisation brought together 38,000 men&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title=Resistance!: Occupied Europe and Its Defiance of Hitler |last=Lande |first=D. A. |year=2000 |publisher=MBI |location= |isbn=978-0-7603-0745-8 |url=https://archive.org/details/resistanceoccupi00land/page/200 |page=[https://archive.org/details/resistanceoccupi00land/page/200 200] }}&lt;/ref&gt; who were formed into seven [[border guard]] regiments and the fictitiously named&lt;ref name=florence/&gt; [[20th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Estonian)|20th Estonian SS-Volunteer Division]],&lt;ref name=axishistory&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.axishistory.com/index.php?id=1931|publisher=Axis History Factbook|title=20. Waffen-Grenadier-Division der SS (estnische Nr. 1)}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=hiio2&gt;{{cite book|author1=Toomas Hiio  |author2=Peeter Kaasik |lastauthoramp=yes |year=2006|pages=927–968|chapter=Estonian units in the Waffen-SS|editor1=Toomas Hiio |editor2=Meelis Maripuu |editor3=Indrek Paavle |title=Estonia 1940–1945: Reports of the [[Estonian International Commission for the Investigation of Crimes Against Humanity]]|location=Tallinn}}&lt;/ref&gt; commonly referred to among the German Armed Forces as the Estonian Division.&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt; Combined with the [[Finnish Infantry Regiment 200]] (voluntary Estonians in the Finnish army) and the conscripts within the Waffen SS, a total of 70,000 Estonian troops were under Nazi German arms in 1944.&lt;ref name= white/&gt;

===Formation of Army Detachment "Narwa"===
In February 1944, the L and LIV Army Corps along with the [[III (Germanic) SS Panzer Corps]] were on the left flank of the 18th Army as they retreated to Narva. On 4 February, the Sponheimer Group was released from the 18th Army and subordinated directly to the Army Group North. In support of the forces already in place, Hitler ordered reinforcements. The [[Panzer-Grenadier-Division Feldherrnhalle]], with over 10,000 troops and their equipment, was airlifted from [[Belorussia]] into Estonia via the airfield at [[Tartu]] on 1 February. A week later, the 5th Battalion of the Panzergrenadier [[Großdeutschland Division]] arrived at the front. The Grenadier Regiment Gnesen (an ad hoc regiment formed from replacement army units in Poland) was sent from Germany and arrived on 11 February. Three days later, the 214th Infantry Division was transferred from Norway. Over the next two weeks various units were added to the group, including the [[11 SS|11th SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Division "Nordland"]], several divisions of the Wehrmacht, the Estonian Division and local Estonian border guard and [[Estonian Auxiliary Police]] battalions. Infantry General [[Otto Sponheimer]] was replaced by General [[Johannes Frießner]] and the Sponheimer Group was renamed Army Detachment "Narwa" on 23 February. The Army Group North ordered the deployment of "Narwa" on 22 February in the following positions: III SS Panzer Corps deployed to Narva, Ivangorod Bridgehead on the east bank of the river and north of Narva; the XXXXIII Army Corps against the Krivasoo Bridgehead south of the city; and the XXVI Army Corps to the sector between the Krivasoo Bridgehead and Lake Peipus. As of 1 March 1944, there were a total of 123,541 personnel subordinated to the Army Group in the following order of battle:&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;
* [[III SS (Germanic) Panzer Corps]] – SS-Obergruppenführer [[Felix Steiner]]
** [[11th SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Division Nordland|11th SS Panzergrenadier Division "Nordland"]]
** [[23rd SS Volunteer Panzer Grenadier Division Nederland|4th SS Panzergrenadier Brigade "Nederland"]]
** [[20th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Estonian)]]
* [[XXVI Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXVI Army Corps]] – General [[Anton Grasser]]
** [[11th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|11th Infantry Division]]
** [[58th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|58th Infantry Division]]
** [[214th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|214th Infantry Division]]
** 225th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)
** 3rd Estonian Border Guard Regiment (as of 15 April)
* [[XXXXIII Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXXXIII Army Corps]] – General der Infanterie [[Karl von Oven]]
** [[61st Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|61st Infantry Division]]
** [[170th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|170th Infantry Division]]
** [[227th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|227th Infantry Division]]
** [[Feldherrnhalle Panzergrenadier Division]]
** Gnesen Grenadier Regiment

Separate units:
* Eastern sector, coastal defence (the staff of the 2nd Anti-Aircraft Division as the HQ) – ''Lieutenant General [[Alfons Luczny]]''
** [[Estonian Regiment "Reval"]]
** 3 Estonian police battalions
** 2 Estonian eastern battalions

Other military units:
* Artillery Command No. 113
* High Pioneer Command No. 32
* [[502nd Heavy Tank Battalion (Germany)|502nd Heavy Tank Battalion]]
* 752nd Anti-Tank Battalion
* 540th Special Infantry (Training) Battalion

In the summer of 1944, the Panzergrenadier Division Feldherrnhalle and seven infantry divisions were removed from the Narva Front,&lt;ref name=laar/&gt; leaving 22,250 troops at the location.&lt;ref name=newton&gt;{{cite book|author=Steven H. Newton|title=Retreat from Leningrad: Army Group North, 1944/1945|publisher=Schiffer Books|location=Atglen, Philadelphia|year=1995|isbn=0-88740-806-0}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Combat activity==
[[File:Narva Feb10 Apr23 44.jpg|thumb|300px|Soviet map of the beginning of the Estonian Operation, February – April 1944]]
{{Further|Battle for Narva Bridgehead}}

===Formation of bridgeheads===
{{Main|Kingisepp–Gdov Offensive}}
Launching the Kingisepp–Gdov Offensive on 1 February, the Soviet 2nd Shock Army's 109th Rifle Corps captured the town of [[Kingisepp]] on the first day.&lt;ref name=glantz/&gt; The German 18th Army was forced into new positions on the eastern bank of the Narva River.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; Forward units of the 2nd Shock Army crossed the river and established several bridgeheads on the west bank to the north and south of the city of Narva on 2 February. The 2nd Shock Army expanded the bridgehead in the Krivasoo Swamp south of Narva five days later, temporarily cutting the Narva–Tallinn Railway behind the III SS Panzer Corps. Govorov was unable to encircle the smaller German Army Group, which called in reinforcements. These came mostly from the newly mobilised Estonians, motivated to resist the looming Soviet return. At the same time, the Soviet 108th Rifle Corps landed units across Lake Peipus 120 kilometres south of Narva and established a bridgehead around the village of Meerapalu. By a coincidence, the I.Battalion, SS Volunteer Grenadier Regiment 45 (1st Estonian), which was headed for Narva, reached the same area. A battalion of the 44th Infantry Regiment (consisting of personnel from East Prussia), the I.Battalion, 1st Estonian and an air squadron destroyed the Soviet bridgehead on 15–16 February. The Mereküla Landing Operation was conducted as the 517-strong 260th Independent Naval Infantry Brigade landed at the coastal borough of Mereküla behind the Sponheimer Group lines. However, the unit was almost completely destroyed.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

===Narva Offensives, 15–28 February and 1–4 March===
{{Main|Narva Offensive (15–28 February 1944) |Narva Offensive (1–4 March 1944)}}
The Soviet 30th Guards Rifle Corps and the 124th Rifle Corps launched a new Narva Offensive on 15 February.&lt;ref name=glantz2/&gt; The resistance by units of the Sponheimer Group exhausted the Soviet army, which halted its offensive. Both sides used the pause for [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead#Reinforcements|bringing in additional forces]]. The fresh SS Volunteer Grenadier Regiments 45 and 46 (1st and 2nd Estonian) accompanied by units of the "Nordland" Division [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead#Destruction of Soviet bridgeheads north of Narva|destroyed the Soviet bridgeheads]] north of Narva by 6 March. The newly arrived 59th Army attacked westwards from the Krivasoo Swamp and encircled the strong points of the 214th Infantry Division and Estonian [[658th Eastern Battalion|658th]] and 659th Eastern Battalions. The resistance of the encircled units gave the German command time to move in all available forces and to stop the 59th Army units' advance.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

===6–24 March===
[[File:Narvafronten, 1944 - Narvafront038.jpg|left|thumb|300px|Narva after artillery and air raids, 1944]]
The Soviet air force conducted an air raid, leveling the historic town of Narva on 6 March. An air and artillery shock of 100,000 shells and grenades at the "Nordland" and "Nederland" detachments in Ivangorod prepared the way for the 30th Guards Rifle Division's attack on 8 March. Simultaneous pitched battles took place north of the town, where the 14th Rifle Corps supported by the artillery of the [[8th Estonian Rifle Corps]] attempted to re-establish a bridgehead. Regiments of the Estonian SS Division repulsed the attacks, causing great Soviet losses.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

Soviet [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead#Soviet air assaults at civilians|air assaults against civilians]] in Estonian towns were a part of the offensive, aimed at forcing the Estonians away from supporting the German side. The Soviet [[Long Range Aviation]] branch [[Bombing of Tallinn in World War II|assaulted the Estonian capital]] of Tallinn on the night of 8–9 March. Approximately 40% of the housing was destroyed in the city; 25,000 people were left homeless and 500 civilians were killed. The result of the air raid was the opposite of what the Soviets intended, as people felt disgusted by the [[Soviet war crimes|Soviet atrocities]]; more men answered the German conscription call.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

The Soviet tank [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead#End of offensive|attack at Auvere Station]] was stopped by a squadron of the [[502nd Heavy Tank Battalion (Germany)|502nd Heavy Tank Battalion]] on 17 March. The [[Narva Offensive (18–24 March 1944)|ensuing offensive]] continued for another week&lt;ref name=glantz2/&gt; until the Soviet forces had suffered enough casualties to switch over to a defensive stance. This enabled "Narwa" to [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead#Strachwitz counteroffensive|take the initiative]].&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

===Strachwitz offensive===
The [[Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz von Gross-Zauche und Camminetz|Strachwitz]] Battle Group [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead#Strachwitz offensive|annihilated the Soviet]] 8th Army shock troop wedge at the western end of the Krivasoo Bridgehead on 26 March. The German battle group destroyed the eastern tip of the bridgehead on 6 April. ''Generalmajor'' [[Hyacinth Graf Strachwitz von Groß-Zauche und Camminetz]], inspired by the success, tried to eliminate the whole bridgehead but was unable to proceed due to the spring thaw that had rendered the swamp impassable for the [[Tiger I]] tanks.&lt;ref name=carius&gt;{{cite book|title=Tigers in the Mud: The Combat Career of German Panzer Commander Otto Carius|year= 2004|publisher=Stackpole Books|author=Otto Carius|authorlink=Otto Carius|isbn=0-8117-2911-7}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of April, the parties had mutually exhausted their strengths. [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead#Narva Offensives, May and June|Relative calm]] settled on the front until late July 1944.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

===The Soviets capture Narva===
{{Main|Narva Offensive (July 1944)}}
The Soviet [[Operation Bagration|breakthrough in Belorussia]] and [[Vyborg–Petrozavodsk Offensive|Karelian Offensive]] forced the Army Group North to withdraw a large portion of their troops from Narva to the central part of the Eastern Front and to Finland. As there were insufficient forces for the defence of the former front line at Narva in July, the German army detachment began preparations for withdrawal to the Tannenberg defence line in the Sinimäed Hills 16 kilometres from Narva. The commanders of the Leningrad Front were unaware of the preparations; they designed a new Narva Offensive. Shock troops from the Finnish front were concentrated near the town, giving the Leningrad Front a 4:1 superiority both in manpower and equipment. Before the German forces had implemented their plan, the Soviet 8th Army launched their offensive; the [[Battle of Auvere]] was the result. The I.Battalion, 1st Estonian and the 44th Infantry Regiment repulsed the attack, inflicting heavy losses on the 8th Army. The "Nordland" and "Nederland" detachments in [[Ivangorod]] left their positions quietly during the night before 25 July. The evacuation was carried out according to the German plans until the 2nd Shock Army resumed the offensive in the morning. Supported by 280,000 shells and grenades from 1360 assault guns, the army crossed the river north of the town. The II.Battalion, 1st Estonian Regiment kept the Soviet shock Army from capturing the highway behind the retreating troops. The defensive operation led to the destruction of the SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Regiment 48 "General Seyffardt" due to tactical errors. The Soviet forces captured Narva on 26 July.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

===Tannenberg Line===
{{Main|Battle of Tannenberg Line}}
[[File:Tannenberg1944.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Battle of Tannenberg Line]], 26–29 July 1944]]
The Soviet vanguard 201st and 256th Rifle Divisions [[Battle of Tannenberg Line#July 26|attacked the Tannenberg Line]] and captured part of the Orphanage Hill, the easternmost of the area. The Anti-Tank Company, SS Panzergrenadier Regiment 24 "Danmark" returned the hill to the hands of the "Narwa" the following night. The III (Germanic) SS Panzer Corps repulsed subsequent [[Battle of Tannenberg Line#July 27|Soviet attempts]] to capture the hills by tanks on the following day. The SS Reconnaissance Battalion 11 and the I.Battalion, Waffen Grenadier Regiment 47 (3rd Estonian) launched a counterattack during the night before 28 July. The assault collapsed under the Soviet tank fire which destroyed the Estonian battalion. In a pitched battle carried over to the next day without a break in the fighting, the two Soviet armies forced "Narwa" into new positions at the Grenadier Hill, the central one.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

The climax of the Battle of Tannenberg Line was the Soviet attack of 29 July. The shock units suppressed the German resistance on the Orphanage Hill, while the Soviet main forces suffered heavy casualties in the subsequent assault at the Grenadier Hill. The Soviet tanks encircled it and the Tower Hill, the westernmost one. Steiner, the commander of the III SS Panzer Corps, sent out the remaining seven tanks, which hit the surprised Soviet armour and forced them back. This enabled an improvised battle group led by Hauptsturmführer [[Paul Maitla]] to launch a counterattack which recaptured the Grenadier Hill. Of the 136,830 Soviets initiating the offensive on 25 July, a few thousand had remained fit for combat by 1 August. The Soviet tank regiments had been demolished.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

With swift reinforcements, the two Soviet armies continued their attacks. The Stavka demanded the destruction of the "Narwa" and the capture of [[Rakvere]] by 7 August. The 2nd Shock Army was back to 20,000 troops by 2 August while numerous attempts using unchanged tactics failed to break the multinational defence of the "Narwa". Leonid Govorov, the commander of the Leningrad Front terminated the offensive on 10 August.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

==Casualties==
During the Soviet era, the losses in the battle of Narva were not released by the Soviets.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt; In recent years, Russian authors have published some figures&lt;ref name=desjat/&gt;&lt;ref name=rodin&gt;{{Cite journal|author=V. Rodin|date=5 October 2005|title=Na vysotah Sinimyae: kak eto bylo na samom dele. (On the Heights of Sinimäed: How It Actually Was)|publisher= Vesti|language=Russian}}&lt;/ref&gt; but not for the whole course of the battles.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt; The number of Soviet casualties can only be estimated indirectly.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;

The Army Detachment "Narwa" lost 23,963 personnel as dead, wounded and missing in action in February 1944.&lt;ref name="newton"/&gt; During the following months through to 30 July 1944, an additional 34,159 German personnel were lost, 5,748 of them dead and 1,179 missing in action.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; The total German casualties during the [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead|initial phase of the campaign]] was approximately 58,000 men, 12,000 of them dead or missing in action. From 24 July to 10 August 1944, the German forces buried 1709 men in Estonia.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Unpublished data by the [[German War Graves Commission]]&lt;/ref&gt; Adding the troops missing in action, the number of dead in the period is estimated at approximately 2,500. Accounting the standard ratio of 1/4 of the wounded as irrecoverable losses, the number of German casualties in the later period of the battle was approximately 10,000. The total German casualties during the Battle of Narva is estimated at 14,000 dead or missing and 54,000 wounded or sick.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;

==Aftermath==
===Baltic Offensive===
{{Further|Baltic Offensive (1944)}}
On 1 September, Finland announced the cessation of military cooperation with Germany to sign an [[Continuation War#Armistice and aftermath|armistice with the Soviet Union]].&lt;ref name="EIHC"/&gt; On 4 September, Finland opened access for the Soviets to Finnish waters. With the Soviet [[Shyaulyay Offensive|offensive at Riga]] threatening to complete their encirclement, the Army Group North started preparations for the withdrawal of troops from Estonia in an [[Tallinn Offensive|operation codenamed Aster]]. The possible transportation corridors were thoroughly prepared using maps at headquarters.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Felix Steiner (1980). Die Freiwilligen der Waffen-SS: Idee und Opfergang (Volunteers of Armed SS. In German). Schütz, Oldendorf, Preuss&lt;/ref&gt; On 17 September 1944, a naval force under Vice-Admiral [[Theodor Burchardi]] began evacuating elements of the German formations and Estonian civilians. Within six days, around 50,000 troops and 1,000 prisoners had been removed.&lt;ref name=mitchamp149&gt;Mitcham, S. German Defeat in the East 1944 – 45, Stackpole, 2007, p.149&lt;/ref&gt; The elements of the 18th Army in Estonia were ordered to withdraw into Latvia.

The Soviet [[1st Baltic Front|1st]], [[2nd Baltic Front|2nd]] and 3rd Baltic Fronts launched their Baltic Offensive on 14 September. The operation was aimed at cutting off the Army Group North in Estonia. After much argument, Adolf Hitler agreed to allow the total evacuation of the troops in mainland Estonia. The 2nd Shock Army launched its Tallinn Offensive on 17 September from the [[Tartu Offensive|Emajõgi River Front]] in South Estonia. At midnight on 18 September, the Army Detachment "Narwa" left its positions in the Tannenberg Line. The 8th Army reconnaissance reported the evacuation five hours after it had been completed and the Soviets started to chase the troops towards Estonian harbours and the Latvian border. The III SS Panzer Corps reached Pärnu by 20 September, while the II SS Corps retreated southwards to form the 18th Army's rearguard.&lt;ref name="mitchamp149"/&gt; The Soviet armies advanced to take Tallinn on 22 September. The Soviets had demolished the harbour at [[Haapsalu]] by 24 September. The German Panzer Corps evacuated [[Vormsi]] Island just off the coast on the following day,&lt;ref name=naval/&gt; successfully completing the evacuation of mainland Estonia with only minor casualties.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; The 8th Army went on to take the remaining [[West Estonian archipelago]] in the [[Moonsund Landing Operation]]. The Baltic Offensive resulted in the expulsion of the German forces from Estonia, a large part of Latvia, and [[Lithuania]].

During the withdrawal from Estonia, the German command released thousands of native Estonian conscripts from military service. The Soviet command began conscripting Baltic natives as areas were brought under Soviet control.&lt;ref name=Muriev&gt;D. Muriyev, ''Preparations, Conduct of 1944 Baltic Operation Described'', ''Military History Journal'' (USSR Report, Military affairs), 1984–9, page. 27&lt;/ref&gt; While some ended up serving on both sides, thousands joined the [[Forest Brothers]] partisan detachments to avoid conscription.

Army Group North land lines of communication were permanently severed from [[Army Group Centre]] and it was relegated to the [[Courland Pocket]], an occupied Baltic seashore area in Latvia. On 25 January, Adolf Hitler renamed Army Group North the "Courland", implicitly realising that there was no possibility of restoring a new land corridor between Courland and East Prussia.&lt;ref&gt;On 25 January, Hitler renamed three army groups: the North became the Courland; the Centre became the North and the [[Army Group A|A]] became Army Group Centre&lt;/ref&gt; The Red Army commenced the encirclement and reduction of the pocket, enabling the Soviets to focus on operations towards East Prussia. The [[Army Group Courland]] retained a possibility of being a major threat. Operations by the Red Army against the Courland Pocket continued until the surrender of Army Group Courland on 9 May 1945, when close to 200,000 Germans were taken prisoner there.

===Outcome for Finland===
{{Main|Continuation War#Overtures for peace}}
The lengthy German defence during the Battle of Narva denied the Soviets the use of Estonia as a favorable base for amphibious invasions and air attacks against [[Helsinki]] and other Finnish cities. Stavka's hopes of assaulting Finland from Estonia and forcing it into capitulation were diminished. Finnish [[Chief of Defence (Finland)|Chief of Defence]] [[Carl Gustav Emil Mannerheim]] repeatedly reminded the German side that in the event their troops in Estonia retreated, Finland would be forced to make peace even on extremely unfavourable terms. Thus, the prolonged Battle of Narva helped Finland avoid a Soviet occupation, sustained its capacity for resistance and enabled them to enter negotiations for the [[Moscow Armistice]] on their own terms.&lt;ref name=paulman&gt;{{cite book|language=Russian|author =F.I.Paulman|title=Ot Narvy do Syrve (From Narva to Sõrve)|publisher=Eesti Raamat|location=Tallinn|year=1980|pages=7–119|chapter=Nachalo osvobozhdeniya Sovetskoy Estoniy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=desjat&gt;{{cite book|author=В.Бешанов|title=Десять сталинских ударов (Ten Shocks of Stalin)|year=2004|publisher=Харвест, Minsk}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=glantz/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;&lt;ref name="newton" /&gt;

===Attempt to restore Estonian Government===
{{Main|National Committee of the Republic of Estonia}}
The lengthy German defence prevented a swift Soviet breakthrough into Estonia and gave the underground National Committee of the Republic of Estonia enough time to attempt to re-establish Estonian independence. On 1 August 1944, the national committee pronounced itself Estonia's highest authority and on 18 September 1944, acting head of state Uluots appointed a new government led by [[Otto Tief]]. Over the radio in English, the government declared its neutrality in the war. The government issued two editions of the [[Riigi Teataja]] (State Gazette) but did not have time to distribute them. On 21 September, the national forces seized the government buildings in [[Toompea]], Tallinn and ordered the German forces to leave.&lt;ref name=vm2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://web-test.vm.ee/estonia/pea_172/kat_509/7786.html|publisher=Estonian Ministry of Foreign Affairs|title=The Otto Tief government and the fall of Tallinn|year=2006|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090821104518/http://web-test.vm.ee/estonia/pea_172/kat_509/7786.html|archivedate=21 August 2009|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?ei=cm01R5fMF5SysgP38dmFAg&amp;id=V4siAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=%22Otto+Tief+%22&amp;q=Otto+Tief&amp;pgis=1#search Estonia. Sept.21] Bulletin of International News by Royal Institute of International Affairs Information Dept.&lt;/ref&gt; The flag of Estonia was hoisted at the tower of [[Pikk Hermann]], to be removed by the Soviets four days later. The [[Estonian Government in Exile]] served to carry the continuity of the Estonian state forward until 1992, when it handed its credentials over to the incoming President, [[Lennart Meri]].

===Civilian refugees===
The delay of the Soviet advance allowed over 25,000 Estonians and 3,700 Swedes to flee to neutral Sweden and 6,000 Estonians to Finland. Thousands of refugees died on boats and ships sunk in the Baltic Sea.&lt;ref name=white&gt;{{cite book|author=Estonian State Commission on Examination of Policies of Repression|url=http://www.just.ee/orb.aw/class=file/action=preview/id=12709/TheWhiteBook.pdf|publisher=Estonian Encyclopedia Publishers|title=The White Book: Losses inflicted on the Estonian nation by occupation regimes. 1940–1991|year=2005|chapter=Human Losses|page=32|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130114130824/http://www.just.ee/orb.aw/class%3Dfile/action%3Dpreview/id%3D12709/TheWhiteBook.pdf|archivedate=14 January 2013|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; In September, 90,000 soldiers and 85,000 Estonian, Finnish and German refugees and Soviet prisoners of war were evacuated to Germany.&lt;ref name=naval/&gt; The sole German cost of this evacuation was the loss of a steamboat. More German naval evacuations followed from Estonian ports,&lt;ref name=naval&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.feldgrau.com/baltsea.html|title=Naval War in the Baltic Sea 1941–1945|author=Arvo L. Vercamer|publisher=feldgrau.com}}&lt;/ref&gt; where up to 1,200 people were drowned in Soviet attacks.&lt;ref name=white/&gt;

===Soviet reoccupation===
{{Main|Occupation of the Baltic states|Estonian Soviet Socialist Republic}}
Soviet rule of Estonia was re-established by force, and [[Sovietization of the Baltic states#World War II 1944 re-occupation|sovietisation]] followed, mostly carried out in 1944–1950. The forced [[Kolkhoz|collectivisation of agriculture]] began in 1947 and was completed after the [[Operation Priboi|deportation of 22,500 Estonians in March 1949]]. All private farms were confiscated and farmers were made to join the collective farms. Besides the armed resistance of the [[Forest Brothers]], a number of underground nationalist schoolchildren groups were active. Most of their members were sentenced to long terms of imprisonment. The punitive actions decreased rapidly after Stalin's death in 1953; from 1956 to 1958, many of the deportees and political prisoners were allowed to return to Estonia. Political arrests and numerous other [[crimes against humanity]] were committed throughout the occupation period until the late 1980s. Nevertheless, the attempt to integrate Estonian society into the Soviet system failed. Although the armed resistance was defeated, the population remained anti-Soviet. This helped the Estonians to organise a [[Singing revolution|new resistance movement]] in the late 1980s, regain their independence in 1991, and then rapidly develop a modern society.&lt;ref&gt;"Phase III: The Soviet Occupation of Estonia from 1944". ''In: Estonia since 1944: Reports of the [[Estonian International Commission for the Investigation of Crimes Against Humanity]]'', pp. VII–XXVI. Tallinn, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;

==References and notes==
===Footnotes===
{{Reflist|group=nb}}

===References===
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book |title=Hitler's Army: the evolution and structure of German forces |last=McTaggart |first=Pat |date=2003 |editor-last=Command Magazine |publisher=Combined Books |location=Cambridge, MA |isbn=978-0306812606 |pages=287–308 |chapter=The Battle of Narva, 1944 |chapterurl=https://books.google.com/books?id=K5ptwGy4i2sC&amp;pg=PA287&amp;dq |url=https://books.google.com/?id=K5ptwGy4i2sC&amp;pg }}
* {{Cite book |title=Historical Dictionary of Estonia |last=Miljan |first=Toivo |year=2004 |publisher=Scarecrow Press |location= |isbn=978-0-8108-4904-4 |pages= |url=https://books.google.com/?id=XKWRct15XfkC&amp;dq }}

{{Good article}}

{{World War II}}

{{authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle of Narva}}
[[Category:Battle of Narva (1944)| ]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:Reichskommissariat Ostland]]
[[Category:Estonian Soviet Socialist Republic]]
[[Category:1944 in Estonia]]</text><sha1>4u03mtldjnyzr5iln14jutcnq32eb7k</sha1></revision></page>