<page><title>Narva Offensive (1–4 March 1944)</title><ns>0</ns><id>23703690</id><revision><id>950702560</id><parentid>927887257</parentid><timestamp>2020-04-13T12:13:19Z</timestamp><contributor><username>InternetArchiveBot</username><id>27015025</id></contributor><comment>Rescuing 2 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="16996" xml:space="preserve">{{for|the main article|Battle of Narva (1944)}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict   = Narva Offensive (1–4 March 1944)
| image      = Narva Feb10 Apr23 44.jpg
| image_size = 
| caption    = Soviet map of the beginning of Estonian Operation (February – April 1944)
| partof     = [[Eastern Front (World War II)]]
| place      = [[Narva]], [[Estonia]]
| date       = 1–4 March 1944
| result     = German defensive victory
| combatant1  ={{flag|Nazi Germany|name=Germany}}
| combatant2  ={{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1  ={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Johannes Frießner]]
| commander2  ={{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Leonid A. Govorov]]
| strength1   = 123,541&lt;ref name=hiio&gt;{{cite book|author=Toomas Hiio|year=2006|pages=1035–1094|chapter=Combat in Estonia in 1944|editor1=Toomas Hiio |editor2=Meelis Maripuu |editor3=Indrek Paavle |title=Estonia 1940–1945: Reports of the [[Estonian International Commission for the Investigation of Crimes Against Humanity]]|location=Tallinn}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 200,000&lt;ref name=laar&gt;{{cite book|author=Mart Laar|title=Sinimäed 1944: II maailmasõja lahingud Kirde-Eestis (Sinimäed Hills 1944: Battles of World War II in Northeast Estonia)|publisher= Tallinn: Varrak|year= 2006|language=Estonian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;100 armoured vehicles&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|language=Russian|author =F.I.Paulman|title=Ot Narvy do Syrve (From Narva to Sõrve)|publisher=Eesti Raamat|location=Tallinn|year=1980|pages=7–119|chapter=Nachalo osvobozhdeniya Sovetskoy Estoniy}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;2,500 artillery pieces&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;800 aircraft&lt;ref name="hiio"/&gt;
| casualties1 = thousands&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;&lt;ref name=narwa/&gt;
| casualties2 = Many more than the Germans&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Leningrad and Baltics 1941-1944}}{{Campaignbox Estonia 1944}}
}}

The '''Narva Offensive (1–4 March 1944)''' ([[Estonian language|Estonian]]: ''Putki lahing'') was an [[military operation|operation]] conducted by the Soviet [[Leningrad Front]]. It was aimed at the conquest of the [[Ida-Viru|Narva Isthmus]] from the German [[Battle of Narva (1944)#Formation of Army Detachment "Narwa"|army detachment "Narwa"]].&lt;ref name=glantz2&gt;{{cite book|author=[[David M. Glantz]]|location=Glemson, South Carolina|url=http://www.strom.clemson.edu/publications/sg-war41-45.pdf|publisher=Strom Thurmond Institute of Government and Public Affairs, Clemson University|year=2001|title=The Soviet-German War 1941-1945: Myths and Realities|access-date=2009-07-22|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110709141048/http://www.strom.clemson.edu/publications/sg-war41-45.pdf|archive-date=2011-07-09|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; At the time of the operation, [[Joseph Stalin]], the supreme commander of the Soviet Armed Forces, was personally interested in taking Estonia, viewing it as a precondition to forcing Finland out of the war.

The Soviet 59th Army attacked westwards from the Krivasoo Bridgehead south of the city of [[Narva]] and encircled the strong-points of the 214th Infantry Division and the Estonian [[658th Eastern Battalion|658th]] and 659th [[Ostlegionen#Ostbataillone|East Battalions]]. The resistance of the encircled units gave time for the command of the "Narwa" to move in all available forces and stop the Soviet advance. To the north of Narva, the fresh SS 45th and 46th ([[20th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Estonian)|1st and 2nd Estonian]]) Volunteer Grenadier Regiments accompanied by units of the [[11th SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Division Nordland|11th SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Division "Nordland"]] counter-attacked and reduced the Soviet bridgehead.

==Prelude==

===Preceding combat===
Units of the [[20th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Estonian)|20th Estonian SS Volunteer Division]] were tasked with destroying the Siivertsi bridgehead, which was defended by the 1,100-strong 378th Rifle Division equipped with 20 assault guns. The attack was commanded by Standartenführer Paul Vent.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; The SS 45th (1st Estonian) Waffen Grenadier Regiment made a direct assault on the bridgehead on [[Narva Offensive (15–28 February 1944)|29 February]]. Simultaneously, the SS 46th (2nd Estonian) Waffen Grenadier Regiment, in their attempt to attack from the left flank, ran into the Soviet fortifications and a minefield, which they [[Narva Offensive (15–28 February 1944)|crossed]].

===Preparations and goals===
The operational goals of the Soviet offensive was to break through to the Vasknarva-[[Jõhvi]] Road and the Narva-[[Tallinn]] road and to capture the village of Jõhvi and the town of [[Rakvere]].&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

The setbacks in the [[Narva Offensive (15–28 February 1944)]] came as an unpleasant surprise to the leadership of the Leningrad Front, blaming it on the arrival of the Estonian Division.&lt;ref name=rodin&gt;{{Cite journal|author=V. Rodin|date=October 5, 2005|title=Na vysotah Sinimyae: kak eto bylo na samom dele. (On the Heights of Sinimäed: How It Actually Was)|publisher= Vesti|language=Russian}}&lt;/ref&gt; Since the beginning of January, the Leningrad Front had lost 227,440 troops killed, wounded or missing in action, which constituted more than half of the troops who participated in the [[Leningrad-Novgorod Strategic Offensive]]. Both sides rushed reinforcements into the area.&lt;ref name=lentsman&gt;{{cite book|author=L. Lentsman|year=1977|title= Eesti rahvas Suures Isamaasõjas (Estonian Nation in Great Patriotic War)|publisher= Eesti Raamat|location= Tallinn|language= Estonian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2&gt;{{cite book |title=Estonia in World War II |last=Laar |first=Mart |year=2005 |publisher=Grenader |authorlink=Mart Laar|location=Tallinn}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 59th Army was brought to Narva and the [[8th Estonian Rifle Corps]] placed under the command of the Leningrad Front.

==Deployments==
[[File:Narva area.png|thumb|300px|Situation around Narva, March 1944.]]

===German===
Army Group North ordered the deployment of the [[Battle of Narva (1944)#Formation of Army Detachment "Narwa"|army detachment "Narwa"]] on 22 February in the following positions: III SS Panzer Corps deployed to the north of Narva and the bridgehead on the east bank of the river, the XXXXIII Army Corps against the Krivasoo Bridgehead and the XXVI Army Corps to the sector between the bridgehead and Lake Peipus. As of 1 March 1944, there were a total of 123,541 personnel subordinated to the army group in the following order of battle:&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;
*XXVI Army Corps - ''[[General of the Infantry (Germany)|General der Infanterie]] Anton Grasser''
*XXXXIII Army Corps - ''General der Infanterie [[Karl von Oven]]''
*[[III SS (Germanic) Panzer Corps]] - ''SS-Obergruppenführer [[Felix Steiner|Felix Martin Julius Steiner]]''

Separate units:
*Eastern Sector, Coastal Defence (Staff of 2nd Anti-Aircraft Division as HQ) - ''Lieutenant General [[Alfons Luczny]]''
**[[Estonian Regiment "Reval"]]
**3 [[Estonian Police]] battalions
**[[658th Eastern Battalion|658th]] and 659th Estonian Eastern Battalions

Other military units:
*Artillery Command No. 113
*High Pioneer Command No. 32
*[[502nd Heavy Tank Battalion (Germany)|502nd Heavy Tank Battalion]]
*752nd Anti-Tank Battalion
*540th Special Infantry (Training) Battalion

===Soviet===
Three Soviet armies were deployed during the course of the operation. The 2nd Shock Army was placed in the sector against the German bridgehead and north to the Gulf of Finland; the 59th Army south of the city of Narva and the [[8th Army (Soviet Army)|8th Army]] south of the 59th Army along the 50&amp;nbsp;km long Narva river stretching down to Lake Peipus. Detailed information on the size of the Soviet forces at the Narva front during the Winter-Spring campaign has not been published by any sources. It is impossible to give an overview on the Soviet strength until the Red Army archival information is made available to non-Russian investigators or published.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; Estonian historian Hannes Walter has estimated the number of Soviet troops at 205,000&lt;ref name=walter&gt;{{cite web|url=http://historicaltextarchive.com/sections.php?op=viewarticle&amp;artid=383|author=Hannes Walter|publisher=Historical Text Archive|location=Mississippi|title=Estonia in World War II|url-status=bot: unknown|archiveurl=https://archive.is/20120523231619/http://historicaltextarchive.com/sections.php?op=viewarticle&amp;artid=383|archivedate=2012-05-23}}&lt;/ref&gt; which is in accordance with the number of divisions multiplied by the assumed sizes of the divisions presented by the Estonian historian [[Mart Laar]], accounting for roughly 200,000 troops.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt; The order of battle of the Leningrad Front as of 1 March 1944, is:&lt;ref&gt;[http://tashv.nm.ru/BoevojSostavSA/1944/19440301.html Боевой состав Советской Армии на 1 марта 1944 г.] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20080514124834/http://tashv.nm.ru/BoevojSostavSA/1944/19440301.html |date=2008-05-14 }} (Order of battle of the Soviet Army on 1 March 1944)&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[2nd Shock Army]] - ''Lieutenant General Ivan Fedyuninski''
**[[43rd Rifle Corps]] - ''Major General Anatoli Andreyev''
**[[109th Rifle Corps]] - ''Major General Ivan Alferov''
**[[124th Rifle Corps]] - ''Major General Voldemar Damberg''
*[[8th Army (Soviet Union)|8th Army]] - ''Lieutenant General [[Filipp Starikov]]''
**[[6th Rifle Corps]] - ''Major General Semyon Mikulski''
**[[112th Rifle Corps]] - ''Major General Filipp Solovev''
**[[115th Rifle Corps]] - (HQ with no troops assigned by 1 Apr 1944)
*[[59th Army (Soviet Union)|59th Army]] - ''Lieutenant General Ivan Korvnikov''
**[[117th Rifle Corps]] - ''Major General Vasili Trubachev''
**[[122nd Rifle Corps]] - ''Major General Panteleimon Zaitsev''

Separate detachments:
*[[8th Estonian Rifle Corps]] - ''Lieutenant General Lembit Pärn''&lt;ref&gt;8th and 14th Rifle Corps may have been under 42nd Army, but the source above does not list them as such.&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[14th Rifle Corps]] - ''Major General Pavel Artyushenko''
*[[124th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|124th Rifle Division]] - ''Colonel Papchenko Danilovich''
*[[30th Guards Rifle Corps]] - ''Lieutenant General Nikolai Simonyak''
*46th, 260th and 261st Separate Guards Heavy Tank and 1902nd Separate Self-propelled Artillery regiments&lt;ref&gt;Операция "Нева-2" http://www.rkka.ru/memory/baranov/6.htm chapter 6, Baranov, V.I., Armour and people, from a collection "Tankers in the combat for Leningrad"Lenizdat, 1987 (Баранов Виктор Ильич, Броня и люди, из сборника "Танкисты в сражении за Ленинград". Лениздат, 1987)&lt;/ref&gt;
*[[3rd Breakthrough Artillery Corps]] - ''Major General N. N. Zhdanov''
*[[3rd Guards Tank Corps]] - ''Major General I. A. Vovchenko''

==Combat activity==

===Southern wing===
On 1 March, units of the newly arrived Soviet 59th Army, supported by the fire of 2,500 assault guns and more than 100 tanks, attacked the German 214th Infantry Division from the Krivasoo Bridgehead. The objective of the attack was the nearest connecting road in the village of [[Pühtitsa Convent|Kuremäe]]. After three days of heavy fighting, the Soviet army broke through the defence and advanced towards the [[Alajõe Parish|Vasknarva]]–[[Jõhvi]] Highway.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|language=Russian|author =F.I.Paulman|title=Ot Narvy do Syrve (From Narva to Sõrve)|publisher=Eesti Raamat|location=Tallinn|year=1980}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviets encircled the strong points of the 214th Infantry Division and the Estonian [[658th Eastern Battalion|658th]] and 659th Eastern Battalions, which continued resisting. Lieutenant General Ivan Korvnikov, in charge of the Soviet 59th Army, delayed the advance, citing a lack of artillery support and scarcity of manpower.&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt; This gave time for Frießner to move in all available forces and stop the Soviet advance.&lt;ref name=glantz&gt;{{cite book|author=David M. Glantz|title=The Battle for Leningrad: 1941-1944|publisher=University Press of Kansas|year=2002|location=Lawrence|isbn=0-7006-1208-4|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/battleforleningr00glan}}&lt;/ref&gt; Units of the 59th Army attacked towards the northwest from the Krivasoo bridgehead on 4 March.&lt;ref name=krivo&gt;{{cite book|title=Битва за Нарву, февраль-сентябрь 1944 год (The Battle for Narva, February–September 1944)|author=Евгений Кривошеев|author2=Николай Костин|language=Russian|chapter=I. Sraženie dlinoj v polgoda (Half a year of combat)|pages=9–87|location=Tallinn|publisher=Eesti raamat|year=1984}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A Soviet regiment of the 2nd Rifle Division attempted a surprise assault over the northeastern tip of Lake Peipus in order to seize the road along the north shore of the lake on 2 March. Up to 500 of them were killed by the 225th Infantry Division, a large number of weapons were captured, including seven assault guns.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;&lt;ref name=narwa&gt;Unpublished material from the official war diary of the [[Battle of Narva (1944)#Formation of Army Detachment "Narwa"|army detachment "Narwa"]]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Northern wing===
The SS Panzergrenadier Regiment 24 "Danmark" counter-attacked and took Siivertsi cemetery. They attacked from the northern suburbs of Narva,&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar/&gt; but could not destroy a Soviet strong-point inside a massive granite monument erected in honour of the soldiers of the Northwestern [[White Army]] in the battle of Narva, 1919. The Soviets were eventually killed by a [[flamethrower]]. An even larger strong-point was in the wreck of a [[Tiger I|Tiger]] tank. It was destroyed by Ago Loorpärg, the commander of an Estonian anti-tank company, firing at it with a captured Soviet 45&amp;nbsp;mm gun incidentally found in a loaded state.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;&lt;ref name=riipalu&gt;{{cite book|author=Harald Riipalu|year=1951|title= Siis, kui võideldi kodupinna eest (When Home Ground Was Fought For)|publisher=Eesti Hääl|location=London|language=Estonian}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1st and 2nd Estonian Regiments squeezed the Soviet bridgehead into a few hundred metres of river bank around the ruins of the borough of Vepsküla.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;

==Aftermath==

===Casualties===
German losses were in the thousands in all sectors.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;&lt;ref name=narwa/&gt; There is no adequate account of the Soviet casualties.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;

===Succeeding combat===

In a surprise attack, the 1st Estonian Regiment split the Siivertsi bridgehead into three parts and 'rolled' it down on 5 March.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;&lt;ref name=riipalu/&gt; A small Soviet bridgehead still left on the west bank was cleared by the II.Battalion, 2nd Estonian Regiment by 6 March.&lt;ref name=laar/&gt;

Soviet aviation conducted an air raid, leveling the historical town of Narva. An air and artillery bombardment of 100,000 shells and bombs were aimed at the [[11th SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Division Nordland|11th SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Division "Nordland"]] and the [[23rd SS Volunteer Panzer Grenadier Division Nederland|4th SS Volunteer Panzergrenadier Brigade "Nederland"]] in [[Ivangorod]] on the opposite bank from Narva. It also prepared the 30th Guards Rifle Division's attack on 8 March. Simultaneous pitched battles took place north of the town, where the 14th Rifle Corps supported by artillery from the [[8th Estonian Rifle Corps]] attempted to break through the defence of the 1st and 2nd Estonian Regiments. The defenders repulsed the attacks with great losses for the Soviets.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

The Soviet [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead#Soviet air assaults at civilians|air assaults against civilians]] in Estonian cities were aimed at forcing the Estonians away from supporting the Germans during the Soviet offensive. Soviet [[Long Range Aviation]] [[Bombing of Tallinn in World War II|assaulted the Estonian capital]] Tallinn on the night before 9 March. Approximately 40% of the housing space was destroyed in the city, 500 civilians were killed, 25,000 people were left without shelter. The result of the air raid was the opposite to the Soviet aim, as the people felt disgusted by the [[Soviet war crimes|Soviet atrocities]] and more men answered the German call.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

The Soviet tank [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead#End of Narva Offensive|attack at Auvere station]] on 17 March was stopped by the 502nd Heavy Tank Battalion. Fierce fighting continued for another week until the Soviet forces were compelled to go onto the defensive after suffering many casualties. This enabled the "Narwa" to [[Battle for Narva Bridgehead#Strachwitz offensive|take the initiative]].&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{coord|59.3833|N|28.2000|E|source:wikidata|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Narva Offensive (1-4 March 1944)}}
[[Category:Battle of Narva (1944)]]
[[Category:Battles involving Estonia]]
[[Category:Reichskommissariat Ostland]]
[[Category:Estonian Soviet Socialist Republic]]
[[Category:1944 in Estonia]]
[[Category:March 1944 events]]</text><sha1>joan0qe5yqqf71se7ea4o1n1n59d2fn</sha1></revision></page>