<page><title>Battle of Someri</title><ns>0</ns><id>17281530</id><revision><id>916741931</id><parentid>900287192</parentid><timestamp>2019-09-20T12:01:34Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Monkbot</username><id>20483999</id></contributor><minor /><comment>[[User:Monkbot/task 16: remove replace deprecated dead-url params|Task 16]]: replaced (2×) / removed (0×) deprecated |dead-url= and |deadurl= with |url-status=;</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="9448" xml:space="preserve">{{See also|Baltic Sea campaigns (1939–1945)}}
{{more footnotes|date=August 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Someri
| partof      = [[Continuation War]]
| image       = Uusimaa.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = [[Finnish gunboat Uusimaa]]
| date        = 8–10 July 1942
| place       = [[Sommers]] in [[Gulf of Finland]]
| coordinates = {{Coord|60.207|N|27.643|E|type:event|display=inline,title|format=dms}}
| result      = [[Finland|Finnish]] victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|Finland}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany]]
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Finland}} Unknown
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} Unknown
| strength1   = unknown
| strength2   =
| casualties1 = 23 killed&lt;br&gt;68 wounded&lt;br&gt;2 gunboats damaged&lt;br&gt;2 minesweepers damaged&lt;ref name=Solomon&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.navy.ru/history/events/desant.htm|title=Погибший десант|author=Solomon, B.|year=1997|accessdate=4 February 2011|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080418034457/http://www.navy.ru/history/events/desant.htm|archivedate=18 April 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Kijanen&gt;{{cite book|author= Kijanen, Kalervo|title=Suomen Laivasto 1918–1968 II|year=1968|publisher=Meriupseeriyhdistys/Otava| location=Helsinki}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = 7 patrol boats sunk{{#tag:ref|Patrol boats refer both [[MO class small guard ship|MO-boat]] type patrol boats and [[G-5 class motor torpedo boat|TKA-boat]] type motor torpedo boats.|group="Notes"}}&lt;br&gt;5 aircraft shot down&lt;br&gt;128 killed&lt;br&gt;149 captured&lt;br&gt;200 drowned&lt;br&gt;1 gunboat damaged&lt;br&gt;1 minesweeper damaged&lt;br&gt;11 patrol boats damaged&lt;ref name=Solomon /&gt;
}}
{{Campaignbox Continuation War}}

The '''Battle of Someri''' was a battle in the [[Gulf of Finland]] during [[World War II]] on 8–9 July 1942, between the Soviet Union and Finland. Starting as a modest operation to clear a Finnish observation post from a small island, it became one of the largest surface ship engagements in the Baltic theater.

==Background==
During the Russo-Finnish [[Winter War]] (1939–40), Soviet forces captured several Finnish islands in the eastern [[Gulf of Finland]]. In March 1940 these were ceded to the [[Soviet Union]] in accordance with the [[Moscow Peace Treaty]]. The Soviets occupied some of them with small garrisons. When the [[Continuation War]] began in June 1941 the islands were generally ignored; in autumn 1941, however, the Finnish Navy attempted to occupy the small, rocky island of [[Sommers|Someri (now Sommers, Russia)]], mistakenly thinking it had been abandoned by the Soviets. Coming under fire from the defenders, the small Finnish landing force hastily withdrew. Over the next few weeks the Finns shelled and bombed the island several times in hopes of forcing the Soviet garrison to depart. Finally in December 1941, as Soviet forces evacuated Hanko and several other islands in the [[Gulf of Finland]], the garrison on Someri was withdrawn to [[Moshchny Island]]. Finnish coastal forces occupied the island soon after. It proved to be a good position for observing Soviet movements in the area.&lt;ref name=Kijanen /&gt;

==Order of battle==
===Finnish===
The 100-man Finnish garrison on the island was equipped with two 75&amp;nbsp;mm field guns, a few 45&amp;nbsp;mm anti-tank guns and 20&amp;nbsp;mm automatic cannons, and several machine guns.&lt;ref name=Aromaa&gt;{{cite web|url=http://kotisivut.fonet.fi/~aromaa/Navygallery/Background/Wartime/Someri.htm|title=Battle of Someri|author=Aromaa, Jari|date=24 May 2006|accessdate=4 February 2011|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20110720181039/http://kotisivut.fonet.fi/~aromaa/Navygallery/Background/Wartime/Someri.htm|archive-date=20 July 2011|url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; During the battle the garrison was reinforced with an additional 100 men. The [[Finnish Navy]] deployed 3 gunboats (''[[Finnish gunboat Turunmaa|Turunmaa]]'', ''[[Finnish gunboat Hämeenmaa|Hämeenmaa]]'', and ''[[Finnish gunboat Uusimaa|Uusimaa]]''), 2 minelayers (''[[Finnish minelayer Riilahti|Riilahti]]'', and ''[[Finnish minelayer Ruotsinsalmi|Ruotsinsalmi]]''), 6 [[VMV class patrol boat]]s and 4 motor torpedo boats to the area. In addition, several small minesweepers were used to carry ammunition for the gunboats and reinforcements for the garrison. The [[Finnish Air Force]] supported the naval forces and sortied several flights of fighters ([[Brewster F2A Buffalo]] and [[Fokker D.XXI]]) and bombers ([[Bristol Blenheim]] and [[Dornier Do 17]]) to the area.

===German===
Germany sent two [[M class minesweeper (Germany)|M class minesweepers]] (''M-18'' and ''M-37''&lt;ref name=Solomon /&gt;) and an older minesweeper/tender, the ''Nettelbeck'', to support Finnish forces. A converted civilian ship – SAT ''Ost'' (Schwere Artillerie Trager – Heavy Artillery Carrier) – was also moved to the area to counter Soviet naval artillery, which was believed to be superior to that of the Finnish and German ships.&lt;ref name=Kijanen /&gt;

===Soviet===
The original Soviet landing force consisted of 256 lightly armed men (later reinforced by an additional 57 men from [[Moshchny Island]]) supported by a force of ~30 patrol (MO) and motor torpedo (TKA) boats. When the initial landing failed to surprise or overpower the Finnish defenders, more naval forces were deployed to the area. These consisted of two large minesweepers (''T-205'', ''T-207''), the [[Uragan class guard ship]] ''Burya'' (''Буря''), the auxiliary gunboat ''Kama'' (''Кама''), and additional patrol and motor torpedo boats. The [[Soviet Air Force]] repeatedly attacked Finnish ships and positions on the island with [[Ilyushin Il-4|Il-4]] (DB-3F) &amp; [[Petlyakov Pe-2|Pe-2]] bombers and [[Ilyushin Il-2|Il-2]] ground attack aircraft protected by [[Polikarpov I-153|I-153]], [[Yakovlev Yak-1|Yak-1]] and [[Lavochkin-Gorbunov-Gudkov LaGG-3|LaGG-3]] fighters.

==Battle==
Shortly after midnight, on 8 July 1942, Soviet aircraft bombed [[Sommers|Someri]], causing minor damage, after which 26 Soviet patrol and motor torpedo boats approached the island. Heavy firing erupted as the Soviet landing force moved ashore. Though considerably outnumbered, the heavily armed Finns, fighting from well-prepared positions, drove off many of the boats and contained the landing force in the eastern half of the island. Alerted by the garrison, a sizable portion of the Finnish Navy, as well as several flights from the Finnish Air Force, came to Someri's defense. They were able to clear the immediate vicinity of the island, but, as they drove off Soviet motor torpedo boats, repelled attacking Soviet aircraft, and bombarded Soviet troops ashore, the Finnish gunboats' ammunition stores dwindled rapidly, and they were forced to depart for resupply.

Finnish forces supported by a newly arrived German minesweeper managed to bring reinforcements to the island before noon, but once again, repeated Soviet MTB and air attacks depleted the ammunition stores on the gunboats. Soviet artillery ships started their approach and forced the Finnish ships to depart for resupply, which provided an opening for the Soviet boats to approach and in turn reinforce their landing force. Returning Finnish gunboats drove the Soviet boats away from the island before nightfall. On shore, the Soviet landing force was pushed into a small corner on the east end of the island, but managed to hold its positions there. During the night Soviet ships shelled from a distance, while a few Soviet boats managed to reach the island under cover of darkness.

On the morning of 9 July most of the naval activity came to an end as Soviet boats withdrew, though the larger Soviet ships continued shelling the area. Finnish forces, reinforced by the German SAT ''Ost'', armed with a single 152mm gun—heavier than any guns aboard the Soviet ships—attempted to drive them away, and the Soviet ships withdrew under cover of smokescreens. This proved to be the final surface action of the battle. During the morning the last Soviet pockets of resistance had been cleared from the island. There were several more Soviet aerial attacks, but no further landing attempts.

==Results==
Finnish and German forces reported sinking over 16 Soviet patrol and motor torpedo boats, and credited the Finnish Air Force with sinking a Soviet auxiliary gunboat;&lt;ref name=Kijanen /&gt; Soviet reports, on the other hand, claimed that several large vessels (Finnish gunboats or large German minesweepers) had been sunk.&lt;ref name=Solomon /&gt;

The relatively weak performance of the Finnish gunboats showed how badly outdated their main armaments had become, and prompted the Finnish Navy to upgrade them; however, due their old age, weak hulls, and lack of resources, only ''Hämeenmaa'' and ''Uusimaa'' were modified before the end of the war.&lt;ref name=Kijanen /&gt;

In September 1944, under the terms of the armistice ending the Continuation War, Someri (now Sommers) reverted to Russian sovereignty.

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group="Notes"}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Someri 1942}}
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Continuation War]]
[[Category:1942 in Finland]]
[[Category:Baltic Sea operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Finland]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:July 1942 events]]</text><sha1>9o4m333wx3bkmx4qbxm1emtdnffo87n</sha1></revision></page>