<page><title>Vitebsk–Orsha Offensive</title><ns>0</ns><id>15980981</id><revision><id>964173948</id><parentid>949876422</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-24T00:25:51Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>2600:1002:B105:78BE:9D08:43B6:CCAC:7975</ip></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="15488" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2018}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Vitebsk-Orsha Offensive
|image=File:Operation bagration battle wizebsk 1944 june 22-27.png
|image_size = 300px
|partof=[[Operation Bagration]]
|place=[[Belorussian SSR]]
|coordinates = {{Coord|55.2|N|30.2|E|display=INLINE,title}}
|date=23–28 June 1944
|result=Soviet victory
|combatant1=[[File:Flag of Germany 1933.svg|22px]] [[Nazi Germany]]
|combatant2={{flagicon|USSR}} [[Soviet Union]]
|commander1=[[Georg-Hans Reinhardt]] ([[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer Army]])&lt;br /&gt;[[Kurt von Tippelskirch]] ([[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|Fourth Army]])
|commander2=[[Hovhannes Bagramyan]] ([[1st Baltic Front]])&lt;br /&gt;[[Ivan Chernyakhovsky]] ([[3rd Belorussian Front]])
|strength1=14 infantry divisions&lt;br /&gt;2 panzer divisions&lt;br /&gt;(exact number of troops unknown)
|strength2=?
|casualties1=41,700 killed&lt;br /&gt;126 tanks and assault guns destroyed&lt;br /&gt;1,840 motor vehicles&lt;br /&gt;17,800 taken prisoner&lt;br&gt;{{tl|Citation needed}}
|casualties2=11,014 killed&lt;br /&gt; 318 tanks destroyed&lt;br /&gt;113 aircraft shot down&lt;br&gt;{{tl|Citation needed}}}}


The '''Vitebsk–Orsha Offensive''' ({{lang-ru|Витебско-Оршанская наступательная операция}}) was part of the Belorussian Strategic Offensive of the [[Red Army]] in summer 1944, commonly known as [[Operation Bagration]]. During the offensive, Soviet troops captured [[Vitebsk]] and [[Orsha]]. A Soviet breakthrough during the offensive helped achieve the encirclement of German troops in the subsequent [[Minsk Offensive]].

==Planning==
The immediate goals of the Soviet offensive were:
* Break through the defences of [[3rd Panzer Army]] to the north and south of [[Vitebsk]] and encircle the city, which occupied a [[Salient (military)|salient]] in the German lines.
* Break through the heavily fortified area around the main [[Moscow]]-[[Minsk]] highway and liberate the town of [[Orsha]].
* Commit motorised / cavalry exploitation forces through the gap opened once the highway had been cleared, opening the way for the [[encirclement]] of the German [[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|4th Army]] in the [[Minsk Offensive Operation]].

Soviet intelligence had revealed the depth of the German defences on the [[Moscow]]–[[Minsk]] highway near [[Orsha]]. As a result, the attack of [[Kuzma Galitsky|Galitsky's]] [[11th Guards Army]] in this sector was to be preceded by specialised engineer units; [[Mine roller|mine rolling]] [[T-34|PT-34]] tanks of the 116th Separate Engineering Tank Regiment were committed along with assault engineer companies and [[assault gun]] regiments in several waves against the fortified and mined positions of the [[78th Sturm Division]].

==Deployments==

===''Wehrmacht''===
* [[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer Army]] ([[Colonel-General]] [[Georg-Hans Reinhardt]])
** [[IX Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|IX Corps]] (General [[Rolf Wuthmann]])
** [[LIII Corps (Germany)|LIII Corps]] (General [[Friedrich Gollwitzer]])
** [[VI Corps (Germany)|VI Corps]] (General [[Georg Pfeiffer]])
* Northern flank of [[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|Fourth Army]] (General [[Kurt von Tippelskirch]])
** [[XXVII Corps (Germany)|XXVII Corps]] (General [[Paul Völckers]])
* Reserve: [[German 14th Infantry Division|14th Infantry Division]], [[German 286th Security Division|286th Security Division]]

The cities of [[Vitebsk]] and [[Orsha]] had been declared ''Fester Platz'' - fortified towns to be held at all costs - under the command of Gollwitzer (Vitebsk) and General Traut of the XXVII Corps' [[78th Sturm Division]] (Orsha).

The above units were under the overall command of [[Army Group Centre]] (Field-Marshal [[Ernst Busch (military)|Ernst Busch]]).

===Red Army===
* [[1st Baltic Front]] (General [[Hovhannes Bagramyan]])
** [[4th Shock Army (Soviet Union)|4th Shock Army]]
** [[6th Guards Army (Soviet Union)|6th Guards Army]]
** [[43rd Army (Soviet Union)|43rd Army]]
** [[3rd Air Army]]
* [[3rd Belorussian Front]] (General [[Ivan Chernyakhovsky]])
** [[11th Guards Army]] (General [[Kuzma Galitsky]])
** [[5th Army (Soviet Union)|5th Army]]
** [[39th Army (Soviet Union)|39th Army]]
** [[31st Army (Soviet Union)|31st Army]]
** [[5th Guards Tank Army]] (General [[Pavel Rotmistrov]])
** [[1st Air Army]]

Marshal [[Aleksandr Vasilevsky]] was appointed to coordinate the operations of the two Fronts involved.

==The offensive==

===Vitebsk===

Army Group Centre's northern flank was defended by the [[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer Army]] under the command of [[Georg-Hans Reinhardt]]; the lines ran through marshy terrain in the north, through a [[Salients, re-entrants and pockets|salient]] round the city of [[Vitebsk]], to a sector north of the main [[Moscow]]–[[Minsk]] road, held by the [[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|Fourth Army]]. It was opposed by the [[1st Baltic Front]] of [[Hovhannes Bagramyan]], and [[Ivan Chernyakhovsky|Chernyakhovsky]]'s [[3rd Belorussian Front]], who were given the task of breaking through the defences to the north and south of [[Vitebsk]] and cutting off the salient.

It was in this sector that Soviet forces had their greatest initial gains. The Soviet [[43rd Army (Soviet Union)|43rd Army]] broke the defences of the German [[IX Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|IX Corps]], to the north of [[Vitebsk]], within hours, pushing towards the [[Daugava River|Dvina]] river. South of the city, the [[VI Corps (Germany)|VI Corps]]' [[299th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|299th]] and [[197th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|197th]] Infantry Divisions simply disappeared beneath an overwhelming Soviet assault, with a particularly effective breakthrough by the [[5th Army (Soviet Union)|5th Army]] at the junction of the 299th and [[256th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|256th]] Infantry Divisions' sectors.{{sfnp|Dunn|2000|pp=1-2}} By 24 June, the German position in Vitebsk itself, held by the central [[LIII Corps (Germany)|LIII Corps]] of four divisions, was already serious, as Soviet forces were clearly intending to encircle the city, but no reserves were available to shore up the collapsing defences, and requests to withdraw German troops to the second defense lines, the 'Tiger' line, were denied by the ''[[Oberkommando des Heeres]]''.

By 25 June [[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer Army]] was disintegrating. In the north, IX Corps had been broken and pushed over the [[Daugava River|Dvina]], blowing the bridges during its retreat. In the south much of the VI Corps had been annihilated, and its southernmost divisions (the [[299th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|299th]] and [[256th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|256th]] Infantry Divisions) had become separated from the remainder of Third Panzer Army by heavy attacks around [[Bogushevsk]], where they attempted to make a final stand in the 'Hessen' line, the third defence zone. The Soviet 43rd and [[39th Army (Soviet Union)|39th]] Armies were now converging behind Vitebsk, trapping the entire LIII Corps. LIII Corps' commander, [[Friedrich Gollwitzer]], had transferred the [[German 4th Luftwaffe Field Division|4th Luftwaffe Field Division]] south-west of the city in order to spearhead a breakout, while the [[246th Volksgrenadier Division (Germany)|246th Infantry Division]] attempted to hold open the Dvina crossings.  [[Oberkommando des Heeres|OKH]] however, denied all requests for complete evacuation: the [[German 206th Infantry Division|206th Infantry Division]] was ordered to stay in the city and fight to the last man.{{sfnp|Zaloga|1996|p=52}}
[[File:158th Rifle Division Vitebsk June 1944.jpg|thumb|Troops of the [[158th Rifle Division]] fighting near the Vitebsk railway station during the assault on the city]]
Soviet plans in this sector met with overwhelming success. The 4th Luftwaffe Field Division was cut off and destroyed by the 39th Army on the evening of 25 June, and by the next day the 246th Infantry and [[German 6th Luftwaffe Field Division|6th Luftwaffe Field]] Divisions, fighting their way along the road from Vitebsk, had also been encircled. [[Adolf Hitler|Hitler]] insisted that a staff officer be parachuted into Vitebsk to remind Gollwitzer that the trapped 206th Infantry Division should not withdraw; [[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer Army]]'s commander, Reinhardt, was only able to get this decision reversed by insisting on being parachuted in himself if Hitler continued to order it.{{sfnp|Mitcham|2001|p=24}} By the evening Soviet forces were fighting their way into the city and Gollwitzer finally ordered the garrison to withdraw too, in defiance of the [[Oberkommando des Heeres|Supreme High Command of the German Army]] orders.

By 27 June LIII Corps had been dispersed, its 30,000 men being almost all killed or taken prisoner; a group of several thousand from the 4th Luftwaffe Field Division initially managed to break out, but was liquidated in the forests west of Vitebsk.&lt;ref name=glantz&gt;The Soviet record, given in Glantz, p.85, states that this group was first intercepted by the 179th Rifle Division at Lake Sarro on 26 June, and was eventually destroyed near Iakubovschina on 27 June.&lt;/ref&gt; The remnants of IX Corps were retreating to the west, falling back on [[Polotsk]] with the [[6th Guards Army (Soviet Union)|6th Guards Army]] in pursuit: VI Corps was also largely destroyed. [[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer Army]] had been effectively shattered within days, and [[Vitebsk]] liberated: even more significantly, a huge gap had been torn in the German lines to the north of Fourth Army in the former VI Corps sector.

===Orsha===
The central sector of Soviet operations was against the long front of [[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|Fourth Army]], which was under the overall command of [[Kurt von Tippelskirch]]. Soviet plans envisaged the bulk of it, the [[XXXIX Panzer Corps (Germany)|XXXIX Panzer Corps]] and [[XII Corps (Germany)|XII Corps]], being encircled while pinned down by attacks from the [[2nd Belorussian Front]] in the parallel [[Mogilev Offensive Operation]]. By far the most important Soviet objective, however, was immediately to the north: the main [[Moscow]]–[[Minsk]] road and the town of [[Orsha]], which the southern wing of [[Ivan Chernyakhovsky|Chernyakhovsky]]'s [[3rd Belorussian Front]] was ordered to take. A breakthrough in this area, against General [[Paul Völckers]]' [[XXVII Corps (Germany)|XXVII Corps]], would form the northern 'pincer' of the encirclement aimed at destroying Fourth Army. The Minsk road was protected by extensive defensive works manned by the [[78th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|78th Sturm Division]], a specially reinforced unit with extra artillery and [[Sturmgeschutz|assault gun]] support. Orsha itself had been designated a ''Fester Platz'' or strongpoint under 78th Sturm Division's commander, with the [[25th Panzergrenadier Division (Germany)|25th Panzergrenadier Division]] holding the lines to the south. As a result of the strong defenses in this sector, Soviet plans included the commitment of heavily armed engineer units to assist in a breakthrough.

[[Kuzma Galitsky|Galitsky]]'s [[11th Guards Army]] attacked towards Orsha on 23 June but initially made little headway. By the next day, the Soviet [[1st Guards Rifle Division]] was able to break through the German lines in a marshy, thinly-held area to the north of the 78th Sturm Division, which was ordered back to the 'Hessen' line, the third defence zone. It was now struggling to maintain contact with the 25th Panzergrenadier Division to the south. Chernyakhovsky, encouraged by the 1st Guards Rifle Division's progress, pushed a mixed cavalry / mechanised exploitation force into the breach in the German lines. On 25 June, the German defences began to rupture; a counter-attack at [[Orekhovsk]] failed.{{sfnp|Zaloga|1996|pp=56-7}}

Völckers' position was further threatened by the near-collapse of the Third Panzer Army's VI Corps, immediately to the north. At 11:20 on 25 June the VI Corps, which had been cut off from its parent formation, was reassigned to Fourth Army.{{sfnp|Dunn|2000|p=149}} Part of its reserve, the [[German 14th Infantry Division|14th Infantry Division]], was brought up to try to slow the Soviet advance north of Orsha. By midnight, however, the 11th Guards Army had shattered the remnant of VI Corps in the 'Hessen' line, and the 78th Sturm Division's situation was becoming untenable: 26 June saw the German forces in retreat. Soviet tank forces of the [[2nd Guards Tank Corps]] were able to push up the road towards [[Minsk]] at speed, with a subsidiary force breaking off to encircle Orsha, which was liberated on the evening of 26 June. The main exploitation force, [[Pavel Rotmistrov]]'s [[5th Guards Tank Army]], was then committed through the gap torn in the German lines. VI Corps finally crumbled completely, its rear elements falling back towards [[Borisov (Belarus)|Borisov]] in disarray: its commander, General [[Georg Pfeiffer]], was killed on 28 June after losing contact with his divisions. Völckers was ordered to hold fast, but lacked the necessary resources despite shifting his [[260th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|260th Infantry Division]] northwards and moving the [[German 286th Security Division|286th Security Division]] into the lines.{{sfnp|Dunn|2000|pp=149-50}}

The operation effectively ceased with the arrival of 5th Guards Tank Army's forward units at the [[Berezina]] on 28 June.

==Consequences==
In terms of its objectives within the broader structure of [[Operation Bagration]], the offensive was a complete success:
* The two key cities and communication / transport centres of Vitebsk and Orsha were captured.
* Heavy damage was inflicted on German forces, with the LIII Corps of Third Panzer Army being almost completely eliminated and other corps suffering high levels of casualties and loss of equipment.
* The breakthrough of exploitation forces at Orsha, in combination with a similar breakthrough in the south in the parallel [[Bobruysk Offensive Operation]], set up the planned encirclement of the bulk of the German Fourth Army in the following [[Minsk Offensive Operation]].

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|25em}}

==References==
* {{cite book |last=Dunn |first=Walter S. |year=2000 |title=Soviet Blitzkrieg: The Battle for White Russia, 1944 |publisher=Lynne Riener |isbn=9781555878801 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Glantz |first=David M. |authorlink=David Glantz |year=2004 |title=Byelorussia 1944: The Soviet General Staff Study |publisher=Routledge |isbn=9780415351164 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Mitcham |first=Samuel W. |authorlink=Samuel W. Mitcham |year=2001 |title=Crumbling Empire: the German Defeat in the East, 1944 |publisher=Praeger |isbn=9780275968564 |ref=harv |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/crumblingempireg00mitc }}
* {{cite book |last=Niepold |first=Gerd |translator-last=Simpkin |translator-first=Richard |year=1987 |title=Battle for White Russia: The destruction of Army Group Centre June 1944 |location=London |publisher=Brassey's |isbn=9780080336060 |ref=harv }}
* {{cite book |last=Zaloga |first=Steven |year=1996 |title=Bagration 1944: The Destruction of Army Group Centre |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] |isbn=9781855324787 |ref=harv }}

{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vitebsk-Orsha Offensive}}
[[Category:Battles involving the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Operation Bagration]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Strategic operations of the Red Army in World War II]]
[[Category:June 1944 events]]</text><sha1>g9fpctsnpdljhvrdg3pih8ss76wpz6d</sha1></revision></page>