<page><title>Bobruysk Offensive</title><ns>0</ns><id>15980999</id><revision><id>917012833</id><parentid>902935766</parentid><timestamp>2019-09-21T21:08:17Z</timestamp><contributor><username>The Anomebot2</username><id>1979668</id></contributor><comment>Removing geodata: {{coord missing|Belarus}}</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="11847" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Bobruysk Offensive
|image=Operation_bagration-bobruisk_operation-june_24-27_1944.png
|caption=Development of the bobruisk operation during soviet offensive operation bagration from june 24, 1944, 0400 AM to june 27, 1944, 0900 PM
|partof=[[Operation Bagration]]
|place=[[Byelorussian Soviet Socialist Republic|Belorussian SSR]]
|coordinates = {{Coord|53.1|N|29.2|E|display=INLINE,title}}
|date=23–28 June 1944

|result=Soviet Victory

|combatant1={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|combatant2={{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
|commander1={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Hans Jordan]]&lt;br /&gt; ([[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|Ninth Army]]) 
|commander2={{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]]&lt;br /&gt;([[1st Belorussian Front]])
|strength1=90,000
|strength2=?
|casualties1=50,000 killed, 20,000 captured, 12,000 escaped encirclement
|casualties2=?
|}}

The '''Bobruysk Offensive''' ({{lang-ru|Бобруйская наступательная операция}}) was part of the Belorussian Strategic Offensive of the [[Red Army]] in summer 1944, commonly known as [[Operation Bagration]]. In less than a week in late June 1944, the Soviet [[3rd Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Army]] broke through in the north of the sector, trapping the German [[XXXV Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXXV Corps]] against the [[Berezina]]. The [[65th Army (Soviet Union)|65th Army]] then broke through the [[XXXXI Panzer Corps|XXXXI ''Panzer'' Corps]] to the south; by 27 June, the two German corps were encircled in a pocket east of [[Bobruysk]] under constant aerial bombardment.

Up to 70,000 Axis soldiers were killed or taken prisoner. Bobruysk was liberated on 29 June after intense street fighting.

==Role in the conflict==
{{Main|Operation Bagration}}

==Planning==

===Operational goals===
The operational goals of the Bobruysk Offensive within the context of [[Operation Bagration]] were twofold:

*To break through the defensive positions of [[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|Ninth Army]] and take the heavily fortified city of [[Bobruysk]].
*Commit motorised / cavalry exploitation forces through the gap opened, opening the way for a major encirclement of much of the remainder of Army Group Centre in the [[Minsk Offensive]].

===German intelligence===
Ninth Army headquarters had argued particularly strongly that a major attack against Army Group Centre was imminent, and General Jordan had bitterly complained about the high command's refusal to sanction tactical withdrawals, but the Army Group commander, Field Marshal [[Ernst Busch (military)|Busch]], had brushed these concerns aside.&lt;ref name=dunnp181to183&gt;Dunn, pp.181-83&lt;/ref&gt; Patrols of the [[134th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|134th Infantry Division]] had revealed a buildup in the sector of the [[35th Guards Rifle Corps (Soviet Union)|35th]] and [[41st Guards Rifle Corps (Soviet Union)|41st]] Guards Rifle Corps opposite; each of the three regiments of the German divisions was faced with a full-strength Soviet rifle division of 7,200 men.&lt;ref name=dunnp181&gt;Dunn, p.181&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ninth Army was, in general, made up of lower quality divisions than Fourth Army to its north; this may have reflected a belief on the part of the OKH that the terrain in Ninth Army's sector was more easily defensible.&lt;ref name=dunnp188&gt;Dunn, pp.188-9&lt;/ref&gt;

==Deployments==

===''Wehrmacht''===
*[[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|Ninth Army]] (General [[Hans Jordan]])
**[[XXXV Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXXV Corps]] (Lieutenant-General [[Kurt-Jürgen Freiherr von Lützow]])
**[[XXXXI Panzer Corps (Germany)|XXXXI Panzer Corps]] (Lieutenant-General [[Edmund Hoffmeister]])
**[[LV Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|LV Corps]] (General [[Friedrich Herrlein]])
**Reserve: [[20th Panzer Division]], [[707th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|707th Infantry Division]] (Major General [[Gustav Gihr]])

The city of Bobruysk had been designated a ''Fester Platz'', or fortified area to be held at all costs, under the command of Major-General [[Adolf Hamann]].

The above units were under the overall command of [[Army Group Centre]] (Field-Marshal [[Ernst Busch (military)|Ernst Busch]]).

===Red Army===
*[[1st Belorussian Front]] (Marshal [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]])
**[[3rd Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Army]] (General [[Alexander Gorbatov]])
**[[28th Army (Soviet Union)|28th Army]]
**[[48th Army (Soviet Union)|48th Army]]
**[[65th Army (Soviet Union)|65th Army]] (General [[Pavel Batov]])
**[[16th Air Army]]
**Cavalry-mechanised group under command of Lieutenant-General Pliev, including 1st Mechanised Corps, 4th Guards Cavalry Corps

The above units were under the command of the special representative to ''[[Stavka]]'', Marshal [[Georgy Zhukov]].

==The offensive==
In the southern sector of operations, where the [[1st Belorussian Front]] under [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]] faced [[Hans Jordan]]'s [[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|Ninth Army]], the main Soviet objective was Bobruysk and the southern crossings of the [[Berezina]], which would open up the route for the southern 'pincer' of the main encirclement. (Army Group Centre's southernmost flank was covered by [[2nd Army (Wehrmacht)|Second Army]] in the [[Pripet Marshes]], but this area was largely bypassed by the Soviet offensive.) Rokossovsky had bravely staked his reputation on a plan for a complex double-envelopment of the German forces at Babruysk, in opposition to [[Joseph Stalin]]'s preferred plan of a single breakthrough in the sector.&lt;ref name=montefiorep483&gt;Sebag-Montefiore, pp.483-4&lt;/ref&gt;

Rokossovsky's attack, as with the other initial offensive operations of Operation Bagration, was preceded by a heavy artillery bombardment. The first assault, against strong German defences, was however repulsed with heavy casualties. Rokossovsky ordered further artillery preparation for July 24, which eventually resulted in a collapse of the [[134th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|134th Infantry Division]] to the north of the sector, as the Soviet [[Third Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Army]] pushed forward; the [[20th Panzer Division]] began to counter-attack, but Jordan then ordered it to turn southwards and confront a new breakthrough by the Soviet [[65th Army (Soviet Union)|65th Army]] under [[Pavel Batov|Batov]].&lt;ref name=zaloga6162&gt;Zaloga, pp.61-61&lt;/ref&gt;

===The encirclement of the German corps===
By June 27, Soviet forces were converging near Bobruysk, trapping the five divisions of [[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|Ninth Army]]'s northernmost corps, Lieutenant-General [[Kurt-Jürgen Freiherr von Lützow|von Lützow]]'s [[XXXV Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXXV Corps]], east of the Berezina. Elements of the central [[XXXXI Panzer Corps (Germany)|XXXXI Panzer Corps]] were also trapped, along with the 20th Panzer Division. The disorganised German divisions commenced a series of desperate attempts to escape the pocket, which stretched for several kilometers along the river's eastern bank: the Soviets reported large fires on 27 June as the Germans destroyed their heavy equipment and attempted to break out, but Soviet air attack and artillery inflicted appalling casualties on the encircled forces.&lt;ref name=glantz104105&gt;Glantz, pp.104-105; the Soviet analysis claims that von Lützow, realising the seriousness of the situation, gave his unit commanders authority for independent action in attempting to break out northwards or towards Babruysk. It states that many men even attempted to swim across the Berezina in an effort to escape.&lt;/ref&gt; In the meantime, Hitler had relieved Jordan of command due to his confusing instructions to 20th Panzer; Ninth Army was dealt another blow when its main communications headquarters was destroyed by bombing. On the following day, reinforcements arrived behind German lines in the form of [[12th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|12th Panzer Division]], whose commander was greeted by Ninth Army's chief of staff with the words "Good to see you — Ninth Army no longer exists!"&lt;ref name=Adair_p135&gt;Adair, p.135&lt;/ref&gt;

===The breakout of XLI Panzer Corps===

[[File:Operation_bagration_bobruisk_operation_final_stage.png|thumb|right|final stage of bobruisk operation (june 27, 0900 PM - july 1 1944)]]

Faced with Ninth Army's imminent collapse, [[Oberkommando des Heeres|OKH]] authorised a withdrawal.  Lieutenant-General [[Adolf Hamann]], Commander (''Commandant'') of Bobruysk, was ordered to hold the town with one division, Lieutenant-General [[Edmund Hoffmeister]]'s [[383rd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|383rd Infantry Division]].  Thousands of wounded were abandoned in the [[Babruysk fortress|citadel]].  The remnants of [[20th Panzer Division]], with a handful of tanks and assault guns, formed a spearhead for XXXXI Panzer Corps' breakout attempt which was placed under Hoffmeister's overall command, while 12th Panzer Division attacked from the [[Svislach River]] to meet the retreating troops. Though a breakout was achieved through positions held by the Soviet [[356th Rifle Division]] of 65th Army, the German forces were again subjected to intense artillery bombardment and air attack as they attempted to make their way along the roads south of Minsk.

===The 65th Army takes Bobruysk===
Batov's 65th Army now fought their way into Bobruysk street by street against stiff resistance from the German rearguard. Bobruysk, in ruins and with much of its population killed during the German occupation, was liberated on June 29, the 383rd Infantry Division commencing withdrawal towards dawn: no further elements of Ninth Army would escape from east of the Berezina. The German breakout had allowed around 12,000 troops - mostly demoralised and without weapons - from the pocket east of Bobruysk to get out, but the Soviets claimed 20,000 taken prisoner. A further 50,000 were dead: Soviet accounts speak of the area being carpeted with bodies and littered with abandoned ''materiel''. The Soviet writer, [[Vasily Grossman]], entered Bobruysk shortly after the end of the battle:

&lt;blockquote&gt;"Men are walking over German corpses. Corpses, hundreds and thousands of them, pave the road, lie in ditches, under the pines, in the green barley. In some places, vehicles have to drive over the corpses, so densely they lie upon the ground [...] A cauldron of death was boiling here, where the revenge was carried out"&lt;ref name=Beevor_p273&gt;Beevor and Vinogradova, p.273&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Ninth Army had been decisively defeated, and the southern route to [[Minsk]] was open.

== Accounts, further reading ==
In addition to Vasily Grossman, the writer and future dissident [[Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn]] was present at Babruysk as an artillery officer; the experience is mentioned in ''[[The Gulag Archipelago]]''.

Gerd Niepold, the 1st Staff Officer of [[12th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|12th Panzer Division]], later wrote a comprehensive account of [[Operation Bagration]], ''Mittlere Ostfront Juni 1944''.
==Citations==
{{reflist|2}}
==References==
* Beevor, Antony and Vinogradova, Luba (eds), ''A Writer at War: Vasily Grossman with the Red Army'', Pimlico, 2006, {{ISBN|978-1-84595-015-6}}
* Dunn, W. ''Soviet Blitzkrieg: The Battle for White Russia, 1944'', Lynne Riener, 2000, {{ISBN|978-1-55587-880-1}}
* [[David Glantz|Glantz, D.M.]] ''Belorussia 1944 — The Soviet General Staff Study''
* Mitcham, S. ''German Defeat in the East, 1944-5'', Stackpole, 2007
* Niepold, G., translated by Simpkin, R., ''Battle for White Russia: The destruction of Army Group Centre June 1944'', Brassey's, London, 1987, {{ISBN|0-08-033606-X}}
* [[Simon Sebag Montefiore|Sebag Montefiore, S.]] ''Stalin: The Court of the Red Tsar'', Phoenix, London, 2004, {{ISBN|0-7538-1766-7}}
* Zaloga, S. ''Bagration 1944: The Destruction of Army Group Centre'', [[Osprey Publishing]], 1996, {{ISBN|978-1-85532-478-7}}

[[Category:Operation Bagration]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]</text><sha1>kp4pr38kxvmnqwnltm12dmxgtorg45s</sha1></revision></page>