<page><title>Šiauliai Offensive</title><ns>0</ns><id>16615948</id><revision><id>943950448</id><parentid>877805216</parentid><timestamp>2020-03-04T20:10:09Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Estopedist1</username><id>13892613</id></contributor><minor /><comment>link fixed (+wikifying)</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="8018" xml:space="preserve">{{no footnotes|date=October 2008}}

{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Šiauliai Offensive
|image=
|caption=
|partof=[[Operation Bagration]] / [[Eastern Front of World War II|Eastern Front]]
|place=[[Belorussian SSR]], [[Lithuania]], and [[Latvia]]
|coordinates={{coord|56|N|24|E|region:LT_type:event|display=inline,title}}
|date=July 5, 1944 &amp;ndash; August 29, 1944 
|result=Soviet victory
|combatant1={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|USSR|1936}}
|commander1=[[Georg-Hans Reinhardt]]&lt;br/&gt;([[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer Army]])&lt;br/&gt;[[Paul Laux]] ([[16th Army (Wehrmacht)|Sixteenth Army]])
|commander2=[[Hovhannes Bagramyan]]&lt;br/&gt;([[1st Baltic Front]])
|strength1=
|strength2=
|casualties1=
|casualties2=
|campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Leningrad and Baltics 1941–1944}}
}}

The '''Šiauliai Offensive''' ({{lang-ru|Шяуляйская наступательная}}) was an operation of the Soviet forces of the [[1st Baltic Front]], commanded by General [[Hovhannes Bagramyan]], conducted from July 5 to August 29, 1944, during the [[Second World War]]. It was part of the third phase of the [[Operation Bagration|Belorussian Strategic Offensive Operation]] (also known as [[Operation Bagration]]), and drove German troops from much of [[Lithuania]], with the main tactical objective of the city of [[Šiauliai]] ({{lang-ru|Шяуля́й}}, {{lang-de|Schaulen}}).

==Deployments==

===Wehrmacht===
*Elements of [[Army Group Centre]] (Field-Marshal [[Walter Model]])
**Northern wing of [[3rd Panzer Army]] (Colonel-General [[Georg-Hans Reinhardt]])
***[[XXVI Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXVI Corps]] (General [[Gerhard Matzky]])
*Elements of [[Army Group North]] (Colonel-General [[Johannes Frießner]])
**Southern wing of [[16th Army (Wehrmacht)|16th Army]] (General [[Paul Laux]])

===Red Army===
*[[1st Baltic Front]] (General [[Hovhannes Bagramyan]])
**[[2nd Guards Army (Soviet Union)|2nd Guards Army]] (General-Lieutenant [[Porfiry Chanchibadze]])
**[[6th Guards Army (Soviet Union)|6th Guards Army]] (General-Lieutenant [[Ivan Chistyakov]])
**[[39th Army (Soviet Union)|39th Army]] (General-Lieutenant [[Ivan Lyudnikov]])
**[[43rd Army (Soviet Union)|43rd Army]] (General-Lieutenant [[Afanasy Beloborodov]])
**[[51st Army (Soviet Union)|51st Army]] (General-Lieutenant [[Yakov Kreizer]])

==The offensive==

===Initial phase===
In July 1944, The Soviet [[Operation Bagration]] had been achieving great success. [[Army Group Centre]] was in tatters, and the northern edge of the Soviet assault threatened to trap [[Army Group North]] in [[Latvia]] and [[Estonia]]. Front forces (the [[6th Guards Army (Soviet Union)|6th Guards]] and [[43rd Army (Soviet Union)|43rd Armies]]), participating in the [[Operation Bagration|Belorussian Strategic Offensive Operation]], advanced to the line of the [[Druya river]], west of [[Voropaevo]] and [[Naroch Lake]] from July 4, having the mission of beginning an advance in the direction of [[Švenčionys]], [[Kaunas]] and by part of the forces towards [[Panevėžys]] and [[Šiauliai]]. Also included in the composition of the Front for this operation was the [[39th Army (Soviet Union)|39th Army]], which had to be concentrated on the left wing of the Front by July 10. The Front was also reinforced by the 2nd Guards and 51st Armies from the [[Reserve of the Supreme High Command#World War II|''Stavka'' Reserve]], though these could only arrive in the front sector by the second half of July. The offensive began on 5 July with an assault by the forces of two rifle corps of the 6th Guards and three rifle corps of 43rd Armies, with support from a reduced [[1st Tank Corps (Soviet Union)|1st Tank Corps]].

Facing them were German troops of two corps, which were positioned on adjacent wings of Army Groups North and Centre. [[Hyazinth Graf Strachwitz]]'s tanks had been sent to the Latvian capital, [[Riga]] and had halted the advance of [[Hovhannes Bagramyan]]'s [[1st Baltic Front]] in late July, 1944. Strachwitz's Panzerverband was broken up in late July. From the morning of July 10 39th Army was introduced into the battle, conducting an assault towards Kaunas. By July 12 the frontage of the offensive of three armies increased to 200&amp;nbsp;km, the opposing troops of [[Army Group North]]. By early August, the Soviet forces were in position to cut off Army Group North from Army Group Centre.

===Transfer of main attack from Kaunas to Šiauliai===
As a result of the offensive's development, ''Stavka'' shifted the direction of the main attack of the 1st Baltic Front from Kaunas to Šiauliai. 39th Army, together with the sector of its offensive was transferred to the [[3rd Belorussian Front]] on July 14 (see the [[Kaunas Offensive Operation]]). In exchange, 1st Baltic Front received the [[3rd Guards Mechanized Corps]].

For the development of the offensive on the Šiauliai axis, the 2nd Guards and 51st Armies were introduced into the battle on July 14. By July 22 their troops had captured [[Panevežys]] - an important communications center of Army Group North. On July 27, the 3rd Guards Mechanized Corps, in cooperation with the combined arms units of 51st Army, captured [[Šiauliai]], which had been held by a scratch force led by [[Hellmuth Mäder]]. The troops of the right wing of the Front in interaction with the forces of the [[2nd Baltic Front]] took [[Daugavpils]].

Pressing home the attack, the forces of the Front on July 30 overran strong points and road junctions [[Biržai]] and [[Bauska]], and by July 31 had reached [[Jelgava]]. The Front's mobile detachments entered [[Tukums]] and reached the coast of the [[Gulf of Riga]], cutting the land communications of Army Group North.

===German counter-attacks===
At the end of July and beginning of August Bagramyan's forces repulsed German counter-attacks in the region of [[Biržai]] (some 4 infantry divisions and to 100 tanks and assault guns, according to Soviet estimates) and [[Raseiniai]] (one infantry and one tank division). ''Panzerverband von Strachwitz'' was reformed, this time from elements of the [[101st Panzer Brigade]] of Oberst [[Meinrad von Lauchert]] and the newly formed [[SS Panzer Brigade Gross]]. Inside the pocket, the remaining panzers and [[StuG III|StuGs]] of the ''Hermann von Salza'' and the last of Jähde's Tigers were formed into another Kampfgruppe to attack from the inside.

On 19 August, the counter-attack, which had been dubbed [[Operation Doppelkopf]] got underway. It was preceded by a bombardment by the [[German cruiser Prinz Eugen|cruiser ''Prinz Eugen'''s]] 203&amp;nbsp;mm guns, which destroyed forty-eight T-34s assembling in the square at [[Tukums]].  During these defensive actions, the ground forces were supported by the [[3rd Air Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Air Army]]. By August 20 the German forces, by counterattacks in the regions west of [[Tukums]] and [[Sloka, Latvia|Sloka]] and with support from the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'', were able to push the Soviet troops away from the coastline in the southern sector and to restore the sea communications of their formations around [[Riga]]. Strachwitz and the SS Division Nordland met on the 21st, and contact was restored between the army groups.

==Aftermath==
By that point, Army Group North was extremely vulnerable to being cut off. The 1st Baltic Front resumed its offensive that autumn, finally destroying much of [[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer Army]] and severing the connection between the German Army Groups Centre and North, in the [[Memel Offensive Operation]].

==References==
*Hinze, R. ''Ostfrontdrama 1944'', Motorbuchverlag Stuttgart, 1998
*''Fight for the Soviet Baltic in the Great Patriotic War 1941-1945'', Riga, 1967

{{DEFAULTSORT:Siauliai Offensive}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Operation Bagration]]
[[Category:Lithuania in World War II]]
[[Category:Strategic operations of the Red Army in World War II]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:July 1944 events]]
[[Category:August 1944 events]]</text><sha1>hdl58fl41imeor8tyqejxyx3wb00db1</sha1></revision></page>