<page><title>Kaunas Offensive</title><ns>0</ns><id>16068388</id><revision><id>842470671</id><parentid>833157829</parentid><timestamp>2018-05-22T17:30:05Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Dross</username><id>23728166</id></contributor><minor /><comment>good lead; ibx cu</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="7147" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Kaunas Offensive
| partof      = [[Operation Bagration]]
| image       = Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-732-0137-14, Ostpreussen, Wilkowischken, Schützenpanzer.jpg
| caption     = [[Wehrmacht]] armored personnel carrier in [[Vilkaviškis]] during the Kaunas Offensive
| date        = July 28 - August 28, 1944
| place       = [[Kaunas]] area, [[Lithuania]]
| coordinates = {{coord|54|55|N|24|00|E|region:LT_type:event|display=inline,title}}
| result      = Soviet victory
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]
| combatant2  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Walter Model]]&lt;br&gt;([[Army Group Centre]])
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Ivan Chernyakhovsky]]&lt;br&gt;([[3rd Belorussian Front]])
| strength1   = 
| strength2   = 
| casualties1 = 
| casualties2 = 
}}
{{Campaignbox Leningrad and Baltics 1941-1944}}

The '''Kaunas Offensive''' ({{lang-ru|Каунасская наступательная}}) was part of the third phase of the [[Operation Bagration|Belorussian Strategic Offensive]] of the [[Red Army]] in summer 1944, commonly known as [[Operation Bagration]]. The Kaunas offensive was executed by the 3rd Belorussian Front on July 28 – August 28, 1944, with the aim of destroying the German concentration on the western bank of the [[Neman river]], the liberation of [[Kaunas]], and reaching the boundaries of [[East Prussia]].

==Planning==
After completing the [[Vilnius Offensive Operation]], the troops of the 3rd Belorussian Front (the 11th Guards, 5th, 31st, 33rd, 39th Armies, the 5th Guards Tank Army and 1st Air Army) were engaged in intense fighting with German forces on the approaches to the Neman river during the second half of July, and were preparing for the continuation of the offensive. They were resisted by formations and units of the [[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer]] and [[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|Fourth]] Armies of the German [[Army Group Centre]], under the command of [[Field-Marshal]] [[Walter Model]]. Towards the end of July, German units concentrated in the direction of Kaunas, according to Soviet estimates, included elements of 10 infantry and 2 tank divisions, 2 infantry brigades and 30 separate regiments and battalions.

''[[Stavka]]'' assigned to the forces of the Front the mission of pressing home the attack on the Kaunas axis not later than 1–2 August, through assaults by the 39th Army together with the 5th Guards Tank Army from the north, and the 5th and 33rd Armies from the south to occupy Kaunas – the most important defensive position on the approaches to East Prussia. The plan called for the Red Army troops to advance to the borders of East Prussia by the 10 August and assume a defensive configuration in preparation for advancing into East Prussia.

As with the parallel defence against the [[Belostock Offensive]] to the south, Model concentrated on a holding / delaying action using the few units available to him. The German Order of Battle for mid-July showed units from a large number of divisions in the area, but many of these were fragments that had escaped from the encirclement of the bulk of Army Group Centre in the previous phases of Operation Bagration; see deployments below.&lt;ref name=hinzep42&gt;Hinze, p.42, gives a full OOB&lt;/ref&gt;

==Deployments==

===''Wehrmacht''===
*[[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer Army]] (Colonel-General [[Georg-Hans Reinhardt]])
**''[[Korpsabteilung|Korpsabteilung G]]'' (remnants of [[95th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|95th]], [[197th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|197th]] and [[256th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|256th]] Infantry Divisions that had escaped the previous phase of Operation Bagration)
**[[XXVI Corps (Germany)|XXVI Corps]] (parts of [[6th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|6th Panzer]]  and other divisions) (General [[Gerhard Matzky]])
**[[IX Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|IX Corps]] (remnants) (General [[Rolf Wuthmann]])
*Northern wing of [[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|Fourth Army]] (General [[Kurt von Tippelskirch]] to 18 July, then General [[Friedrich Hoßbach]])
**[[XXXIX Panzer Corps (Germany)|XXXIX Panzer Corps]] (reconstructed) (General [[Dietrich von Saucken]])
**[[7th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|7th Panzer Division]]

===Red Army===
*[[3rd Belorussian Front]] (General [[Ivan Chernyakhovsky]])
**[[11th Guards Army (Soviet Union)|11th Guards Army]] (General [[Kuzma Galitsky]])
**[[5th Army (Soviet Union)|5th Army]]
**[[33rd Army (Soviet Union)|33rd Army]] (Lieutenant-General [[Vasily Kryuchenkin]])
**[[39th Army (Soviet Union)|39th Army]] (Lieutenant-General [[Ivan Lyudnikov]])&lt;ref&gt;Part 4, Людников И. И. Дорога длиною в жизнь. — М.: Воениздат, 1969. Road the length of a lifetime, Moscow, Voenizdat, 1969 [http://militera.lib.ru/memo/russian/lyudnikov_ii/index.html]&lt;/ref&gt;
**[[31st Army (Soviet Union)|31st Army]]
**[[5th Guards Tank Army]] (General [[Pavel Rotmistrov]])
**[[1st Air Army (Soviet Union)|1st Air Army]]

==The offensive==
On 28 July the forces of the Front went over to the offensive, and by the end of 29 July they had advanced 5–17&amp;nbsp;km. By July 30 the German resistance on the approaches to the [[Neman River|Neman]] was broken. In the 33rd Army sector, the [[2nd Guards Tank Corps]] was introduced into the breakthrough: their rapid advance to [[Vilkaviškis]] threatened the German forces before Kaunas with encirclement and the Germans were forced to retreat.

Using the success of the Tank Corps, the troops of the 33rd Army entered and secured Vilkaviškis and the railway station of [[Mariampolė]] on 31 July. Troops of the 5th Army broke into Kaunas and on the morning of 1 August took control of  it. Towards the beginning of August the forces of the Front advanced up to 50&amp;nbsp;km and subsequently enlarged the breakthrough to 230&amp;nbsp;km, liberating more than 900 villages, townships, towns and small cities.

During August, Raus' Third Panzer Army was reinforced and mounted a counter-offensive on the Front's northern flank in [[Operation Doppelkopf]]. German troops also delivered a series of strong counter-attacks south-west and west of Kaunas. Having countered these, the 3rd Belorussian Front's troops moved a further 30–50&amp;nbsp;km and advanced towards deliberately prepared German fortified positions on the line east of [[Raseiniai]] and [[Kybartai]] - [[Suwałki]]. From 29 August on the orders of ''Stavka'', the Front went over to the defensive. As a result of the Kaunas operation the forces of the 3rd Belorussian Front reached the eastern borders of [[East Prussia]].

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
{{More footnotes|date=October 2008}}
*Hinze, R. ''Ostfrontdrama 1944''
*''Fight for the Soviet Baltic in the Great Patriotic War 1941-1945'', book 2, Riga, 1967
*Karvyalis V. A. ''The liberation of the Lithuanian SSR from Hitler's occupation (1944-1945)'', Vilnius, 1975.

[[Category:Operation Bagration]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Lithuania in World War II]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:July 1944 events]]
[[Category:August 1944 events]]</text><sha1>8qfefb53c1wujm9jnerhnct3gmi3qia</sha1></revision></page>