<page><title>Battle of Tali-Ihantala</title><ns>0</ns><id>26626798</id><revision><id>958737354</id><parentid>956227386</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-25T13:09:59Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Havsjö</username><id>35067771</id></contributor><minor /><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="37970" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=March 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict    = Battle of Tali-Ihantala
|image       = Tali-Ihantala.jpg
|image_size  = 300px
|caption     = Finnish soldiers marching next to a destroyed Soviet [[T-34]] tank
|partof      = the [[Continuation War]] of [[World War II]]
|date        = June 25 to July 9, 1944
|place       = {{Coord|60|46|N|28|53|E|name=Battle of Tali-Ihantala|display=inline,title}}&lt;br /&gt;[[Karelian Isthmus]]
|result      = Finnish victory&lt;ref name="Jowett 2006 p. 14"&gt;[[#FAW2006|Jowett &amp; Snodgrass (2006)]]. p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Mcateer-184"/&gt;&lt;ref name="battlesandsieges-467"&gt;[[#battlesandsieges|Jaques (2007)]] p. 467&lt;/ref&gt;
|combatant1  = {{flag|Finland}}&lt;br /&gt;'''Supported by:'''&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Nazi Germany}}
|combatant2  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
|commander1  = {{nowrap|{{Flagicon|Finland}} [[C.G.E. Mannerheim]]}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Finland}} [[Karl Lennart Oesch]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Kurt Kuhlmey]]
|commander2  = {{Flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Leonid Govorov]]&lt;br /&gt;{{Flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Dmitry Gusev]]&lt;br /&gt;{{nowrap|{{Flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Aleksandr Cherepanov (general)|Aleksandr Cherepanov]]}}
|strength1   = {{flagicon|Finland}} 50,000&lt;ref&gt;[[#FAW2006|Jowett &amp; Snodgrass (2006)]]. "Finnish forces total about 50,000 men of IV Corps (LtGen Taavetti Laatikainen), with 50 per cent of the nation's entire complement of artillery committed to the battle. The main Finnish assets committed at Tali-Ihantala are the 3rd, 4th, 6th &amp; 18th Divs, the 'Lagus' Armd Div, and the 3rd 'Blue' brigade. The Finnish artillery perform magnificently, and their accurate fire is one of the main factors in the victory." p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} 4,000{{sfn|Nenye ''et al.''|2016|p=244}}
|strength2   = 150,000&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#FAW2006|Jowett &amp; Snodgrass (2006)]]. "The main Soviet attacking force is the 21st Army, with a total of 150,000 men in 14 infantry divisions, with tank brigades, artillery, and other heavy support assets." p. 13.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Punaiset panssarit – Puna-armeijan panssarijoukot 1918–1945 (Red tanks – the Red Army's armoured forces 1918–1945)|last= Kantakoski|first= Pekka |year= 1998|publisher=Hämeenlinna : Ilves-Paino|isbn=951-98057-0-2|pages= 512|language = fi}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Nenye ''et al.''|2016|p=244}}&lt;br&gt;'''Soviet sources:'''&lt;br&gt;48,000–60,000&lt;ref name=Shigin&gt;[[#Shigin|Shigin (2004)]], pp. 270–271, 316&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties1 ={{flagicon|Finland}} '''Finnish:''' c. 8,750 total
* 1,350 killed{{sfn|Nenye ''et al.''|2016|p=244}}
* 1,100 missing{{sfn|Nenye ''et al.''|2016|p=244}}
* 6,300 wounded&lt;ref name="Koskimaa" /&gt;
* 3 tanks destroyed {{sfn|Nenye ''et al.''|2016|p=243}}
* 12 aircraft{{sfn|Nenye ''et al.''|2016|p=243}}
{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} '''German:''' 
* 33 aircraft{{sfn|Nenye ''et al.''|2016|p=243}}
|casualties2 ='''Finnish estimate:'''&lt;br/&gt;600 tanks&lt;ref name="Philip Jowett p.14"&gt;Philip Jowett &amp; Brent Snodgrass p.14&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;284–320 aircraft&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;'''Later Finnish estimate''':&lt;br&gt;21st Army:&lt;br /&gt;estimated 4,500–5,500 killed&lt;br /&gt;13,500–14,500 wounded&lt;ref name="MoscowMOD"&gt;Archives of Soviet Ministry of Defence, daily casualty reports of 21. Army June 29 – July 10, 1944, 10-day casualty summaries of 21. Army, June–July 1944. Daily reports consists 3,198 KIA, 363 MIA and 13,125 WIA. With the information of 10-day summaries, the casualties of the first four days of the battle could be estimated, which gives total Soviet losses to about 22,000 from which 4,500–5,500 KIA/MIA. According to Soviet military medication statistics from the wounded, about 6% died to their wounds, and those would not be included in the numbers above.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Manninen"/&gt;{{verify source|date=May 2011}}&lt;br /&gt;23rd Army:&lt;br /&gt;1,458 killed, 288 missing, 6,159 wounded&lt;ref name="raunio_kilin_def"/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;'''27,500 total casualties'''
|campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Continuation War}}
}}
The '''Battle of Tali-Ihantala''' (June 25 to July 9, 1944) was part of the Finnish-Soviet [[Continuation War]] (1941–1944), which occurred during World War II. The battle was fought between [[Finland|Finnish]] forces—using war materiel provided by [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]—and [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] forces. To date, it is the largest battle in the history of the [[Nordic countries]].&lt;ref name="Lunde-306"/&gt;

The battle marked a point in the Soviet offensive when the Finnish forces first prevented the Soviets from making any significant gains.&lt;ref name=FAW&gt;Jowett, P., Snodgrass, B. Finland at War 1939–45 Osprey Publishing. 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Baryshnikov&gt;[[#Baryshnikov|Baryshnikov (2006)]]&lt;/ref&gt; Earlier at Siiranmäki and Perkjärvi the Finns had halted advancing Soviet forces.&lt;ref&gt;[[#Lunde|Lunde (2011)]] pp. 286–287&lt;/ref&gt; The Finnish forces achieved a defensive victory against overwhelming odds.&lt;ref name="Mcateer-184"/&gt;&lt;ref name="battlesandsieges-467"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Lunde-379"/&gt;

After the Soviets had failed to create any breakthroughs at Tali-Ihantala, [[Battle of Vyborg Bay (1944)|Vyborg Bay]], or [[Battle of Vuosalmi|Vuosalmi]], the Soviet [[Leningrad Front]] started the previously planned transfer&lt;ref name=Baryshnikov/&gt;&lt;ref name=Zolotarev&gt;[[#Zolotarev|Zolotarev (1999)]], pp. 97–98, 368&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Vasilevsky&gt;{{cite book |script-title=ru:Дело моей жизни|trans-title=The Point of My Life|url=http://militera.lib.ru/memo/russian/vasilevsky/23.html|last=Vasilevsky|first=Aleksandr|authorlink=Aleksandr Vasilevsky|year=1978|publisher=Politizdat|location=Moscow|page=412|language=Russian}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="moisala-152"&gt;[[#Moisala|Moisala &amp; Alanen (1988)]] pp. 152–154&lt;/ref&gt; of troops from the Karelian Isthmus to support [[Operation Bagration]], where they were encountering particularly fierce resistance.&lt;ref name="Mcateer-184"/&gt; Though the Leningrad Front failed to advance into Finland as ordered by the [[Stavka]],&lt;ref name="moisala-152"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lehmus K. Tuntematon Mannerheim. Hels., 1967, pp. 179–180&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wirtanen A. Salaiset keskustelut Lahti, 1967, p. 268&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Wirtanen A. Poliitiset muistdmat Hels., 1972, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Seppälä H. Taistelu Leningradista ja Suomi, pp. 272–273&lt;/ref&gt; some historians state that the [[Vyborg–Petrozavodsk Offensive|offensive]] did eventually force Finland from the war.&lt;ref name=Glantz&gt;[[#Glantz|Glantz (1998)]], pp. 201–203&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Erickson&gt;[[#Erickson|Erickson (1993)]], pp. 329–330&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Lunde-end"/&gt;

==Background==
[[File:Karelian Isthmus.png|thumb|300px|right|Map of the Karelian Isthmus. The River Vuoksi can be seen originating from near the city Imatra.]]
[[File:Many Karelias.png|middle|thumb|200px|Parts of Karelia, as they are traditionally divided.]]
{{Main|Continuation War}}

After the initial Finnish advance of 1941, the Continuation War was stabilized to [[trench warfare]] with very little activity on either side. When the [[Siege of Leningrad]] was lifted in January 1944, the [[Stavka#Stavka of the RKKA during World War II|Stavka]] received orders to plan an [[Fourth strategic offensive|offensive against Finland]] to push it out of the war.

The Soviet attack on the Finnish front commenced on the [[Karelian Isthmus]] on June 9, 1944, (coordinated with the Allied [[Invasion of Normandy]]). Three Soviet armies were pitted there against the Finns, among them several experienced [[Guards unit|Guard formations]].&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"&gt;{{cite book |first=Matti |last=Koskimaa |year=1993 |title=Veitsenterällä : vetäytyminen Länsi-Kannakselta ja Talin-Ihantalan suurtaistelu kesällä 1944 |publisher=WSOY |ISBN=951-0-18811-5}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The attack soon breached the Finnish front line of defence in [[Valkeasaari]] on June 10, and the Finnish forces retreated to their secondary defence line, the [[VT-line]] (which ran between [[Vammelsuu]] and [[Solovyovo, Priozersky District, Leningrad Oblast|Taipale]]). The Soviet attack was supported by a massive artillery barrage, air bombardments, and armoured forces.&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt;

The VT-line was breached in [[Sahakylä]] and [[Kuuterselkä]] on June 14; and after a failed counterattack in Kuuterselkä by the Finnish armoured division, the Finnish defence had to be pulled back to the [[VKT-line]] (Viipuri – [[Kuparsaari]] – Taipale).&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt;

The abandonment of the VT-line was followed by a week of retreat and delaying battles. The Soviet offensive was crowned when the city of Viipuri (Russian: Vyborg) was captured by the Soviets on June 20 after only a short battle. Despite the Red Army’s great success in smashing two Finnish defense lines and capturing a substantial piece of territory in just ten days, it had failed to destroy the Finnish army which was able to concentrate its depleted forces on the VKT-line, and had time to get reinforcements from the other main front north of Lake Ladoga.&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt;

[[Carl Gustaf Emil Mannerheim|Baron Mannerheim]], the Finnish commander in chief, had asked for German help on June 12, and on June 16 the Flight Detachment Kuhlmey (a composite ad hoc wing of about 70 dive bombers and ground attack fighters, with a fighter and an air transport component) arrived in Finland. A few days later the battalion-sized 303 Assault Gun Brigade and the [[122nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|122nd Division]] ''Greif'' also arrived; but after that the Germans offered only  supplies, the most important of which were [[Panzerfaust]] [[anti-tank]] weapons.&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt; During one engagement the Finns destroyed 25 Soviet tanks with the Panzerfaust weapons.&lt;ref&gt;Jowlett &amp; Snodgrass p. 14&lt;/ref&gt;

On June 21 the Stavka ordered the [[Leningrad Front]] to breach the defensive line and advance to [[Lake Saimaa]].&lt;ref name=Zolotarev/&gt;

On June 21 the Finnish government asked the Soviets about the possibility for peace and accompanying Soviet conditions. The Soviet response arrived on June 23; it demanded a signed statement to the effect that Finland was ready to surrender and was asking for peace, but the Finnish government rejected this.

German Foreign Minister [[Joachim von Ribbentrop|Ribbentrop]] arrived on June 22 and demanded a guarantee that Finland would fight to the end as a precondition of continued German military support. President Ryti [[Ryti-Ribbentrop Agreement|gave this guarantee]] as a personal undertaking.

==Order of battle==
{{refimprove section|date=June 2013}}

===Finnish===
HQ of the Commander of the Isthmus Forces (Lieutenant general [[Karl Lennart Oesch]])
* Finnish [[Finnish 4th Corps|IV AK]] (Lieutenant general [[Taavetti Laatikainen]])
** 3rd Brigade "Blue Brigade" (Colonel Lauri Haanterä)
** [[Finnish 3rd Division (Continuation War)|Finnish 3rd Division]] (Major general [[Aaro Pajari]])
** [[Finnish 4th Division (Continuation War)|Finnish 4th Division]] (Major general Pietari Autti)
** [[Finnish 18th Division (Continuation War)|Finnish 18th Division]] (Major general Paavo Paalu sacked June 26, Colonel Otto Snellman),
** since June 27 [[Finnish 11th Division (Continuation War)|11th Division]] (Major general [[Kaarlo Heiskanen]]).
** [[Finnish 6th Division (Continuation War)|Finnish 6th Division]] (Major general [[Einar Vihma]])
* [[Finnish Armoured Division]] (Major general [[Ruben Lagus]])
* LeR 3 (Lieutenant colonel E. Magnusson) (33 [[Messerschmitt Bf 109]], 18 [[Brewster Buffalo]] 239 Fighters and 1 [[Fokker C.X]] reconnaissance)
* LeR 4 (Colonel O. Sarko) (33 [[Bristol Blenheim]], 12 [[Junkers Ju 88]], 8 [[Dornier Do 17]]Z bombers)

===German===
* German air unit [[Detachment Kuhlmey|Gefechtsverband Kuhlmey]] (Oberstleutnant [[Kurt Kuhlmey]]) arrived in Finland on June 16. (23–43 [[Focke-Wulf Fw 190|Fw 190 A-6/F-8]] fighters and ground attack aircraft, 24–30 [[Junkers Ju 87|Ju 87 D Stukas]] and 1–8 [[Bf 109|Bf 109 G-8]] reconnaissance fighters)
* German [[Sturmgeschütz-Brigade 303]] (Hauptmann [[Hans-Wilhelm Cardeneo]]) arrived in Finland on June 22. (22 [[StuG III|StuG III Ausf. G assault guns]], 9 [[StuG III|StuH 42 assault howitzers]])

===Soviet===
The Soviet forces that took part in the battle belonged to the Soviet [[Leningrad Front]] under Marshal [[Leonid Govorov]]'s command.  
* [[Soviet 21st Army]] ([[Dmitry Gusev]]) (Tali-Ihantala region) attacked; 
** [[30th Guards Army Corps|30th Guards Rifle Corps]], 
** [[97th Rifle Corps]], 
** [[108th Rifle Corps]], 
** [[109th Rifle Corps]], 
** [[110th Rifle Corps]].
These five corps had together the [[45th Guards Rifle Division|45th]], [[63rd Guards Rifle Division|63rd]] and [[64th Guards Rifle Division]]s and [[46th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|46th]], [[72nd Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|72nd]], [[90th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|90th]], [[109th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|109th]], [[168th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|168th]], [[178th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|178th]], [[265th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|265th]], 268th, 286th, [[314th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|314th]], [[358th Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|358th]] and [[372nd Rifle Division]]s. 

The 21st Army did not commit all of its forces simultaneously but instead kept some of the forces in reserve and committed them only after the initially committed formations had spent their offensive capability and required rest and refit. Also, at the beginning of the battle, some of the Soviet forces that later took part in the battle were deployed on nearby sections of the front, such as the 108th Rifle Corps with its three divisions being deployed to Vyborg and the Vyborg Bay area. 

* [[Soviet 23rd Army]] ([[Aleksandr Cherepanov (general)|Aleksandr Cherepanov]]) attacked on the front immediately east of the 21st Army towards Noskua.&lt;br&gt; It deployed the Soviet [[6th Rifle Corps]] which consisted of the [[13th Rifle Division|13th]], [[177th Rifle Division|177th]], and [[382nd Rifle Division]]s.

==The terrain==
The Battle of Tali-Ihantala was fought in a small area (100&amp;nbsp;km²) between the northern tip of [[Vyborg Bay]] and the [[River Vuoksi]] around the villages of Tali and Ihantala, 8–14&amp;nbsp;km north-east from Vyborg.

The Soviet forces were concentrated on the area east of the city of Vyborg, from where the attack started, through the southern village of Tali, northwards to [[Ihantala]] (Petrovka). This was the only suitable exit terrain for armoured forces out of the [[Karelian Isthmus]], 10&amp;nbsp;km wide, broken by small lakes and limited by [[Saimaa Canal]] on the west and the [[River Vuoksi]] on the east.

==Tali: June 25–30==
{{refimprove section|date=June 2013}}
[[File:PST-tykki Kannaksella.jpg|thumb|Finnish [[7.5 cm Pak 40]] antitank gun in action]] [[File:StuG III Ausf. G.jpg|thumb|right|Finnish [[Sturmgeschütz III|StuG III]] Ausf. G [[assault gun]]s.]]
[[File:Panzerfaust6.jpg|thumb|Finnish soldiers in a [[Defensive fighting position|foxhole]]. One of the soldiers is holding a [[Panzerfaust]]]]

[[File:Elements of the Sturmgeschütz-Brigade 303.jpg|thumb|right|[[Sturmgeschütz]]-Brigade 303 on the move in city of Lappeenranta.]]
[[File:4406TaisteluosastoKuhlmeynStukia.jpg|thumb|Battle Squadron Kuhlmey´s Stukas returning from mission in Karelian Isthmus in late June 1944.]]

The fighting in the area began on June 20.

===June 20–24===
The first days were a defensive battle that the Finnish 18th Division (6th and 48th Infantry Regiment and 28th Independent Battalion) and 3rd Brigade (4 battalions) and the 3rd battalion of the 13th Regiment (Swedish speaking) fought against the Soviet 97th and 109th Corps and 152nd Tank Brigade. The defenders were hit especially hard by artillery and air attacks, but managed to put up a strong defense that stalled the Soviet advance long enough for Finnish reinforcements to join the battle.&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt;

===June 25–26===
The action of June 25 started at 06:30 with a one-hour Soviet heavy artillery bombardment and air attack, followed by a major Soviet offensive from Tali village at 07:30. The Soviets' goal in the attack was to reach Imatra-Lappeenranta-Suurpäälä before June 28. The 30th Guards Rifle Corps had now also joined the battle.

The Soviet army tried to break through along both sides of Lake Leitimojärvi. The attack on the eastern side of the lake was stopped after three kilometers by the Finnish 4th Division. On the west side, the Soviet infantry of the 45th Guards Division and the 109th Corps got stuck in defensive positions around the hills of Konkkalanvuoret defended by the Finnish regiment JR48.
However, the Soviet 27th Tank Regiment was able to force their way to the Portinhoikka crossroads.

The Soviets also attacked with the 178th Division over the Saarela Strait, which was defended by Finnish regiment JR6's 1st battalion, but the attack was thrown back here as well. Meanwhile, the Soviet 97th Corps attacked the Finnish 3rd Brigade's positions but gained little ground. At this stage the situation was very critical for the Finns, whose units were at risk of being cut off and surrounded. This would inevitably have led to the defeat of the Finnish IV Corps and the loss of the VKT line.

The Finns were able to organize a counterattack with the reserves of the 18th Division, parts of the 17th Division, and some battle groups from the 4th Division. Later that afternoon, the Finnish armored division joined the battle and managed to push the Soviet attackers on the west side of the Lake Leitimojärvi back to their starting point. The Soviet 27th Tank Regiment was annihilated except for six tanks that were captured by the Finns.

===June 27–30===
More Finnish units joined the battle along with the German 303rd ''Sturmgeschütz'' brigade. The Finnish units had been spread out and mixed in the battle, which made the organization of a concentrated defence difficult. The Finnish units were therefore reorganized into two battle groups, BG Björkman and BG Puroma. The Soviets also reinforced their forces with the 108th Corps. At this stage, the Soviet forces included at least one armored brigade, two armored breakthrough regiments, and four assault gun regiments.

The Finns tried to regain the initiative by attacking the four Soviet divisions (46th Guard, 63rd Guard, 64th Guard, 268th Division and the 30th Guards Tank Brigade) – that had broken through east of Leitimojärvi – from three directions, in order to make a "[[Salients, re-entrants and pockets#Motti|motti]]" of the Soviet divisions. The two battle groups, Björkman and Puroma, did manage to advance to within one kilometer of each other but failed to surround the Soviet divisions who had set themselves up into a hedgehog defense around Talinmylly.

The Finnish attack failed because of heavy Soviet resistance especially with massed tanks and artillery, and because communication between several Finnish battalions broke down during the attack. Colonel Puroma said after the war that the one thing he regretted was the failure to make a motti out of Talinmylly. The attack gave the Finnish defenders 72 hours of respite at the same time as the fresh Finnish 6th and 11th Divisions reached the battlefield. Several tank battles took place during this fighting.

On June 28, air activity was high on both sides as Finnish bombers and German Stukas pounded the Soviet formations and the Soviet 276th Bomber Division hit the Finnish troops hard. On June 28, the Finnish commander Oesch gave the order for Finnish units to withdraw back to the line of Vakkila-Ihantalajärvi-Kokkoselkä-Noskuanselkä (still within the VKT line), but they became caught up in a new Soviet offensive.

June 29 was the hardest and worst day for the Finns during the whole battle, and defeat was not far off. The Finnish forces finally managed to restore the line on June 29 after very bloody fighting. On June 30, the Finnish forces retreated from Tali. The heaviest fighting took place between July 1 and July 2 when the Finns lost some 800 men per day.&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt;

==Ihantala: July 1–9==
The ensuing Finnish concentration of artillery fire was the heaviest in the country's military history.&lt;ref name="Jatkosota"&gt;[[Maanpuolustuskorkeakoulu|Maanpuolustuskorkeakoulun historian laitos]], ''Jatkosodan historia 1–6'', 1994&lt;/ref&gt; It was based on the famed fire correction method of Finnish Artillery General [[Vilho Petter Nenonen]], which enabled easy fire correction and quick changes of targets.&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt; At the critical ''Ihantala'' sector of the battle, the Finnish defenders managed to concentrate their fire to the extent of smashing the advancing Soviet spearhead.&lt;ref name="Jatkosota"/&gt; The clever fire control system enabled as many as 21 batteries, totaling some 250 guns, to fire at the same target simultaneously in the battle; the fire controller did not need to be aware of the location of individual batteries to guide their fire, which made quick fire concentration and target switching possible. The Finnish artillery fired altogether over 122,000 rounds of ordnance. This concentration was considered a world record at the time.&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt; These fire missions managed to halt and destroy Soviet forces that were assembling at their jumping off points. On thirty occasions the Soviet forces destroyed were larger than battalion size.{{sfn|Nenye ''et al.''|2016|p=243}}

According to ''Bitva za Leningrad 1941–1944'' ("The Battle of [[Saint Petersburg|Leningrad]]") edited by Lieutenant General S.P. Platonov:&lt;ref name="Platonov"&gt;{{cite book |author=Platonov, S.P. (editor) |year=1964 |title=Битва за Ленинград ("The Battle of Leningrad") |publisher=Voenizdat Ministerstva oborony SSSR}}&lt;/ref&gt;

''"The repeated offensive attempts by the Soviet Forces failed ... to gain results. The enemy succeeded in significantly tightening its ranks in this area and repuls[ing] all attacks of our troops ... During the offensive operations lasting over three weeks, from June 21 to mid-July, the forces of the right flank of the Leningrad front failed to carry out the tasks assigned to them on the orders of the Supreme Command issued on June 21."''

By this time the Finnish army had concentrated half its artillery in the area, along with the army's only armoured division, with [[StuG III]] assault guns as its primary weapon, and the German 303 [[Sturmgeschütz]] Brigade. The defenders now finally had the new German [[anti-tank weapons]] that were previously kept in storage. The Finnish also made good use of German [[Panzerschreck]] anti-tank weapons. With these weapons the Finnish destroyed a large number of Soviet tanks-including 25 in one afternoon engagement.&lt;ref name="Philip Jowett p.14"/&gt;

On July 2 the Finns intercepted a radio message that the [[63rd Guards Rifle Division]] and 30th Armored Brigade were about to launch an attack on July 3 at 04:00 hours. The following morning, two minutes before the supposed attack, 40 Finnish and 40 German bombers bombed the Soviet troops, and 250 guns fired a total of 4,000 artillery shells into the area of the Soviets. On the same day, beginning at 06:00, 200 Soviet planes and their infantry attacked the Finnish troops. By 19:00 the Finnish troops had restored their lines.&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt;

On July 6 the Soviet forces had some success, despite the Finnish 6th Division having 18 artillery battalions and one heavy battery for their defence. However, the Soviets were thrown back the following day, and their counterattacks at 13:30 and 19:00 that day did not amount to anything. By July 7, the focus of the Soviet attacks was already moving to the area of Vuoksi, and the Soviets now began transferring their best troops to the [[Battle of Narva (1944)|Narva front]] in Estonia, to fight the Germans and the [[20 SS|Estonians]]. From July 9, the Soviet troops no longer attempted a break-through. Nevertheless, some fighting continued.&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt; Soviet forces were ordered to cease offensive operations and take up defensive positions on July 10 as the Stavka redeployed forces to the Baltic fronts, where the Red Army was encountering "fierce German and Baltic resistance."&lt;ref&gt;[[#FAW2006|Jowett &amp; Snodgrass (2006)]]. p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Losses==
Finnish sources estimate that the Soviet army lost about 600&lt;ref name="Philip Jowett p.14"/&gt; tanks in the Battle of Tali-Ihantala, mainly to air attacks, artillery, and close defence weapons. Between 284 and 320 Soviet aircraft were shot down.&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt; {{#tag:ref| &lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt; Writes exactly “Finnish and German Air Forces destroyed together 569 enemy air planes during the summer 1944 battles in Karelian Isthmus.  Of these more than half were shot down during the Tali-Ihantala battle.” From that we can assume that the number is something between 284 - 320|group="Notes"}}

The Finnish army reported that 8,561 men were wounded, missing, and/or killed in action. According to Finnish historian Ohto Manninen, the Soviets reported their losses as about 18,000–22,000 killed or wounded, based on the daily and 10-day summary casualty reports of the Soviet 21st Army. The uncertainty about casualties rises from the fact that 25 percent of the forces of the 21st Army didn't participate in the battle.&lt;ref name="Manninen"&gt;[[Ohto Manninen|Manninen, Ohto]], ''Molotovin cocktail, Hitlerin sateenvarjo'', 1994, {{ISBN|951-37-1495-0}}, Painatuskeskus&lt;/ref&gt; In addition to the losses of the Soviet 21st Army, the [[6th Rifle Corps]] of the Soviet 23rd Army that attacked east of the 21st Army closer to Vuoksi waterway suffered 7905 casualties, of which 1458 were [[killed in action]] (KIA) and 288 [[missing in action]] (MIA), without taking the losses of its supporting formations into account.&lt;ref name="raunio_kilin_def"&gt;{{cite book |title= Jatkosodan puolustustaisteluja 1942–44|last1=Raunio |first1=Ari |last2=Kilin |first2=Juri |year=2008 |publisher=Otavan Kirjapaino Oy |location=Keuruu |isbn=978-951-593-070-5 |page=192}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Impact==

The cease-fire between the Soviet Union and Finland began at 07:00, September 4, 1944, although for the following 24 hours the Red Army failed to comply with it.&lt;ref name="Jakobson" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.kevos4.com/Part%2012%20End%20of%20Hostilities.htm Part 12 End of Hostilities for the Continuation War]&lt;/ref&gt;

According to historians Jowett &amp; Snodgrass, Mcateer, Lunde, and Alanen &amp; Moisala, the Battle of Tali-Ihantala, along with other Finnish victories (in the battles of [[Battle of Vyborg Bay (1944)|Vyborg Bay]], [[Battle of Vuosalmi|Vuosalmi]], [[Battle of Nietjärvi|Nietjärvi]], and [[Battle of Ilomantsi|Ilomantsi]]) achieved during the period, finally convinced the Soviet leadership that conquering Finland was proving difficult, and not worth the cost;&lt;ref name="Jowett 2006 p. 14"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Mcateer-184"&gt;[[#Mcacteer|Macteer (2009)]] p. 184&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Lunde-379"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Moisala|Moisala &amp; Alanen (1988)]] pp. 154–155, 258–261&lt;/ref&gt; the battle was possibly the single most important battle fought in the Continuation War, as it largely determined the final outcome of the war, allowing Finland to conclude the war with relatively favorable terms&lt;ref name="Lunde-379"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Jakobson"&gt;[[Max Jakobson|Jakobson, Max]], ''Säkerhetspolitik och historia'', 2007, {{ISBN|978-91-7224-061-2}}, Hjalmarson &amp; Högbergs Bokförlag AB, Essay pp. 164–177 Avvärjningsegern, defensive victory&lt;/ref&gt; and continue its existence as an autonomous, democratic, and independent nation.&lt;ref name="Lunde-379"&gt;[[#Lunde|Lunde (2011)]] p. 379&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[[#Moisala|Moisala &amp; Alanen (1988)]] p. 260&lt;/ref&gt; Finnish researchers state that Soviet sources, such as [[prisoner of war|POW]] interviews, prove that the Soviets intended to advance all the way to Helsinki.&lt;ref name="moisala-85"&gt;[[#Moisala|Moisala &amp; Alanen (1988)]] pp. 85, 152–154&lt;/ref&gt; There also existed an order from Stavka to advance far beyond the borders of 1940.&lt;ref name=Zolotarev/&gt;

According to Lunde, one of the reasons leading to the Soviet failure was the Finns were able to intercept the Soviet radio messages and to forewarn and prompt the Finnish Army to put up a firmly resolved defense.&lt;ref name="Lunde-306"&gt;[[#Lunde|Lunde (2011)]] p. 306&lt;/ref&gt; Also, the existence of the Finnish [[Salpa Line|Salpa Defence Line]] was an important factor in the peace negotiations in autumn 1944.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.battlevault.com/Events/Wolfkrieg-09/WK-09%20Player%20List_files/German/Rob_Prince_Hist.pdf{{Dead link|date=November 2018 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Russian historian Nikolai Baryshnikov contests this mainstream view and has argued that such views exaggerate the significance and misrepresent the outcome of the Finnish defensive battles of 1944, including the Battle of Tali-Ihantala. According to him, conquering Finland was not one of the known goals of the Soviet offensive.&lt;ref name=Baryshnikov/&gt;&lt;ref name=Glantz/&gt;&lt;ref name=Erickson/&gt; According to [[Sergei Shtemenko|General Shtemenko]], the goal was to create a threat to Helsinki and other major political and economic centers in Finland, not conquer the country.&lt;ref name=Baryshnikov/&gt; According to Baryshnikov, after transferring most of their available forces to the Karelian Isthmus and receiving significant aid from Germany, the Finns managed to slow down and stop the Soviet offensive on the Isthmus before it reached the [1940 post- Winter War] Finnish border.&lt;ref name=Baryshnikov/&gt; This boosted the morale of the Finnish troops, who were previously constantly retreating.&lt;ref name=Baryshnikov/&gt; According to Baryshnikov, Finnish propaganda soon started talking about a victory, and after the war this claim of achieving a victory in stopping the Soviets from conquering Finland became an official theme in Finnish historiography.&lt;ref name=Baryshnikov/&gt; 
Baryshnikov's view is not supported by the vast majority of historians.&lt;ref name="Mcateer-184"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Lunde-306"/&gt;&lt;ref name="moisala-152"/&gt;

==Related operations==
{{See also|Battle of Tienhaara|Battle of Vyborg Bay (1944)|l2=Battle of Vyborg Bay|Battle of Vuosalmi}}

On June 22, Soviet forces began [[Operation Bagration|a wide-front push into Eastern Poland and Belorussia]].

At the same time, the Soviet 59th Army attacked the islands in [[Battle of Vyborg Bay (1944)|Vyborg Bay]] from July 4 on, and after several days of fighting forced the vastly outnumbered Finnish forces out from most of the islands&lt;ref name=Baryshnikov/&gt;&lt;ref name="Lunde-307"/&gt; while suffering heavy losses.&lt;ref name="Lunde-307"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |title= Jatkosodan puolustustaisteluja 1942–44|last1=Raunio |first1=Ari |last2=Kilin |first2=Juri |year=2008 |publisher=Otavan Kirjapaino Oy |location=Keuruu |isbn=978-951-593-070-5 |pages=204–205}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, the Soviet attack aimed at crossing Vyborg Bay was a failure as the Soviet troops were thrown back by the German [[122nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|122nd Division]] of the [[Finnish V Corps|V AK]].&lt;ref name="Lunde-307"&gt;[[#Lunde|Lunde (2011)]] p. 307&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="moisala-143"&gt;[[#Moisala|Moisala &amp; Alanen (1988)]] pp. 143–147&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Soviet 23rd Army]] attempted to start the crossing of the [[River Vuoksi]] on July 4 at [[Battle of Vuosalmi|Vuosalmi]], but due to the Finnish defense at Äyräpää Ridge, it was unable to start the crossing before July 9.&lt;ref name="Lunde-308"/&gt;&lt;ref name="moisala-147"&gt;[[#Moisala|Moisala &amp; Alanen (1988)]] pp. 147–152&lt;/ref&gt; Even with the crossing completed, the Soviet forces consisting of elements from three Soviet divisions were not able to expand the beachhead against the defending [[Finnish 2nd Division (Continuation War)|Finnish 2nd Division]], which was later reinforced.&lt;ref name="Koskimaa"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Lunde-308"&gt;[[#Lunde|Lunde (2011)]] pp. 308–309&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="moisala-147"/&gt; The unsuccessful Soviet breakthrough attempts continued there until July 21.&lt;ref name="Lunde-308"/&gt;

In addition to Tali-Ihantala, the Finnish front line held fast at [[Kivisilta]] and [[Battle of Tienhaara|Tienhaara]] to the north of Vyborg Bay.&lt;ref name="Lunde-289"&gt;[[#Lunde|Lunde (2011)]] p. 289&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="moisala-134"&gt;[[#Moisala|Moisala &amp; Alanen (1988)]] p. 134&lt;/ref&gt; There was further [[Battle of Nietjärvi|heavy fighting]] on the northeast side of [[Lake Ladoga]], and in the [[Battle of Ilomantsi]] the Finns were able to encircle two Soviet divisions, though most of the troops were able to escape.&lt;ref name="Lunde-299"&gt;[[#Lunde|Lunde (2011)]] p. 299&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="moisala-127"&gt;[[#Moisala|Moisala &amp; Alanen (1988)]] pp. 127–129&lt;/ref&gt;

On July 12, Soviet troops received an order to stop their attempts to advance and to dig in. Soon, Finnish scouts noticed trains with empty cars advancing towards Vyborg to take troops away from the Finnish front. They were needed for the great push towards Berlin.&lt;ref name="Lunde-306"/&gt;

The Finnish government declined further negotiations in late June and did not ask for peace until the Soviet offensive had been stopped. The Finnish government instead used the Ryti-Ribbentrop agreement to strengthen Finnish forces.&lt;ref name="Lunde-end"&gt;[[#Lunde|Lunde (2011)]] pp. 303–304, 309, 314&lt;/ref&gt; Only after the Soviet offensive had been stopped on all primary fronts, was President Ryti ready to resign on July 28. He, together with leading social-democrat Väinö Tanner, requested that [[Commander-in-Chief]] [[Carl Gustaf Emil Mannerheim|Mannerheim]] accept the candidacy for president, thus freeing Finland from the Ryti-Ribbentrop agreement, which had only been made as a personal pledge of President Ryti. Finland then could ask the Soviet Union for peace.&lt;ref name=Erickson/&gt;&lt;ref name="Lunde-end"/&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group="Notes"}}

==See also==
* ''[[Tali-Ihantala 1944]]'' (film)

==References==
{{reflist}}

=== Bibliography ===
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite web|last=Baryshnikov|first=Nikolai I.|script-title=ru:Феномен фальши: 'Победа в противостоянии'|trans-title=The Phenomenon of Lies: 'The Victory in the Confrontation'|year=2006|work=St. Petersburg and the Countries of Northern Europe|publisher=Russian Christian Humanitarian Academy|location=St. Petersburg|language=Russian|url=http://rhga.ru/science/conferences/y_confer/sever/2006/barishnikov2.htm|accessdate=September 15, 2011|ref=Baryshnikov}}
* {{cite book |last=Baryshnikov |first=Nikolai I. |script-title=ru:Блокада Ленинграда и Финляндия 1941–1944 |trans-title=Finland and the Siege of Leningrad, 1941–1944 |year=2002 |publisher=Johan Beckman Institute |location=St. Petersburg |isbn=952-5412-10-5 |language=Russian |url=http://v-n-baryshnikov.narod.ru/blokada.html|ref=Baryshnikov2}}
* {{cite book|last=Erickson|first=John|title=The Road to Berlin: Stalin's War with Germany|year=1993|publisher=Yale University Press|location=New Haven|isbn=0-300-07813-7|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=6UaU6ZLqK4UC&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|ref=Erickson}}
* {{cite book|last1=Glantz|first1=David|last2=House|first2=Jonathan|title=When Titans Clashed: How the Red Army Stopped Hitler|year=1998|publisher=Kansas University Press|location=Lawrence|isbn=978-0-7006-0899-7|ref=Glantz|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/whentitansclashe00glan_0}}
* {{cite book |last1=Jaques |first1=Tony |title=Dictionary of Battles and Sieges: F–O |publisher=Greenwood Press |location=Westport |year=2007 |isbn=978-0-313-33538-9 |ref=battlesandsieges}}
* {{cite book|last1=Jowett |first1=Philip |authorlink1= |
 last2=Snodgrass |first2=Brent |authorlink2= |
 title=Finland at War 1939–45 |
 publisher=Osprey Publishing |
 location=Botley |
 year=2006 |
 isbn=978-1-84176-969-1 |
 ref=FAW2006 |
 url=https://books.google.com/books?id=p58vtOKyVy8C&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
* {{cite book |last1=Lunde |first1=Henrik, O. |title=Finland's War of Choice |date=2011 |publisher=Casemate Pub |ref=Lunde |isbn=978-1-935149-48-4}}
* {{cite book |last1=Mcateer |first1=Sean |title=500 Days: The War in Eastern Europe, 1944–1945 |year=2009 |publisher=Dorrance Publishing |ref=Mcateer |isbn=978-1-4349-6159-4}}
* {{cite book |title=Kun hyökkääjän tie pysäytettiin (When the attacker was stopped) |last1=Moisala |first1=U.E. |last2=Alanen |first2=Pertti |year=1988 |publisher=Otava |location=Keuruu |isbn=951-1-10386-5 |ref=Moisala|language=Finnish}}
* {{cite book |last1=Nenye |first1=Vesa |last2=Munter |first2=Peter |last3=Wirtanen |first3=Toni |last4=Birks |first4=Chris |title=Finland at War. The Continuation and Lapland Wars 1941–45 |date=2016 |publisher=[[Osprey Publishing]] |location=[[Oxford]] |ref={{harvid|Nenye ''et al.''|2016}}}}
* {{cite book |script-title=ru:Битва за Ленинград: крупные операции, белые пятна, потери|trans-title=Battle for Leningrad: Large-scale Operations, White Spots, Casualties|last=Shigin|first=Grigoriy|year=2004|publisher=Poligon|location=St. Petersburg|isbn= 5-89173-261-0|language=Russian|ref=Shigin}}
* {{cite book|script-title=ru:Русский архив: Великая Отечественная. Ставка ВКГ: Документы и материалы 1944–1945.|trans-title=Russian Archive. The Great Patriotic War. STAVKA. Documents and Materials 1944–45|editor=Zolotarev, V. A.|location=Moscow|publisher=Terra|year=1999|isbn=5-300-01162-2|language=Russian|ref=Zolotarev}}
&lt;!--TEMPLATE-- *{{cite book|last1= |first1= |authorlink1= |
 last2= |first2= |authorlink2= |
 title= |
 publisher= |
 year= |
 isbn= |
 ref=NAME |
 url= }}
--&gt;
{{Refend}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tali-Ihantala, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Continuation War]]
[[Category:Finland in World War II]]
[[Category:Continuation War]]
[[Category:1944 in Finland]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:June 1944 events]]
[[Category:July 1944 events]]
[[Category:Karelo-Finnish Soviet Socialist Republic]]</text><sha1>s0nja8ps7rusmdkf950u6xprmuacqh6</sha1></revision></page>