<page><title>Operation Torch</title><ns>0</ns><id>73236</id><revision><id>967117850</id><parentid>966843814</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-11T07:24:12Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Mathglot</username><id>2544398</id></contributor><comment>Add nav template {{Liberation of France}}.</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="57373" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Allied landing operations in French North Africa during World War II}}
{{multiple issues|
{{more citations needed|date=August 2017}}
{{External links|date=December 2019}}}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=September 2019}}
{{Use British English|date=January 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Operation Torch
|partof= the [[North African Campaign]] of the [[Second World War]]
|image=Operation Torch - map.jpg
|image_size=300px
|caption=A map showing landings during the operation
|date=8–16 November 1942
|place=[[French Morocco]] and [[French Algeria]]
|result= [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] victory
|territory = Anglo-American occupation of Morocco and Algeria&lt;br /&gt;Free France control of [[French West Africa]]&lt;br /&gt;[[Case Anton|German and Italian occupation of southern France]]
|combatant1 = {{flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}
* {{flagcountry|British Raj}}
{{flagcountry|Free France}}
'''Naval only:'''&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Canada|1921}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagdeco|Netherlands}} [[Dutch government-in-exile|Netherlands]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Australia}}
|combatant2 = {{flagdeco|Vichy France}} [[Vichy France]]
* {{flagdeco|Vichy France}} [[French Algeria|Algeria]]
* {{flagicon image|Civil ensign of French Morocco.svg}} [[French protectorate in Morocco|Morocco]]
'''Naval only:'''&lt;br&gt;{{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
|commander1 = {{nowrap|{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]]}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[George S. Patton]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Lloyd Fredendall]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Andrew Cunningham]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Kenneth Arthur Noel Anderson|Kenneth Anderson]]
|commander2 = {{flagicon|Vichy France}} [[François Darlan]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Vichy France}} [[Alphonse Juin]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Vichy France}} [[Charles Noguès]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Vichy France}} [[Frix Michelier]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Ernst Kals]]
|strength1 = '''Ground forces:'''&lt;br /&gt;107,000 troops&lt;br /&gt;33,000 in Morocco&lt;br /&gt;39,000 near Algiers&lt;br /&gt;35,000 near Oran&lt;br /&gt;'''Naval activity:'''&lt;br /&gt;350 warships&lt;br /&gt;500 transports&lt;br /&gt;'''Total: 850'''
|strength2 = '''Ground forces:'''&lt;br /&gt;125,000 troops&lt;br /&gt;210 tanks&lt;br /&gt;500 aircraft&lt;br /&gt;many [[shore batteries]] and artillery pieces&lt;br /&gt;'''Naval activity:'''&lt;br /&gt;{{nowrap|1 [[French battleship Jean Bart (1940)|battleship]] (partially armed)}}&lt;br /&gt;10 other warships&lt;br /&gt;11 submarines&lt;br /&gt;'''Germany:''' 14 submarines&lt;br /&gt;'''Italy''': 14 submarines&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.societaitalianastoriamilitare.org/COLLANA%20SISM/2015%20MATTESINI%20I%20sommergibili%20dell'asse%20e%20l'Operazione%20Torch%201942.pdf I sommergibili dell'Asse e l'Operazione Torch.]&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties1 = '''United States''':&lt;br /&gt;526 dead&lt;br /&gt;'''United Kingdom''':&lt;br /&gt;574 dead&lt;br /&gt;'''All Other Allies''':&lt;br /&gt;756 total wounded&lt;ref&gt;Atkinson, Rick. (2002). ''An Army at Dawn''. p. 159&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;1 escort carrier ({{HMS|Avenger|D14|6}}) sunk with loss of 516 men&lt;br /&gt; 4 destroyers lost&lt;br /&gt;[[Operation Reservist|2 sloops lost]]&lt;br /&gt;6 troopships lost&lt;br /&gt;[[HMS Algerine (J213)|1 minesweeper lost]]&lt;br /&gt;[[HMS Tynwald|1 auxiliary anti-aircraft ship lost]]
|casualties2 = '''Vichy France:'''&lt;br /&gt;1,346+ dead&lt;br /&gt;1,997 wounded&lt;br /&gt;several shore batteries destroyed&lt;br /&gt;all artillery pieces captured&lt;br /&gt;1 light cruiser lost&lt;br /&gt;5 destroyers lost&lt;br /&gt;6 submarines lost&lt;br /&gt;2 [[flotilla leader]]s lost&lt;br /&gt;'''Germany:''' 8 submarines lost by 17 November&lt;br /&gt;'''Italy:''' 2 submarines lost by 17 November&lt;ref&gt;''Granito'' and ''Emo''. ''Navi militari perdute'', Italian Navy Historical Branch, page 61-62.&lt;/ref&gt;
}}
{{Campaignbox North Africa}}
{{Campaignbox Free French}}
{{Campaignbox Vichy France Military in World War II}}
{{Campaignbox Mediterranean Campaign}}

'''Operation Torch''' (8–16 November 1942) was an [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] invasion of [[French North Africa]] during the [[Second World War]].  The French colonies in the area were dominated by the [[Vichy France|Vichy French]], formally aligned with Germany but of mixed loyalties. Reports indicated that they might support the Allies. The American General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]], commanding the operation, planned a three-pronged attack on [[Casablanca]] (Western), [[Oran]] (Center) and [[Algiers]] (Eastern), then a rapid move on [[Tunis]].

The Western Task Force encountered unexpected resistance and bad weather, but Casablanca, the principal French Atlantic naval base, was captured after a short siege. The Center Task Force suffered some damage to its ships when trying to land in shallow water but the Vichy French ships were sunk or driven off; Oran surrendered after bombardment by British battleships. The Eastern Task Force met less opposition because the [[French Resistance]] had staged a coup in Algiers and the Allies were able to push inland and compel surrender on the first day.

The success of Torch caused Admiral [[François Darlan]], commander of the Vichy French forces to order co-operation with the Allies, in return for being retained as High Commissioner, with many other Vichy officials keeping their jobs. Darlan was assassinated soon after and the [[Free French]] gradually came to dominate the government. Torch was a compromise operation that met the British objective of securing victory in North Africa while allowing American armed forces the opportunity to engage in the fight against Nazi Germany on a limited scale.&lt;ref&gt;Wilmott, H.P. p.&lt;/ref&gt; It was the first mass involvement of US troops in the [[Mediterranean and Middle East theatre of World War II|European–North African Theatre]], and saw the first major [[airborne assault]] carried out by the United States.

==Background==
&lt;!--[[Jewish exodus from Arab and Muslim countries]] links here--&gt;

The [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] planned an Anglo-American invasion of north-western Africa/[[Maghreb]]—[[Morocco]], [[Algeria]] and [[Tunisia]], territory nominally in the hands of the [[Vichy France|Vichy French]] government. With [[Second Battle of El Alamein|British forces advancing]] from Egypt, this would eventually allow the Allies to carry out a [[pincer movement|pincer operation]] against Axis forces in North Africa. The Vichy French had around 125,000 soldiers in the territories as well as coastal artillery, 210 operational but out-of-date tanks and about 500 aircraft, half of which were [[Dewoitine D.520]] fighters—equal to many British and U.S. fighters.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Watson|2007|p=50}}&lt;/ref&gt; These forces included 60,000 troops in Morocco, 15,000 in Tunisia, and 50,000 in Algeria, with coastal artillery, and a small number of tanks and aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.stamfordhistory.org/ww2_torch.htm "The Stamford Historical Society Presents: Operation Torch and the Invasion of North Africa"]&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, there were 10 or so warships and 11 submarines at [[Casablanca]].

The Allies believed that the Vichy French forces would not fight, partly because of information supplied by American [[Consul (representative)|Consul]] [[Robert Daniel Murphy]] in [[Algiers]]. The French were former members of the Allies and the American troops were instructed not to fire unless they were fired upon.{{sfn|Playfair|Molony|Flynn|Gleave|2004|pp=126, 141–42}}
However, they harbored suspicions that the Vichy French navy would bear a grudge over the British [[attack on Mers-el-Kebir]] in 1940. An assessment of the sympathies of the French forces in North Africa was essential, and plans were made to secure their cooperation, rather than resistance. German support for the Vichy French came in the shape of air support. Several ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' bomber wings undertook anti-shipping strikes against Allied ports in [[Algiers]] and along the North African coast.

General [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]] was given command of the operation, and he set up his headquarters in [[Gibraltar]]. The Allied Naval Commander of the Expeditionary Force would be Admiral [[Andrew Browne Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Sir Andrew Cunningham]]; his deputy was [[Vice-Admiral]] [[Sir Bertram Ramsay]], who would plan the amphibious landings.

Senior US commanders remained strongly opposed to the landings and after the western Allied [[Combined Chiefs of Staff]] (CCS) met in London on 30 July, 1942 General [[George Marshall]] and Admiral [[Ernest King]] declined to approve the plan. Marshall and other U.S. generals advocated the [[Operation Sledgehammer|invasion of northern Europe]] later that year, which the British rejected.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Husen|first1=editor, David T. Zabecki ; assistant editors, Carl O. Schuster, Paul J. Rose, William H. Van|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=gYDN-UfehEEC&amp;pg=PA1270&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwiNp_GU4vXLAhUBWxQKHd9CDkQQ6AEIPTAG#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=World War II in Europe : an encyclopedia|date=1999|publisher=Garland Pub.|isbn=9780824070298|page=1270}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Mackenzie|first1=S.P.|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=GsUFBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA55&amp;&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwicw4jk4PXLAhVBlhQKHepMDJUQ6AEINzAF#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=The Second World War in Europe: Second Edition|date=2014|publisher=Routledge|isbn=1317864719|pages=54–55}}&lt;/ref&gt; After Prime Minister [[Winston Churchill]] pressed for a landing in French North Africa in 1942, Marshall suggested instead to President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] that the U.S. abandon the [[Germany first]] strategy and take the offensive in the Pacific. Roosevelt said it would do nothing to help Russia.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last1=Ward|first1=Geoffrey C.|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=V73CAwAAQBAJ&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA402#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=The Roosevelts: An Intimate History|last2=Burns|first2=Ken|date=2014|publisher=Knopf Doubleday Publishing Group|year=|isbn=0385353065|location=|pages=402|chapter=The Common Cause: 1939-1944}}&lt;/ref&gt; With Marshall unable to persuade the British to change their minds,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=VRiYAAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA135&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwip0Jbc4vXLAhXIuBoKHXC4DYgQ6AEIQzAH#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false|title=Routledge Handbook of US Military and Diplomatic History|date=2013|publisher=Taylor and Francis|isbn=9781135071028|location=Hoboken|page=135}}&lt;/ref&gt; President Roosevelt gave a direct order that Torch was to have precedence over other operations and was to take place at the earliest possible date, one of only two direct orders he gave to military commanders during the war.

===Allied plans===

[[File:Operation Torch.jpg|thumb|A map of Allied convoys heading from the British Isles to North Africa.]]
Planners identified Oran, Algiers and Casablanca as key targets. Ideally there would also be a landing at Tunis to secure Tunisia and facilitate the rapid interdiction of supplies travelling via Tripoli to Rommel's forces in Libya. However, Tunis was much too close to the Axis airfields in Sicily and Sardinia for any hope of success. A compromise would be to land at Bône ([[Annaba]]) in eastern Algeria, some {{convert|300|mi|km}} closer to Tunis than Algiers. Limited resources dictated that the Allies could only make three landings and Eisenhower – who believed that any plan must include landings at Oran and Algiers – had two main options: either the western option, to land at Casablanca, Oran and Algiers and then make as rapid a move as possible to Tunis some {{convert|500|mi|km}} east of Algiers once the Vichy opposition was suppressed; or the eastern option, to land at Oran, Algiers and Bône and then advance overland to Casablanca some {{convert|500|mi|km}} west of Oran. He favoured the eastern option because of the advantages it gave to an early capture of Tunis and also because the Atlantic swells off Casablanca presented considerably greater risks to an amphibious landing there than would be encountered in the Mediterranean.

The Combined Chiefs of Staff, however, were concerned that should Operation Torch precipitate [[Spain during World War II|Spain]] to abandon neutrality and join the Axis, the Straits of Gibraltar could be closed cutting the entire Allied force's lines of communication. They therefore chose the Casablanca option as the less risky since the forces in Algeria and Tunisia could be supplied overland from Casablanca (albeit with considerable difficulty) in the event of closure of the straits.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eisenhower|1948|pp=88–89}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Marshall's opposition to Torch delayed the landings by almost a month, and his opposition to landings in Algeria led British military leaders to question his strategic ability; the Royal Navy controlled the Strait of Gibraltar, and Spain was unlikely to intervene as Franco was hedging his bets. The Morocco landings ruled out the early occupation of Tunisia. Eisenhower told Patton that ''the past six weeks were the most trying of his life''.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last = Smith | first = Jean Edward | title = Eisenhower in War and Peace | publisher = Random House | date = 2012 | location = New York | pages = 214–15 | isbn = 978-0-679-64429-3 }}&lt;/ref&gt; In Eisenhower's acceptance of landings in Algeria and Morocco, he pointed out that the decision removed the early capture of Tunis from the probable to only the remotely possible because of the extra time it would afford the Axis to move forces into Tunisia.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Eisenhower|1948|p=90}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Intelligence gathering===
In July 1941, [[Mieczysław Zygfryd Słowikowski|Mieczysław Słowikowski]] (using the codename "''Rygor''"—Polish for "Rigor") set up "[[Agency Africa]]", one of the Second World War's most successful intelligence organizations.&lt;ref&gt;Tessa Stirling ''et al.'', ''Intelligence Co-operation between Poland and Great Britain during World War II'', vol. I: ''The Report of the Anglo-Polish Historical Committee'', London, [[Vallentine Mitchell]], 2005&lt;/ref&gt; His Polish allies in these endeavors included Lt. Col. [[Gwido Langer]] and Major [[Maksymilian Ciężki]]. The information gathered by the Agency was used by the Americans and British in planning the amphibious November 1942 Operation Torch&lt;ref name="WSC_Closing the Ring"&gt;{{cite book|last=Churchill|first=Winston Spencer|title=The Second World War: Closing the Ring |year=1951|publisher=Houghton Mifflin Company, Boston|page=643}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Major General Rygor Slowikowski, ''In the Secret Service: The Lightning of the Torch'', The Windrush Press, London 1988, s. 285&lt;/ref&gt; landings in North Africa.

===Preliminary contact with Vichy French===
To gauge the feeling of the Vichy French forces, Murphy was appointed to the American consulate in Algeria. His covert mission was to determine the mood of the French forces and to make contact with elements that might support an Allied invasion. He succeeded in contacting several French officers, including [[General]] [[Charles Mast]], the French commander-in-chief in Algiers.

These officers were willing to support the Allies but asked for a clandestine conference with a senior Allied General in Algeria. [[Major General]] [[Mark W. Clark]]—one of Eisenhower's senior commanders—was dispatched to [[Cherchell]] in Algeria aboard the British submarine {{HMS|Seraph|P219|6}} and met with these Vichy French officers on 21 October 1942.

With help from the Resistance, the Allies also succeeded in slipping French General [[Henri Giraud]] out of Vichy France on HMS ''Seraph''—passing itself off as an American submarine—intending to offer him the post of commander in chief of French forces in North Africa after the invasion. However, Giraud would take no position lower than commander in chief of all the invading forces, a job already given to Eisenhower. When he was refused, he decided to remain "a spectator in this affair".

==Battle==
[[File:OPERATION-TORCH-OVERVIEW.png|center|650px|A map showing landings during Operation Torch.]]
The Allies organised three amphibious task forces to simultaneously seize the key ports and airports in Morocco and Algeria, targeting [[Casablanca]], [[Oran]] and Algiers. Successful completion of these operations was to be followed by an eastwards advance into Tunisia.

A Western Task Force (aimed at Casablanca) was composed of American units, with [[Major general (United States)|Major General]] [[George S. Patton]] in command and [[Rear Admiral]] [[Henry Kent Hewitt]] heading the naval operations. This Western Task Force consisted of the U.S. [[3rd Infantry Division (United States)|3rd]] and [[9th Infantry Division (United States)|9th Infantry Divisions]], and two battalions from the [[2nd Armored Division (United States)|U.S. 2nd Armored Division]] — 35,000&amp;nbsp;troops in a convoy of over 100&amp;nbsp;ships. They were transported directly from the United States in the first of a new series of [[UG convoys]] providing logistic support for the North African campaign.&lt;ref&gt;Hague 2000 pp. 179–80&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Supermarine Spitfire Mark Vs assembled by the Special Erection Party in Gibraltar for Operation Torch, 1942.jpg|thumb|240px|left|A shipment of 116 [[Supermarine Spitfire]]s sent by sea was assembled in just 11 days at [[Gibraltar International Airport|RAF North Front]], [[Gibraltar]]. Many of these Spitfires served with the [[United States Army Air Forces]], including the aircraft in the foreground, ''EP 365'' ([[308th Fighter Squadron|308th FS]], [[31st Fighter Group]]). ]]

The Center Task Force, aimed at Oran, included the U.S. [[509th Infantry Regiment (United States)|2nd Battalion, 509th Parachute Infantry Regiment]], the [[1st Infantry Division (United States)|U.S. 1st Infantry Division]], and the [[1st Armored Division (United States)|U.S. 1st Armored Division]]—a total of 18,500&amp;nbsp;troops. They sailed from the United Kingdom and were commanded by Major General [[Lloyd Fredendall]], the naval forces being commanded by [[Commodore (rank)|Commodore]] Thomas Troubridge.

Torch was, for propaganda purposes, a landing by U.S. forces, supported by British warships and aircraft, under the belief that this would be more palatable to French public opinion, than an Anglo-American invasion. For the same reason, Churchill suggested that British soldiers might wear U.S. Army uniforms, although there is no evidence that this tactic was implemented.&lt;ref name="mangold 159"&gt;Peter Mangold, 2012, ''Britain and the Defeated French: From Occupation to Liberation, 1940–1944'', London, I.B.Tauris, p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt; ([[Fleet Air Arm]] aircraft did carry [[United States military aircraft national insignia#Roundels|US "star" roundels]] during the operation,&lt;ref&gt;J. D. Brown, 1968, ''Carrier Operations in World War II: The Royal Navy'', London, Ian Allan, p. 93.&lt;/ref&gt; and two British destroyers flew the [[Flag of the United States|Stars and Stripes]].&lt;ref name="mangold 159"/&gt;) In reality, the Eastern Task Force—aimed at Algiers—was commanded by [[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieutenant-General]] [[Kenneth Arthur Noel Anderson|Kenneth Anderson]] and consisted of a brigade from the [[78th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|British 78th]] and the [[34th Infantry Division (United States)|U.S. 34th Infantry Divisions]], along with two British commando units ([[No. 1 Commando|No.&amp;nbsp;1]] and [[No. 6 Commando|No.&amp;nbsp;6 Commandos]]), together with the RAF Regiment providing 5 squadrons of infantry and 5 Light anti-aircraft flights, totalling 20,000&amp;nbsp;troops. During the landing phase, ground forces were to be commanded by U.S. Major General [[Charles W. Ryder]], [[Commanding officer|Commanding General]] (CG) of the 34th Division and naval forces were commanded by Royal Navy [[Vice-Admiral]] [[Sir Harold Burrough]].

[[U-boat]]s, operating in the eastern Atlantic area crossed by the invasion convoys, had been drawn away to attack trade [[convoy SL 125]].&lt;ref&gt;Edwards 1999 p. 115&lt;/ref&gt;
Aerial operations were split into two, east of [[Cape Tenez]] in Algeria, with British aircraft under [[Air Marshal]] Sir [[William Welsh (RAF officer)|William Welsh]] and west of Cape Tenez, all American aircraft under Major General [[Jimmy Doolittle]], under the direct command of Major General Patton. [[Curtiss P-40 Warhawk|P-40s]] of the [[33rd Fighter Group]] were launched from U.S. Navy escort carriers and landed at [[Port Lyautey]] on 10 November. Additional air support was provided by the carrier {{USS|Ranger|CV-4|6}}, whose squadrons intercepted Vichy aircraft and bombed hostile ships.

===Casablanca===
[[File:American ships landing during Operation Torch, November 1942 (26688233893).jpg|thumb|American ships preparing to land off Safi during Operation Blackstone]]
The Western Task Force landed before daybreak on 8 November 1942, at three points in Morocco: [[Safi, Morocco|Safi]] ([[Operation Blackstone]]), [[Mohammedia|Fedala]] ([[Operation Brushwood]], the largest landing with 19,000&amp;nbsp;men), and Mehdiya-[[Kenitra|Port Lyautey]] ([[Battle of Port Lyautey|Operation Goalpost]]). Because it was hoped that the French would not resist, there were no preliminary bombardments. This proved to be a costly error as French defenses took a toll on American landing forces. On the night of 7 November, pro-Allied General [[Antoine Béthouart]] attempted a ''[[coup d'etat]]'' against the French command in Morocco, so that he could surrender to the Allies the next day. His forces surrounded the villa of General [[Charles Noguès]], the Vichy-loyal high commissioner. However, Noguès telephoned loyal forces, who stopped the coup. In addition, the coup attempt alerted Noguès to the impending Allied invasion, and he immediately bolstered French coastal defenses.

[[File:Operation Torch - message from the president of United States to the citizens of Casablanca.jpg|thumb|A flyer in French and Arabic that was distributed by Allied forces in the streets of Casablanca, calling on citizens to cooperate with the Allied forces.]]
At Safi, the objective being capturing the port facilities to land the Western Task Force's medium tanks, the landings were mostly successful.{{sfn|Howe|1993|pp=97, 102}} The landings were begun without covering fire, in the hope that the French would not resist at all. However, once French coastal batteries opened fire, Allied warships returned fire. By the time the 3rd Battalion, [[67th Armored Regiment]] arrived, French snipers had pinned the assault troops (most of whom were in combat for the first time) on Safi's beaches. Most of the landings occurred behind schedule. Carrier aircraft destroyed a French truck convoy bringing reinforcements to the beach defenses. Safi surrendered on the afternoon of 8 November. By 10 November, the remaining defenders were pinned down, and the bulk of Harmon's forces raced to join the siege of Casablanca.

At Port-Lyautey, the landing troops were uncertain of their position, and the second wave was delayed. This gave the French defenders time to organize resistance, and the remaining landings were conducted under artillery bombardment. With the assistance of air support from the carriers, the troops pushed ahead, and the objectives were captured. At Fedala, weather disrupted the landings. The landing beaches again came under French fire after daybreak. Patton landed at 08:00, and the beachheads were secured later in the day. The Americans surrounded the port of Casablanca by 10 November, and the city surrendered an hour before the final assault was due to take place. Casablanca was the principal French Atlantic naval base after German occupation of the European coast. The [[Naval Battle of Casablanca]] resulted from a sortie of French cruisers, destroyers, and submarines opposing the landings. A cruiser, six destroyers, and six submarines were destroyed by American gunfire and aircraft. The incomplete French battleship {{Ship|French battleship|Jean Bart|1940|2}}—which was docked and immobile—fired on the landing force with her one working gun turret [[USS Massachusetts (BB-59)#Atlantic operations|until disabled by the 16-inch calibre American naval gunfire]] of USS ''Massachusetts'', the first such heavy-calibre shells fired by the [[United States Navy|U.S. Navy]] anywhere in World War II. Two U.S. destroyers were damaged.

===Oran===

[[File:Seatrain Lakehurst after discharging tanks at Safi North Africa.png|thumb|left|[[USS Lakehurst (APV-3/APM-9)#Ship usage in World War II and Vietnam|USS ''Lakehurst'']] (formerly ''Seatrain New Jersey''), after discharging medium tanks at Safi, Morocco.]]
The Center Task Force was split between three beaches, two west of Oran and one east. Landings at the westernmost beach were delayed because of a French convoy which appeared while the minesweepers were clearing a path. Some delay and confusion, and damage to landing ships, was caused by the unexpected shallowness of water and sandbars; although periscope observations had been carried out, no reconnaissance parties had landed on the beaches to determine the local maritime conditions. This helped inform subsequent amphibious assaults—such as [[Operation Overlord]]—in which considerable weight was given to pre-invasion reconnaissance.

The [[1st Ranger Battalion (United States)|U.S. 1st Ranger Battalion]] landed east of Oran and quickly captured the shore battery at [[Arzew]]. An attempt was made to land U.S. infantry at the harbour directly, in order to quickly prevent destruction of the port facilities and scuttling of ships. [[Operation Reservist]] failed, as the two [[Banff class sloop|''Banff''-class]] [[Sloop-of-war|sloops]] were destroyed by crossfire from the French vessels there. The Vichy French naval fleet broke from the harbor and attacked the Allied invasion fleet but its ships were all sunk or driven ashore.&lt;ref name="R&amp;C"&gt;Rohwer &amp; Hummelchen 1992 p. 175.&lt;/ref&gt; The commander of Reservist, Capt. F. T. Peters, was posthumously awarded the Victoria Cross for valour in leading the attack through Oran harbour in the face of point blank fire.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web | url=https://www.veterans.gc.ca/eng/remembrance/memorials/canadian-virtual-war-memorial/Detail/2495305 |title = Frederick Thornton Peters - the Canadian Virtual War Memorial - Veterans Affairs Canada|date = 20 February 2019}}&lt;/ref&gt; French batteries and the invasion fleet exchanged fire throughout 8–9 November, with French troops defending Oran and the surrounding area stubbornly; bombardment by the British battleships brought about Oran's surrender on 9 November.

====Airborne landings====
Torch was the first major airborne assault carried out by the United States. The [[509th Infantry Regiment (United States)|2nd Battalion, 509th Parachute Infantry Regiment]], aboard 39 [[Douglas C-47 Skytrain|C-47 Dakotas]], flew all the way from [[Cornwall]] in England, over [[Spain]], to drop near Oran and capture airfields at [[Tafraoui]] and [[Es Sénia|La Sénia]], respectively {{convert|15|mi}} and {{convert|5|mi|0}} south of Oran.{{sfn|Playfair|Molony|Flynn|Gleave|2004|pp=146–147, map 19}} The operation was marked by communicational and navigational problems owing to the anti-aircraft and beacon ship HMS ''Alynbank'' broadcasting on the wrong frequency.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite book|title=Operation Torch 1942: The invasion of French North Africa|last=Lane Herder|first=Brian|publisher=Bloomsbury Publishing|year=2017|isbn=9781472820556|pages=42}}&lt;/ref&gt; Poor weather over Spain and the extreme range caused the formation to scatter and forced 30 of the 37 air transports to land in the dry salt lake to the west of the objective.{{sfn|Playfair|Molony|Flynn|Gleave|2004|p=149}} Of the other aircraft, one pilot became disoriented and landed his plane in [[Gibraltar]]. Two others landed in [[French protectorate in Morocco|French Morocco]] and three in [[Spanish protectorate in Morocco|Spanish Morocco]], where another Dakota dropped its paratroopers by mistake. A total of 67 American troops were interned by [[Francisco Franco|Franco]]'s forces until February 1943. Tafraoui and La Sénia were eventually captured but the role played by the airborne forces in Operation Torch was minimal.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Airborne in World War II: An Illustrated History of America's|last=Haskew|first=Michael E.|publisher=McMillan|year=2017|isbn=9781250124470|pages=44}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Algiers===

====Resistance and coup====
As agreed at Cherchell, in the early hours of 8 November, the [[Géo Gras Group]], 400 mainly Jewish French Resistance fighters staged a coup in the city of Algiers.&lt;ref&gt;Documentary film presenting the dominant role of Jewish resistance fighters in Algiers&lt;/ref&gt; Starting at midnight, the force under the command of [[Henri d'Astier de la Vigerie]] and [[José Aboulker]] seized key targets, including the telephone exchange, radio station, governor's house and the headquarters of the [[19th Army Corps (France)|19th Corps]].

Robert Murphy took some men and then drove to the residence of General [[Alphonse Juin]], the senior French Army officer in North Africa. While they surrounded his house (making Juin a hostage) Murphy attempted to persuade him to side with the Allies. Juin was treated to a surprise: Admiral [[François Darlan]]—the commander of all French forces—was also in Algiers on a private visit. Juin insisted on contacting Darlan and Murphy was unable to persuade either to side with the Allies. In the early morning, the local Gendarmerie arrived and released Juin and Darlan.

====Invasion====
[[File:Near Algiers, "Torch" troops hit the beaches behind a large American flag "Left" hoping for the French Army not fire... - NARA - 195516.jpg|thumb|upright=1.3|American soldiers land near Algiers.  The soldier at the dune line is carrying a flag because it was hoped the French would be less likely to fire on Americans.]]

On 8 November 1942, the invasion commenced with landings on three beaches—two west of Algiers and one east. Under the command of Major-General Charles W. Ryder, commanding general of the U.S. 34th Infantry Division, the [[11th Infantry Brigade and Headquarters South East|11th Brigade Group]] from the British 78th Infantry Division, landed on the right hand beach, the US [[168th Infantry Regiment (United States)|168th Regimental Combat Team]], from the 34th Infantry Division, supported by 6 Commando and most of 1 Commando on the middle beach while the US [[39th Infantry Regiment (United States)|39th Regimental Combat Team]], also from the US 34th Infantry Division, supported by the remaining 5 troops from 1 Commando, landed on the left hand beach. The [[36th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|36th Brigade Group]] from the British 78th Infantry Division stood by in floating reserve.{{sfn|Playfair|Molony|Flynn|Gleave|2004|p=126, 140–41, map 18}} Though some landings went to the wrong beaches, this was immaterial because of the lack of French opposition. All the coastal batteries had been neutralized by the French Resistance and one French commander defected to the Allies. The only fighting took place in the port of Algiers, where in [[Operation Terminal]], two British destroyers attempted to land a party of US [[United States Army Rangers|Army Rangers]] directly onto the dock, to prevent the French destroying the port facilities and scuttling their ships. Heavy artillery fire prevented one destroyer from landing but the other was able to disembark {{nowrap|250 Rangers}} before it too was driven back to sea.&lt;ref name="R&amp;C"/&gt; The US troops pushed quickly inland and General Juin surrendered the city to the Allies at 18:00.

==Aftermath==

===Political results===
[[File:Operation Torch plaque persp.png|thumb|250px|A plaque commemorating Operation Torch at the [[American War Memorial, Gibraltar|American War Memorial]] in Gibraltar.]]

It quickly became clear that Giraud lacked the authority to take command of the French forces. He preferred to wait in Gibraltar for the results of the landing. However, Darlan in Algiers had such authority. Eisenhower, with the support of Roosevelt and Churchill, made an agreement with Darlan, recognizing him as French "High Commissioner" in North Africa. In return, Darlan ordered all French forces in North Africa to cease resistance to the Allies and to cooperate instead. The deal was made on 10 November, and French resistance ceased almost at once. The French troops in North Africa who were not already captured submitted to and eventually joined the Allied forces.&lt;ref&gt;Eisenhower, Dwight. Crusade in Europe, pp. 99–105, 107–10. New York: Doubleday, 1948.&lt;/ref&gt; Men from French North Africa would see much combat under the Allied banner as part of the [[French Expeditionary Corps (1943–44)|French Expeditionary Corps]] (consisting of 112,000 troops in April 1944) in the [[Italian Campaign (World War II)|Italian campaign]], where Maghrebis (mostly Moroccans) made up over 60% of the unit's soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;Paul Gaujac, ''Le Corps expéditionnaire français en Italie'', Histoire et collections, 2003, p. 31&lt;/ref&gt;

When [[Adolf Hitler]] learned of Darlan's deal with the Allies, he immediately ordered [[Case Anton|the occupation of Vichy France]] and sent troops to Tunisia.

The Eisenhower/Darlan agreement meant that the officials appointed by the Vichy regime would remain in power in North Africa. No role was provided for [[Free France]], which was supposed to be France's government-in-exile and had taken charge in other French colonies. That deeply offended [[Charles de Gaulle]], the head of Free France. It also offended much of the British and American public, who regarded all Vichy French as Nazi collaborators and Darlan as one of the worst. Eisenhower insisted, however, that he had no real choice if his forces were to move on against the Axis in Tunisia, rather than fight the French in Algeria and Morocco.

Though de Gaulle had no official power in North Africa, much of its population now publicly declared Free French allegiance, putting pressure on Darlan. On 24 December, [[Fernand Bonnier de La Chapelle]], a French resistance fighter and anti-fascist monarchist, assassinated Darlan. (Bonnier de La Chapelle was arrested on the spot and executed two days later.)

Giraud succeeded Darlan but, like him, replaced few of the Vichy officials. He even ordered the arrest of the leaders of the Algiers coup of 8 November, with no opposition from Murphy.

The French North African government gradually became active in the Allied war effort. The limited French troops in Tunisia did not resist German troops arriving by air; [[Jean-Pierre Esteva|Admiral Esteva]], the commander, obeyed orders to that effect from Vichy. The Germans took the airfields there and brought in more troops. The French troops withdrew to the west and, within a few days, began to skirmish against the Germans, encouraged by small American and British detachments who had reached the area. While that was of minimal military effect, it committed the French to the Allied side. Later, all French forces were withdrawn from action and properly reequipped by the Allies.

Giraud supported that but also preferred to maintain the old Vichy administration in North Africa. Under pressure from the Allies and de Gaulle's supporters, the French régime shifted, with Vichy officials gradually replaced and its more offensive decrees rescinded. In June 1943, Giraud and de Gaulle agreed to form the "''[[French Committee of National Liberation|Comité français de Libération nationale]]''" (CFLN), with members from both the North African government and from de Gaulle's "French National Committee". In November 1943, de Gaulle became head of the CFLN and ''de jure'' head of government of France and was recognized by the U.S. and Britain.

In another political outcome of Torch (and at Darlan's orders), the previously-Vichyite government of [[French West Africa]] joined the Allies.

===Military consequences===
====Toulon====
{{main|Scuttling of the French fleet in Toulon}}
One of the terms of the [[Second Armistice at Compiègne]] agreed to by the Germans was that southern France would remain [[zone libre|free of German occupation]] and governed by Vichy. The lack of determined resistance by the Vichy French to the Allied invasions of North Africa and the new policies of de Gaulle in North Africa convinced the Germans that France could not be trusted. Moreover, the Anglo-American presence in French North Africa invalidated the only real rationale for not occupying the whole of Metropolitan France since it was the only practical means to deny the Allies use of the French colonies. The Germans and the Italians [[Case Anton|immediately occupied]] southern France, and German troops moved to seize the French fleet in the port of Toulon from 10 November. The naval strength of the Axis in the Mediterranean would have been greatly increased if the Germans had succeeded in seizing the French ships, but every important ship was [[scuttling of the French fleet in Toulon|scuttled at dock]] by the French Navy before the Germans could take them.

====Tunisia====
{{Main|Tunisia Campaign}}
After the German and Italian occupation of Vichy France and their unsuccessful attempt to capture the interned French fleet at Toulon ([[scuttling of the French fleet in Toulon|Operation Lila]]), the French [[Army of Africa (France)|''Armée d’Afrique'']] sided with the Allies, providing a third corps ([[XIX Army Corps (France)|XIX Corps]]) for Anderson. Elsewhere, French warships, such as the battleship {{Ship|French battleship|Richelieu||2}}, rejoined the Allies.

On 9 November, Axis forces started to build up in Tunisia and were unopposed by the local French forces under General Barré. Wracked with indecision, Barré moved his troops into the hills and formed a defensive line from Teboursouk through Medjez el Bab and ordered that anyone trying to pass through the line would be shot. On 19 November, the German commander, [[Walter Nehring]], demanded passage for his troops across the bridge at Medjez and was refused. The Germans attacked the poorly-equipped French units twice and were driven back. However, the French had taken heavy casualties, and lacking artillery and armour, Barré was forced to withdraw.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Watson|2007|p=60}&lt;/ref&gt;

After consolidating in Algeria, the Allies [[Tunisia Campaign|struck into Tunisia]]. Elements of the [[First Army (United Kingdom)|British First Army]], under Lieutenant-General Kenneth Anderson, came to within {{convert|40|mi|km|0}} of [[Tunis]] before a [[counterattack]] at [[Djedeida]] thrust them back. In January 1943, German and Italian troops under [[Generalfeldmarschall]] [[Erwin Rommel]], retreating westward from [[Libya]], reached Tunisia.

The [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|British Eighth Army]] in the east, commanded by Lieutenant-General [[Bernard Montgomery]], stopped around [[Tripoli]] to allow reinforcements to arrive, build up the Allied advantage and repair its port. In the west, the forces of the First Army came under attack at the end of January, were forced back from the Faïd Pass and suffered a reversal at [[Battle of Sidi Bou Zid|Sidi Bou Zid]] on 14–15 February. Axis forces pushed on to Sbeitla and then to the [[Battle of Kasserine Pass|Kasserine Pass]] on 19 February, where the American II Corps retreated in disarray until heavy Allied reinforcements halted the Axis advance on 22 February. Fredendall was replaced by [[George Patton]].

[[General (United Kingdom)|General]] [[Harold Alexander, 1st Earl Alexander of Tunis|Sir Harold Alexander]] arrived in Tunisia in late February to take charge of the new [[18th Army Group]] headquarters, which had been created to take overall control of both the Eighth Army and the Allied forces already fighting in Tunisia. The Axis forces again [[Battle of Medenine|attacked eastward at Medenine]] on 6 March but were easily repulsed by the Eighth Army. Rommel advised Hitler to allow a full retreat to a defensible line but was denied, and, on 9 March, Rommel left Tunisia to be replaced by [[Jürgen von Arnim]], who had to spread his forces over {{convert|100|mi|km}} of northern Tunisia.

The setbacks at Kasserine forced the Allies to consolidate their forces and develop their [[line of communication|lines of communication]] and administration so that they could support a major attack. The First and Eighth Armies then attacked the Axis in April. Hard fighting followed, but the Allies cut off the Germans and Italians from support by naval and air forces between Tunisia and [[Sicily]]. On 6 May, as the culmination of [[Operation Vulcan]], the British took Tunis and American forces reached [[Bizerte]]. By 13 May, the Axis forces in Tunisia had surrendered. That opened the way for the [[Allied invasion of Sicily]] in July.

== Later influence ==
Despite Operation Torch's role in the war and logistical success, it has been largely overlooked in many popular histories of the war and in general cultural influence.&lt;ref name="ec" &gt;{{cite news|author1=R.B.S.|title=Remembering Operation Torch on its 75th anniversary|url=https://www.economist.com/blogs/democracyinamerica/2017/11/shining-light|accessdate=12 November 2017|work=[[The Economist]]|date=9 November 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[The Economist]]'' speculated that to be because French forces were the initial enemies of the landing, making for a difficult fit into the war's overall narrative in general histories.&lt;ref name="ec" /&gt;

The operation was America's first armed deployment in the [[Arab world]] since the [[Barbary Wars]] and, according to ''The Economist'', laid the foundations for America's postwar [[Middle East]] policy.&lt;ref name="ec" /&gt;

==Orders of battle==

===Western Task Force – Morocco===
{{multiple image
| direction = horizontal
| width = 230
| header = Ground and naval commanders for Western Task Force
| image1 = George_S._Patton_and_Rear_Admiral_H._Kent_Hewitt_cropped.jpg
| caption1 = Maj. Gen. George S. Patton and Rear Adm. H. Kent Hewitt aboard CA ''Augusta''
| align = 
| total_width = 
| alt1 = 
| image2 = 
| caption2 = 
}}

Vice Admiral [[H. Kent Hewitt]], USN&lt;ref&gt;Morison 1947, pp. 36–39&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Major General [[George S. Patton]], USA&lt;br /&gt;
'''Northern Attack Group (Mehedia)'''
* Brig. Gen. [[Lucian K. Truscott]] (9,099 officers and enlisted)
** [[60th Infantry Regiment (United States)|60th Infantry Regiment (Reinforced)]] of [[9th Infantry Division (United States)|9th Infantry Division]]
** 1st Battalion of [[66th Armor Regiment|66th Armored Regiment]] of [[2nd Armored Division (United States)|2nd Armored Division]]
** 1st Battalion of 540th Engineers

'''Center Attack Group (Fedhala)'''
* Maj. Gen. J.W. Anderson (18,783 officers and enlisted)
** [[3rd Infantry Division (United States)|3rd Infantry Division]]
*** [[7th Infantry Regiment (United States)|7th Infantry Regiment (Reinforced)]]
*** [[15th Infantry Regiment (United States)|15th Infantry Regiment (Reinforced)]]
*** [[30th Infantry Regiment (United States)|30th Infantry Regiment (Reinforced)]]

'''Southern Attack Group (Safi)'''
* Maj. Gen. [[Ernest N. Harmon]] (6,423 officers and enlisted)
** [[47th Infantry Regiment (United States)|47th Regimental Combat Team]] of [[9th Infantry Division (United States)|9th Infantry Division]]
** 3rd and elements of 2nd Battalion of [[67th Armored Regiment]] of [[2nd Armored Division (United States)|2nd Armored Division]]

===Central Task Force – Oran===
{{multiple image
 | direction = horizontal
 | width = 110
 | header = Ground and naval commanders for Central Task Force
 | image1 = Lloyd_fredendall.jpg
 | caption1 = Maj. Gen. Lloyd R. Fredendall
 | image2 = Rear_Admiral_Troubridge_1945_IWM_A_28419 cropped.jpg
 | caption2 = Commodore Thomas Troubridge
}}

Commodore [[Thomas Hope Troubridge]], RN&lt;ref&gt;Morison 1947, p. 223&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Major General [[Lloyd R. Fredendall]], USA&lt;br /&gt;
Approx. 39,000 officers and enlisted
* 1st Ranger Battalion
* 1st Armored Division, Maj. Gen. [[Orlando Ward]]
** Combat Command B
** 6th Armored Infantry Regiment
* 1st Infantry Division, Maj. Gen. [[Terry de la Mesa Allen, Sr.#World War II|Terry Allen]]
** 16th Infantry Regiment
** 18th Infantry Regiment
** 26th Infantry Regiment

===Eastern Task Force – Algiers===
{{multiple image
 | direction = horizontal
 | width = 110
 | header = Ground and naval commanders for Eastern Task Force
 | image1 = Charles_W._Ryder2.jpg
 | caption1 = Maj. Gen. Charles W. Ryder
 | image2 = Vice_Admiral_Sir_Harold_Martin_Burrough_A20779.jpg
 | caption2 = Rear Adm. Sir Harold M. Burrough
}}

Rear Admiral [[Harold Burrough|Sir Harold M. Burrough]], RN&lt;ref&gt;Morison 1947, p. 190&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Major General [[Charles W. Ryder]], USA&lt;br /&gt;
Approx. 33,000 officers and enlisted
* British (approx. 23,000)
** No. 1 Commando
** No. 6 Commando
** 5 squadrons of RAF Regiment
** 78th Infantry Division, Maj. Gen. [[Vyvyan Evelegh]]
*** 11th Infantry Brigade
*** 36th Infantry Brigade
* United States (approx. 10,000)
** 9th Infantry Division, Maj. Gen. [[Manton S. Eddy]]
*** 39th Infantry Regiment
** 34th Infantry Division, Maj. Gen. [[Charles W. Ryder]]
*** 135th Infantry Regiment
*** 168th Infantry Regiment

===French Army – Morocco===
* Fez Division (Maj. Gen. Maurice-Marie Salbert)
** 4th Moroccan Rifle Regiment
** 5th Moroccan Rifle Regiment
** 11th Algerian Rifle Regiment
** 1st Foreign Cavalry Regiment
* Meknès Division (Maj. Gen. Andre-Marie-François Dody)
** 7th Moroccan Rifle Regiment
** 8th Moroccan Rifle Regiment
** 3rd Moroccan Spahis Regiment
* Casablanca Division (Brig. Gen. [[Antoine Béthouart]])
** 1st Moroccan Rifle Regiment
** 6th Moroccan Rifle Regiment
** Colonial Moroccan Infantry Regiment
** 1st Hunters of Africa Regiment
* Marrakech Division (Brig. Gen. Henry Jules Jean Maurice Martin)
** 2nd Moroccan Rifle Regiment
** 2nd Foreign infantry Regiment
** 4th Moroccan Spahis Regiment

===French Army – Algeria===
* Algiers Division (Maj. Gen. [[Charles Mast]])
** 1st Algerian Rifle Regiment
** 9th Algerian Rifle Regiment
** 3rd Zouaves Regiment
** 2nd Hunters of Africa Regiment
** 1st Algerian Spahis Regiment
* Oran Division (Gen. Robert Boissau)
** 2nd Algerian Rifle Regiment
** 6th Algerian Rifle Regiment
** 15th Senegalese Rifle Regiment
** 1st Foreign Regiment
* Moroccan Division
** 7th Moroccan Rifle Regiment
** 3rd Algerian Rifle Regiment
** 4th Tunisian Rifle Regiment
** 3rd Foreign Rifle Regiment

==See also==
{{Portal|World War II|United States}}
* [[List of World War II Battles]]
* [[Mieczysław Zygfryd Słowikowski]]
* {{RMS|Mooltan||6}} Troopship
* [[North African Campaign timeline]]
* [[Operation Flagpole (World War II)]]
* [[Allied invasion of Sicily|Operation Husky]]
* [[Operation Kingpin (World War II)]]
* [[17th Armored Engineer Battalion]]
* [[Marching Regiment of the Foreign Legion]]

==References==
'''Notes'''
{{Reflist|30em}}
{{more footnotes|date=November 2011}}

==Bibliography==
::'''War Official reports'''
* Les Cahiers Français, ''La part de la Résistance Française dans les évènements d'Afrique du Nord'' (Official reports of French Resistance Group leaders who seized Algiers on 8 November 1942, to allow allied landing), Commissariat à l'Information of Free French Comité National, London, Aug. 1943.

::'''War correspondent report'''
* Melvin K. Whiteleather, ''Main street's new neighbors'', J.B. Lippincott Co., Philadelphia, 1945.

::'''Academic works'''
* {{Cite journal|first=Professeur José|last=Aboulker|author2=Levisse-Touzé, Christine|title=''8 novembre 1942: Les armées américaine et anglaise prennent Alger en quinze heures''|language=French|location=Paris|journal=Espoir|issue=n° 133|year=2002}}
* Aboulker, Professeur José, ''La victoire du 8 novembre 1942 La resistance et le débarquement des Alliés à Alger'', Editions du Félin=Paris 2012'
* {{Cite book|first=Bruce|last=Allen|title=Exit Rommel: The Tunisian Campaign, 1942–43|location=Mechanicsburg, PA|publisher= Stackpole Books|year=2007|isbn=978-0-8117-3381-6|series=Stackpole Military History Series|origyear=1999}}
* {{Cite book|last=Anderson|first=Charles R.|url=http://www.history.army.mil/brochures/algeria/algeria.htm|title=Algeria-French Morocco 8 November 1942-11 November 1942|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]|location=Washington|year=1993|id=CMH Pub 72-11|series=WWII Campaigns|isbn=0-16-038105-3}}
* {{Cite book|first=William B.|last=Breuer|title=Operation Torch: The Allied Gamble to Invade North Africa|location=New York| publisher=St.Martins Press|year=1985}}
* {{Cite book|first=J. D.|last=Brown|title=Carrier Operations in World War II: The Royal Navy|location=London| publisher=Ian Allan|year=1968}}
* {{Cite book|first=Professeur Yves Maxime|last=Danan|title=La Vie Politique à Alger de 1940 à 1944|language=French|location=Paris| publisher=L.G.D.J.|year=1963}}
* Danan, Professeur Yves Maxime,  ''République Française Capitale Alger,  1940-1944,  Souvenirs'',  L'Harmattan, Paris, 2019.
* {{cite book|first=Dwight D.|last=Eisenhower|title=Crusade in Europe|url=https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.226615|location=London|publisher=William Heinemann|year=1948|oclc= 559866864|ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|title=Dönitz and the Wolf Packs|url=https://archive.org/details/donitzwolfpacks0000edwa|url-access=registration|author=Edwards, Bernard|publisher=Brockhampton Press|year=1999|isbn=1-86019-927-5}}
* {{Cite book|first=Arthur L.|last=Funk|title=The Politics of Torch|publisher=University Press of Kansas|year=1974}}
* {{Cite book|title=The Allied Convoy System 1939–1945|author=Hague, Arnold|publisher=Naval Institute Press|year=2000|isbn= 1-55750-019-3}}
* {{Cite book|last=Howe|first=George F.|url=http://www.history.army.mil/html/books/006/6-1-1/index.html|title=North West Africa: Seizing the Initiative in the West|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]|location=Washington, D.C.|year=1993|origyear=1957|id=CMH Pub 6-1|lccn=57060021 |series=The United States Army in World War II |ref=harv}}
* {{Cite book|first=Christine|last=Levisse-Touzé|title=L'Afrique du Nord dans la guerre, 1939–1945|language=French|location=Paris| publisher=Albin Michel|year=1998}}
* {{Cite book|last=Lewis|first=Adrian S.|title=Omaha Beach: a flawed victory|year=2001|publisher=University of North Carolina Press|location=Chapel Hill|isbn=0-8078-2609-X}}
* {{Cite book|title=Command Decisions|editor=Kent Roberts Greenfield|url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/70-7_0.htm|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]]|year=2000|origyear=1960|id=CMH Pub 70-7|chapter=Chapter 7: The Decision to Invade North Africa (Torch)|first=Leo J.|last=Meyer|chapterurl=http://www.history.army.mil/books/70-7_07.htm}}
* {{Cite book|first=Henri|last=Michel|title=Darlan|publisher=Hachette|location=Paris|year=1993}}
* {{Cite book|last=Morison|first=Samuel Eliot|title=Operations in North African Waters: Vol. II of History of United States Naval Operations in World War II|year=1947|publisher=Little, Brown and Co.|location=Boston|isbn=0-7858-1303-9}}
* {{Cite book|first=Sam|last=Moses|title=At All Costs; How a Crippled Ship and Two American Merchant Mariners Turned the Tide of World War II|publisher=Random House|date=November 2006}}
* O'Hara, Vincent P. (2015) ''Torch: North African and the Allied Path to Victory'' (Annapolis: Naval Institute, 2015). x, 371 pp.
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Playfair|Molony|Flynn|Gleave|2004}}
|first1=Major-General I. S. O. |last1=Playfair |author1-link=Ian Stanley Ord Playfair |first2=Brigadier C. J. C. |last2=Molony |first3=Captain F. C. |last3=Flynn R.N. |first4=Group Captain T. P. |last4=Gleave |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=J. R. M. |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |title=The Mediterranean and Middle East: The Destruction of the Axis Forces in Africa |volume=IV |series=History of the Second World War United Kingdom Military Series |orig-year=1st [[HMSO]] 1966 |year=2004 |location=Uckfield, UK |publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |isbn=1-84574-068-8 |lastauthoramp=y}}
* {{Cite book|title=Chronology of the War at Sea 1939–1945|author1=Rohwer, J. |author2=Hummelchen, G. |lastauthoramp=yes | publisher=Naval Institute Press|year=1992|isbn=1-55750-105-X}}
* Salinas, Alfred (2013) ''Les Américains en Algérie 1942–1945'' (in French), L'Harmattan, Paris
* {{Cite book|last=Watson|first=Bruce Allen|title=Exit Rommel: The Tunisian Campaign, 1942–43| location=Mechanicsburg, PA|publisher=Stackpole Books|year=2007|isbn=978-0-8117-3381-6|series= Stackpole Military History Series|origyear=1999|oclc=40595324|ref=harv}}
*{{Cite book|last=Willmott|first=H.P.|url=https://archive.org/details/june194400will|title=June, 1944|publisher=Blandford Press|year=1984|isbn=0-7137-1446-8|location=Poole, Dorset}}

::'''General'''
* {{cite book|first=Rick|last=Atkinson|authorlink=Rick Atkinson|title=An Army at Dawn|publisher=Henry Holt|year=2002|isbn=0-8050-6288-2|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/armyatdawnwarinn00atki}}

'''Further reading'''
* [http://www.history.army.mil/books/70-7_07.htm The Decision to Invade North Africa (TORCH)] part of ''[http://www.history.army.mil/books/70-7_0.htm Command Decisions]'' a publication of the [[United States Army Center of Military History]]
* [http://www.history.army.mil/brochures/algeria/algeria.htm Algeria-French Morocco] a book in the ''U.S. Army Campaigns of World War II'' series of the [[United States Army Center of Military History]]

==External links==
{{Prone to spam|date=December 2019}}
{{Z148}}&lt;!--     {{No more links}}

       Please be cautious adding more external links.

Wikipedia is not a collection of links and should not be used for advertising.

     Excessive or inappropriate links will be removed.

 See [[Wikipedia:External links]] and [[Wikipedia:Spam]] for details.

If there are already suitable links, propose additions or replacements on
the article's talk page.

--&gt;
{{Commons|Operation Torch|Operation Torch}}
{{Wikisource|US Army Campaigns of World War II Series/Algeria-French Morocco}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050208000842/http://www.usswashington.com/dl08no42c.htm A detailed history of 8 November 1942]
* [http://www.combinedops.com/Torch.htm Combined Ops]
* [http://airgroup4.com/operation-torch.htm History and photos of the operations of the USS Ranger and its Air Group during Operation Torch]
* [http://www.ynetnews.com/articles/0,7340,L-4621656,00.html (North African Jewish Resistance to Nazis and the Holocaust)]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20050819234512/http://war.megabaze.com/page_html/009-Algerian%20Resistance-1942 The accord Franco-Américan of Messelmoun (in French)]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090503114041/http://www.remuseum.org.uk/corpshistory/rem_corps_part16.htm Royal Engineers Museum] Royal Engineers and Second World War (Operation Torch){{dead link|date=September 2011}}
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/rep/TORCH/DDE-Torch.html Report of the Commander-in-Chief Allied Forces to the Combined Chief of Staff on Operations in North Africa]
* [http://www.historynet.com/magazines/world_war_2/3026106.html Operation Torch: Allied Invasion of North Africa] article by Williamson Murray
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090108083606/http://www.american-divisions.com/doc.asp?documentid=138&amp;pagenumber=1 Eisenhower's report on operation Torch]
* [http://www.wwiireels.com Operation TORCH Motion Pictures from the National Archives]
* [http://www.defensemedianetwork.com/stories/operation-torch-ybsob-decoded/ Operation Torch]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20131005164526/http://desertwar.net/operation-torch.html Operation Torch World War II]

{{Liberation of France}}
{{France topics}}
{{World War II}}
{{Dwight D. Eisenhower}}
{{Authority control}}

{{Coord|35.085|-2.029|type:country|display=title}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Torch, Operation}}
[[Category:1942 in Gibraltar]]
[[Category:1942 in Tunisia]]
[[Category:Algeria in World War II]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations involving the United States]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:Gibraltar in World War II]]
[[Category:Invasions by Australia]]
[[Category:Invasions by Canada]]
[[Category:Invasions by the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Invasions by the United States]]
[[Category:Military battles of Vichy France]]
[[Category:Military history of Algeria]]
[[Category:Military history of Canada during World War II]]
[[Category:Military history of Morocco]]
[[Category:Morocco in World War II]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:North African Campaign]]
[[Category:November 1942 events]]
[[Category:Tunisia in World War II]]
[[Category:United States Army Rangers]]
[[Category:World War II invasions]]
[[Category:Land battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom|O]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom|O]]</text><sha1>mct8oonnjqd57s0bn2gi41prgm3olay</sha1></revision></page>