<page><title>Slovak National Uprising</title><ns>0</ns><id>44215204</id><revision><id>965390036</id><parentid>964926984</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-01T01:39:20Z</timestamp><contributor><username>AyodeleA1</username><id>30697721</id></contributor><comment>/* Aftermath */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="28153" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=November 2019}}
{{short description|Rebellion}}
{{More footnotes|date=April 2009}}
{{infobox military conflict
| conflict          = Slovak National Uprising
| partof            = the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
| image             = Povstalecka kolona.jpg
| image_size        = 305px
| caption           = Convoy of Slovak insurgent army vehicles near Kelemeš (today part of Prešov)
| date              = 29 August – 28 October 1944
| place             = [[Slovak Republic (1939–1945)|Slovakia]]
| coordinates       = 
| map_type          = 
| latitude          = 
| longitude         = 
| map_size          = 
| map_caption       = 
| map_label         = 
| territory         = 
| result            = German and  [[Hlinka Guard]] victory
*Continued partisan resistance
| status            = 
| combatant1        = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Slovakia|1938}} [[Slovak Republic (1939–45)|Slovak Republic]]
*[[File:Flag of the Hlinka party (1938–1945) variant 2.svg|23px]] [[Hlinka Guard Emergency Divisions|POHG]]
| combatant2        = {{flagicon|Czechoslovakia}} {{illm|First Czechoslovak Army in Slovakia|cs|1. československá armáda na Slovensku}}&lt;br&gt;
*[[File:Roundel of Slovak Insurgent (1944).svg|18px]] [[Slovak Insurgent Air Force]]
 {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Soviet Air Force]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[US Army Air Force]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[office of Strategic Services|OSS]]
| commander1        = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Gottlob Berger]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Hermann Höfle (SS Obergruppenführer)|Hermann Höfle]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Slovakia|1938}} [[Otomar Kubala]]
| commander2        = {{flagicon|Czechoslovakia}} [[Ján Golian]]{{KIA}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Czechoslovakia}} [[Rudolf Viest]]{{KIA}}
| units1            = 
| units2            = 
| units3            = 
| strength1         = 40,000, later increased to 83,000
| strength2         = 18,000 initially, later increased to 78,000
| casualties1       = 4200 killed, 5,000 wounded, 300 captives
| casualties2       = 12,000 KIA and murdered in reprisals
| notes             = 
}}

{{History of Slovakia}}
The '''Slovak National Uprising''' ({{lang-sk|Slovenské národné povstanie}}, abbreviated SNP) was an armed insurrection organized by the Slovak [[Resistance during World War II|resistance]] movement during [[World War II]]. This resistance movement was represented mainly by the members of the [[Democratic Party (Slovakia, 1944)|Democratic Party]], but also by [[Czech Social Democratic Party|social democrat]]s and [[Communist Party of Slovakia (1939)|Communists]], albeit on a smaller scale. It was launched on 29 August 1944 from [[Banská Bystrica]] in an attempt to resist German troops that had occupied Slovak territory and to overthrow the [[collaborationist]] government of [[Jozef Tiso]]. Although the resistance was largely defeated by German forces, guerrilla operations continued until the [[Soviet Army]], [[I Corps (Czechoslovakia)|Czechoslovak Army]] and [[Romania in World War II|Romanian Army]] liberated [[Fascist Slovakia]] in 1945.

In the post-war period, many political entities, mainly the Communists, attempted to "hijack" the uprising to their credit. The [[Communism|Communist]] regime in [[Czechoslovak Socialist Republic|Czechoslovakia]] presented the Uprising as an event initiated and governed by Communist forces.&lt;ref&gt;Plevza, V. (Editor): ''History of Slovak National Uprising 1944'' - 5. vol. Bratislava, Nakladateľstvo Pravda, 1985, pp. 488-496 (In Slovak)&lt;/ref&gt; Slovak ultranationalists, on the other hand, claim that the uprising was a plot against the Slovak nation, as one of its main objectives was to oust the regime of the puppet Slovak state and reestablish [[Czechoslovakia]], in which Slovaks were dominated by [[Czechs]]. In fact, many factions fought in the uprising, the largest of which were units of the [[Slovak Republic (1939–45)#Slovak forces during the campaign against the Soviet Union|Slovak Army]], Democratic resistance, Communist [[Partisan (military)|partisans]], and international forces. Given this factionalization, the Uprising did not have unambiguous popular support. Yet the participants and supporters of the Uprising represented every religion, class, age, and [[antinazism|anti-Nazi]] political faction of the Slovak nation.&lt;ref&gt;Mičev, S. (Ed.), 2009, ''Slovak National Uprising 1944.'' Múzeum SNP, Banská Bystrica, p. 123 (In Slovak)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Lacko, M.: ''Slovak National Uprising 1944''. Bratislava, Slovart, 2008 (In Slovak)&lt;/ref&gt;

==Preliminaries==

[[Edvard Beneš]], leader of the [[Czechoslovak government in exile]] in London, initiated preparations for a possible revolt in 1943 when he contacted dissident elements of the [[Slovak Army]]. In December 1943, various groups that would be involved in the uprising&amp;mdash;the government in exile, Czechoslovak democrats and Communists, and the Slovak army&amp;mdash;formed the underground {{illm|Illegal Slovak National Council|sk|Ilegálna Slovenská národná rada}}, and signed the so-called "Christmas Treaty", a joint declaration to recognize Beneš' authority and to recreate Czechoslovakia after the war. The council was responsible for creating the preparatory phase of the uprising.

In March 1944, Slovak army [[Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Ján Golian]] took charge of the preparations. Conspirators stockpiled money, ammunition and other supplies in military bases in central and eastern Slovakia. The rebelling forces called themselves [[Czechoslovak Forces of the Interior]] and the {{illm|First Czechoslovak Army|cs|1. československá armáda na Slovensku}}. Approximately 3,200 Slovak soldiers deserted and joined partisan groups or the [[Soviet Army]]. In April 1944, [[History of the Jews in Slovakia|Slovak Jews]] [[Rudolf Vrba]] and [[Alfred Wetzler]] escaped from [[Auschwitz]] and published a [[Vrba–Wetzler report|detailed report]] about the operation of the gas chambers at Auschwitz.

In summer 1944, the partisans intensified their war against German occupation forces, mainly in the mountains of north-central Slovakia. In July, Soviet troops in [[Poland]] began to advance towards Slovakia. By August 1944, Soviet troops were at [[Krosno]], Poland, within {{convert|40|km|mi}} of the northeastern Slovak border.

Two heavily armed divisions of the Slovak Army, together with the entire eastern [[Slovenske Vzdusne Zbrane|Slovak Air Force]], were deliberately relocated to [[Prešov]] in north-eastern Slovakia in the summer of 1944 to execute one of two planned options to begin the uprising. The two options were:

# Capture [[Dukla Pass]] (joining Poland and Slovakia through the Carpathian Mountains) when the Soviet ([[1st Ukrainian Front]] under [[Marshal of the Soviet Union|Marshal]] [[Ivan Konev]]) arrived.
# As ordered by Golian, capture Dukla Pass immediately and hold the pass against any German forces until the Soviet Army could arrive.

[[Colonel]] {{illm|Viliam Talský|sk}} was the chief of staff of the two divisions. He had agreed in advance with the insurrection's army leadership and the uprising planning committee of the Slovak National Council to execute either of these two plans, depending on the circumstances. On 23 August 1944, Romania, initially Slovakia's ally, [[King Michael's Coup|changed sides]] in favor of the Allies. On 28 August 1944 in [[Martin, Slovakia|Martin]], a group of Communist partisans under Soviet direction killed 24 German soldiers returning from Romania.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.valka.cz/10796-Misia-generala-Otta Slovak language article about the event in Martin]&lt;/ref&gt; The next day, German troops began to occupy Slovakia to put down the rebellion. German arrangements for the occupation were completed a few weeks earlier.

At 19:00 hours on 29 August 1944, Slovak [[Defence Minister]] [[General]] [[Ferdinand Čatloš]] announced on state radio that Germany had occupied Slovakia. At 20:00, Golian sent the coded message to all units to begin the uprising. But instead of adhering to the agreed plan, on 30 August Colonel Talský and the entire eastern Slovak Air Force flew to a prearranged landing zone in Poland to join the Soviet Army, and abandoned the two divisions at Prešov. The two divisions, left in chaos and without leadership, were quickly disarmed on the afternoon of 30 August without a single shot. Consequently, the uprising commenced prematurely and lost a crucial component of their plan, as well as the two most heavily armed divisions.

==Forces==

[[File:Nastupeni povstalci.jpg|thumb|Slovak mutineer forces in 1944]]
Accounts of the exact numbers of combatants vary. At first, the rebel [[Slovak partisans|Slovak partisan]] forces consisted of an estimated 18,000 soldiers. The total increased to 47,000 after mobilization on 9 September 1944, and later to 60,000, plus 18,000 partisans from over 30 countries. The [[Slovak Insurgent Air Force]] had a small number of mostly obsolete planes.

In addition to Slovak forces ({{illm|First Czechoslovak Army|cs|1. československá armáda na Slovensku}}), the combatants included various other groups: escaped French prisoners of war, [[Soviet partisan]]s, and [[Special Operations Executive]] (SOE) and [[Office of Strategic Services]] (OSS) operatives. The Slovak side had to use mostly [[biplane]]s and improvised [[armored train]]s to fight against the better equipped German weapons. In addition to Soviet aid, United States [[B-17 Flying Fortress]] bombers, escorted by [[North American P-51 Mustang|North American P-51B Mustang's]] landed at [[Sliač Airport|Tri Duby]] airfield on 7 October 1944 and brought supplies and three OSS teams, headed by a naval officer, Lieutenant James Holt Green. They also took out 18 Allied pilots shot down over Slovakia&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|title=Joseph Morton, Associated Press, Followed the Dawes Mission to Mauthausen - History? Because it's Here!|url=http://historybecauseitshere.weebly.com/joseph-morton-associated-press-followed-the-dawes-mission-to-mauthausen.html|last=Warnes|first=Kathy|date=2013-06-01|url-status=live|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20130601025028/http://historybecauseitshere.weebly.com/joseph-morton-associated-press-followed-the-dawes-mission-to-mauthausen.html|archive-date=2013-06-01|access-date=2020-05-03}}&lt;/ref&gt; and five French partisans.

After the uprising started, Czechoslovak officials in exile discussed the possibility of bringing in Czechoslovak units deployed on the Eastern Front with the Soviet Army. Two such units were brought in. On 15–17 September 1944, the {{illm|1st Czechoslovak Independent Fighter Regiment|cs|První československý samostatný stíhací letecký pluk}} landed at {{illm|Zolná|cs|Zolná (Zvolen)}} airfield near [[Zvolen]] with 21 [[Lavochkin La-5]] fighters.&lt;ref&gt;Fajtl, F. ''První doma'' ("First at home"), Naše vojsko, Prague, 1980, 291 pp. (in Czech)&lt;/ref&gt; Later the {{illm|2nd Czechoslovak Parachute Brigade|cs|2. československá paradesantní brigáda v SSSR}} was transferred from the Carpathians, arriving 25 September to 15 October.

==Course of the uprising==

===Uprising begins===
[[File:Map Slovak National Uprising in 1944 - first days.png|thumb|left|upright=1.4|Situation map in first days of Slovak National Uprising]]
Rebels began the uprising on 29 August at 8:00&amp;nbsp;p.m. under the command of Ján Golian. They entered [[Banská Bystrica]] in the morning of 30 August and made it their headquarters. German troops disarmed the Eastern Slovak Army on 31 August. Many of the soldiers were sent to camps in Germany while others escaped and joined the Soviet-controlled partisans or returned home. On 5 September Ján Golian became the commander of all the rebel forces in Slovakia and was given the rank of General. Slovak forces in central Slovakia mobilized 47,000 men. His first analysis of the situation predicted that insurgents could resist German attacks for about two weeks.&lt;ref&gt;Nosko J.: Thus insurgent army fought (Takto bojovala povstalecká armáda). Bratislava, NVK International, spol. s.r.o. 1994, p. 77 (In Slovak)&lt;/ref&gt;

Guards at the three main labor camps, Sereď, Nováky, and Vyhne, fled at the beginning of the uprising and most Jewish prisoners left.{{sfn|Nižňanský|Rajcan|Hlavinka|2018|pp=876, 882}}{{sfn|Nižňanský|Rajcan|2018|pp=888}} About 1,600{{sfn|Bauer|2002|p=139}} to 2,000{{sfn|Rothkirchen|2001|p=600}} Jews fought as partisans, ten percent of the total insurgent force.{{sfn|Kubátová|2014|p=516}} Fifteen percent of Jewish partisans were killed.{{sfn|Rothkirchen|2001|p=600}} Many Jewish partisans hid their religious affiliation due to antisemitism in the partisan movement.{{sfn|Fatran|1996|p=119}}

By 10 September the rebels had gained control of large areas of central and eastern Slovakia, including two [[airfield]]s, which were used by the Soviet Air Force to fly in equipment.

===Momentum lost===
[[File:Karte Slowakischer Nationalaufstand 1944 - Schlussoffensive.png|thumb|upright=1.8|The German offensive retakes territory.]]
The pro-German government of Tiso remained in power in [[Bratislava]]. Germany moved 40,000 [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] soldiers under [[Gottlob Berger]] to suppress the uprising, which detained and disarmed two Slovak divisions and 20,000 soldiers that had been supposed to secure the mountain passes to help the Red Army. Beneš had met with Stalin and Molotov in Moscow in December 1943 to secure Soviet support for the uprising, but Soviet premier Joseph Stalin and the Soviet military command [[Stavka]] failed to deliver the needed support on time to the insurgent army and even blocked Western offers of military aid, as they had done only a few weeks earlier during the [[Warsaw uprising]]. Meanwhile, General Konev and the Soviet partisan headquarters in Kiev, Ukraine, continued to undermine the Slovak insurgent army by ordering partisan groups operating in forward positions in Slovakia to conduct operations independently of the Slovak insurgent army and avoid coordination. The Soviet-led partisans even demanded and took desperately needed weapons and munitions that had been stored for the Slovak uprising. The vast majority of Soviet airdrops of weapons over insurgent-held territory in Eastern and Northern Slovakia were quickly confiscated by [[Soviet partisans]] and little ended up in the hands of the much stronger and better trained Slovak insurrectional army.{{citation needed|date=November 2011}}

[[File:Ján Golian2.jpg|thumb|right|upright|[[Ján Golian]], one of the main organizers and commander of the rebel forces.]]
On 8 September, the Red Army began an [[Battle of the Dukla Pass|offensive on the Dukla Pass]] on the Slovak-[[Poland|Polish]] border and tried to fight through the [[Carpathian Mountains]] to penetrate into Slovakia. This poorly planned and late action resulted in tremendous casualties on both sides and became bogged down for nearly two months.

Beneš, the Soviet partisans, and various Slovak factions began to argue among themselves, each seeking operational control. Despite repeated efforts, General Golian could not persuade the different sides to coordinate their efforts. General [[Rudolf Viest]] flew in and took command on 7 October, with Golian becoming his second-in-command. Viest could not control the situation when political rivalries resurfaced in the face of military failure.

The uprising also coincided with the stalling of the Soviet summer offensive, the failure of the Warsaw Uprising, and other troubles on the side of the Western allies. The Red Army and its Czechoslovak allies failed to quickly penetrate the Dukla Pass despite fierce fighting between 8 September and 28 October; they suffered 85,000 casualties (21,000 dead). The Czechoslovak government in exile failed to convince Western allies to ignore Stalin's obstructionism and send more supplies to the area.

On 17 September two B-17 Flying Fortresses flew in the OSS mission of [[Lieutenant]] James Holt-Green. The SOE team of Major John Sehmer followed the next day on its way to [[Hungary]]. Their reports confirmed the suspicions of Western Allies that the situation of the uprising was worsening.

===Counteroffensive===

[[File:Jozef Tiso decorates German soldiers.jpg|thumb|Jozef Tiso decorates German soldiers in Banská Bystrica after the uprising]]
On 19 September, German command replaced SS-Obergruppenführer [[Gottlob Berger|Berger]], who had been in charge of the troops fighting the Uprising, with General [[Hermann Höfle (SS general)|Höfle]]. By that time Germans had 48,000 soldiers; they consisted of eight German divisions, including four from the [[Waffen-SS]] and one pro-Nazi Slovak formation.

On 1 October the rebel army was renamed the {{illm|First Czechoslovak Army in Slovakia|cs|1. československá armáda na Slovensku}}, in order to symbolize the beginning of the Czech-Slovak reunification that would be recognized by the Allied forces.

A major German counteroffensive began on 17–18 October when 35,000 German troops entered the country from Hungary, which had been under German military occupation since 19 March 1944. Stalin demanded that his advancing Second Ukrainian Front led by General Malinovsky be immediately diverted from Eastern Slovakia to Budapest. The western advance of Soviet forces came to a sudden halt in late October 1944, when Stalin's interests focused on Hungary, Austria and Poland rather than Slovakia or the Czech lands. By the end of October, Axis forces (six German divisions and one pro-Nazi Slovak unit) had taken back most of the territory from the insurgents and encircled the fighting groups. Battles cost at least 10,000 casualties on both sides.

Insurgents had to evacuate Banská Bystrica on 27 October just prior to the German takeover. SOE and OSS agents retreated to the mountains alongside the thousands of others fleeing the German advance. The rebels prepared to change their strategy to that of guerrilla warfare. On 28 October, Viest sent London a message that said the organized resistance had ended. On 30 October, General Höfle and President Tiso celebrated in Banská Bystrica and awarded medals to German soldiers for their part in the suppression of the uprising.

The main OSS team, along with two British officers and a soldier, a Czech officer, two American civilians and war correspondent [[Joseph Morton (correspondent)|Joseph Morton]] were cornered near the village of [[Polomka]] by Christmas 1944, under heavy winter conditions, and captured on 26 December by a 300-man strong German SS anti-partisan unit.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; All of them were taken to [[Mauthausen concentration camp]], where the agents and soldiers were executed in January 1945. Morton's life was not spared, and he was also shot to death on 24 January 1945.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=North|first=Don|url=https://books.google.com.ar/books?id=2XnP3ypSH6MC&amp;pg=PT82&amp;lpg=PT82&amp;dq=%22Holt+Green%22+%22taken+prisoner%22+Slovakia&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=XrXE0E71DT&amp;sig=ACfU3U0Fh6DA9ZPPOnFuKFfKQYAq4sq7vQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwjN7fezhpjpAhULGbkGHUHRCAwQ6AEwAXoECAoQAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=%22Holt%20Green%22%20%22taken%20prisoner%22%20Slovakia&amp;f=false|title=Inappropriate Conduct: Mystery of a Disgraced War Correspondent|date=2013-01-09|publisher=iUniverse|isbn=978-1-4759-5540-8|language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Aftermath===
{{further|The Holocaust in Slovakia#Resumption of deportations|Kremnička and Nemecká massacres}}
[[Image:Banska Bystrica.Denkmal, 2006.jpg|thumb|left|Memorial of the Slovak National Uprising in [[Banská Bystrica]]]]
[[Image:Pancierovy vlak-Zvolen.jpg|thumb|right|[[Armored train Hurban]] (replica) preserved in [[Zvolen]]]]
Nonetheless, partisans and the remains of the regular forces continued their efforts in the mountains. In retaliation, [[Einsatzgruppe H]] and the [[Hlinka Guard Emergency Divisions]] executed many Slovaks suspected of aiding the rebels as well as Jews who had avoided deportation until then, and destroyed 93 villages on suspicion of [[collaboration]]. Several villages were burned to the ground and all their inhabitants were murdered, as in [[Ostrý Grúň]] and [[Kľak]] (21 January 1945) or [[Kalište (Slovakia)|Kalište]] (18 March 1945). A later estimate of the death toll was 5,304 and authorities discovered 211 [[mass grave]]s that resulted from those atrocities. The largest executions occurred in [[Kremnička]] (747 killed, mostly Jews and Roma) and [[Nemecká]] (900 killed).

On 3 November, the Germans captured Golian and Viest in [[Pohronský Bukovec]]; they later interrogated and executed them.

SOE and OSS teams eventually united and sent a message in which they requested immediate assistance. Germans surrounded both groups on 25 December and captured them. Some of the men were summarily executed. Germans took the rest to [[Mauthausen-Gusen concentration camp|Mauthausen]] [[concentration camp]] where they were tortured and executed.

The German victory only postponed the eventual downfall of the pro-Nazi regime. Six months later, the [[Red Army]] had overrun Axis troops in Czechoslovakia. By December 1944 Romanian and Soviet troops had driven German troops out of southern Slovakia in the [[Battle of Budapest]]. On 19 January 1945, the Red Army took [[Bardejov]], [[Svidník]], [[Prešov]] and [[Košice]] in Eastern Slovakia. On 3–5 March they had taken over northwest Slovakia. On 25 March they entered Banská Bystrica and on 4 April marched into [[Bratislava]].

The main military objectives were not achieved due to the bad timing of the uprising and lack of cooperation by Soviet partisans. This undermined the plans of the insurrectional Slovak army. The guerrilla struggle, however, tied up significant German forces that could otherwise have reinforced the [[Wehrmacht]] on the eastern front against the advancing [[1st Ukrainian Front]] to the north and south of Slovakia. Nevertheless, much of Slovakia was left devastated by the Uprising and the German counter-offensive and occupation.

29 August is a [[Slovak National Uprising Anniversary|national holiday]] in Slovakia.  Starting in 1947 various [[Commemorative coins of Czechoslovakia]] were minted in remembrance of the uprising.

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

===Sources===
* {{cite book |last1=Bauer |first1=Yehuda |title=Rethinking the Holocaust |date=2002 |publisher=Yale University Press |isbn=978-0-300-09300-1 |ref=harv |language=en |location=New Haven }}
*{{cite journal |last1=Fatran |first1=Gila |title=Die Deportation der Juden aus der Slowakei 1944–1945|trans-title=The deportation of the Jews from Slovakia 1944–45 |language=de |journal=Bohemia: Zeitschrift für Geschichte und Kultur der Böhmischen Länder |date=1996 |issue=37 |pages=98–119 |url=https://biblio.hiu.cas.cz/documents/19854 |ref=harv}}
*{{cite book |last1=Kubátová |first1=Hana |editor1-last=Henry |editor1-first=Patrick |title=Jewish Resistance Against the Nazis |date=2014 |publisher=[[Catholic University of America Press]] |location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=978-0-8132-2589-0 |pages=504–518 |ref=harv |language=en |chapter=Jewish Resistance in Slovakia, 1938–1945}}
*{{cite encyclopedia|last1=Nižňanský |first1=Eduard |last2=Rajcan |first2=Vanda  |first3=Ján |last3=Hlavinka |entry=Nováky|editor1-last=Megargee|editor1-first=Geoffrey P. |editor2-last=White|editor2-first=Joseph R.|editor3-last=Hecker|editor3-first=Mel |series=[[Encyclopedia of Camps and Ghettos]] |volume=3 |title=Camps and Ghettos under European Regimes Aligned with Nazi Germany |isbn=978-0-253-02373-5|location=Bloomington |publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum |ref=harv |date=2018|pp=874–877|translator-last=Kramarikova|translator-first=Marianna}}
*{{cite encyclopedia|last1=Nižňanský |first1=Eduard |last2=Rajcan |first2=Vanda  |first3=Ján |last3=Hlavinka |entry=Sereď|editor1-last=Megargee|editor1-first=Geoffrey P. |editor2-last=White|editor2-first=Joseph R.|editor3-last=Hecker|editor3-first=Mel |series=[[Encyclopedia of Camps and Ghettos]] |volume=3 |title=Camps and Ghettos under European Regimes Aligned with Nazi Germany |isbn=978-0-253-02373-5|location=Bloomington |publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum |ref=harv |date=2018|pp=881–883|translator-last=Kramarikova|translator-first=Marianna}}
*{{cite encyclopedia|last1=Nižňanský |first1=Eduard |last2=Rajcan |first2=Vanda |entry=Vyhne|editor1-last=Megargee|editor1-first=Geoffrey P. |editor2-last=White|editor2-first=Joseph R.|editor3-last=Hecker|editor3-first=Mel |series=Encyclopedia of Camps and Ghettos |volume=3 |title=Camps and Ghettos under European Regimes Aligned with Nazi Germany |isbn=978-0-253-02373-5|location=Bloomington |publisher=United States Holocaust Memorial Museum |ref=harv |date=2018|pp=887–888|translator-last=Kramarikova|translator-first=Marianna}}
*{{cite encyclopedia|entry=Slovakia|last1=Rothkirchen|first1=Livia|pp=595–600 |editor1-last=Laqueur |editor1-first=Walter |editor2-last=Baumel |editor2-first=Judith Tydor |title=Holocaust Encyclopedia |date=2001 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven |language=en|isbn=978-0-300-08432-0|ref=harv}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite journal |first1=Martin D. |last1=Brown |title=The SOE and the failure of the Slovak National Uprising |url=http://www.historytoday.com/martin-d-brown/soe-and-failure-slovak-national-uprising |journal=History Today |year=2004 |volume=54 |issue=12}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Findor |first1=Andrej |title=(De)Constructing Slovak National Mythology|url=https://www.ceeol.com/search/article-detail?id=274909 |journal=Sociológia - Slovak Sociological Review |date=2002 |issue=3 |pages=195–208 |id={{CEEOL|274909}} |language=English |issn=0049-1225|url-access=registration}} 
*{{cite book |last1= Prečan |first1=Vilém|chapter=The Slovak National Uprising: the most dramatic moment in the nation’s history |editor1-last=Teich |editor1-first=Mikuláš |editorlink=Mikuláš Teich|editor2-last=Kováč |editor2-first=Dušan |editor2-link=Dušan Kováč |editor3-last=Brown |editor3-first=Martin D. |title=Slovakia in History |title-link=Slovakia in History  |date=2011 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=Cambridge |isbn=978-1-139-49494-6}}
*{{cite journal |last1=Radonic |first1=Ljiljana |title=Slovak and Croatian invocation of Europe: the Museum of the Slovak National Uprising and the Jasenovac Memorial Museum |journal=Nationalities Papers |date=20 November 2018 |volume=42 |issue=3 |pages=489–507 |doi=10.1080/00905992.2013.867935}}
*{{cite book |last1=Syrný |first1=Marek |title=Slovenské národné povstanie: Slovensko a Európa v roku 1944 |date=2014 |publisher=Muzeum Slovenského Národného Povstania |isbn=978-80-89514-30-4 |language=sk}}

==External links==
{{commons|Slovak National Uprising}}
*[http://www.muzeumsnp.sk/?language=en Slovak National Uprising Museum] in Banská Bystrica
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20080316011438/http://www.czechpatriots.com/csmu/ Czechoslovak military units in USSR] (1942–1945)
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20070827101214/http://www.snp.sk/index_eng.php Slovak National Uprising Anniversary website]
*{{YouTube|jHov_bRfqQA|Modern Russian movie interviewing soldiers seen in the World War II German propaganda video}} (Czech)

{{World War II}}
{{Czechoslovakia in World War Two}}
{{Holocaust Slovakia}}

[[Category:Slovak National Uprising| ]]
[[Category:1944 in Slovakia]]
[[Category:Slovakia during World War II]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Eastern European World War II resistance movements]]
[[Category:Military history of Slovakia during World War II]]
[[Category:Uprisings during World War II]]
[[Category:Eastern European theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:World War II resistance movements]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Czechoslovakia]]
[[Category:August 1944 events]]
[[Category:September 1944 events]]
[[Category:October 1944 events]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Hungary]]
[[Category:Slovak independence movement]]</text><sha1>mlimcqp4rgck6wbdl3yeaeb881qjpkt</sha1></revision></page>