<page><title>Tallinn Offensive</title><ns>0</ns><id>17194406</id><revision><id>927893393</id><parentid>927122983</parentid><timestamp>2019-11-25T13:16:33Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Pamrel</username><id>35261024</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="21416" xml:space="preserve">{{Coord|59|26|N|24|44|E|display=title}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict   = Tallinn Offensive
| image      =
| image_size = 300px
| caption    = A Soviet map of the operation.
| partof     = [[Eastern Front (World War II)]]
| place      = [[Estonia]]
| date       = 17–26 September 1944
| result     = Soviet victory
| combatant1 = {{flag|Nazi Germany|name=Germany}}
* {{flagicon image|Estnische Legion crop.svg}} [[20th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Estonian)|Estonian conscripts]],&lt;br /&gt; [[estonian Auxiliary Police|auxiliary police]], border guards&lt;br /&gt; and [[Omakaitse|militia]]
| combatant2  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| combatant3  = {{flagicon|Estonia}} [[Estonia]]n pro-independence troops
| commander1  = [[Ferdinand Schörner]]
| commander2  = [[Leonid Govorov]]
| commander3  = [[Johan Pitka]]
| strength1   = 50,000 troops&lt;ref name=mitcham/&gt;&lt;br /&gt;50 vessels&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;
| strength2   = 195,000 troops&lt;ref name=losses/&gt;
| strength3   = 2,000 troops&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;
| casualties1 =
| casualties2 =
| campaignbox =
{{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Campaignbox Leningrad and Baltics 1941-1944}}
{{Campaignbox Estonia 1944}}
}}
The '''Tallinn Offensive''' ({{lang-ru|Таллинская наступательная операция}}) was a strategic offensive by the [[Red Army]]'s [[2nd Shock Army|2nd Shock]] and [[8th Army (Soviet Union)|8th]] Armies and the [[Baltic Fleet]] against the [[Wehrmacht|German]] [[Battle of Narva (1944)#Formation of Army Detachment "Narwa"|Army Detachment ''Narwa'']] and [[Estonia]]n units in mainland Estonia on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]] on 17–26 September 1944. Its German counterpart was the abandonment of the Estonian territory in a retreat codenamed '''Operation Aster''' (German: '''''Unternehmen Aster''''').

The Soviet offensive commenced with the Soviet 2nd Shock Army breaching the defence of the II Army Corps along the [[Emajõgi]] River in the vicinity of [[Tartu]]. The defenders managed to slow the Soviet advance sufficient for Army Detachment ''Narwa'' to be evacuated from mainland Estonia in an orderly fashion.&lt;ref name=mcateer&gt;{{Cite book|author=Sean M. Mcateer|title=500 Days: The War in Eastern Europe, 1944-1945|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Bg8drRyDGhEC&amp;q=Estonia#v=snippet&amp;q=Estonia&amp;f=false|publisher=Red Lead Press|location=Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania|year=2008|page=273}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 18 September, the [[Constitution of Estonia|constitutional]] [[Estonian Government in Exile|Government of Estonia]] captured the [[Toompea|government buildings]] in Tallinn from the Germans and the city was abandoned by the German forces by 22 September. The Leningrad Front seized the capital and took the rest of mainland Estonia by 26 September 1944.

==Background==

===Prelude===
{{Main|Battle of Narva (1944)|Operation Bagration|Tartu Offensive|Riga Offensive (1944)}}

Attacks by the [[Leningrad Front]] had pushed [[Army Group North]] west of [[Lake Peipus]], resulting in a series of [[Battle of Narva (1944)|operations around Narva]].&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; In the south, Soviet forces had advanced towards the Baltic coast at the end of [[Operation Bagration]] the [[Belarus|Belorussian]] strategic offensive (June–August 1944) against [[Army Group Centre]].&lt;ref name=losses&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://lib.ru/MEMUARY/1939-1945/KRIWOSHEEW/poteri.txt|author= Г.Ф.Кривошеев|title=Россия и СССР в войнах XX века: Потери вооруженных сил|year=2001|publisher=Olma-Press}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet Tallinn Offensive was designed as a part of the [[Baltic Offensive]] to eliminate the positions of Army Group North along the Baltic.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

[[Stavka]] began an intricate supply and transport operation, to move the 2nd Shock Army from the [[Battle of Tannenberg Line|Narva front]] to the ''Emajõgi'' river on September 5, 1944. The 25th River Boat Brigade and engineer troops were ordered by Stavka to ferry the units over Lake Peipus. Five crossings were built from the Russian settlement of Pnevo across the {{convert|2|km|mi|abbr=on}}-wide sound of ''Lämmijärv'' to the Estonian village of Mehikoorma. Forty-six vessels worked 24 hours a day to carry 135,000 troops, 13,200 horses, 9,100 lorries, 2,183 artillery and 8,300 tons of ammunition across the lake.&lt;ref name=paulman&gt;{{Cite book|language=Russian|author =F.I.Paulman|title=Ot Narvy do Syrve (From Narva to Sõrve)|publisher=Eesti Raamat|location=Tallinn|year=1980|pages=123–125}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' units observed the move without intervening.&lt;ref name=laar231&gt;{{Cite book|author=[[Mart Laar]]|title=Emajõgi 1944: Teise Maailmasõja lahingud Lõuna-Eestis (Emajõgi River 1944: Battles of World War II in South Estonia)|language= Estonian|location= Tallinn|publisher= Varrak|page=231}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 2nd Shock Army acquired command over the Emajõgi front from the 3rd Baltic Front on 11 September 1944.&lt;ref name=paulman/&gt;

The three Soviet Baltic Fronts launched their [[Riga Offensive Operation]] on 14 September, along the German 18th Army front segment from the town of [[Madona]] in [[Latvia]] to the mouth of the [[Väike Emajõgi]] river. In the Estonian section, from the [[Valga, Estonia|Valga]] railway junction to Lake [[Võrtsjärv]], the Soviet 3rd Baltic Front attacked the German [[XXVIII Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXVIII Army Corps]].&lt;ref name=hiio&gt;{{Cite book|author=Toomas Hiio|year=2006|title=Combat in Estonia in 1944. In: Toomas Hiio, Meelis Maripuu, Indrek Paavle (Eds.). Estonia 1940–1945: Reports of the Estonian International Commission for the Investigation of Crimes Against Humanity|location=Tallinn|pages=1035–1094}}&lt;/ref&gt; The German and Estonian [[Omakaitse]] units held their positions and prevented the Army Detachment ''Narwa'' from being encircled in Estonia.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

===Soviet objectives===
The Soviet forces attempted to capture Estonia and its capital Tallinn.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; Stavka hoped a quick breakthrough at the [[Tartu Offensive|Emajõgi front]] would open a path for the armoured units to the north, thus cutting the Army Detachment ''Narwa'' off from the rest of Army Group North. The Red Army command presumed that the main direction of retreat for the German forces would be Tallinn, and concentrated their forces there in an attempt to block the roads.&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

===German objectives===
Army Group North had already considered abandoning Estonia in February 1944, during the Soviet [[Kingisepp-Gdov Offensive]]. A large number of units would have been freed up with changes to the front, but the [[Battle of Narva (1944)|Narva front]] continued to be defended on [[Hitler]]'s orders. The German Command considered it important to maintain control over the southern shore of the [[Gulf of Finland]] to ease the situation in [[Finland]] and keep the [[Soviet Baltic Fleet]] trapped in the eastern bay of the gulf. Retaining the [[oil shale]] reserves and [[oil shale industry]] in [[Ida-Viru]] was important for economic reasons.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

The [[Moscow Armistice|exit of Finland]] from the war on 3 September provided the political impetus for abandoning Estonia. The next day, Generaloberst [[Heinz Guderian]] suggested that it would not be possible to hold [[Ostland]] and ordered plans for the evacuation operation, codenamed ''Königsberg'', to be drawn up. Hitler, however, declared that Ostland must not be given up at any cost, since doing so would provide support to those Finns that did not favour the new course of the government, and would influence [[Sweden]] to maintain its current foreign policy. After lunch, Guderian ordered that the ''Königsberg'' plan nevertheless be secretly initiated. On the next day, [[Oberst]] Natzmer visited the headquarters of Army Detachment ''Narwa'' to discuss details of the evacuation. On 11 September, the evacuation of Estonia was discussed in the Army Headquarters at length. On 15 September, the Commander-in-Chief of the Army Group, Generaloberst [[Ferdinand Schörner]], requested that Guderian convince Hitler to order the evacuation of German troops from the continental part of Estonia, codenamed Operation Aster. Schörner emphasised that although the front was still holding, delaying the order would mean the units in Estonia would be trapped. Hitler agreed on 16 September.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

According to the plan, the main forces of Army Group ''Narwa'' had to withdraw mainly through [[Viljandi]] and [[Pärnu]] to [[Riga]]. In order to do that, II Army Corps at the [[Tartu Offensive|Emajõgi front]] and XXVIII Army Corps at the Väike Emajõgi had to keep the front line stable until the Army Detachment had passed behind them. Officially, the beginning of the operation was supposed to be September 19. The retreat was to be gradual, over several lines of resistance. The withdrawal was to be backed mainly by the units consisting of Estonians, who, by the estimates of the German army command, would not have wanted to leave Estonia anyway.&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt; A naval force under Vice-Admiral [[Theodor Burchardi]] began evacuating elements of the German formations along with some civilians on 17 September. The headquarters prepared a detailed plan to leave their positions at the [[Battle of Tannenberg Line|Narva front]] on the night of 18–19 September.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

===Estonian objectives===
Various Estonian troops, which used men who had [[desertion|deserted]] from the [[20th Waffen Grenadier Division of the SS (1st Estonian)]], [[Omakaitse]] militia, border defence and [[Estonian Auxiliary Police|auxiliary police]] battalions, had no general planning. However, their aim was to defend the independence of Estonia.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

==Comparison of forces==
By the beginning of the Tallinn Offensive on 17 September at the Emajõgi front, the II German Army Corps was reduced to a modest division of 4,600 men,&lt;ref name=laar4/&gt; while defending against the 140,000 men of the 2nd Shock Army.&lt;ref name=laar4&gt;{{Cite book|author=[[Mart Laar]]|title=Emajõgi 1944: Teise Maailmasõja lahingud Lõuna-Eestis (Emajõgi River 1944: Battles of World War II in South Estonia)|language=Estonian|location= Tallinn|publisher= Varrak|page=237}}&lt;/ref&gt; While the II Army Corps had practically no armoured forces, the 3rd Baltic Front deployed 300 armoured vehicles. The Red Army placed 2,569 artillery pieces along the 90-kilometre front line, pitting 137 pieces of artillery per kilometre against a practically nonexistent German artillery.&lt;ref name=laar2&gt;{{Cite book|chapter=Attempt made by Otto Tief's Government to restore the independence of Estonia|pages=60–71|title=Estonia in World War II |last=Laar |first=Mart |year=2005 |publisher=Grenader| authorlink=Mart Laar|location=Tallinn}}&lt;/ref&gt; The 15,000 strong [[III SS (Germanic) Panzer Corps]] stood against the Soviet [[8th Army (Soviet Union)|8th Army]] numbering  55,000 troops at the Narva front.&lt;ref name=laar336&gt;{{cite book|author=Mart Laar|title=Sinimäed 1944: II maailmasõja lahingud Kirde-Eestis (Sinimäed Hills 1944: Battles of World War II in Northeast Estonia)|publisher= Tallinn: Varrak|year= 2006|language=Estonian|page=336}}&lt;/ref&gt; The pro-independence Estonian troops numbered 2,000.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

==Operations==
The 3rd Baltic Front commenced their offensive in the early morning of 17 September. After the German II Army Corps were subjected to an artillery barrage of 132,500 shells, the three leading rifle corps crossed the Emajõgi River in the 25&amp;nbsp;km long section of the front east of [[Tartu]] and breached the defences. The 2nd Shock Army forced its way through to the German divisional headquarters and artillery positions. Only ''Kampfgruppe'' [[Alfons Rebane|Rebane]], stationed near Tartu, held their frontage,&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; albeit with heavy losses.&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt; Army Detachment ''Narwa'' and XXVIII Corps, the northernmost elements of Army Group North, were at risk of getting encircled and destroyed. General [[Ferdinand Schörner]] ordered II Army Corps to abandon the defence of the Emajõgi and to move quickly around the northern tip of Lake Võrtsjärv to Latvia.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

Six Estonian border defence regiments, the 113th Security Regiment, and remnants of the 20th Waffen SS Division retreating from the most distant part of the Narva front in the Krivasoo swamp were blocked by the advance units of the [[8th Estonian Rifle Corps]] and destroyed in the battles of [[Battle of Porkuni|Porkuni]] and Avinurme on 20 and 21 September.&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt; Estonians of the Soviet rifle corps murdered their compatriots that had been taken prisoner at Porkuni and the wounded sheltering in the [[Avinurme Parish]] church.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt;

The defence allowed Army Detachment ''Narwa'' to escape from Estonia as the III (Germanic) SS Panzer Corps and the 11th Infantry Division abandoned their positions, unbeknownst to the Soviet 8th Army. The Soviet forces began advancing in the early morning, took [[Jõhvi]], and by evening reached the [[Toila]]–Jõhvi–Kurtna line, also taking 63 POWs. The Panzer Corps itself declared 30 dead or MIA, and 30 wounded. On the night of 20 September, the headquarters of the Corps were near [[Pärnu]] on the southwestern coast, alongside the "Nederland", "Nordland" and the 11th Infantry Division headquarters. The "Nordland" and the 11th Infantry divisions were sent to [[Latvia]], under the command of the [[16th Army (Wehrmacht)|16th Army]]. The "Nederland" was left to organise the defence of Pärnu. On 23 September, "Nederland" dynamited the harbour and retreated to Latvia. On 24 September near [[Ikla]] on the Latvian border the rearguard of the "Nederland" carried out its final battle on Estonian ground, destroying 12–15 Soviet tanks.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

Military personnel, the wounded, institutions and industries, prisoners and civilians were mostly evacuated by sea. The chief of evacuation for the navy was the [[Admiral (Germany)|Admiral]] of the Eastern Baltic Sea, [[Theodor Burchardi]]. He was mainly responsible for securing the evacuation from Tallinn and [[Paldiski]]. For this purpose, he commanded the 24th Landing Flotilla, 14th Security Flotilla, 31st Mine Trawler Flotilla, 5th Security Flotilla and 1st Evacuation Flotilla, with a total of approximately 50 small warships, launches, escort ships and other vessels.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; Within six days, around 50,000 troops, 20,000 civilians, 1,000 [[POW]]s and 30,000 tons of goods were removed from Estonia,&lt;ref name=mitcham&gt;{{cite book|page=150|author=Mitcham, S.|title= German Defeat in the East 1944 - 45|publisher= Stackpole|year= 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mcateer/&gt; 38,000 of the military personnel by sea. In the course of the evacuation from Tallinn, the following ships suffered serious damage from Soviet air army attacks: on board the "Nettelbeck" and "Vp 1611", 8 people killed and 29 wounded; the "RO-22" hit and 100 personnel killed; the [[hospital ship]] "Moero", with 1,155 refugees, wounded and crew on board, sunk in the middle of the Baltic sea with 637 dead. The evacuation by sea, despite the fact that the time for evacuation was much shorter than planned, was considered a complete success, with only 0.9% of the evacuees killed.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

On 18 September 1944, the provisional government formed by the [[National Committee of the Republic of Estonia]] in Tallinn re-declared the independence of Estonia.&lt;ref name=frucht&gt;{{Cite book|title=Eastern Europe |last=Frucht |first=Richard |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=2005 |publisher=ABC-CLIO |location= |isbn=1-57607-800-0 |page=111 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=lVBB1a0rC70C&amp;pg=PA111&amp;dq }}&lt;/ref&gt; Estonian military units clashed with German troops in Tallinn, seizing the state offices at [[Toompea]]. The government appealed to the Soviet Union to recognize the independence of the republic.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?ei=cm01R5fMF5SysgP38dmFAg&amp;id=V4siAAAAMAAJ&amp;dq=%22Otto+Tief+%22&amp;q=Otto+Tief&amp;pgis=1#search By Royal Institute of International Affairs. Information Dept. p. 825 Published 1945]&lt;/ref&gt;

By the time the advance units of the Leningrad Front arrived at Tallinn early on 22 September, German troops had practically abandoned the city&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; and the streets were empty.&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt; The last German unit to leave Tallinn that morning was the 531st Navy Artillery Battalion. Before embarkation, all stationary artillery and armaments, special equipment, guns that could not be evacuated, ammunition, the telephone exchange, the radio broadcast house, locomotives and railroad cars, and the railway were destroyed. The Tallinn power plant was fired upon from the sea and the Old City Harbour was destroyed. The retreating German units had no combat contact with the Red Army in Tallinn.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; The Government of Estonia had failed to concentrate the Estonian soldiers retreating from the Narva and Emajõgi fronts, as the units were scattered and mixed with the German detachments withdrawing towards Latvia.&lt;ref name=laar2/&gt; Therefore, the government lacked significant military forces to repulse the Soviet forces concentrated around Tallinn. The units securing the national capital and the government were led by [[Rear Admiral]] [[Johan Pitka]].&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; Troops of the Leningrad Front seized Tallinn on 22 September. [[Jüri Uluots]], acting [[President of Estonia]], fled to Sweden.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=The Baltic States, Years of Dependence, 1940-1990 |last=Taagepera |first=Rein |authorlink= |coauthors= |year=1993 |publisher=University of California Press |location= |isbn=0-520-08228-1 |page=69 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=piLpC4EEtzQC&amp;pg=PA69&amp;dq }}&lt;/ref&gt; In the following days, several pro-independence Estonian battle groups attacked the Soviet troops in [[Harju County|Harju]] and [[Lääne County|Lääne]] counties without success.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt;

==Aftermath==
{{Main|Moonsund Landing Operation|Baltic Offensive}}

The German evacuation had been carried out in an orderly fashion. Army Group North's plans had paid off and both the Soviets and the ''[[Oberkommando der Wehrmacht]]'' (German High Command) was surprised and impressed by the speed of the evacuation.&lt;ref name=mcateer/&gt; The [[8th Army (Soviet Union)|8th Army]] went on to take the remaining [[West Estonian archipelago|West Estonian islands]] (Moonsund archipelago) in the [[Moonsund Landing Operation]], an [[amphibious warfare|amphibious]] attack.&lt;ref name=hiio/&gt; Overall, the Baltic Offensive resulted in the expulsion of [[Nazi Germany|German]] forces from Estonia, [[Lithuania]] and a large part of Latvia.

===Soviet reoccupation===
{{Main|Occupation of the Baltic states|Estonian Soviet Socialist Republic}}
Soviet rule of Estonia was re-established by force, and [[sovietisation]] followed, which was mostly carried out in 1944–1950. The forced [[Kolkhoz|collectivisation of agriculture]] began in 1947, and was completed after the [[Operation Priboi|mass deportation of Estonians in March 1949]]. All private farms were confiscated, and farmers were made to join the collective farms. An armed [[resistance movement]] of '[[forest brothers]]' was active until the mass deportations. A total of 30,000 participated or supported the movement; 2,000 were killed. The Soviet authorities fighting the forest brothers suffered also hundreds of deaths. Among those killed on both sides were innocent civilians. Besides the armed resistance of the forest brothers, a number of underground nationalist schoolchildren groups were active. Most of their members were sentenced to long terms of imprisonment. The punitive actions decreased rapidly after [[Joseph Stalin]]'s death in 1953; from 1956–58, a large part of the deportees and political prisoners were allowed to return to Estonia. Political arrests and numerous other kind of [[crimes against humanity]] were committed all through the occupation period until the late 1980s. After all, the attempt to integrate Estonian society into the Soviet system failed. Although the armed resistance was defeated, the population remained anti-Soviet. This helped the Estonians to organise a [[Singing revolution|new resistance movement]] in the late 1980s, regain their independence in 1991, and then rapidly develop a modern society.&lt;ref&gt;"Phase III: The Soviet Occupation of Estonia from 1944". In: ''Estonia since 1944: Reports of the [[Estonian International Commission for the Investigation of Crimes Against Humanity]]'', pp. VII–XXVI. Tallinn, 2009&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Clear}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
* Glantz, D. ''Soviet Military Deception in the Second World War'', Frank Cass, London, 1989, {{ISBN|0-7146-3347-X}}
* Vercamer, A. [http://www.feldgrau.com/baltsea.html Naval war in the Baltic], article accessed 18/04/08
{{Refend}}

{{World War II}}

{{Good article}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:1944 in Estonia]]
[[Category:Battles involving Estonia]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Military history of Estonia during World War II]]
[[Category:Strategic operations of the Red Army in World War II]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Reichskommissariat Ostland]]
[[Category:Estonian Soviet Socialist Republic]]
[[Category:History of Tallinn]]
[[Category:September 1944 events]]</text><sha1>71n76pkeeycm2bppoibys1j72w2nxbd</sha1></revision></page>