<page><title>Battle of Memel</title><ns>0</ns><id>5298547</id><revision><id>919915719</id><parentid>916221991</parentid><timestamp>2019-10-06T16:35:58Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Filiep</username><id>1065306</id></contributor><comment>/* Red Army */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="9563" xml:space="preserve">{{other uses}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Memel
| partof      = the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = 
| caption     = 
| date        = 5–22 October 1944 (main offensive); 28 January 1945 (end of siege)
| place       = [[Klaipėda]] ([[Lithuania]] / [[East Prussia]])
| coordinates = {{coord|55|40|N|21|30|E|display=inline,title|region:LT_type:event}}
| result      = Soviet victory
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]
| combatant2  = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}
| commander1  = [[Erhard Raus]]&lt;br&gt;([[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer Army]])&lt;br&gt;[[Hans Gollnick]]&lt;br&gt;([[XXVIII Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXVIII Corps]])
| commander2  =  [[Hovhannes Bagramyan]]&lt;br&gt;([[1st Baltic Front]])
| strength1   = 
| strength2   = 
| casualties1 = 
| casualties2 = 
}}
{{Campaignbox Axis–Soviet War}}
The '''Battle of Memel''' or the '''Siege of Memel''' ({{lang-de|Erste Kurlandschlacht}}) was a battle which took place on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] during World War II. The battle began when the [[Red Army]] launched its ''Memel Offensive Operation'' ({{lang-ru|Мемельская наступательная операция}}) in late 1944. The offensive drove remaining [[Wehrmacht|German]] forces in the area that is now [[Lithuania]] and [[Latvia]] into a small bridgehead in [[Klaipėda]] (Memel) and its port, leading to a three-month siege of that position.

The bridgehead was finally crushed as part of a subsequent Soviet offensive, the [[East Prussian Offensive]], in early 1945.

==Prelude==

The Soviet [[Belorussian Offensive]] of June–August 1944 (commonly known as [[Operation Bagration]]) had seen the German [[Army Group Centre]] nearly destroyed and driven from what is now [[Belarus]], most of what is now [[Lithuania]] and much of [[Poland]]. During August and September of that year, a series of German counter-offensives - [[Operation Doppelkopf|Operations Doppelkopf and Casar]] - succeeded in stalling the Soviet advance and maintaining the connection between the German Army Groups Centre and North; however, ''[[Stavka]]'' made preparations for an attack by the [[1st Baltic Front]] against the positions of the Third Panzer Army and thence towards [[Klaipėda|Memel]], splitting the two Army Groups.

Soviet General Bagramyan planned to make his main attack in a 19&amp;nbsp;km sector to the west of [[Šiauliai]]. He concentrated up to half of his entire force in this area, using concealment techniques to ensure there was not a corresponding build-up of German forces, and attempting to convince the German command that the main axis of attack would be towards [[Riga]].&lt;ref name=glantzp434&gt;Glantz, pp..434-5&lt;/ref&gt;

==Deployments==

===Wehrmacht===
*Various miscellaneous units of the Kriegsmarine.
*Northern wing of [[3rd Panzer Army|Third Panzer Army]] (General [[Erhard Raus]])
**[[XXVIII Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXVIII Corps]] (General [[Hans Gollnick]])
**[[XL Panzer Corps (Germany)|XL Panzer Corps]] (General [[Sigfrid Henrici]])

===Red Army===

*[[1st Baltic Front]] (General [[Hovhannes Bagramyan]])
**[[5th Guards Tank Army]] (General [[Vasily Volsky]])
**[[43rd Army (Soviet Union)|43rd Army]] (Lieutenant-General [[Afanasy Beloborodov]])
**[[51st Army (Soviet Union)|51st Army]] (Lieutenant-General [[Yakov Kreizer]])
**[[4th Shock Army (Soviet Union)|4th Shock Army]] (Lieutenant-General [[Pyotr Malyshev]])
**[[6th Guards Army (Soviet Union)|6th Guards Army]] (Lieutenant-General [[Ivan Chistyakov]])

*[[3rd Belorussian Front]]
**[[39th Army (Soviet Union)|39th Army]] (Lieutenant-General [[Ivan Lyudnikov]])

==The offensive==

On 5 October, Bagramyan opened the offensive against Raus' Third Panzer Army on a sixty-mile front, concentrating his breakthrough force against the relatively weak [[551st Volksgrenadier Division (Germany)|551st Volksgrenadier Division]].&lt;ref name=mitchamp151&gt;Mitcham, p.151&lt;/ref&gt; The latter collapsed on the first day, and a 16&amp;nbsp;km (10 mile) penetration was achieved; Bagramyan then committed Volsky's [[5th Guards Tank Army]] to the breach, aiming for the coast to the north of Memel. There was a general collapse of the Third Panzer Army's positions by 7 October, and a penetration further south by Beloborodov's 43rd Army. Within two days, it had reached the coast south of Memel, while Volsky had encircled the town from the north. In the south, the northern flank of Chernyakhovsky's [[3rd Belorussian Front]] was advancing on [[Tilsit]]. Third Panzer Army's headquarters were overrun by the 5th Guards Tank Army, and Raus and his staff had to fight their way into Memel.&lt;ref name=glantzp440&gt;Glantz, p.440&lt;/ref&gt;

The neighbouring Army Group commander, [[Ferdinand Schoerner]], signalled on 9 October that he would mount an attack to relieve Memel if troops could be freed up by evacuating [[Riga]]. A decision on this matter was delayed, but the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' managed to withdraw much of the garrison and some civilians from the port in the meantime.&lt;ref name=mitchamp152&gt;Mitcham, p.152&lt;/ref&gt; The German XXVIII Corps under Gollnick held a defensive line around the town itself.

The success of the offensive in the northern sector encouraged the Soviet command to authorise the 3rd Belorussian Front to attempt to break through into the main area of East Prussia. This offensive, the [[Gumbinnen Operation]], ran into extremely strong German resistance and was halted within a few days.

==The siege==

The stalling of the Gumbinnen Operation meant that Soviet forces (mainly from the 43rd Army) settled down to a blockade of the German troops that had withdrawn into Memel. The German force, largely made up of elements from the [[Großdeutschland Division|Großdeutschland]] and [[58th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|58th Infantry]] Divisions and the [[7th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|7th Panzer Division]], was aided by heavily fortified tactical defences, artillery fire from ships (including the ''[[German cruiser Prinz Eugen|Prinz Eugen]]'') in the [[Baltic Sea|Baltic]], and a tenuous connection with the remainder of East Prussia over the [[Curonian Spit]].

The blockade, and defence, was maintained through November, December and much of January, during which period the remaining civilians who had fled into the town, and military wounded, were evacuated by sea. During this time, the Großdeutschland and 7th Panzer Divisions were withdrawn, having suffered heavy losses, and were replaced by the [[95th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|95th Infantry Division]], which arrived by sea.

The town was finally abandoned on 27 January 1945. The success of the Soviet [[East Prussian Offensive]] to the south made the position of the bridgehead untenable, and it was decided to withdraw the XXVIII Corps from the town into [[Sambia Peninsula|Samland]] to assist in the defence there; the remaining troops of the 95th and 58th Infantry Divisions were evacuated to the Curonian Spit, where the 58th Division acted as a rearguard for the withdrawal.&lt;ref name=pillau&gt;Most of the evacuated formations were later destroyed around [[Pillau]], with the 95th being cut off and destroyed at [[Palmnicken]] in mid-April.&lt;/ref&gt; The last organized German units left at 4am on 28 January, Soviet units taking possession of the harbour a few hours later.  

==Aftermath==
Memel, which had been part of [[Lithuania]] only between 1923 and 1939 prior to being reincorporated into [[Germany]], was transferred to the [[Lithuanian SSR]] under the Soviet administration. In 1947 it was formally renamed using the Lithuanian name, [[Klaipėda]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last=Wellmann |first=Christian |url=http://www.schiff.uni-kiel.de/pdf_files/KaliningradChallenge-ContestedTerritory(Wellmann).pdf |format=PDF |title=Recognising Borders: Coping with Historically Contested Territory |accessdate=2007-03-01 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20061106192530/http://www.schiff.uni-kiel.de/pdf_files/KaliningradChallenge-ContestedTerritory%28Wellmann%29.pdf |archivedate=2006-11-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==

*[[1939 German ultimatum to Lithuania]]
*[[Operation Hannibal]], the evacuation effort by the ''Kriegsmarine'' beginning January 1945
*[[East Prussian Operation]], Soviet offensive that finally eliminated the Memel pocket
*[[Courland Pocket]]

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
*[[David Glantz|Glantz, D.]] ''Soviet Military Deception in the Second World War'', Routledge, 1989, {{ISBN|0-7146-3347-X}}
* {{Cite book
  |last=Mitcham
  |first=Samuel W
  |year=2007
  |title=The German Defeat in the East, 1944–45
  |location=Mechanicsburg, PA
  |publisher=[[Stackpole Books]]
  |isbn=978-0-8117-3371-7
}}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060410214910/http://www.onwar.com/maps/wwii/eastfront2/eprussia45.htm Map of the Soviet Advance into East Prussia &amp; Siege of Königsberg January 13 - May 9, 1945] This shows clearly how Memel was already surrounded and besieged.
*[[Erhard Raus|Raus, E.]] ''Panzer Operations'', Da Capo, 2005, {{ISBN|0-306-81409-9}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Memel 1944}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:History of Klaipėda]]
[[Category:1944 in Lithuania]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Lithuania in World War II]]
[[Category:20th century in Klaipėda]]
[[Category:1944 in Germany]]
[[Category:1945 in Germany]]
[[Category:1945 in Lithuania]]
[[Category:January 1945 events]]</text><sha1>al9e67xw2dyp58j1orpekmrtuj4nk9s</sha1></revision></page>