<page><title>Siege of Budapest</title><ns>0</ns><id>2632913</id><revision><id>957315759</id><parentid>956456625</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-18T06:34:06Z</timestamp><contributor><username>I dream of horses</username><id>9676078</id></contributor><minor /><comment>clean up, [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: german → German, internationally- → internationally , 1944-1945 → 1944–1945</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="42536" xml:space="preserve">{{for|earlier battles there|Battle of Buda (disambiguation)}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict = Siege of Budapest
| partof = the [[Budapest Offensive]] ([[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]])
| image = Russian Soldier Budapest.JPG
| caption = A [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] soldier writing "Budapest" in [[Cyrillic script|Cyrillic]] on a signpost after the siege
| date = 24 December 1944 – 13 February 1945&lt;br /&gt;({{Age in years, months, weeks and days|month1=12|day1=24|year1=1944|month2=02|day2=13|year2=1945}})
| place = [[Budapest]], [[Kingdom of Hungary|Hungary]]
| result = Allied victory
| combatant1 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Hungary (1920–46)}} [[Government of National Unity (Hungary)|Hungary]]
| combatant2 = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Soviet Union]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} [[Kingdom of Romania|Romania]]
| commander1 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Karl Pfeffer-Wildenbruch]]{{POW}}&lt;br/&gt;{{nowrap|{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Gerhard Schmidhuber]]{{KIA}}}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Hungary (1920–46)}} [[Dezső László]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Hungary (1920–46)}} [[Iván Hindy]]{{POW}}
| commander2 = {{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Rodion Malinovsky]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Fyodor Tolbukhin]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Romania}} {{ill|Nicolae Șova|ro}}
| strength1 = '''In the city:'''{{sfn|Frieser|Schmider|Schönherr|Schreiber|2007|p=897}}
:79,000 men
:{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} 41,000 men (ration strength)
:{{flagicon|Kingdom of Hungary (1920–46)}} 38,000 men (ration strength)
:489 guns
:125 tanks and assault guns
:117 heavy anti-tank guns
| strength2 = '''In the city:'''{{sfn|Frieser|Schmider|Schönherr|Schreiber|2007|p=898}}{{sfn|Ungváry|2003|p=324}}
:177,000 men
:1,000 guns
| casualties1 = '''3 November–15 February:''' 137,000 men{{sfn|Ungváry|2003|p=331–332}}&lt;br/&gt;'''24 December–15 February:''' 114,000 men{{sfn|Ungváry|2003|p=331–332}}&lt;br/&gt;'''City:'''
:79,000 men
*{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} 30,000 killed
*{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} 11,000 captured
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Hungary (1920–46)}} 9,000 killed
*{{flagicon|Kingdom of Hungary (1920–46)}} 29,000 captured
'''Relief attempts:'''
:35,000 men
*8,000 killed
*26,000 wounded
*1,000 captured
| casualties2 = '''3 November–11 February:''' 280,000 men{{sfn|Ungváry|2003|p=331–332}}&lt;br/&gt;
'''Relief attempts:'''
:80,000 men
*15,000 killed
*60,000 wounded
*5,100 captured
| casualties3 = '''76,000 civilians dead'''{{sfn|Ungváry|2003|p=330}}&lt;br/&gt;38,000 civilians died in the siege (7,000 executed)&lt;br/&gt;38,000 died in labour or POW camps
}}
{{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Campaignbox Hungary 1944-1945}}
{{Romanian military actions in World War II}}

The '''Siege of Budapest''' or '''Battle of Budapest''' was the 50-day-long encirclement by [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] and [[Kingdom of Romania|Romanian]] forces of the Hungarian [[capital (political)|capital]] of [[Budapest]], near the end of [[World War II]]. Part of the broader [[Budapest Offensive]], the siege began when Budapest, defended by [[Kingdom of Hungary (1920–1946)|Hungarian]] and [[Nazi Germany|German]] troops, was first encircled on 26 December 1944 by the [[Red Army]] and the [[Romanian Army]]. During the siege, about 38,000 civilians died through starvation or military action. The city unconditionally surrendered on 13 February 1945. It was a strategic victory for the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] in their push towards [[Berlin]].&lt;ref name="Ungvary 512"/&gt;

==General situation==
Having suffered nearly 200,000 deaths in three years fighting the [[Soviet Union]], and with the front lines approaching its own cities, Hungary was by early 1944 ready to exit [[World War II]]. As political forces within Hungary pushed for an end to the fighting, Germany preemptively launched [[Operation Margarethe]] on 19 March 1944, and entered Hungary.

In October 1944, after successive Allied victories at [[Operation Overlord|Normandy]] and [[Falaise pocket|Falaise]], and after the collapse of the Eastern Front following the stunning success of the Soviet summer offensive, [[Operation Bagration]], Regent of Hungary [[Miklós Horthy]] again attempted to negotiate a separate peace with the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]]. Upon hearing of Horthy's efforts, Hitler launched [[Operation Panzerfaust]] to keep Hungary on the Axis side, and forced Horthy to abdicate. Horthy and his government were replaced by "Hungarist" [[Ferenc Szálasi]], led by the far-right [[Nazism|National Socialist]] [[Arrow Cross Party]]. As the new right-wing government and its German allies prepared the defense of the capital, [[IX SS Mountain Corps]], consisting of two [[Waffen-SS]] divisions, was sent to Budapest to strengthen the city's defense.

==Soviet offensive==
The besieging Soviet forces were part of [[Rodion Malinovsky]]'s [[2nd Ukrainian Front]]. Formations that actually took part in the fighting appear to have included the [[53rd Army (Soviet Union)|53rd Army]], [[7th Guards Army]], portions of the [[3rd Ukrainian Front]], including the [[46th Army (Soviet Union)|46th Army]], and the Romanian [[First Army (Romania)|7th Army Corps]].&lt;ref name="Ungvary 512"/&gt;

Arrayed against the Soviets was a collection of [[Nazi Germany|German]] Army (''[[German Army (Wehrmacht)|Heer]]''), ''Waffen-SS'' and [[Royal Hungarian Army|Hungarian Army]] forces. The Siege of Budapest was one of the bloodiest sieges of World War II.

===Encirclement of Budapest===
[[File:BUDAPEST 45 V.jpg|thumb|right|A counterattack of Soviet infantry and tanks of the 18th tank corps]]
[[File:Map of German defensive lines in Hungary 1944.png|thumb|Map of German defensive lines (German: Stellung) in Hungary 1944]]
The Red Army started its offensive against the city on 29 October 1944. More than 1,000,000 men, split into two operating [[maneuver warfare|maneuver groups]], advanced. The plan was to isolate Budapest from the rest of the German and Hungarian forces. On 7 November 1944, Soviet and Romanian troops entered the eastern suburbs, 20 kilometers from the old town. The Red Army, after a much-needed pause in operations, resumed its offensive on 19 December. On 26 December, a road linking Budapest to [[Vienna]] was seized by Soviet troops, thereby completing the encirclement. The Nazi-supported "Leader of the Nation" (''Nemzetvezető''), [[Ferenc Szálasi]], had already fled from the city on 9 December.

As a result of the Soviet link-up, nearly 33,000 German and 37,000 Hungarian soldiers, as well as over 800,000 civilians, became trapped within the city. Refusing to authorize a withdrawal, [[Adolf Hitler]] had declared Budapest a fortress city (''[[German World War II strongholds|Festung]] Budapest''), which was to be defended to the last man. ''Waffen SS'' General [[Karl Pfeffer-Wildenbruch]], the commander of the [[IX Waffen Mountain Corps of the SS (Croatian)|IX Waffen SS Alpine Corps]], was put in charge of the city's defenses.

Budapest was a major target for [[Joseph Stalin]]. The [[Yalta Conference]] was approaching, and Stalin wanted to display his full strength to [[Winston Churchill]] and [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]]. He therefore ordered General [[Rodion Malinovsky]] to seize the city without delay.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| last=Deak| first=István| title=Endgame in Budapest| work=Hungarian Quarterly| date=Autumn 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1986-064-15, Ungarn, Straßenkämpfe, ungarische Pak.jpg|thumb|left|Hungarian troops man a [[7.5 cm Pak 40]] antitank gun in a Budapest suburb]]
During the night of 28 December 1944, the 2nd and 3rd Ukrainian Front contacted the besieged Germans by radios and loudspeakers, and told them about a negotiation for the city's [[Capitulation (surrender)|capitulation]]. The Soviets promised to provide humane surrender conditions and not to mistreat the German and Hungarian prisoners.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| first=S. M.| last=Shtemenko| title=The Soviet General Staff at War| volume=2| url=http://militera.lib.ru/memo/russian/shtemenko/24.html| quote=''Советское командование стремилось избежать ненужного кровопролития, сохранить для венгерского народа все то, что было создано руками замечательных мастеров прошлого. 29 декабря противнику, окруженному в Будапеште, были направлены ультиматумы командования 2-го и 3-го Украинских фронтов, предусматривавшие гуманные условия капитуляции. Венгерским генералам, офицерам и солдатам гарантировалось, например, немедленное возвращение домой. Но парламентер 2-го Украинского фронта капитан М. Штейнмец был встречен огнем и убит, а парламентеру 3-го Украинского фронта капитану И. А. Остапенко от-ветили отказом капитулировать и при возвращении выстрелили в спину.| date=1 October 2001| publisher=University Press of the Pacific| isbn=978-0898756036| language=Russian}}&lt;/ref&gt; They also promised that the emissaries' groups would not bring weapons and would appear in cars with white flags.

The next day, two groups of Soviet emissaries appeared as expected. The first, belonging to the 3rd Ukrainian Front, arrived at 10:00 AM in the Budafok sector and was taken to the headquarters of General Wildenbruch. Their negotiating effort was a failure; Wildenbruch refused the surrender conditions and sent the Soviet agents back to the battlefield. While the emissaries were ''en route'' to their camps, the Germans suddenly opened fire, killing Captain I. A. Ostapenko. Lieutenant N. F. Orlov and Sergeant Ye. T. Gorbatyuk quickly jumped into a trench and narrowly escaped. Owing to heavy German fire, the Soviets were not able to retrieve Ostapenko's body until the night of 29 December. He was buried at Budafok with full military honors.&lt;ref name="militera.lib.ru"&gt;{{cite book| url=http://militera.lib.ru/memo/russian/andruschenko_sa/05.html| title=Начинали мы на Славутиче| first=Sergey Aleksandrovich| last=Andrushchenko| trans-title=We began at Slavutych| publisher=Institute of History of the USSR| location=Moscow| year=1979| chapter=5: For Hungary's Capital}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first= Semyon Prokofievich| last=Serikh| url=http://militera.lib.ru/memo/russian/seryh_sp/03.html| title=Бессмертный батальон| trans-title=Immortal Battalion| publisher=Military Publishing| location=Moskva| year=1988| chapter=3: The Immortal Battalion}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url=http://militera.lib.ru/h/samsonov2/18.html| title=Крах фашистской агрессии 1939-1945| first=Alexander Mikhilovich| last=Samsonov| trans-title=The collapse of the invading fascists 1939-1945| publisher=Institute of History of the USSR| location=Moskva| year=1980| chapter=18 Helping the European people — Section 7: The Red Army at Hungary}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The second group of emissaries belonged to the 2nd Ukrainian Front and arrived at 11:00 AM in the Kispest sector. When the emissaries arrived, the German garrison fired at them. The leader of the emissaries, Captain Miklós Steinmetz, appealed for a negotiation, but to no avail. He was killed together with his two subordinates when the German fire struck the Soviet car.&lt;ref name="militera.lib.ru"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| url=http://militera.lib.ru/memo/russian/russiyanov_in/17.html| first=Ivan Nikitich| last=Russiyanov| title=В боях рожденная| trans-title=In the Battle Born| publisher=Institute of History of the USSR| location=Moscow| year=1982| chapter=17: The Fight for Hungary| page=188}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===First German relief attempt===
The Soviet offensive began in the eastern suburbs, advancing through [[Pest, Hungary|Pest]], making good use of the large central avenues to speed up their progress. The German and Hungarian defenders, overwhelmed, tried to trade space for time to slow down the Soviet advance. They ultimately withdrew to shorten their lines, hoping to take advantage of the hilly nature of [[Buda (city)|Buda]].

In January 1945, the Germans launched a three-part counter-offensive codenamed [[Operation Konrad]]. This was a joint German-Hungarian effort to relieve the encircled garrison of Budapest. Operation Konrad I was launched on 1 January. The German [[IV SS Panzer Corps]] attacked from [[Tata, Hungary|Tata]] through hilly terrain north-west of Budapest in an effort to break the siege. On 3 January, the Soviet command sent four more divisions to meet the threat. This Soviet action stopped the offensive near [[Bicske]], less than 20 kilometers west of Budapest. The Germans were forced to withdraw on 12 January.

They then launched Operation Konrad II on 7 January. The IV SS Panzer Corps attacked from [[Esztergom]] toward Budapest Airport in an attempt to capture it and improve ability to supply the city by air. This offensive was halted near the airport.

{{command structure
| name        = Besieging Force, Pest Sector
| date        = Jan 1945
| parent      = 
| subordinate =

'''30th Rifle Corps:'''
*25th Gds rifle division
*151st rifle division
*155th rifle division
*16th artillery division
*18th Gds howitzer artillery brigade
*49th Gds cannon artillery brigade
*115 Gds anti-tank artillery regiment

'''18th Gds Rifle Corps:'''
*66th Gds rifle division
*68th Gds rifle division
*297th rifle division
*317th rifle division
*17th cannon artillery brigade
*152nd cannon artillery brigade
*95th howitzer artillery brigade
*27th mortar brigade
*48th "Katyusha" regiment
*14th assault engineer brigade

'''VII Romanian Army Corps:'''
*2nd Infantry Division
*19th Infantry Division
*9th Cavalry Division

'''Tank units'''
''Used during storm of Pest:''
*Two battalions from 23rd Tank Corps
*3rd tank brigade
*A company from 39th tank brigade
(Totaling 22 tanks)

''Used during the storming of Buda:''
*A company from 23rd Tank Corps
*A company from 5th Gds Tank Corps
(Totaling 19 tanks)

'''Artillery on 1 January'''
*203-mm howitzer – 48
*152-mm gun/howitzer – 172
*122-mm gun/howitzer – 294
*76-mm divisional gun – 191
*76-mm regimental gun – 174
*45-mm/57-mm AT gun – 158
}}

===Combat in the city===
Meanwhile, [[urban warfare]] in Budapest increased in intensity. Re-supply became a decisive factor because of the loss of the [[Ferihegy]] airport on 27 December 1944, just before the start of the siege. Until 9 January 1945, German troops were able to use some of the main avenues as well as the park next to [[Buda Castle]] as landing zones for [[Airplane|plane]]s and [[military glider|glider]]s, although they were under constant artillery fire from the Soviets. Before the [[Danube]] froze, some supplies could be sent on [[barge]]s, under the cover of darkness and fog.

Nevertheless, food shortages were more and more common and soldiers had to rely on finding their own sources of sustenance, some even resorting to eating their own horses. The extreme temperatures also affected German and Hungarian troops.

Soviet troops quickly found themselves in the same situation as the Germans had in [[Stalingrad]]. Their men were nonetheless able to take advantage of the urban terrain by relying heavily on snipers and sappers to advance. Fighting broke out in the [[sanitary sewer|sewer]]s, as both sides used them for troop movements. Six Soviet [[marines]] even managed to get to Castle Hill and capture a German officer before returning to their own lines – still underground. But such feats were rare because of ambushes in the sewers set up by the [[Axis powers of World War II|Axis]] troops using local inhabitants as guides.

In mid-January, [[Csepel Island]] was taken, along with its military factories, which were still producing [[Panzerfaust]]s and [[shell (projectile)|shell]]s, even under Soviet fire. Meanwhile, in Pest, the situation for the Axis forces deteriorated, with the [[garrison]] facing the risk of being cut in half by the advancing Soviet troops.

On 17 January 1945, Hitler agreed to withdraw the remaining troops from Pest to try to defend Buda. All five bridges spanning the [[Danube]] were clogged with traffic, evacuating troops and civilians. German troops destroyed the bridges 18 January, despite protests from Hungarian officers. One of them was the famous [[Chain Bridge (Budapest)|Chain Bridge]], dating from 1849.

===Second German relief attempt===
On 18 January 1945, the IV SS Panzer Corps, whose relocation to the region north-east of Lake Balaton had been completed on the previous day, was again thrown into battle. This was Operation Konrad III. In two days the Germans tanks reached the [[Danube]] at Dunapentele, tearing the Soviet Transdanubian front apart, and by 26 January the offensive had reached a point roughly 25 kilometers from the ring around the capital.

Stalin ordered his troops to hold their ground at all costs, and two [[Army Corps]] that were dispatched to assault Budapest were hastily moved to the south of the city to counter the German offensive. Nevertheless, German troops who got to less than 20 kilometres from the city were unable to maintain their impetus due to fatigue and supply problems. Budapest's defenders asked permission to leave the city and escape the encirclement. Hitler refused.

German troops could no longer hold their ground; they were forced to withdraw on 28 January 1945, and to abandon much of the occupied territory with the notable exception of [[Székesfehérvár]]. The fate of the defenders of Budapest was sealed.

{{command structure
| name        = Budapest assault group
| date        = January 21, 1945
| parent      = 
| subordinate =

'''75th Gds Rifle Corps'''
*113th rifle division
*180th rifle division
*Two regiments from 109th rifle division
Total 14,179 men.

'''37th Gds Rifle Corps'''
*108th rifle division
*316th rifle division
*320th rifle division
Total 16,645 men.

'''18th Gds Rifle Corps'''
*66th Gds rifle division
*68th Gds rifle division
*297th rifle division
*317th rifle division
Total 13,140 men.

*5th artillery division
*7th artillery division
*16th artillery division
*462nd mortar regiment
*48th "Katyusha" regiment
*12th assault engineer brigade
*14th assault engineer brigade
*Tank company (9 [[T-34]])

'''Artillery on 1 February'''
*203-mm howitzer – 69
*152-mm gun/howitzer – 116
*122-mm gun/howitzer – 160
*76-mm divisional gun – 245
*76-mm regimental gun – 60
*57-mm AT gun – 20
*45-mm AT gun – 114
*82-mm mortar – 307
*120-mm mortar – 213
*"Katyusha" – 24

'''Additional units'''
*83rd naval infantry brigade
}}

===The Battle for Buda===
Unlike [[Pest (city)|Pest]], which is built on flat terrain, [[Buda]] is built on hills. This allowed the defenders to site artillery and fortifications above the attackers, greatly slowing the Soviet advance. The main citadel, ([[Gellért Hill]]), was defended by ''Waffen-SS'' troops who successfully repelled several Soviet assaults. Nearby, Soviet and German forces were fighting for the city cemetery amongst shell-opened tombs; it would last for several days.

The fighting on [[Margaret Island]], in the middle of the Danube, was particularly merciless. The island was still attached to the rest of the city by the remaining half of the Margaret Bridge and was used as a parachute drop zone as well as for covering improvised airstrips set up in the city center. The 25th Guards Rifle Division operated from the Soviet side in combat on the island (for losses see below).

On 11 February 1945, Gellért Hill finally fell after six weeks of fighting when the Soviets launched a heavy attack from three directions simultaneously. Soviet artillery was able to dominate the entire city and to shell the remaining Axis defenders, who were concentrated in less than two square kilometres and suffering from malnutrition and disease.

Despite the lack of supplies, the Axis troops refused to surrender and defended every street and house. By this time, some captured Hungarian soldiers defected and fought on the Soviet side. They were known collectively as the "[[Volunteer Regiment of Buda]]".

After capturing the [[Budapest Déli railway station|southern railway station]] during a two-day bloodbath, Soviet troops advanced to Castle Hill. On 10 February, after a violent assault, Soviet marines established a bridgehead on Castle Hill, while almost cutting the remaining garrison in half.

===Breakout and surrender===
Hitler still forbade the German commander, Pfeffer-Wildenbruch, to abandon Budapest or to attempt a breakout. But the glider flights ([[DFS 230]]) bringing in supplies had ended a few days earlier and parachute drops had also been discontinued.

In desperation, Pfeffer-Wildenbruch decided to lead the remnants of his troops out of Budapest. The German commander did not typically consult the Hungarian commander of the city. However, Pfeffer-Wildenbruch now uncharacteristically included General [[Iván Hindy]] in this last desperate breakout attempt.

On the night of 11 February, some 28,000 German and Hungarian troops began to stream north-westwards away from Castle Hill. They moved in three waves. Thousands of civilians were with each wave. Entire families, pushing prams, trudged through the snow and ice. Unfortunately for the would-be escapees, the Soviets awaited them in prepared positions around the [[Széll Kálmán tér]] area.

Troops, along with the civilians, used heavy fog to their advantage. The first wave managed to surprise the waiting Soviet soldiers and artillery; their sheer numbers allowed many to escape. The second and third waves were less fortunate. Soviet artillery and rocket batteries bracketed the escape area, with deadly results that killed thousands. Despite heavy losses, five to ten thousand people managed to reach the wooded hills northwest of Budapest and escape towards Vienna, but only 600–700 German and Hungarian soldiers reached the main German lines from Budapest.&lt;ref name="Ungvary 512"&gt;{{cite book |last=Ungvary |first=Krisztian |author2=Ladislaus Lob |author3=John Lukacs |title=The siege of Budapest: One Hundred Days in World War II |publisher=Yale University Press |date=April 11, 2005| pages=512 |isbn=0-300-10468-5 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=cLY1z-XLd_IC&amp;pg=PR5&amp;lpg=PR5&amp;dq=AFTER+THE+BATTLE+40+-+BUDAPEST+1944&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=508J-yFNh6&amp;sig=Z0L2C-mBHopRCDyyzoXL2tx2F8g&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=jmeET7L0NZHpggey7s3eBw&amp;ved=0CEEQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;q=ukrainian%20front&amp;f=false}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="DRZW 922"&gt;* {{cite book
 | last1 = Frieser
 | first1 = Karl-Heinz
 | author-link1 = Karl-Heinz Frieser
 | first2 =Klaus 
 | last2 = Schmider
 | first3 =Klaus 
 | last3 = Schönherr
 | first4 = Gerhard 
 | last4 = Schreiber
 | first5 = Kristián 
 | last5 = Ungváry
 | author-link5 = Krisztián Ungváry
 | first6 =Bernd 
 | last6=Wegner
 | work = [[Das Deutsche Reich und der Zweite Weltkrieg]] [Germany and the Second World War]
 | volume = VIII
 | title = Die Ostfront 1943/44 – Der Krieg im Osten und an den Nebenfronten
 | trans-title = The Eastern Front 1943–1944: The War in the East and on the Neighbouring Fronts
 | publisher = Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt 
 | location = München
 | year = 2007
 | isbn = 978-3-421-06235-2
 | language = German
 | ref = harv
 | page=922
}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The majority of the escapees were killed, wounded, or captured by the Soviet troops. Pfeffer-Wildenbruch and Hindy were captured by waiting Soviet troops as they emerged from a tunnel running from the Castle District.

==Aftermath==

The remaining defenders finally surrendered 13 February 1945. German and Hungarian military losses were high, with entire divisions having been eliminated. The Germans lost all or most of the [[German 13th Panzer Division|13th Panzer Division]], [[German Panzer Division Feldherrnhalle 1|60th Panzergrenadier Division ''Feldherrnhalle'']], [[8th SS Cavalry Division Florian Geyer|8th SS Cavalry Division ''Florian Geyer'']] and the [[22nd SS Volunteer Cavalry Division Maria Theresia|22nd SS Volunteer Cavalry Division ''Maria Theresa'']]. The Hungarian I Corps was virtually annihilated, as well as the 10th and 12th Infantry Divisions and the 1st Armored Division.

The Soviet forces suffered between 100,000 and 160,000 casualties. The Soviets claimed that they had trapped 180,000 German and Hungarian 'fighters' in the pocket, and declared they had captured 110,000 of these soldiers. However, immediately after the siege, they rounded up thousands of Hungarian civilians and added them to the prisoner-of-war count, allowing the Soviets to validate their previously inflated figures.&lt;ref name=Zwack/&gt;

Budapest lay in ruins, with more than 80 percent of its buildings destroyed or damaged, with historical buildings like the [[Hungarian Parliament Building]] and the Castle among them. All seven bridges spanning the [[Danube]] were destroyed.

In January 1945, 32,000 ethnic [[Germans of Hungary#Expulsion|Germans from within Hungary]] were arrested and transported to the Soviet Union as forced laborers. In some villages, the entire adult population were taken to labor camps in the [[Donets Basin]].&lt;ref name=Wasserstein&gt;{{cite web |first=Bernard |last=Wasserstein |title=History: European Refugee Movements After World War Two |publisher=[[BBC]] |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwtwo/refugees_02.shtml}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Ther"&gt;{{cite book| first=Philipp| last=Ther| title=Deutsche Und Polnische Vertriebene: Gesellschaft und Vertriebenenpolitik in SBZ/ddr und in Polen 1945–1956| year=1998| isbn=978-3525357903| trans-title=German and Polish displaced persons: IDPs society and politics in SBZ/DDR and Poland, 1945-1956| url=https://www.amazon.co.uk/Deutsche-Polnische-Vertriebene-Vertriebenenpolitik-Geschichtswissenschaft/dp/3525357907/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1417469848&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=Deutsche+Und+Polnische+Vertriebene%3A+Gesellschaft+und+Vertriebenenpolitik+in+SBZ%2Fddr+und+in+Polen+1945%E2%80%931956#reader_3525357907|url-access=subscription }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|21}} Many died there as a result of hardship and ill-treatment. Overall, more than 500,000 Hungarians were transported to the Soviet Union (including between 100,000 and 170,000 [[Germans of Hungary|Hungarian ethnic Germans]]).&lt;ref name=EU38&gt;{{cite web |url=http://cadmus.iue.it/dspace/bitstream/1814/2599/1/HEC04-01.pdf |title=The Expulsion of 'German' Communities from Eastern Europe at the end of the Second World War |first1=Steffen |last1=Prauser |first2=Arfon |last2=Rees |year=2004 |publisher=European University Institute |location=Florence |oclc=646024457}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|38}}

With the exception of [[Operation Frühlingserwachen|Operation Spring Awakening]] (''Unternehmen Frühlingserwachen''), which was launched in March 1945, the siege of Budapest was the last major operation on the southern front for the Germans. The siege further depleted the ''Wehrmacht'' and especially the ''Waffen-SS''. For the Soviet troops, the Siege of Budapest was a final rehearsal before the [[Battle of Berlin]]. It also allowed the Soviets to launch the [[Vienna Offensive]]. On 13 April 1945, exactly two months after the surrender of Budapest, Vienna fell.&lt;ref name="Isaev"&gt;{{cite book| last=Isaev| first=A. V.| title=1945-y. Triumf v nastuplenii i v oborone: ot Vislo-Oderskoy do Balatona| trans-title=1945: Triumph both in offence and defence: from Vistula-Oder to Balaton| location=Moscow| year=2008| isbn=978-5-9533-3474-7| pages=196, 199, 201}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Raoul Wallenberg]], Sweden's [[special envoy]] in Budapest between July and December 1944, had issued protective [[passport]]s and sheltered Jews in buildings [[Extraterritoriality|designated as Swedish territory]], saving tens of thousands of lives.&lt;ref name=YV&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www1.yadvashem.org/search/index_search.html |title=Yad Vashem database |quote=...who saved the lives of tens of thousands of Jews in Budapest during World War II ... and put some 15,000 Jews into 32 safe houses.|accessdate=2007-02-12 |publisher=[[Yad Vashem]] |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070207032351/http://www1.yadvashem.org/search/index_search.html |archivedate=February 7, 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; On January 17, 1945,&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://www.raoul-wallenberg.eu/articles/raoul-wallenbergs-arrest-order-signed-by-bulganin-in-january-1945/| title=Raoul Wallenberg’s arrest order, signed by Bulganin in January 1945| publisher=Searching for Raoul Wallenberg| accessdate=2014-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt; Wallenberg, who allegedly had links with British, American and Swedish intelligence,&lt;ref name=Time/&gt; was detained by Soviet authorities and taken to Moscow with his Hungarian driver, Vilmos Langfelder. He subsequently [[forced disappearance|disappeared]] in the [[USSR]] and his fate is still unknown.&lt;ref name=Time&gt;{{cite news| url=http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1807803,00.html |work=[[Time (magazine)|Time]] |title=Unraveling Raoul Wallenberg's Secrets |date=May 19, 2008 |last=Nadler |first=John}}&lt;/ref&gt;

After the city's surrender, occupying troops forcibly conscripted all able-bodied Hungarian men and youth to build pontoon bridges across the Danube River. For weeks afterward, especially after the spring thaw, bloated bodies piled up against these same pontoons and bridge pylons.&lt;ref name=Zwack&gt;{{cite web| title=World War II: Siege of  Budapest| first=Peter B. |last=Zwack |url=http://www.historynet.com/world-war-ii-siege-of-budapest.htm | publisher=HistoryNet| accessdate=21 December 2012 |date=June 12, 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Impact on civilians===
According to researcher and author [[Krisztián Ungváry]], some 38,000 [[civilian]]s died during the siege: about 13,000 from military action and 25,000 from starvation, disease and other causes. Although the Soviet staff gave orders prohibiting ill-treatment of prisoners of war and civilians to almost every unit&lt;ref name="Ungvary 512"/&gt;{{rp|278}} and took harsh measures against the violators,&lt;ref name="Ungvary 512"/&gt;{{rp|295}} after the end of hostilities Budapest was flooded by Soviet [[desertion|deserters]] living on pillage and fighting against the [[NKVD|Soviet security service]] and police,&lt;ref name="Ungvary 512"/&gt;{{rp|294}} and excesses such as looting and mass [[rape]] were carried out by Soviets and Hungarian criminals.&lt;ref name="Ungvary 512"/&gt;{{rp|286, 294}} Despite the fact that the Soviets often took children and entire families under their protection and had a taboo on hurting children,&lt;ref name="Ungvary 512"/&gt;{{rp|293}} a high number of women and girls were raped,&lt;ref name="Ungvary 512"/&gt;{{rp|348–350}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal| first=Mark| last=James| title=Remembering Rape: Divided Social Memory and the Red Army in Hungary 1944–1945| journal=[[Past &amp; Present (journal)|Past &amp; Present]] |url=http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/past_and_present/v188/188.1mark.html| doi=10.1093/pastj/gti020| volume=188| issue=August 2005| pages=133–161| issn=1477-464X| publisher=Oxford University Press}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=rape group=notes&gt;"The worst suffering of the Hungarian population is due to the rape of women. Rapes—affecting all age groups from ten to seventy are so common that very few women in Hungary have been spared." Swiss embassy report cited in Ungváry 2005, p.350. (Krisztian Ungvary ''The Siege of Budapest'' 2005)&lt;/ref&gt; although estimates vary from 5,000 to 200,000.&lt;ref name=Bessel&gt;{{cite book |last=Bessel |first=Richard |author2=Dirk Schumann |title=Life after Death: Approaches to a Cultural and Social History of Europe |publisher=Cambridge University Press |date=May 5, 2003 |pages=376 |isbn=0-521-00922-7 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=NilW70Yol74C}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|129}} Professor Andrea Pető warns that "uncertain, wild estimates" were used for political purposes in Hungary to divert public attention away from the crimes committed by that country, including rapes committed against Soviet women by Hungarians.&lt;ref name=Bessel/&gt;{{rp|133}}&lt;ref name=revisionism group=notes&gt;"...the uncertain, wild numbers circulating publicly allowed Hungary to redefine its national identity after the war, creating the myth that Hungary suffered at the hands of not only Nazi Germany but also the Red Army. In Hungary, mentioning the crimes (rape and looting) committed by the Red Army was viewed as a diversion of public attention away from the crimes committed by Hungary as a part of the Nazi war machine. Because the Red Army was stationed in Hungary permanently after 1945, the rapes became a nonissue at the level of public discourse. A predictable development of post-1989 Hungarian historiography has been to stress the martyrdom of Hungary, following the lead of scholarship written and published in the West by Hungarian emigres who were far away not only from archival sources but also from the monolithic historical explanation of communist historiography. The uncertain, wild estimates allowed both Austria and Hungary to redefine their national identities after the war, creating for Austria the myth of the first victim to suffer not only from Nazi Germany but from the Red Army as well." Andrea Pető. Memory and the Narrative of Rape in Budapest and Vienna in 1945 // Life after Death, Cambridge University Press, 2003, p. 133&lt;/ref&gt; Hungarian girls were kidnapped and taken to Red Army quarters, where they were imprisoned, repeatedly raped and sometimes murdered.&lt;ref name="Naimark"&gt;{{cite book |first=Norman M. |last=Naimark |title=The Russians in Germany: A History of the Soviet Zone of Occupation, 1945–1949 |publisher=Cambridge: Belknap |year=1995 |isbn=0-674-78405-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|70–71}}
&lt;!--===Casualties of the Soviet and Romanian forces===
'''VII Romanian Army Corps:''' (for all of January, it has been deduced from the structure of attacking forces):
*Corps staff - seven killed, 19 wounded, three missing, three sick.
*2nd Infantry Division - 147 killed, 654 wounded, 29 missing, 149 sick.
*19th Infantry Division – 181 killed, 936 wounded, 12 missing, 42 sick.
*9th Cavalry Division – 79 killed, 272 wounded, six sick.
[[File:Budapest medal.jpg|thumb|100px|The [[Orders, decorations, and medals of the Soviet Union|''Budapest Medal'']] was awarded to all [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] service personnel who took part in the battle]]
'''18th Soviet Rifle Corps''' (66th Guards, 68th Guards, 297th, 317th rifle divisions, 1–10 January) – 791 killed, 2,588 wounded, 50 missing, 72 sick.
'''25th Guards rifle division''' (20–31 January) – in all 452 men, including 29 killed.
'''All besieging forces''' (1–10 February) – 1,044 killed, 3,411 wounded, 52 missing, 276 sick.--&gt;

==Memoirs and diaries==
The events in the [[Naphegy]] and [[Krisztinaváros]] neighborhoods of Budapest are told in a few surviving diaries and memoirs. Charles Farkas (Farkas Karoly) was born in 1926 and includes his experience during the siege in his memoir ''Vanished by the Danube: Peace, War, Revolution, and Flight to the West''. László Dezső, a 15-year-old boy in 1944, lived at 32 Mészáros Street with his family. This area was heavily attacked because of its proximity to the [[Southern Railway Station (Budapest)|Southern Railway Station]] (Déli pályaudvar) and the strategic importance of the hill. Dezső kept a diary throughout the siege.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rev.hu/html/hu/tanulmanyok/1945elott/bpostroma.htm Deseő László naplója] (Hungarian) {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070127101545/http://www.rev.hu/html/hu/tanulmanyok/1945elott/bpostroma.htm |date=January 27, 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; The memoirs of András Németh also describe the siege and the bombing of the empty school buildings which he and his fellow soldiers used as an observation post.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| url=http://mek.oszk.hu/02800/02801/02801.htm#7| first=Németh| last=András| title=Buda| work=Mostohafiak| language=Hungarian| accessdate=2014-12-01}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The memoirs of Heinz Landau, ''Goodbye Transylvania'', present a German soldier's view of the battle. ''Pinball Games: Arts of Survival in Nazi and Communist Eras'',&lt;ref name=Eber&gt;{{cite book| publisher=Trafford Publishing| date=17 May 2010| url=https://www.amazon.com/Pinball-Games-George-F-Eber/dp/1426924801#reader_1426924801| title=Pinball Games: Arts of Survival in Nazi and Communist Eras| last=Eber| first=George F.| isbn=978-1-42693-688-3}}&lt;/ref&gt; written by George F. Eber, a richly detailed account of a 20-year-old Hungarian and his family living through the siege, was published posthumously in 2010. It chronicles the clever strategies employed for survival and outlined the boredom and terror of a family that was trapped, but would not capitulate. Eber, who had become an internationally known architect, included sketches with the memoir. One of them depicts a Russian soldier silhouetted against a Budapest wall on the first night the Germans were driven out of his neighborhood. The memoir also includes an account of World War II and the post-war transition of the country into Soviet-style Communism.

The memoirs of the 14-year-old dispatch runner of the Vannay Volunteer Battalion, [[Ervin Y. Galantay]], give an insight into the battle and urban combat. The diary of the young runner describes day-to-day life and survival of both civilians and soldiers. It was published in English by the Militaria press in Budapest in 2005, under the title ''Boy Soldier''.

Joseph Szentkiralyi, who had worked in the United States prior to World War II, had been deported to Hungary as an [[enemy alien]] after the war began. During the siege, he and his family endured constant artillery bombardment and street-by-street tank and infantry battles between the Germans, the remnants of the [[Royal Hungarian Army]], and the attacking Romanian, and Soviet forces. Szentkiralyi, wanted for questioning by Hungarian army officers, hid on the upper floors of buildings during bombing raids to avoid capture. To prevent starvation and help keep their families alive, Szentkiralyi and others risked their lives to leave their bomb shelters at night and butcher frozen horse carcasses they found in the streets. At the end, daily rations consisted of melted snow, horse meat, and 150 grams of bread. Szentkiralyi worked for the Allies after the war ended. Learning that he faced imminent arrest, he fled to Switzerland to avoid detention and likely execution by the Soviets.&lt;ref name="pinewebhistory"&gt;{{cite web |title=White Stag History Since 1933 |url=http://whitestag.org/history/history.html |first1= Joe| last1=St. Clair |first2=Brian |last2=Phelps |first3=Béla |last3=Bánáthy| year=1996 |accessdate=2008-08-03}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Budapest Offensive]]
* [[Soviet occupation of Hungary]]
* [[Forced labor of Hungarians in the Soviet Union]]
* [[Hospital in the Rock]]
* [[Budapest Ghetto]]

==Notes==
&lt;references group="notes"/&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book
 | last1 = Frieser
 | first1 = Karl-Heinz
 | author-link1 = Karl-Heinz Frieser
 | first2 =Klaus 
 | last2 = Schmider
 | first3 =Klaus 
 | last3 = Schönherr
 | first4 = Gerhard 
 | last4 = Schreiber
 | first5 = Kristián 
 | last5 = Ungváry
 | author-link5 = Krisztián Ungváry
 | first6 =Bernd 
 | last6=Wegner
 | work = [[Das Deutsche Reich und der Zweite Weltkrieg]] [Germany and the Second World War]
 | volume = VIII
 | title = Die Ostfront 1943/44 – Der Krieg im Osten und an den Nebenfronten
 | trans-title = The Eastern Front 1943–1944: The War in the East and on the Neighbouring Fronts
 | publisher = Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt 
 | location = München
 | year = 2007
 | isbn = 978-3-421-06235-2
 | language = German
 | ref = harv
 }}
* {{cite book
 | first1 = Kristián 
 | last1 = Ungváry
 | author-link5 = Krisztián Ungváry
 | title = Budapest Ostroma
 | trans-title = Battle for Budapest
 | publisher = I.B. Tauris
 | location = London
 | year = 2003
 | isbn = 1 86064 727 8 
 | language = Hungarian
 | ref = harv
 }}
*John F. Montgomery, ''Hungary: The Unwilling Satellite''. Devin-Adair Company, New York, 1947. Reprint: Simon Publications, 2002. Available online at [http://historicaltextarchive.com/books.php?op=viewbook&amp;bookid=7&amp;pre=1 Historical Text Archive] and at the [http://www.hungarianhistory.com/lib/montgo/ Corvinus Library of Hungarian History].
*Gosztony, Peter: ''Der Kampf um Budapest, 1944/45, München'' : Schnell &amp; Steiner, 1964.
*Nikolai Shefov, ''Russian fights'', Lib. Military History, M. 2002.
*James Mark. ''Remembering Rape: Divided Social Memory and the Red Army in Hungary 1944–1945.'' Past and Present 2005: 188: 133–161 (Oxford University Press).
*[[Krisztián Ungváry]], ''The Siege of Budapest: One Hundred Days in World War II'' (trans. Ladislaus Löb), Yale University Press, 2005, {{ISBN|0-300-10468-5}}
*Source about Soviet casualties, estimated at 80,000, not 160,000: https://archive.is/20121221115318/http://www.victory.mil.ru/war/oper/15.html
*Ervin V. Galantay. ''Boy Soldier – Budapest 1944–45'', Militaria press, Budapest 2005. 319p. With photos, sketches and footnotes.
*Balázs Mihályi: Budapest battlefield guide 1944–1945, Underground, Budapest 2015, 164p., {{ISBN|9631225518}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070930201524/http://www.historynet.com/magazines/mhq/3033336.html World War II: Siege of Budapest]

{{World War II}}

{{coord missing|Hungary}}
{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Budapest, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:Sieges involving the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:Sieges involving Germany]]
[[Category:Sieges involving Romania]]
[[Category:Sieges involving Hungary]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Hungary]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Romania]]
[[Category:History of Budapest]]
[[Category:Urban warfare]]
[[Category:Hungary–Soviet Union relations]]
[[Category:1944 in Hungary]]
[[Category:1945 in Hungary]]
[[Category:1940s in Budapest]]
[[Category:Sieges of World War II]]
[[Category:December 1944 events]]
[[Category:January 1945 events]]
[[Category:February 1945 events]]
[[Category:Encirclements in World War II]]</text><sha1>2apb41xbxfj0u2hte66ljt8hit56ker</sha1></revision></page>