<page><title>Naval Battle of Casablanca</title><ns>0</ns><id>25445764</id><revision><id>963903421</id><parentid>963815609</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-22T13:18:29Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Snagemit</username><id>39030591</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="35741" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Naval Battle of Casablanca
| partof      = [[Operation Torch]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = Jeanbart.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = ''Jean Bart'' at Casablanca under attack by aircraft from USS ''Ranger''
| date        = 8–16 November 1942
| place       = [[Casablanca]], [[French protectorate of Morocco|French Morocco]]
| result      = American victory
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|United States|1912}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Vichy France}} &lt;br&gt; {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagdeco|United States|1912}} [[Henry Kent Hewitt|Henry Hewitt]]
| commander2  = {{flagdeco|Vichy France|naval}} Félix Michelier &lt;br&gt; {{flagdeco|Nazi Germany|naval}} [[Ernst Kals]]
| strength1   = 1 aircraft carrier &lt;br&gt; 1 escort carrier &lt;br&gt; 1 battleship &lt;br&gt; 3 heavy cruisers &lt;br&gt; 1 light cruiser &lt;br&gt; 14 destroyers &lt;br&gt; 15 troopships &lt;br&gt; 347 landing craft &lt;br&gt; 108 aircraft
| strength2   = 1 battleship &lt;br&gt; 1 light cruiser &lt;br&gt; 2 flotilla leaders &lt;br&gt; 7 destroyers &lt;br&gt; 8 sloops &lt;br&gt; 11 minesweepers &lt;br&gt; 13 submarines &lt;br&gt; 7 aircraft
| casualties1 = 174 killed &lt;br&gt; 4 troopships sunk &lt;br&gt; 150 landing craft sunk &lt;br&gt; 5 aircraft destroyed &lt;br&gt; 1 battleship damaged &lt;br&gt; 1 heavy cruiser damaged &lt;br&gt; 2 destroyers damaged &lt;br&gt; 1 oiler damaged
| casualties2 = 462 killed &lt;br&gt; 200 wounded &lt;br&gt; 1 battleship damaged &lt;br&gt; 1 light cruiser destroyed &lt;br&gt; 4 destroyers sunk &lt;br&gt; 7 submarines sunk &lt;br&gt; 1 submarine scuttled &lt;br&gt; 7 aircraft destroyed &lt;br&gt; 2 submarines damaged &lt;br&gt; 1 destroyer grounded &lt;br&gt; 2 flotilla leaders grounded &lt;br&gt; 1 submarine grounded
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox North Africa}}
{{Campaignbox Atlantic Campaign}}
}}

The '''Naval Battle of Casablanca''' was a series of naval engagements fought between [[United States Navy|American]] ships covering the [[Operation Torch|invasion of North Africa]] and [[Vichy France|Vichy French]] ships defending the [[Neutrality (international relations)|neutrality]] of [[French Morocco]] in accordance with the [[Second Armistice at Compiègne]] during [[World War II]].&lt;ref&gt;Auphan &amp; Mordal (1976), p. 210&lt;/ref&gt; The last stages of the battle consisted of operations by [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[U-boat]]s which had reached the area the same day the French troops surrendered.{{#tag:ref|Robert Cressman, in his book USS Ranger:the Navy's first flattop from keel to mast, 1934–1946, recounts the sinking of three troopships by ''U-130'' on 12 November.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book| first=Robert| last=Cressman| title=USS Ranger: the Navy's first flattop from keel to mast, 1934–46| publisher= Brassey's |location=Washington, D.C.| year=2003| page=291| isbn=978-1-57488-720-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; ''U-130'' was one of the submarines ordered to investigate early reports of invasion convoys on 2 November&lt;ref name="Blair88"&gt;Blair (1998), p. 88&lt;/ref&gt; after sailing from France on 29 October.&lt;ref&gt;Blair (1998), p. 736&lt;/ref&gt; All were delayed by battle damage or mechanical difficulties.&lt;ref name="Blair88"/&gt; ''U-130'' approached the Fedala troopship anchorage after Casablanca had surrendered by sailing along the Moroccan coast on the evening of 11 November&lt;ref&gt;Blair (1998), p. 110&lt;/ref&gt;|group="note"}}

Allied military planners anticipated an all-American force assigned to seize the [[Atlantic Ocean|Atlantic]] [[port]] city of [[Casablanca]] might be greeted as liberators. An invasion task force of 102 American ships carrying 35,000 American soldiers approached the Moroccan coast undetected under cover of darkness. French defenders interpreted the first contacts as a diversionary raid for a major landing in [[Algeria]]; and Germany regarded the surrender of six Moroccan [[Division (military)|divisions]] to a small [[commando]] raiding force as a clear violation of French obligations to defend Moroccan neutrality under the [[Armistice of 22 June 1940]] at Compiègne.&lt;ref&gt;Potter &amp; Nimitz (1960), pp. 568–574&lt;/ref&gt; An escalating series of surprised responses in an atmosphere of mistrust and secrecy caused the loss of four U.S. [[troopship]]s and the deaths of 462 men aboard 24 French ships opposing the invasion.&lt;ref&gt;Auphan &amp; Mordal (1976), pp. 210, 228–229 &amp; 236&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
[[Morocco]] was a protectorate of France at the time of World War II. The [[Vichy France|French government at Vichy]] had surrendered to Germany after the [[Battle of France]], signing an [[Second Armistice at Compiègne|Armistice with Nazi Germany]]. General [[Charles de Gaulle]] led French forces opposed to the surrender and to the Vichy government, continuing the war on the side of Great Britain and the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]]. The Vichy regime—which controlled Morocco—was thus officially neutral, but in practical terms the Armistice obliged Vichy to resist any attempt to seize French territory or equipment for use against Germany. British forces had bombarded the French [[Attack on Mers-el-Kébir|at Mers-el-Kébir]] after the French rejected demands to join the Allies or sail to a neutral port, leading to much ill-will between France and Britain. The [[Federal government of the United States|United States government]] had previously recognized the Vichy regime as legitimate. Military planning for [[Operation Torch]] in 1942 emphasized American troops in the initial landing forces on the basis of intelligence estimates they would be less vigorously opposed than British soldiers.&lt;ref&gt;Potter &amp; Nimitz (1960), p. 567&lt;/ref&gt;

===American forces===
[[Troopship]] [[UG convoys|convoy UGF 1]] left [[Chesapeake Bay]] on 23 October 1942 and was joined on 26 October by a [[covering force]] of [[battleship]]s and [[cruiser]]s sailing from [[Casco Bay]] and on 28 October by the [[aircraft carrier]] {{USS|Ranger|CV-4|6}}, and the [[escort carriers]] {{USS|Sangamon|CVE-26|2}}, {{USS|Suwannee|CVE-27|2}}, {{USS|Chenango|CVE-28|2}}, and {{USS|Santee|CVE-29|2}} sailing from [[Bermuda]]. These ships were screened by 38 American [[destroyer]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Blair (1998), p. 92&lt;/ref&gt; The resulting Task Force 34 (TF&amp;nbsp;34) included 102 ships for the invasion of Morocco under the command of Rear Admiral [[Henry Kent Hewitt]] aboard the flagship [[heavy cruiser]] {{USS|Augusta|CA-31|6}}. As TF&amp;nbsp;34 sailed, the British [[submarine]] {{HMS|Seraph|P219|6}} landed Major General [[Mark W. Clark]] near [[Algiers]] to [[Operation Flagpole (World War II)|meet with pro-American French military officers]] stationed in Algeria. French officers shared information about defensive arrangements; but the Americans did not share critical invasion details of timing, strength and distribution of forces.&lt;ref&gt;Potter &amp; Nimitz (1960), pp. 568–571&lt;/ref&gt; No information was provided to key French leaders including Armed Forces Commander in Chief Admiral [[François Darlan]], North African Commander in Chief General [[Alphonse Juin]], or Moroccan Resident General Charles Noguès.&lt;ref&gt;Auphan &amp; Mordal (1976), pp. 212–215&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Casablanca SPOT 1208.jpg|left|thumb|Casablanca in 2006 picture from space.]]

===French forces===
In 1942, Casablanca was the principal Vichy-controlled port on the Atlantic (all of France′s Atlantic coast having been [[German occupation of France during World War II|occupied by Germany since 1940]]) and the most important Vichy-controlled naval base after [[Toulon]]. Naval gunners manned the El Hank [[coastal artillery]] battery of four {{convert|194|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns and four {{convert|138|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns.  One quadruple [[380 mm/45 Modèle 1935 gun]] turret of the modern battleship {{Ship|French battleship|Jean Bart|1940|2}} was operational, although the battleship remained incomplete following escape from the [[Saint-Nazaire]] shipyards during the German invasion of 1940. One light cruiser, two [[flotilla leader]]s, seven [[destroyer]]s (two already damaged by collision), eight [[Sloop-of-war|sloops]], 11 [[Minesweeper (ship)|minesweepers]], and 11 submarines were in port on the morning of 8 November.&lt;ref&gt;Auphan &amp; Mordal (1976), p. 228&lt;/ref&gt;

Most French personnel attending General Clark′s pre-invasion meeting were army officers. Information subsequently conveyed in pre-invasion contact with army personnel stationed in Morocco was interpreted as a request for recommendations. No pre-invasion contact has been documented with Vice Admiral Michelier, who commanded naval forces responsible for the defense of Casablanca. Admiral Michelier was not yet in the confidence of North African officers in contact with the Americans, since he had been a member of the Armistice Commission until assuming his Casablanca post less than a month before the invasion.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://alamer.fr/index.php?NIUpage=31&amp;Param1=1615|title=ALAMER: Mémoire des Équipages des marines de guerre, commerce, pêche &amp; plaisance de 1939 à 1945|accessdate=18 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==
French defenders were placed on alert status when Algerian invasion convoys were detected passing through the [[Strait of Gibraltar]].&lt;ref&gt;Auphan &amp; Mordal (1976), pp. 212–218&lt;/ref&gt; Destinations remained unclear, and TF&amp;nbsp;34 remained undetected as it split into three groups on 7 November. Concealed by darkness, a northern group (six troopships and two cargo ships escorted by the battleship {{USS|Texas|BB-35|6}}, the light cruiser {{USS|Savannah|CL-42|6}} and six destroyers)&lt;ref&gt;Karig (1946), p. 191&lt;/ref&gt; prepared to land 9,000 troops of the 60th infantry Regiment reinforced with 65 light tanks to seize the [[Port Lyautey]] airfield; and a southern group (four troopships and two cargo ships escorted by the battleship {{USS|New York|BB-34|6}}, the light cruiser {{USS|Philadelphia|CL-41|6}} and six destroyers)&lt;ref&gt;Karig (1946), p. 184&lt;/ref&gt; prepared to land 6,500 troops of the 47th Infantry Regiment reinforced with 90 medium and light tanks near the phosphate port of [[Safi, Morocco|Safi]] to cover the southern approaches to Casablanca, while the center group prepared to land the Casablanca occupation force of 19,500 troops of the 3rd Infantry Division&lt;ref name="karig201"/&gt; reinforced with 79 light tanks near [[Fedala]] {{convert|15|mi|km|abbr=on}} northeast of Casablanca.&lt;ref&gt;Potter &amp; Nimitz (1960), pp. 571–572&lt;/ref&gt; Naval coastal defense batteries flanked both ends of the Fedala landing beach with four {{convert|138|mm|in|abbr=on}} guns on Pont Blondin &lt;ref group="note"&gt;Some references identify this eastern battery by the Arabic ''Chergui'' sometimes [[Anglicize]]d as ''Sherki''. (Willoughby, p. 210)&lt;/ref&gt; to the east and three {{convert|10|cm|in|abbr=on}} and two {{convert|75|mm|in|0|abbr=on}} guns in Fedala on the point sheltering the western end of the beach.&lt;ref&gt;Auphan &amp; Mordal (1976), p. 231&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===8 November===
[[File:Aerial view of Casablanca harbour in 1942.jpg|thumb|left|Aerial view of Casablanca harbour, 9 November. ''Jean Bart'' is at the far left. Note the sunken ships in the center.]]
Center group troopships {{USS|William P. Biddle|APA-8|6}}, {{USS|Leonard Wood|APA-12|2}},&lt;ref group="note" name="uscg"&gt;Ship manned by [[United States Coast Guard]] crew. (Willoughby, p. 208)&lt;/ref&gt; {{USS|Joseph T. Dickman|APA-13|2}},&lt;ref group="note" name="uscg"/&gt; {{USS|Tasker H. Bliss|AP-42|2}}, {{USS|Hugh L. Scott|AP-43|2}}, {{USS|Joseph Hewes|AP-50|2}}, {{USS|Edward Rutledge|AP-52|2}}, {{USS|Charles Carroll|APA-28|2}}, {{USS|Thomas Jefferson|APA-30|2}}, {{USS|Ancon|AGC-4|2}}, {{USS|Elizabeth C. Stanton|AP-69|2}}, {{USS|Thurston|AP-77|2}}, {{USS|Arcturus|AKA-1|2}}, {{USS|Procyon|AKA-2|2}}, and {{USS|Oberon|AKA-14|2}}&lt;ref name="karig201"&gt;Karig (1946), p. 201&lt;/ref&gt; anchored {{convert|8|mi|nmi km|lk=on|abbr=on}} off Fedala at midnight. Loaded landing craft rendezvoused and left the line of departure at 06:00.&lt;ref group="note" name="time"&gt;Morocco observed [[Greenwich Mean Time]] (GMT) time; but, at 7°&amp;nbsp;35′ West, Casablanca was 30 minutes behind the prime meridian. Astronomical sunrise was 06:54 GMT on the day of the invasion. TF&amp;nbsp;34's clocks were apparently set to [[UTC-1]]. The commencement of ''Massachusetts''{{'}} shelling of Casablanca harbor is reported as 08:04 by Auphan &amp; Mordal, but 07:04 by USN sources Karig and Potter &amp; Nimitz. Times specified in those references have been adjusted to GMT to conform to other references and clarify the sequence of events.&lt;/ref&gt; Pont Blondin coast defense batteries were alerted by the noise of landing craft engines and illuminated the beach approaches with searchlights but the searchlights were extinguished when the landing craft support boats opened fire with [[machine gun]]s. The destroyer {{USS|Wilkes|DD-441|2}} and a scout boat tasked with marking red beach 2 moved out of position while maneuvering to avoid an unidentified boat evaluated as potentially hostile; and landing craft ran onto rocks while running at full speed rather than reaching their intended beach. Twenty-one of the 32 landing craft from ''Leonard Wood'' were wrecked. Eight of the ship's surviving landing craft were wrecked in heavy surf landing later waves.&lt;ref&gt;Willoughby (1957), p. 210&lt;/ref&gt;

3,500 American troops were ashore by dawn; but early morning mist concealed the size of the invasion force. Fedala coast defense batteries opened fire on the landing craft shortly after 07:00.&lt;ref group="note" name="time"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Potter &amp; Nimitz (1960), pp. 572–575&lt;/ref&gt; At 07:20,&lt;ref group="note" name="time"/&gt; Admiral Hewitt authorized four American destroyers supporting the landing craft to open fire on the French shore batteries.&lt;ref name="karig203"/&gt; French gunners damaged the destroyers {{USS|Ludlow|DD-438|6}} and {{USS|Murphy|DD-603|2}},&lt;ref name="cressman"&gt;Cressman (2000), p. 129&lt;/ref&gt; and at 07:25&lt;ref group="note" name="time"/&gt; the destroyers were defended by the heavier guns of the cruisers ''Augusta'' and {{USS|Brooklyn|CL-40|2}} screening the troopships.&lt;ref name="p&amp;n575"&gt;Potter &amp; Nimitz (1960), p. 575&lt;/ref&gt; ''Ludlow'' and ''Wilkes'' silenced the Pont Blondin battery, while ''Augusta'' silenced the Fedala battery. ''Murphy'', {{USS|Wainwright|DD-419|2}}, and other U.S. vessels engaged two French aircraft just before 07:00 on 8 November, ultimately driving them off.&lt;ref name="cressman"/&gt;
[[File:USS Wichita (CA-45) under fire off Casablanca on 8 November 1942.jpg|thumb|right|The [[heavy cruiser]] {{USS|Wichita|CA-45|6}} under fire off Casablanca.]]

The French submarines ''[[French submarine Amazone (1931)|Amazone]]'', {{ship|French submarine|Antiope||2}}, {{ship|French submarine|Méduse|1930|2}}, {{ship|French submarine|Orphée||2}} and {{ship|French submarine|Sibylle|1932|2}} sortied to defensive patrol stations at 07:00.&lt;ref name="a&amp;m230"&gt;Auphan &amp; Mordal (1960), p. 230&lt;/ref&gt; At 07:50,&lt;ref group="note" name="time"/&gt; French fighters rose to intercept a force of bombers from ''Ranger'' and ''Suwanee''. The French fighters were engaged by fighters from ''Ranger'' in a dogfight that felled seven French and four&lt;ref name="p&amp;n575"/&gt; or five&lt;ref name="a&amp;m230"/&gt; American planes. Bombs started falling on Casablanca Harbor at 08:04.&lt;ref group="note" name="time"/&gt; Ten civilian freighters and liners were sunk&lt;ref name="a&amp;m230"/&gt; and French submarines {{ship|French submarine|Amphitrite|1930|2}}, {{ship|French submarine|Oréade||2}}, and {{ship|French submarine|Psyché|1932|2}} were destroyed at their moorings before they could get underway.&lt;ref name="cressman"/&gt; The American covering force of {{USS|Massachusetts|BB-59|2}}, {{USS|Wichita|CA-45|2}} and {{USS|Tuscaloosa|CA-37|2}} screened by destroyers {{USS|Mayrant|DD-402|2}}, {{USS|Rhind|DD-404|2}}, ''Wainwright'', and {{USS|Jenkins|DD-447|2}} appeared offshore and ''Massachusetts''{{'}} {{convert|16|in|mm|abbr=on}} guns were added to the bombardment.&lt;ref name="a&amp;m230"/&gt; The El Hank battery observed gunfire from the covering force and straddled ''Massachusetts'' with its first salvo. The operational turret aboard the incomplete battleship {{Ship|French battleship|Jean Bart|1940|2}} also opened fire and was targeted by ''Massachusetts''. ''Jean Bart'' had fired only seven rounds before ''Massachusetts''{{'}} fifth salvo jammed the turret rotating mechanism on ''Jean Bart''. ''Massachusetts''{{'}} heavy 16-inch projectiles caused significant damage although few actually exploded because they had been fitted with [[fuze]]s manufactured in 1918.&lt;ref&gt;Atkinson (2002), p. 131&lt;/ref&gt; The covering force then targeted El Hank Battery from 08:40&lt;ref name= "karig206"&gt;Karig (1946), p. 206&lt;/ref&gt; to 09:25.&lt;ref group="note" name="time"/&gt;&lt;ref name="p&amp;n575"/&gt;
[[File:MassKamaichi.jpg|thumb|right|''Massachusetts''{{'}}s nine 16-inch guns (shown firing in the Pacific) gave United States forces a significant naval artillery advantage at Casablanca.]]
[[File:80-G-323977 (34996394605).jpg|thumb|Aerial attack on a French submarine off the coast of French Morocco]]

While the covering force engaged El Hank Battery west of Casablanca, seven ships of the French 2nd Light Squadron sortied from Casablanca harbor at 09:00&lt;ref name="a&amp;m230"/&gt; under cover of a smoke screen to attack the troopships anchored off Fedala to the east.&lt;ref name="p&amp;n575"/&gt; The French destroyer {{Ship|French destroyer|Milan||2}} sortied with destroyers {{ship|French destroyer|Fougueux||2}} and {{ship|French destroyer|Boulonnais||2}}. At 09:20, the French squadron was strafed by fighter planes from ''Ranger''.&lt;ref name="a&amp;m230"/&gt; French gunners sank a landing craft and scored hits on ''Ludlow''.&lt;ref name="a&amp;m233"&gt;Auphan &amp; Mordal (1976), p. 233&lt;/ref&gt; ''Milan'' beached after being damaged by gunfire from ''Wilkes'',&lt;ref name="r&amp;h175"&gt;Rohwer &amp; Hummelchen (1992), p. 175&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name= "brown"&gt;Brown (1995), p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; ''Wichita'', and ''Tuscaloosa''.&lt;ref name="cressman"/&gt; ''Massachusetts'' and ''Tuscaloosa'' engaged the French destroyers ''Fougueux'' at 10:00 and ''Boulonnais'' at 10:12.&lt;ref name="brown"/&gt; ''Fougueux'' sank at 10:40.&lt;ref name="a&amp;m233"/&gt; The French [[light cruiser]] {{Ship|French cruiser|Primauguet|1924|2}} sortied with flotilla leader destroyer {{ship|French destroyer|Albatros||2}} and destroyers {{ship|French destroyer|Brestois||2}} and {{ship|French destroyer|Frondeur||2}}. Engaged by ''Massachusetts'', the ''Primauguet'' force was outgunned; ''Primauguet'' had been under refit and was not fully operational but returned fire nonetheless. The French flotilla was also engaged by ''Augusta'' and ''Brooklyn'' from 11:00 to 11:20.&lt;ref name="brown"/&gt; ''Albatros'' beached to avoid sinking. The remaining ships returned to Casablanca harbor where ''Primauguet'' beached and burnt out and the two destroyers capsized. Forty-five crew members were killed aboard ''Primauguet'', and more than 200 more wounded. The French submarine ''Amazone'' missed ''Brooklyn'' with a salvo of torpedoes.&lt;ref name="cressman"/&gt;&lt;ref name="r&amp;h175"/&gt; ''Sibylle'' disappeared on a patrol station between Casablanca and Fedala, but the cause of her destruction remains uncertain.&lt;ref name= "cressman"/&gt;&lt;ref name="a&amp;m235"&gt;Auphan &amp; Mordal (1976), p. 235&lt;/ref&gt; Surviving French submarines {{ship|French submarine|Sidi-Ferruch|Q181|2}} and {{ship|French submarine|Le Conquerant|Q171|2}} sortied without torpedoes to avoid destruction in the harbor. {{ship|French submarine|Le Tonnant|Q172|2}} managed to load a few torpedoes before leaving. ''Augusta'' sank ''Boulonnais''&lt;ref name="cressman"/&gt; at noon&lt;ref name="a&amp;m233"/&gt; and the only French destroyer remaining operational was {{ship|French destroyer|L'Alcyon||2}}.&lt;ref name="p&amp;n575"/&gt;&lt;ref name="a&amp;m233"/&gt;

A less significant victim of this engagement was the boat in which [[George S. Patton|General Patton]] had intended to reach the beach from the flagship ''Augusta''. The boat had been swung out on davits in preparation for launch when [[muzzle flash#Muzzle blast|muzzle blast]] from the cruiser's 8-inch guns blew out the bottom of the boat, causing most of Patton's luggage to be lost overboard.&lt;ref&gt;Atkinson (2002), p. 132&lt;/ref&gt;

Three small French warships emerged from Casablanca harbor in the early afternoon to rescue sailors from the sunken destroyer ''Fougueux'', but the rescue ships were turned back by shellfire from the American covering force.&lt;ref group="note"&gt;Potter and Nimitz refer to a destroyer and two sloops, and Auphan and Mordal identify the destroyer as ''L'Alcyon''. Cressman identifies the three ships as the 1969-ton colonial sloop ''La Grandiere'' with second class sloops ''La Gracieuse'' and ''Commandant Delage''. ''La Grandiere'' was about the size of a destroyer with three {{convert|14|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns and a maximum speed of 15 knots. ''Jane's Fighting Ships'' refers to the second class sloops as 20-knot, 630-ton minesweepers armed with two {{convert|9|cm|in|abbr=on}} guns.&lt;/ref&gt; French planes bombed and strafed the landing beach at intervals throughout the day, but caused little damage.&lt;ref name=w211&gt;Willoughby (1957), p. 211&lt;/ref&gt; Workmen had repaired ''Jean Bart''{{'}}s turret by sundown, and El Hank Battery remained operational. Nearly half of the 347 American landing craft had been destroyed, and fewer than 8,000 troops had been landed. Five French submarines still stalked the invasion fleet.&lt;ref&gt;Potter &amp; Nimitz (1960), p. 576&lt;/ref&gt;

===9 November===
Dawn found the Fedala landing beaches lashed by {{convert|6|ft|m|adj=on}} waves which greatly impeded unloading the invasion troopships. Forty percent of the troops were ashore with barely one percent of their supplies. There were shortages of ammunition, and inadequate medical supplies for the wounded. Communications broke down because radio equipment was still aboard the troopships. The advance toward Casablanca halted because shore parties lacked mechanized equipment to move supplies off the landing beach.&lt;ref&gt;Atkinson (2002), pp. 138–140&lt;/ref&gt;

===10 November===
The French minesweepers ''Commandant Delage'' and ''La Gracieuse'' sortied at 10:00 to open fire on American troops advancing from Fedala to the outskirts of Casablanca.&lt;ref name= "cressman2"&gt;Cressman (2000), p. 130&lt;/ref&gt; The cruiser ''Augusta'' and destroyers {{USS|Edison|DD-439|2}} and {{USS|Tillman|DD-641|2}} chased the minesweepers back into Casablanca harbor before being forced to retreat by gunfire from ''Jean Bart''.&lt;ref name="cressman2"/&gt; Nine dive bombers from ''Ranger''&lt;ref name="karig209"&gt;Karig (1946), p. 209&lt;/ref&gt; hit ''Jean Bart'' with two {{convert|1000|lb|kg|abbr=on}} bombs and sank her at 16:00.&lt;ref name="a&amp;m235"/&gt; ''Jean Bart'' settled into the harbor mud with decks awash.&lt;ref name="p&amp;n577"&gt;Potter &amp; Nimitz (1960), p. 577&lt;/ref&gt; French submarines ''Le Tonnant'', ''Meduse'' and ''Antiope'' launched unsuccessful torpedo salvos at ''Ranger'', ''Massachusetts'' and ''Tuscaloosa'', respectively.&lt;ref name="cressman"/&gt;&lt;ref name= "r&amp;h175"/&gt; ''Meduse'' was crippled by counterattacks and beached off Cape Blanc.&lt;ref name= "cressman2"/&gt;

===11 November===
[[File:TBF mid1942.jpg|right|thumb|250px|A [[Grumman TBF Avenger]] [[torpedo bomber]], mid-1942.]]

Casablanca surrendered on 11 November while 11,000 tons (75 percent) of supplies for the invading troops remained aboard the troopships.&lt;ref&gt;Atkinson (2002), p. 151&lt;/ref&gt; That day German submarines were able to reach the troopships before they completed offloading cargo.&lt;ref name="p&amp;n577"/&gt; In the early evening, {{GS|U-173||2}} torpedoed the destroyer {{USS|Hambleton|DD-455|2}}, the oiler {{USS|Winooski|AO-38|2}} and the troopship ''Joseph Hewes''; around 100 men went down with ''Joseph Hewes''. At this time, ''Bristol'' spotted a surfaced submarine and engaged with her deck guns and finally with depth charges, but is not believed to have sunk the French submarine. ''Sidi Ferruch'' was sunk by [[Grumman TBF Avenger]] [[torpedo bomber]]s from ''Suwanee'' on 11 November.&lt;ref name= "cressman"/&gt;&lt;ref name="cressman2"/&gt;

===Final actions===
The invasion troopships remained in their makeshift anchorage to keep Casablanca's harbor open to unload additional troops from the anticipated arrival of [[UG convoys|convoy UGF-2]]&lt;ref&gt;Atkinson (2002), p. 154&lt;/ref&gt; until {{GS|U-130|1941|2}}—under [[Ernst Kals]]—torpedoed the troopships ''Tasker H. Bliss'', ''Hugh L. Scott'', and ''Edward Rutledge'' on the evening of 12 November, killing 74 additional American servicemen;&lt;ref&gt;Cressman (2000), p. 131&lt;/ref&gt; and prompting undamaged troopships to leave the anchorage and maneuver evasively at sea until they were able to moor in the lee of the Casablanca breakwater on 13 November to complete offloading supplies. Of the American ships damaged by submarine torpedoes on 11 and 12 November, all four troopships sank, but the oiler and destroyer were repaired. Surviving troopships left Casablanca when unloading was completed on 17 November.&lt;ref name=w211/&gt; French submarines ''Amazone'' and ''Antiope'' reached Dakar, and ''Orphee'' returned to Casablanca after the city surrendered.&lt;ref name="r&amp;h175"/&gt; ''Le Conquerant'' was sunk on 13 November by two VP-92 [[Consolidated PBY Catalina|PBY Catalina]] [[flying boat]]s off  Villa Cisneros.&lt;ref&gt;Auphan &amp; Mordal (1976), p. 236&lt;/ref&gt; ''Le Tonnant'' was scuttled off [[Cadiz]] on 15 November.&lt;ref name="r&amp;h175"/&gt; On 16 November, ''U-173'' was sunk off Casablanca by American destroyers.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://uboat.net/boats/u173.html|title=The Type IXC U-boat U-173 - German U-boats of WWII - uboat.net|website=uboat.net|access-date=2019-07-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The [[Ettedgui Synagogue]] in Casablanca's medina was destroyed in the bombardment.&lt;ref name=":1"&gt;{{Cite web|title=Synagogue Ettedgui · Casablanca|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20180627173217/http://mutualheritage-casablanca.univ-tours.fr/items/show/178|date=2018-06-27|website=web.archive.org|access-date=2020-05-18}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Order of battle==

===French 2nd Light Squadron===
{|class="wikitable"
!Ship
!Type
!Displacement
!Speed
!Guns
!Torpedoes
!Notes
|-
|{{ship|French cruiser|Primauguet|1924|2}}
|{{sclass-|Duguay-Trouin|cruiser|0}} light cruiser
|7,249 tons&lt;ref&gt;Masson (1969), p. 90&lt;/ref&gt;
|33 knots
|8 × 155&amp;nbsp;mm (6.1&amp;nbsp;in)
|12
|Beached and burnt out for total loss
|-
|{{ship|French destroyer|Albatros||2}}
|{{sclass-|Aigle|destroyer|2}}
|2,441 tons&lt;ref name="masson112"&gt;Masson (1969), p. 112&lt;/ref&gt;
|36 knots
|5 × [[Canon de 138 mm Modèle 1927|138 mm Mle 1927]] guns
|6
|Beached to avoid sinking
|-
|{{ship|French destroyer|Milan||2}}
|{{sclass-|Aigle|destroyer|2}}
|2,441 tons&lt;ref name="masson112"/&gt;
|36 knots
|5 × 138&amp;nbsp;mm Mle 1927 guns
|6
|Beached to avoid sinking
|-
|{{ship|French destroyer|Boulonnais||2}}
|{{sclass-|Adroit|destroyer|2}}
|1378 tons&lt;ref name="masson124"&gt;Masson (1969), p. 124&lt;/ref&gt;
|33 knots
|4 × 130&amp;nbsp;mm (5.1&amp;nbsp;in)
|6
&lt;ref name="masson126"&gt;Masson (1969), p. 126&lt;/ref&gt;
|Sunk by USS ''Augusta''
|-
|{{ship|French destroyer|Brestois||2}}
|{{sclass-|Adroit|destroyer|2}}
|1378 tons&lt;ref name="masson124"/&gt;
|33 knots
|4 × 130&amp;nbsp;mm (5.1&amp;nbsp;in)
|6
| Capsized
|-
|{{ship|French destroyer|Fougueux||2}}
|{{sclass-|Adroit|destroyer|2}}
|1378 tons&lt;ref name="masson124"/&gt;
|33 knots
|4 × 130&amp;nbsp;mm (5.1&amp;nbsp;in)
|6
|Sunk by 16" gunfire from USS ''Massachusetts''
|-
|{{ship|French destroyer|Frondeur||2}}
|{{sclass-|Adroit|destroyer|2}}
|1,378 tons&lt;ref name="masson124"/&gt;
|33 knots
|4 × 130&amp;nbsp;mm (5.1&amp;nbsp;in)
|6
|Capsized
|-
|{{ship|French destroyer|L'Alcyon||2}}
|{{sclass-|Adroit|destroyer|2}}
|1378 tons&lt;ref name="masson124"/&gt;
|33 knots
|4 × 130&amp;nbsp;mm (5.1&amp;nbsp;in)
|6
|did not sortie
|-
|{{ship|French destroyer|Simoun||2}}
|{{sclass-|Bourrasque|destroyer|2}}
|1,319 tons&lt;ref name="masson124"/&gt;
|33 knots
|4 × 130&amp;nbsp;mm (5.1&amp;nbsp;in)
|6
|repairing collision damage – did not sortie
|-
|{{ship|French destroyer|Tempête||2}}
|{{sclass-|Bourrasque|destroyer|2}}
|1,319 tons&lt;ref name="masson124"/&gt;
|33 knots
|4 × 130&amp;nbsp;mm (5.1&amp;nbsp;in)
|6
|repairing collision damage – did not sortie
|}

===American covering force===
{|class="wikitable"
!Ship
!Type
!Displacement
!Speed
!Guns
!Torpedoes
!Notes
|-valign=top
|{{USS|Massachusetts|BB-59|2}}
|{{sclass-|South Dakota|battleship (1939)|0}} battleship
|35000 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone28"&gt;Silverstone (1968), p. 28&lt;/ref&gt;
|28 knots
|9 × [[16"/45 caliber Mark 6 gun|16"/45 cal]]&lt;br /&gt;20 × [[5"/38 caliber gun|5"/38 cal]]
|none
|Defeated and sank French battleship ''Jean Bart'' in gun duel, sank a [[floating dry dock]] and up to seven merchant ships in the harbor.
Engaged French 2nd Light Squadron, sank at least one destroyer, assisted in engaging light cruiser and other destroyers.
|-
|{{USS|Wichita|CA-45|2}}
| heavy cruiser
|10000 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone79"&gt;Silverstone (1968), p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;
|34 knots
|9 × [[8"/55 caliber gun|8"/55 cal]]&lt;br /&gt;8 × 5"/38 cal
|none
|engaged and help sink several destroyers, Damaged by a coastal battery with 14 wounded
|-
|{{USS|Tuscaloosa|CA-37|2}}
|{{sclass-|New Orleans|cruiser|0}} heavy cruiser
|9975 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone71"&gt;Silverstone (1968), p. 71&lt;/ref&gt;
|32 knots
|9 × 8"/55 cal&lt;br /&gt;8 × [[5"/25 caliber gun|5"/25 cal]]
|none
|Engaged and help sink several destroyers
|-
|{{USS|Mayrant|DD-402|2}}
|{{sclass-|Benham|destroyer|2}}
|1500 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone124"&gt;Silverstone (1968), p. 124&lt;/ref&gt;
|36 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|16
|''Mayrant{{'}}s'' [[gunnery officer]] was [[Franklin Delano Roosevelt Jr.]], son of the [[President of the United States]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Walker |first=Edward K. |year=1985 |title=Mayrant, Roosevelt, and the Med |journal=Proceedings |volume=111 |issue=10 |page=179 |publisher=[[United States Naval Institute]] }}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Rhind|DD-404|2}}
|{{sclass-|Benham|destroyer|2}}
|1500 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone124"/&gt;
|36 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|16
|
|-
|{{USS|Wainwright|DD-419|2}}
|{{sclass-|Sims|destroyer|2}}
|1570 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone126"&gt;Silverstone (1968), p. 126&lt;/ref&gt;
|38 knots
|5 × 5"/38 cal
|12
|
|-
|{{USS|Jenkins|DD-447|2}}
|{{sclass-|Fletcher|destroyer|2}}
|2050 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone132"&gt;Silverstone (1968), p. 135&lt;/ref&gt;
|37 knots
|5 × 5"/38 cal
|10
|
|-
|{{USS|Augusta|CA-31|2}}
|{{sclass-|Northampton|cruiser|2}}
|9050 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone67"&gt;Silverstone (1968), p. 67&lt;/ref&gt;
|32 knots
|9 × 8"/55 cal&lt;br /&gt;8 × 5"/25 cal
|none
|operated independently as Task Force 34 flagship
|-
|{{USS|Brooklyn|CL-40|2}}
|{{sclass-|Brooklyn|cruiser|2}}
|9700 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone85"&gt;Silverstone (1968), p. 85&lt;/ref&gt;
|33 knots
|15 × [[Mark 16/1 triple 6 in /47 Turret|6"/47]]&lt;br /&gt;8 × 5"/25 cal
|(none)
|assigned as escort for center group troopships&lt;br /&gt;engaged 2nd Light Squadron
|-
|{{USS|Rowan|DD-405|2}}
|{{sclass-|Benham|destroyer|2}}
|1500 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone124"/&gt;
|36 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|16
|screened center group troopships off Fedala&lt;br /&gt;engaged 2nd Light Squadron&lt;ref name= "karig207"&gt;Karig (1946), p. 207&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Woolsey|DD-437|2}}
|{{sclass-|Gleaves|destroyer|2}}
|1620 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone126"/&gt;
|37 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|10
|screened center group troopships off Fedala&lt;ref name="karig201"/&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Ludlow|DD-438|2}}
|{{sclass-|Gleaves|destroyer|2}}
|1620 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone126"/&gt;
|37 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|10
|screened center group troopships off Fedala&lt;br /&gt;engaged Pont Blondin Battery&lt;br /&gt;engaged 2nd Light Squadron&lt;ref name="karig20137"&gt;Karig (1946), pp. 201, 203 &amp; 207&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Edison|DD-439|2}}
|{{sclass-|Gleaves|destroyer|2}}
|1620 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone126"/&gt;
|37 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|10
|screened center group troopships off Fedala&lt;ref name="karig201"/&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Wilkes|DD-441|2}}
|{{sclass-|Gleaves|destroyer|2}}
|1620 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone126"/&gt;
|37 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|10
|screened center group troopships off Fedala&lt;br /&gt;engaged Fedala Battery&lt;br /&gt;engaged 2nd Light Squadron&lt;ref name="karig20137"/&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Swanson|DD-443|2}}
|{{sclass-|Gleaves|destroyer|2}}
|1620 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone126"/&gt;
|37 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|10
|screened center group troopships off Fedala&lt;br /&gt;engaged Fedala Battery&lt;br /&gt;engaged 2nd Light Squadron&lt;ref name="karig20137"/&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Bristol|DD-453|2}}
|{{sclass-|Gleaves|destroyer|2}}
|1,620 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone126"/&gt;
|37 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|10
|screened center group troopships off Fedala&lt;ref name="karig201"/&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Boyle|DD-600|2}}
|{{sclass-|Benson|destroyer|2}}
|1,620 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone126"/&gt;
|37 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|5
|screened center group troopships off Fedala&lt;ref name="karig201"/&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Murphy|DD-603|2}}
|{{sclass-|Benson|destroyer|2}}
|1620 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone126"/&gt;
|37 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|5
|screened center group troopships off Fedala&lt;br /&gt;engaged Pont Blondin Battery&lt;ref name= "karig203"&gt;Karig (1946), p. 203&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Tillman|DD-641|2}}
|{{sclass-|Gleaves|destroyer|2}}
|1630 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone126"/&gt;
|37 knots
|4 × 5"/38 cal
|5
|screened center group troopships off Fedala&lt;ref name="karig201"/&gt;
|-
|{{USS|Ranger|CV-4|2}}
| aircraft carrier
|14500 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone38"&gt;Silverstone (1968), p. 38&lt;/ref&gt;
|29 knots
|8 × 5"/25 cal
|(none)
|provided air cover for center group while operating {{convert|130|mi|km|abbr=on}} offshore of Casablanca,&lt;ref name="p&amp;n574"&gt;Potter &amp; Nimitz (1960), p. 574&lt;/ref&gt; her bombers sank ''Jean Bart'' 10 November 42 after she was refloated from being sunk at her stern on 8 November 1942.
|-
|{{USS|Suwannee|CVE-27|2}}
|{{sclass-|Sangamon|escort carrier|2}}
|11400 tons&lt;ref name="silverstone55"&gt;Silverstone (1968), p. 55&lt;/ref&gt;
|18 knots
|2 × 5"/51 cal
|(none)
|provided air cover for center group while operating 130 miles (200&amp;nbsp;km) offshore of Casablanca&lt;ref name="p&amp;n574"/&gt;
|}

==See also==
* [[Attack on Mers-el-Kébir|Battle of Mers-el-Kébir]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=note}}

===Citations===
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
* Atkinson, Rick, ''An Army at Dawn'' (2002) Henry Holt and Company {{ISBN|0-8050-6288-2}}
* [[Gabriel Auphan|Auphan, Paul]] and [[Jacques Mordal|Mordal, Jacques]], ''The French Navy in World War II'' (1976) Greenwood Press {{ISBN|0-8371-8660-9}}
* Blair, Clay, ''Hitler's U-Boat War: The Hunted 1942–1945'' (1998) Random House {{ISBN|0-679-45742-9}}
* Brown, David, ''Warship Losses of World War II'' (1995) Naval Institute Press {{ISBN|1-55750-914-X}}
* Cressman, Robert J. ''The Official Chronology of the U.S. Navy in World War II'' (2000) Naval Institute Press {{ISBN|1-55750-149-1}}
* Kafka, Roger and Pepperburg, Roy L. ''Warships of the World'' (1946) Cornell Maritime Press
* Karig, Walter, CDR, USNR ''Battle Report: The Atlantic War'' (1946) Farrar &amp; Rinehart
* Le Masson, Henri ''The French Navy'' (volume 1) (1969) Doubleday &amp; Company
* Potter, E.B. and Nimitz, Chester W. ''Sea Power'' (1960) Prentice-Hall
* Preston, Antony ''Jane's Fighting Ships of World War II'' (1996) Random House {{ISBN|0-517-67963-9}}
* Rohwer, Jurgen and Hummelchen, Gerhard ''Chronology of the War at Sea 1939–1945'' (1992) Naval Institute Press {{ISBN|1-55750-105-X}}
* Silverstone, Paul H. ''U.S. Warships of World War II'' (1968) Doubleday &amp; Company
* Willoughby, Malcolm F. ''The U.S. Coast Guard in World War II'' (1957) United States Naval Institute

{{coord missing|Morocco}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Casablanca, Naval Battle Of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of the European theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Atlantic and Arctic theatres of World War II]]
[[Category:Naval aviation operations and battles]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:History of Casablanca]]
[[Category:1942 in Morocco]]
[[Category:20th century in Casablanca]]
[[Category:Military battles of Vichy France]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:North African Campaign]]
[[Category:November 1942 events]]</text><sha1>g7z5hemv9i0j0w9he6eo8l0ffbp6ex2</sha1></revision></page>