<page><title>Vistula–Oder Offensive</title><ns>0</ns><id>1634994</id><revision><id>962134149</id><parentid>962088335</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-12T08:38:26Z</timestamp><contributor><username>InternetArchiveBot</username><id>27015025</id></contributor><comment>Bluelink 2 books for [[Wikipedia:Verifiability|verifiability]] (refca)) #IABot (v2.0.1) ([[User:GreenC bot|GreenC bot]]</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="31442" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2012}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Vistula–Oder Offensive
| partof      = the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = Lodz liberation2.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = Soviet troops enter [[Łódź]], led by an [[ISU-122]] [[self-propelled gun]]
| date        = 12 January – 2 February 1945
| place       = [[Occupation of Poland (1939–1945)|Poland]] and [[Former eastern territories of Germany|Eastern Germany]]
| casus       = 
| territory   = Most of Poland occupied by the Soviet Union
| result      = Soviet victory
* [[Liberation of Auschwitz concentration camp|Liberation of Auschwitz]] and other [[Nazi concentration camps]]
| combatant1  = {{Flag icon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany]]
| combatant2  = {{Flag icon|USSR|1936}} [[Soviet Union]]&lt;br /&gt;{{Flag icon|Poland|1928}} [[Polish Armed Forces in the East|Poland]]
| commander1  = {{Flag icon|Nazi Germany}} [[Ferdinand Schörner]]&lt;br /&gt; ([[Army Group A]])&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(From 20 January)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{{Flag icon|Nazi Germany}} [[Josef Harpe]]&lt;br /&gt;([[Army Group A]])&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Until 20 January)&lt;/small&gt;
| commander2  = {{Flag icon|USSR|1936}} [[Georgy Zhukov]]&lt;br /&gt;([[1st Belorussian Front]])&lt;br /&gt;{{Flag icon|USSR|1936}} [[Ivan Konev]]&lt;br /&gt;([[1st Ukrainian Front]])
| strength1   = 450,000 men&lt;ref&gt;Duffy pp. 51, 59&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 2,203,600 men&lt;ref name=glantz&gt;Glantz (1995), p. 300&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties1 = &lt;!--41,805 killed &lt;br&gt;68,515 missing&lt;br&gt;146,368 wounded&lt;ref name = ww2stats&gt;http://ww2stats.com/cas_ger_okh_dec45.html&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name = axishistory.com&gt;http://forum.axishistory.com/viewtopic.php?f=50&amp;t=112689&amp;start=15&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt; Forum and dead link are not accepted. Please find a more decent source.--&gt;

Soviet claim:&lt;br&gt; 295,000 killed&lt;br&gt;147,000 taken prisoner&lt;ref name=Bahm&gt;Bahm, pp. 51-52&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = 43,476 killed or missing &lt;br&gt;150,715 wounded and sick&lt;ref name=glantz/&gt;
}}
{{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Campaignbox Poland 1944-1945}}

The '''Vistula–Oder Offensive''' was a [[Red Army]] operation on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] in the [[European theatre of World War II]] in January 1945. The army made a major advance into German-held territory, capturing [[Kraków]], [[Warsaw]] and [[Poznań]]. The Red Army had built up their strength around a number of key bridgeheads, with two fronts commanded by Marshal [[Georgy Zhukov]] and Marshal [[Ivan Konev]]. Against them, the German [[Army Group A]], led by Colonel-General [[Josef Harpe]] (soon replaced by Colonel-General [[Ferdinand Schörner]]), was outnumbered 5:1. Within days, German commandants evacuated the concentration camps, sending the prisoners on their [[Death marches (Holocaust)|death marches]] to the west, where ethnic Germans also started fleeing. In a little over two weeks, the Red Army had advanced 300 miles (483&amp;nbsp;km) from the [[Vistula]] to the [[Oder]], only 43 miles (69&amp;nbsp;km) from Berlin, which was undefended. However, Zhukov called a halt, owing to continued German resistance on his northern flank (Pomerania), and the advance on Berlin had to be delayed until April.

==Background==
In the wake of the successful [[Operation Bagration]], the [[1st Belorussian Front]] managed to secure two [[bridgehead]]s west of the Vistula river between 27 July and 4 August 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Duffy, p. 11&lt;/ref&gt; The Soviet forces remained inactive during the failed [[Warsaw uprising]] that started on 1 August, though their frontline was not far from the insurgents. The [[1st Ukrainian Front]] captured an additional large bridgehead at [[Sandomierz]] (known as the Baranow bridgehead in German accounts), some 200&amp;nbsp;km south of Warsaw, during the [[Lvov–Sandomierz Offensive]].&lt;ref&gt;Duffy, p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

Preceding the offensive, the Red Army had built up large amounts of [[materiel]] and manpower in the three bridgeheads. The Red Army greatly outnumbered the opposing Wehrmacht in infantry, artillery, and armour. All this was known to German intelligence. General [[Reinhard Gehlen]], head of ''[[Fremde Heere Ost]]'', passed his assessment to [[Heinz Guderian]]. Guderian in turn presented the intelligence results to [[Adolf Hitler]], who refused to believe them, dismissing the apparent Soviet strength as "the greatest imposture since [[Genghis Khan]]".&lt;ref name=Beevorp&gt;Beevor, pp. 6, 7&lt;/ref&gt; Guderian had proposed to evacuate the divisions of [[Army Group North]] trapped in the [[Courland Pocket]] to the Reich via the [[Baltic Sea]] to get the necessary manpower for the defence, but Hitler forbade it. In addition, Hitler commanded that one major operational reserve, the troops of [[Sepp Dietrich]]'s [[6th Panzer Army]], be moved to [[Hungary]] to support [[Operation Frühlingserwachen]].

The offensive was brought forward from 20 January to 12 January because meteorological reports warned of a thaw later in the month, and the tanks needed hard ground for the offensive. It was not done to assist American and British forces during the [[Battle of the Bulge]], as Stalin chose to claim at Yalta.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Beevor |first=Antony |authorlink=Antony Beevor |title=Ardennes 1944: Hitler’s last gamble |publisher=Viking |date=2015 |location=New York |page=[https://archive.org/details/ardennes1944hitl0000beev/page/331 331] |url=https://archive.org/details/ardennes1944hitl0000beev|url-access=registration |doi= |isbn=978-0-670-02531-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Forces involved==
[[File:Easterneurope10.jpg|thumb|400px|Disposition of forces and advance of the Soviet Army]]
===Red Army===
Two Fronts of the Red Army were directly involved. The 1st Belorussian Front, holding the sector around [[Warsaw]] and southward in the [[Magnuszew]] and [[Puławy]] bridgeheads, was led by Marshal Georgy Zhukov; the 1st Ukrainian Front, occupying the Sandomierz bridgehead, was led by Marshal [[Ivan Konev]].

Zhukov and Konev had 163 divisions for the operation with a total of: 2,203,000 infantry, 4,529 tanks, 2,513 [[assault gun]]s, 13,763 pieces of [[field artillery]] (76&amp;nbsp;mm or more), 14,812 [[Mortar (weapon)|mortars]], 4,936 [[anti-tank gun]]s, 2,198 [[Katyusha rocket launcher|Katyusha]] multiple rocket launchers, and 5,000 aircraft.&lt;ref&gt;Duffy pp. 24, 25&lt;/ref&gt;

====Deployments====
* [[1st Belorussian Front]] (Marshal [[Georgy Zhukov]])
** [[47th Army (Soviet Union)|47th Army]] ([[Franz Perkhorovich]])
** [[First Polish Army (1944-1945)|1st Polish Army]] (General [[Stanislav Poplavsky]])
** [[3rd Shock Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Shock Army]] ([[Nikolai Simoniak]])
** [[61st Army (Soviet Union)|61st Army]] ([[Pavel Alexeyevich Belov]])
** [[1st Guards Tank Army (Soviet Union)|1st Guards Tank Army]] ([[Mikhail Katukov]])
** [[2nd Guards Tank Army (Soviet Union)|2nd Guards Tank Army]] ([[Semyon Bogdanov]])
** [[5th Shock Army (Soviet Union)|5th Shock Army]] (in Magnuszew bridgehead) ([[Nikolai Berzarin]]) 
** [[8th Guards Army (Soviet Union)|8th Guards Army]] (in Magnuszew bridgehead) (General [[Vasily Chuikov]])
** [[69th Army (Soviet Union)|69st Army]] (in Puławy bridgehead) ([[Vladimir Kolpakchi]])
** [[33rd Army (Soviet Union)|33rd Army]] (in Puławy bridgehead) ([[Vyacheslav Tsvetayev]])
&lt;br&gt;
* [[1st Ukrainian Front]] (Marshal [[Ivan Konev]])
** [[21st Army (Soviet Union)|21st Army]] ([[Dmitry Gusev]])
** [[6th Army (Soviet Union)|6th Army]] ([[Vladimir Gluzdovsky]])
** [[3rd Guards Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Guards Army]] ([[Vasily Gordov]])
** [[13th Army (Soviet Union)|13th Army]] ([[Nikolai Pukhov]])
** [[4th Tank Army (Soviet Union)|4th Tank Army]] ([[Dmitry Lelyushenko]])
** [[3rd Guards Tank Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Guards Tank Army]] ([[Pavel Rybalko]])
** [[52nd Army (Soviet Union)|52nd Army]] ([[Konstantin Koroteyev]])
** [[5th Guards Army (Soviet Union)|5th Guards Army]] ([[Aleksey Semenovich Zhadov]])
** [[59th Army (Soviet Union)|59th Army]] ([[Ivan Korovnikov]])
** [[60th Army (Soviet Union)|60th Army]] ([[Pavel Kurochkin]])

===Wehrmacht===
Soviet forces in this sector were opposed by [[Army Group A]], defending a front which stretched from positions east of Warsaw southwards along the Vistula, almost to the confluence of the [[San (river)|San]]. At that point there was a large Soviet bridgehead over the Vistula in the area of [[Baranów Sandomierski|Baranów]] before the front continued south to [[Jasło]].

There were three Armies in the Group; the [[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|9th Army]] deployed around Warsaw, the [[German Fourth Panzer Army|4th Panzer Army]] opposite the Baranow salient in the Vistula Bend, and the [[17th Army (Wehrmacht)|17th Army]] to their south.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.onwar.com/maps/wwii/eastfront2/vistula-oder.htm Web map copy] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20060410215142/http://www.onwar.com/maps/wwii/eastfront2/vistula-oder.htm |date=10 April 2006 }} of Ziemke p. 26&lt;/ref&gt; The force had a total complement of 450,000 soldiers, 4,100 artillery pieces, and 1,150 tanks.&lt;ref&gt;Ziemke, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; Army Group A was led by [[Colonel-General]] [[Josef Harpe]] (who was replaced, after the offensive had begun, by Colonel-General [[Ferdinand Schörner]] on 20 January).&lt;ref&gt;Duffy{{Page needed|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Order of battle====
[[File:FestungBreslau6V1945.jpg|thumb|Delegation of German officers walking for negotiations before capitulation of [[Festung Breslau]]]]
* [[Army Group A]] (Colonel-General [[Josef Harpe]] to 20 January; then [[Ferdinand Schörner]])
** [[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|9th Army]] (General [[Smilo Freiherr von Lüttwitz]] to 20 January; then General [[Theodor Busse]])
*** [[LVI Panzer Corps]] (General [[Johannes Block]])
*** [[XXXXVI Panzer Corps (Germany)|XXXXVI Panzer Corps]] (General [[Walter Fries]])
*** [[VIII Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|VIII Corps]] (General [[Walter Hartmann]])
** [[4th Panzer Army]] (General [[Fritz-Hubert Gräser]])
*** [[XLII Corps (Germany)|XLII Corps]] (General [[Hermann Recknagel]])
*** [[XXIV Panzer Corps (Germany)|XXIV Panzer Corps]] (General [[Walther Nehring]])&lt;ref name=nehring&gt;Only two divisions of this corps, the [[16th Panzer Division|16th]] and [[17th Panzer Division]]s, were allocated to Fourth Panzer Army, where they were committed in the attempted defence of Kielce. The remaining two formations, the [[19th Panzer Division|19th]] and [[25th Panzer Division]]s constituted Army Group A's general reserve, and were committed in support of 9th Army.&lt;/ref&gt;
*** [[XLVIII Panzer Corps (Germany)|XLVIII Panzer Corps]] (General [[Maximilian Reichsfreiherr von Edelsheim]])
** [[17th Army (Wehrmacht)|17th Army]] (General [[Friedrich Schulz]])
*** [[LIX Corps (Germany)|LIX Corps]]  (General [[Edgar Rohricht]])
*** [[XI Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XI Corps]] (General [[Rudolf von Bünau (father)|Rudolf von Bünau]])
*** [[XI SS Panzer Corps (Germany)|XI SS Panzer Corps]]  (SS-Obergruppenfuhrer [[Matthias Kleinheisterkamp]])

German intelligence had estimated that the Soviet forces had a 3:1 numerical superiority to the German forces; there was in fact a 5:1 superiority.&lt;ref&gt;Duffy, pp. 51, 59&lt;/ref&gt; In the large Baranow/Sandomierz bridgehead, the Fourth Panzer Army was required to defend from 'strongpoints' in some areas, as it lacked the infantry to man a continuous front line.&lt;ref name=simsp23&gt;Sims and Schilling, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; In addition, on Hitler's express orders, the two German defence lines (the ''Grosskampflinie'' and ''Hauptkampflinie'') were positioned very close to each other, placing the main defences well within striking range of Soviet artillery.&lt;ref&gt;Duffy {{Page needed|date=September 2010}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Offensive==
The offensive commenced in the Baranow bridgehead at 04:35 on 12 January with an intense bombardment by the guns of the 1st Ukrainian Front against the positions of the 4th Panzer Army.&lt;ref name=duffyp67&gt;Duffy, p. 67&lt;/ref&gt; Concentrated against the divisions of XLVIII Panzer Corps, which had been deployed across the face of the bridgehead, the bombardment effectively destroyed their capacity to respond; a battalion commander in the [[68th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|68th Infantry Division]] stated that "I began the operation with an understrength battalion [...] after the smoke of the Soviet preparation cleared [...] I had only a platoon of combat effective soldiers left".&lt;ref name=sims&gt;Captain Reinhardt Mueller, interviewed in Sims and Schilling, p. 24&lt;/ref&gt;

The initial barrage was followed by probing attacks and a further heavy bombardment at 10:00. By the time the main armored exploitation force of the 3rd Guards and 4th Tank Armies moved forward four hours later, the Fourth Panzer Army had already lost up to ⅔ of its artillery and ¼ of its troops.&lt;ref name=hastingsp280&gt;Hastings, p. 280&lt;/ref&gt;

The Soviet units made rapid progress, moving to cut off the defenders at [[Kielce]]. The armored reserves of the 4th Panzer Army's central corps, the XXIV Panzer Corps, were committed, but had suffered serious damage by the time they reached Kielce, and were already being outflanked. The XLVIII Panzer Corps, on the Fourth Panzer Army's southern flank, had by this time been completely destroyed, along with much of Recknagel's XLII Corps in the north. Recknagel himself would be killed by Polish partisans on 23 January. By 14 January, the 1st Ukrainian Front had forced crossings of the [[Nida (river)|Nida]] river, and began to exploit towards [[Radomsko]] and the [[Warthe]]. The 4th Panzer Army's last cohesive formation, the XXIV Panzer Corps held on around Kielce until the night of 16 January, before its commander made the decision to withdraw.
[[File:Eastern Front 1945-01 to 1945-05.png|thumb|300px|World War II Eastern Front during the 1945 Vistula-Oder offensive; the map also shows the [[East Prussian Offensive]], [[Lower Silesian Offensive]], the [[East Pomeranian Offensive]], and the battles in [[Courland Pocket|Courland]]. See here for an [https://web.archive.org/web/20060410215142/http://www.onwar.com/maps/wwii/eastfront2/vistula-oder.htm accurate map].{{dead link|date=July 2016}}]]

The 1st Belorussian Front, to Konev's north, opened its attack on the German 9th Army from the Magnuszew and Puławy bridgeheads at 08:30, again commencing with a heavy bombardment.&lt;ref name=duffyp72&gt;Duffy, p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; The 33rd and 69th Armies broke out of the Puławy bridgehead to a depth of {{convert|30|km|mi|abbr=on}}, while the 5th Shock and 8th Guards Armies broke out of the Magnuszew bridgehead. The 2nd and 1st Guards Tank Armies were committed after them to exploit the breach. The 69th Army's progress from the Puławy bridgehead was especially successful, with the defending LVI Panzer Corps disintegrating after its line of retreat was cut off. Though the 9th Army conducted many local counter-attacks, they were all brushed aside; the 69th Army ruptured the last lines of defence and took [[Radom]], while the 2nd Guards Tank Army moved on [[Sochaczew]] and the 1st Guards Tank Army was ordered to seize bridgeheads over the [[Pilica River|Pilica]] and attack towards [[Łódź]].&lt;ref name=duffyp75&gt;Duffy, p. 75&lt;/ref&gt; In the meantime, the 47th Army had crossed the Vistula and moved towards Warsaw from the north, while the 61st and 1st Polish Armies encircled the city from the south.&lt;ref name=duffyp78&gt;Duffy, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt;

The only major German response came on 15 January, when Hitler (against the advice of Guderian) ordered the ''[[Panzerkorps Großdeutschland]]'' of [[Dietrich von Saucken]] from [[East Prussia]] to cover the breach made in the sector of the 4th Panzer Army, but the advance of Zhukov's forces forced it to detrain at Łódź without even reaching its objective. After covering the 9th Army's retreat, it was forced to withdraw southwest toward the Warthe.&lt;ref name=duffyp80&gt;Duffy, p. 80&lt;/ref&gt;

===Taking of Kraków; escape of the XXIV Panzer Corps===
On 17 January, Konev was given new objectives: to advance towards [[Breslau]] using his mechanised forces, and to use the combined-arms forces of the 60th and 59th Armies to open an attack on the southern flank towards the industrial heartland of Upper Silesia through [[Kraków]]. Kraków was secured undamaged on 19 January after an encirclement by the 59th and 60th Armies, in conjunction with the 4th Guards Tank Corps, forced the German defenders to withdraw hurriedly.&lt;ref name= Duffyp88&gt;Duffy, p. 88&lt;/ref&gt;

The second stage of the 1st Ukrainian Front's objective was far more complex, as they were required to encircle and secure the entire industrial region of Upper Silesia, where they were faced by Schulz's 17th Army. Konev ordered that the 59th and 60th Armies advance frontally, while the 21st Army encircled the area from the north. He then ordered Rybalko's 3rd Guards Tank Army, moving on Breslau, to swing southwards along the upper Oder from 20 January, cutting off 17th Army's withdrawal.&lt;ref name=duffyp91&gt;Duffy, p. 91&lt;/ref&gt;

In the meantime, the shattered remnants of the 4th Panzer Army were still attempting to reach German lines. By 18 January, Nehring and the XXIV Panzer Corps found that their intended route northwards had been blocked, so pulled back to the west, absorbing the remnants of XLII Corps that had escaped encirclement.&lt;ref name=duffyp82&gt;Duffy, p. 82&lt;/ref&gt; Much of the remainder of XLII Corps was destroyed after being trapped around [[Przysucha]]. Screened by heavy fog, the lead elements of XXIV Panzer Corps reached the Warthe on 22 January, and having linked up with Grossdeutschland Panzer Corps of von Saucken, were finally able to cross the Oder, some {{convert|350|km|mi|abbr=on}} from their positions at the start of the Soviet offensive.

===Withdrawal of 17th Army from Upper Silesia===
On 25 January, Schulz requested that he be allowed to withdraw his 100,000 troops from the developing salient around [[Katowice]]/Kattowitz. This was refused, and he repeated the request on 26 January. Schoerner eventually permitted Schulz to pull his forces back on the night of 27 January, while Konev – who had allowed just enough room for the 17th Army to withdraw without putting up serious resistance – secured the area undamaged.&lt;ref name=beevorp60&gt;Beevor, p. 60&lt;/ref&gt;

On Konev's northern flank, the 4th Tank Army had spearheaded an advance to the Oder, where it secured a major bridgehead at [[Ścinawa|Steinau]]. Troops of the 5th Guards Army established a second bridgehead upstream at [[Ohlau]].

===Advance of 1st Belorussian Front===
In the northern sector of the offensive, Zhukov's 1st Belorussian Front also made rapid progress, as 9th Army was no longer able to offer coherent resistance. Its XXXVI Panzer Corps, which was positioned behind Warsaw, was pushed over the Vistula into the neighbouring [[2nd Army (Wehrmacht)|Second Army]] sector.&lt;ref name=duffyp103&gt;Duffy, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt; Warsaw was taken on 17 January, as Army Group A's headquarters issued orders for the city to be abandoned; units of the 2nd Guards and 3rd Shock Armies entering the city were profoundly affected by the devastation wrought by German forces after the [[Warsaw Uprising]].&lt;ref name="duffy, p.104"&gt;Duffy, p. 104&lt;/ref&gt; Hitler, on the other hand, was furious at the abandonment of the 'fortress', arresting Colonel [[Bogislaw von Bonin]], head of the Operations Branch of [[Oberkommando des Heeres|OKH]], and sacking both the 9th Army and XXXVI Panzer Corps commanders; Generals [[Smilo Freiherr von Lüttwitz]] and [[Walter Fries]].

The 2nd Guards Tank Army pressed forward to the Oder, while to the south the 8th Guards Army reached Łódź by 18 January, and took it by 19 January. The 1st Guards Tank Army moved to encircle [[Poznań]] by 25 January, and the 8th Guards Army began to fight its way into the city on the following day, though there was protracted and intense fighting in the [[Battle of Poznań (1945)|Siege of Poznań]] before the city would finally be taken.

To the northeast of Zhukov's 1st Belorussian Front, the lead elements of Marshal [[Konstantin Rokossovsky|Rokossovsky's]] [[2nd Belorussian Front]] taking part in the [[East Prussian Offensive]] had reached the Baltic coast of the [[Vistula delta]] by 24 January and so succeeded in isolating [[Army Group Centre]] in East Prussia.&lt;ref name=Ziemke-31&gt;Ziemke p. 31&lt;/ref&gt; On January 27, the abandoned [[Wolf's Lair]] - Hitler's former headquarters on the Eastern Front, was captured.

===Zhukov's advance to the Oder===
[[File:Arborglyph 1945 Bielinek tree kz01.jpg|thumb|Tree carving in [[Bielinek]] (''Bellinchen''), [[Pomerania]], immediately east of the [[River Oder|Oder]]. It reads, in Russian, "March 1945, Death to the Germans."]]

After encircling Poznań, the 1st Guards Tank Army advanced deep into the fortified region around the [[Obra (river)|Obra]] River against patchy resistance from a variety of ''[[Volkssturm]]'' and ''Wehrmacht'' units. There was heavier resistance, however, on the approaches to the fortress of [[Küstrin]].

The German reorganisation of command structure that resulted in the creation of [[Army Group Vistula]] was accompanied by the release of a few extra formations for the defense; the [[V SS Mountain Corps]], with two reserve infantry divisions, was deployed along the Obra and the prewar border fortifications known as the ''[[Tierschtigel Riegel]]'', while the ''[[Panzergrenadier Division Kurmark (Germany)|Panzergrenadier-Division Kurmark]]'' was ordered to reinforce it.&lt;ref name=letissierp32&gt;Le Tissier, p. 32&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 January 1945 [[Colonel]] Bogislaw von Bonin, the Chief of the Operational Branch of the Army General Staff (''Generalstab des Heeres'') gave Army Group A permission to retreat from Warsaw overruling a direct order from Hitler for them to hold fast. Three days later von Bonin was arrested by the [[Gestapo]] and imprisoned first at [[Flossenbürg concentration camp]] and then [[Dachau concentration camp]]. The officer was eventually [[Transport of concentration camp inmates to Tyrol|liberated along with other prisoners]] in [[South Tyrol]] by the US Army in May 1945.

The military historian Earl Ziemke described the advance thus:
{{quote|On the 25th, Zhukov's main force passed Poznań heading due west towards [[Kuestrin]], on the Oder forty miles east of Berlin. The path of the Soviet advance looked like the work of a gigantic snowplough, its point aimed on a line from Warsaw to Poznań, to Berlin. All of Army Group A was being caught up by the point and the left blade and thrown across the Oder. On the right the German had nothing except a skeleton army group that Hitler had created some days earlier and named Army Group Vistula.|Earl Ziemke&lt;ref name=Ziemke-30-31&gt;Ziemke pp. 30, 31&lt;/ref&gt;}}

On 25 January, Hitler renamed three army groups. Army Group North became [[Army Group Courland]]; Army Group Centre became Army Group North and Army Group A became Army Group Centre.&lt;ref name=Ziemke-32&gt;Ziemke p. 32&lt;/ref&gt;

The 2nd Guards Tank and 5th Shock Armies reached the Oder almost unopposed; a unit of the 5th Shock Army crossed the river ice and took the town of [[Letschin|Kienitz]] as early as 31 January.&lt;ref name= hastingsp295&gt;Hastings, p. 295&lt;/ref&gt;

''[[Stavka]]'' declared the operation complete on 2 February. Zhukov had initially hoped to advance directly on Berlin, as the German defences had largely collapsed. However the exposed northern flank of 1st Belorussian Front in [[Pomerania]], along with a German counter-attack ([[Operation Solstice]]) against its spearheads, convinced the Soviet command that it was essential to clear German forces from Pomerania in the [[East Pomeranian Offensive]] before the Berlin offensive could proceed.

==Liberation of Nazi concentration camps==
In July of 1944, the Soviet [[8th Guards Combined Arms Army|8th Guards]] liberated [[Lublin]], and after a brief skirmish with German forces outside the city, came upon the [[Majdanek concentration camp]]. Although the Soviets invited press from around the world to witness the horrors of the camp, [[World War II|war]] news overshadowed the event. 

After being caught off guard at Majdanek, the Nazis realized that the Soviets would end up finding every camp within Eastern Europe (with all of the prisoners and guards still present) if something were not to be done. As a result, by mid January, the [[Schutzstaffel|SS]] and [[Ordnungspolizei#Police Battalions|Nazi-controlled police units]] had begun forcing thousands of camp prisoners from Poland, East Prussia, [[Silesia]] and Pomerania to walk westward away from the advancing Red Army. The [[Death marches (Holocaust)|death marches]], which took place over hundreds of kilometers in sub-zero conditions without food and medicine, resulted in thousands of concentration camp prisoners and [[The March (1945)|allied POWs]] dying en route. It is estimated that in March and April 1945 at least 250,000 men and women were marched on foot to the heartland of Germany and Austria sometimes for weeks at a time.&lt;ref name="ushmm"&gt;The Holocaust Encyclopedia, [http://www.ushmm.org/outreach/en/article.php?ModuleId=10007734 The largest death marches, winter of 1944-1945.] United States Holocaust Memorial Museum 2015.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="yadvashem"&gt;Yad Vashem, [http://www.yadvashem.org/odot_pdf/Microsoft%20Word%20-%206260.pdf Death Marches.] The Holocaust Martyrs and Heroes Remembrance Authority 2015. PDF direct download.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 27 January, troops from Konev's [[First Ukrainian Front]] ([[322nd Rifle Division (Soviet Union)|322nd Rifle Division]], 60th Army) liberated the [[Auschwitz concentration camp]]. Despite attempts by retreating SS units to destroy parts of the camp, the Soviet forces still found graphic evidence of the [[Holocaust]]. The Soviets would also liberate camps such as [[Kraków-Płaszów concentration camp|Płaszów]], [[Stutthof concentration camp|Stutthof]], and [[Ravensbrück concentration camp|Ravensbrück]].

==Flight of ethnic Germans==
{{Main|Evacuation of German civilians during the end of World War II}}

In anticipation of the approaching Red Army, the retreating Wehrmacht left parts of the German territory largely abandoned. With widespread unchecked chaos erupting, numerous reports of looting and attacks against ethnic Germans emerged. Nazi propaganda had furthermore demonized the Soviet Army so much that most Germans attempted to run.&lt;ref name=Rzheshevsky&gt;Rzheshevsky (2002)&lt;/ref&gt; Millions of ethnic German refugees [[Flight and expulsion of Germans (1944–50)|fled west]] to escape the inevitable persecutions, seeking relative safety in central or western Germany, or even in the custody of the American and British west of the [[Rhine]].&lt;ref&gt;Beevor, pp. 28, 29, 30–37, 46–51&lt;/ref&gt;

==Outcome==
The Vistula–Oder Offensive was a major success for the Soviet military. Within a matter of days the forces involved had advanced hundreds of kilometers, taking much of Poland and striking deep within the pre-war borders of the Reich. The offensive broke the back of Army Group A, and much of Germany's remaining capacity for military resistance. However, the stubborn resistance of German forces in Silesia and Pomerania, as well as continuing fighting in East Prussia, meant that the final offensive towards Berlin was delayed by two months, by which time the ''Wehrmacht'' had once again built up a substantial force on this axis.

==Aftermath==
On 31 January, the Soviet offensive was voluntarily halted, though Berlin was undefended and only approximately {{convert|70|km|mi|abbr=on}} away from the Soviet bridgeheads across the [[Oder]] river. After the war a debate raged, mainly between [[Vasily Chuikov]] and Georgy Zhukov whether it was wise to stop the offensive. Chuikov argued Berlin should have been taken then, while Zhukov defended the decision to stop.

The operation was followed by a period of several weeks of mopping-up and consolidation on the part of the Red Army, along with ongoing hard fighting in pockets in the North. On 16 April, the Red Army jumped off from lines on the [[Battle of the Oder–Neisse|Oder and Neisse Rivers]], the opening phase of the [[Battle of Berlin]], which proved to be the culminating offensive of the war on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]. The relatively rapid progress of this new offensive toward the German heartland seems to illustrate the cumulative extent of the erosion of the [[Wehrmacht]]'s capability to defend a broad front. Nevertheless, they remained dangerous opponents for some weeks longer, especially when allowed or forced to concentrate in limited areas.{{citation needed|date=September 2014}}

==See also==
* [[East Prussian Offensive]], the parallel offensive in East Prussia
* [[Western Carpathian Offensive]], the parallel offensive in Slovakia
* [[Operation Solstice]], German counter-offensive in Pomerania
* [[East Pomeranian Offensive]], the operation to clear the northern flank of 1st Belorussian Front
* [[Silesian Offensives]], operations to clear the southern flank of 1st Ukrainian Front
* [[Battle of Berlin]]

==References==
'''Notes'''
{{Reflist|30em}}
{{more citations needed|date=January 2018}}&lt;!--"Zhukov's advance" section needs more refs; "Outcome" and "Aftermath" sections have no refs--&gt;

'''Bibliography'''
* {{cite book |last=Bahm |first=Karl |title=Berlin 1945: The Final Reckoning |publisher=Motorbooks International |location=St. Paul |year=2001 |isbn=0-7603-1240-0}}
* [[Antony Beevor|Beevor, A]]. ''Berlin: The Downfall 1945'', Penguin Books, 2002, {{ISBN|0-670-88695-5}}
* [[Christopher Duffy|Duffy, C]]. ''Red Storm on the Reich: The Soviet March on Germany, 1945'' Routledge 1991 {{ISBN|0-415-22829-8}}
* Glantz, David M. &amp; House, Jonathan (1995), ''When Titans Clashed: How the Red Army Stopped Hitler'', Lawrence, Kansas: University Press of Kansas, {{ISBN|0-7006-0899-0}}
* {{Cite book|last=Hastings|first=Max|authorlink=Max Hastings|title=Armageddon|publisher=Macmillan| location=New York|year=2004|isbn=978-0-333-90836-5}}
* Le Tissier, T. ''Zhukov at the Oder'', Greenwood, 1996, {{ISBN|0-275-95230-4}}
* {{Cite book|last=Rees|first=Laurence|authorlink=Laurence Rees|title=Auschwitz|url=https://archive.org/details/auschwitznazisfi0000rees|url-access=registration|publisher=BBC Books| location=London|year=2005|isbn=978-0-563-52296-6}}
* {{cite journal |last=Rzheshevsky |first=Oleg A. |script-title=ru:Берлинская операция 1945 г.: дискуссия продолжается |trans-title=The Berlin Operation of 1945: Discussion Continues |journal=Мир истории [World of History] |year=2002 |issue=4 |language=Russian}}
* {{Citation|last1=Sims|first1=D|last2=Schilling|first2=A|title=Breakout from the Sandomierz Bridgehead (pages 20-24)|url=https://sill-www.army.mil/firesbulletin/archives/1990/OCT_1990/OCT_1990_FULL_EDITION.pdf|work=[[Field Artillery (magazine)|Field Artillery]]|date=October 1990}}
* {{Cite book|last=Ziemke|first=Earl|title=Battle for Berlin|publisher=Macdonald|location=London| year=1969|isbn=978-0-356-02960-3}}

{{World War II}}

{{Coord missing|Poland}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vistula-Oder Offensive}}
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:Strategic operations of the Red Army in World War II]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1945]]
[[Category:World War II aerial operations and battles of the Eastern Front]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:January 1945 events]]
[[Category:February 1945 events]]
[[Category:1945 in Germany]]
[[Category:1945 in Poland]]</text><sha1>0mci77kp7wrmya3zy91o9i0ipbdvrtm</sha1></revision></page>