<page><title>Heiligenbeil Pocket</title><ns>0</ns><id>11606281</id><revision><id>957241171</id><parentid>940045711</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-17T20:20:49Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>163.182.236.194</ip></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="15844" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Heiligenbeil Pocket
|image=Russian troops in Frauenburg.jpg
|image_size=300px
|caption=Soviet troops enter Frauenburg, 9 February (?) 1945
|partof=the [[East Prussian Offensive]] in the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
|place=[[East Prussia]]
|date=26 January – 29 March 1945
|result=Soviet victory
|combatant1=[[Image:Flag of Germany 1933.svg|22px]] [[Nazi Germany]]
|combatant2={{flagicon|USSR}} [[Soviet Union]]
|commander1=[[Image:Flag of Germany 1933.svg|22px]] [[Friedrich Hossbach]] ([[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|4th Army]] until January 29)&lt;br/&gt;[[Image:Flag of Germany 1933.svg|22px]] [[Friedrich-Wilhelm Müller|Friedrich Müller]] ([[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|4th Army]] from January 29)
|commander2={{flagicon|USSR}} [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]]&lt;br/&gt;([[2nd Belorussian Front]])&lt;br/&gt; {{flagicon|USSR}} [[Ivan Chernyakhovsky]]&lt;br/&gt;([[3rd Belorussian Front]] until February 18 – KIA that day) &lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|USSR}} [[Aleksandr Vasilevsky]]&lt;br/&gt; ([[3rd Belorussian Front]] from February 19)
|strength1=?150,000
|strength2=?
|casualties1=80,000 killed&lt;br/&gt;50,000 captured&lt;br/&gt;605 tanks&lt;br/&gt;128 planes (According to Soviet information) &lt;ref&gt;http://9may.ru/10.04.1945/inform/m4218&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2=146,780 killed, 97,553 sick or wounded, 2000 tanks and sp guns (estimated){{citation needed|date=July 2016}}
|}}
{{Campaignbox Poland 1944–1945}}
The '''Heiligenbeil Pocket''' or '''Heiligenbeil Cauldron''' ({{lang-de|Kessel von Heiligenbeil}}) was the site of a major [[encirclement]] battle on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] during the closing weeks of [[World War II]], in which the [[Wehrmacht]]'s [[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|4th Army]] was almost entirely destroyed during the Soviet [[Braunsberg Offensive Operation]] (13–22 March 1945). The [[Salients, re-entrants and pockets|pocket]] was located near [[Mamonovo|Heiligenbeil]] in [[East Prussia]] in [[historical eastern Germany|eastern Germany]] (now [[Mamonovo]], [[Kaliningrad Oblast]]), and  the battle, part of a broader Soviet offensive into the region of [[East Prussia]], lasted from 26 January until 29 March 1945.

==Attack on East Prussia==
{{Main|East Prussian Offensive}}
The [[Red Army]]'s [[East Prussian Operation]] commenced on 13 January 1945 with the objective of rolling up the substantial German defences in [[East Prussia]] and cutting off the provincial capital of [[Königsberg]]. The Soviet forces were opposed by the German [[Army Group Centre]], including the [[4th Army (Wehrmacht)|Fourth Army]], under the command of General [[Friedrich Hossbach]]. While the [[3rd Belorussian Front]] initially met strong resistance, the outnumbered German forces soon began to suffer serious ammunition shortages. Colonel-General [[Georg-Hans Reinhardt]], commander of Army Group Centre, warned of the seriousness of the situation as early as 19 January, but was not permitted to make a phased withdrawal.{{citation needed|date = March 2013}}

==The pocket forms==
To save his units from encirclement, Hossbach started to pull the Fourth Army back to the west in direct contravention of orders, abandoning the prepared defences around [[Giżycko|Lötzen]] on 23 January.&lt;ref name=duffyp172&gt;Duffy, p. 172&lt;/ref&gt; By this time, [[Konstantin Rokossovsky|Rokossovsky]]'s [[2nd Belorussian Front]] had already broken through on Hossbach's right; the Soviet [[5th Guards Tank Army]] headed for the Baltic coast, cutting off most of East Prussia. Through a series of forced marches in atrocious winter weather, and accompanied by thousands of civilians, the Fourth Army moved towards [[Elbląg|Elbing]], still held by the [[2nd Army (Wehrmacht)|German Second Army]], but found its path blocked by Soviet forces of the [[48th Army (Soviet Union)|48th Army]] to the east of the town.

An attack beginning on the night of 26 January initially resulted in lead elements of the [[German 28th Jäger Division|28th Jäger Division]] breaking through to Elbing, where they linked up with the [[7th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|7th Panzer Division]]; however German forces were driven back during the next four days after the 48th Army had regrouped. Hossbach's units now found themselves pushed into a ''Kessel'' (pocket) with their backs to the [[Vistula Lagoon|Frisches Haff]].

Hossbach was relieved of command on 29 January, and was replaced by General [[Friedrich-Wilhelm Müller]]. His three corps were given an order to cease their breakout attempt on 30 January.&lt;ref name=duffyp173&gt;Duffy, p. 173&lt;/ref&gt; Along with some units of Second Army, they found themselves encircled in the area of Heiligenbeil and [[Braniewo|Braunsberg]]; many of the civilians trapped with them attempted to escape across the frozen Haff to the [[Vistula Spit|Frische Nehrung]] and thence to [[Baltiysk|Pillau]] or [[Gdańsk|Danzig]], reinforced paths marked by lamps having been constructed across the ice by Fourth Army's engineers.&lt;ref name="Hastings"&gt;Though many accounts describe the ''Wehrmacht'' assisting civilians in escaping East Prussia, others describe civilians being forced off the road along the Frische Nehrung to make way for military traffic, and male refugees being compelled to join ''Volkssturm'' units (see accounts in Hastings, Chapter 10).&lt;/ref&gt;

==Civilian breakout==
As the Nazis had effectively forbidden evacuation of East Prussia's civil population, when the Red Army attacked on 12 January 1945 civilians began a mass flight west to the Baltic sea coast. Many people were killed by Soviet troops, and by severe frost. At the coast, in particular in the harbour of Pillau, the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' managed to evacuate tens of thousands of civilians over the Baltic sea, and encouraged fierce resistance on land, since every delay to the Red Army meant the rescue of additional old people, women and children.

Attempts by the Red Army to break through the German perimeter early in February were fought back, with the Fourth Army receiving heavy artillery support from the German cruisers ''[[German cruiser Admiral Scheer|Admiral Scheer]]'' and ''[[German cruiser Deutschland|Lützow]]'' firing across the Haff from the Baltic sea into the [[Frombork|Frauenburg]] end of the pocket.&lt;ref name=duffyp204&gt;Duffy, p. 204&lt;/ref&gt; Frauenburg itself was taken on February 9, in fierce fighting involving elements of the [[170th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|170th Infantry Division]].&lt;ref name=frauenberg&gt;See [http://eng.9may.ru/24.02.1945/eng_inform/m9004166 RIA Novosti archives] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090227183146/http://eng.9may.ru/24.02.1945/eng_inform/m9004166 |date=2009-02-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt; During one Soviet attack the [[3rd Belorussian Front]]'s commander, General [[Ivan Chernyakhovsky]], was killed by a shell splinter near [[Pieniężno|Mehlsack]]. His successor, Marshal [[Aleksandr Vasilevsky]], having effectively contained the remains of the Army Group, concentrated on assembling reinforcements over the next month. Under the supervision of Major-General [[Karl Henke]], the Germans continued to attempt resupply and evacuations of wounded along the Frische Nehrung, often at night to avoid air attack. A long, narrow corridor through to the besieged garrison of Königsberg was also maintained against the attacks of the [[11th Guards Army]] through a joint effort by the garrison, and by the [[Großdeutschland Division|Großdeutschland Panzergrenadier Division]].&lt;ref name=duffyp162&gt;Duffy, pp. 161–2&lt;/ref&gt;

Though the German forces in East Prussia had no realistic hope of victory, and were severely short of manpower, ammunition, and fuel, they continued to offer strong resistance, inflicting extremely high casualties (584,788+) on the Red Army during the East Prussian Operation.&lt;ref name=casualties&gt;Official Soviet figures gave a total of 584,788 casualties for the entire area of the offensive during the period from 13 March – 25 April.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Ad hoc'' battle groups were often bolstered by civilians press-ganged into the ''[[Volkssturm]]'', and many East Prussian villages and towns had been turned into fortified strongpoints, in addition to the substantial fortifications centred on [[Lidzbark Warmiński|Heilsberg]].&lt;ref name=hastingsp307&gt;Hastings, p. 307&lt;/ref&gt; The fighting was prolonged in order to keep open civilian escape routes, and because requests to evacuate the main body of the Fourth Army were refused by the [[Oberkommando des Heeres|German High Command]].

The Soviet attack, however, came tragically late for the remaining inmates of the [[Heiligenbeil concentration camp]], along with other camps in the area. Even as Hossbach's forces were attempting to break out of East Prussia, the prisoners were [[Palmnicken#Massacre of Palmnicken|driven to the coast]] and ordered to commit suicide by marching into the Baltic Sea.

==Destruction of the 4th Army==
[[File:BraniewoCemetry.JPG|thumb|Monument in Braniewo (Braunsberg) honoring fallen Red Army soldiers]]
The pocket was finally crushed in an operation lasting from 13 March – 29 March, officially known as the '''Braunsberg Offensive Operation''', in preparation for the [[Battle of Königsberg|final assault on Königsberg]],

The Red Army quickly moved to cut communication between the ''Kessel'' and Königsberg, their troops reaching the coastline about 5 miles from the city on 15 March. A crossing of the [[Prokhladnaya River|Frisching]] River was forced in a night attack on the night of 17–18 March, further rolling up German defences of the ''Kessel'' from the east.&lt;ref name=Lanzap274&gt;Lanza, p. 274&lt;/ref&gt; Clearer weather from 18 March allowed an intensive aerial bombardment of the Fourth Army's positions.&lt;ref name=duffyp205&gt;Duffy, p. 205&lt;/ref&gt;

With most communications cut, German forces remaining in the pocket were now faced with either death or being taken prisoner. Some 'elite' units, such as the [[Fallschirm-Panzergrenadier Division 2 Hermann Göring]] and the [[24th Panzer Division]], were evacuated by sea, but others were gradually cut off in a series of small pockets on the coast, in some cases actually digging into the coastal embankments or beaches. POW reports suggested that many German units were now seriously understrength, with the [[50th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|50th Infantry Division]], for example, able to field only a single incomplete regiment.&lt;ref name=RIA2&gt;See [http://eng.9may.ru/18.03.1945/eng_inform/m9004206 RIA Novosti archives] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090227183548/http://eng.9may.ru/18.03.1945/eng_inform/m9004206 |date=2009-02-27 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Soviets finally took Braunsberg on 20 March. Heiligenbeil, covering the small port of Rosenberg, was attacked with phosphorus bombs on 22 March and successfully stormed on 25 March, the town suffering almost complete destruction. Rosenberg itself was taken on 26 March, with the remnants of the Fourth Army falling back on the Kahlholzer Haken [[peninsula]], where the perimeter was defended by troops from the [[Großdeutschland Division|Panzerkorps "Großdeutschland"]] and the 28th Jäger Division. The last evacuations took place on the morning of 29 March from Kahlholz and [[Balga]], where a remnant of the [[German 562nd Grenadier Division|562nd Volksgrenadier Division]] was destroyed forming a rearguard (its commander, [[Helmuth Hufenbach]], receiving a posthumous promotion to [[Major-General]]).&lt;ref name=duffyp206&gt;Duffy, p. 206&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=weiszacker&gt;Future German President [[Richard von Weizsäcker]] was amongst the military personnel on the final boats from Balga.&lt;/ref&gt; Soviet sources claimed 93,000 enemy dead and 46,448 taken prisoner during the operation; German sources claim that many troops in the ''Kessel'' were successfully evacuated to the Frische Nehrung. Given the chaos prevailing at this stage of the war, it is unlikely that accurate figures will ever be determined, many soldiers having simply disappeared.&lt;ref name=welcker&gt;Meier-Welcker, in ''Die Abwehrkämpfe am Nordflügel der Ostfront 1944–45'', states that 57,585 troops and a further 70,535 wounded were evacuated from Rosenberg and Balga after 13 April (pp. 374–5). Soviet figures from Duffy, p. 206&lt;/ref&gt; Further elements of the Fourth Army continued to resist around Pillau, and latterly on the Frische Nehrung, until May.

The 4th Army's archives were buried in a forest near the town of Heiligenbeil (now known as [[Mamonovo]], [[Russia]]), in an area still littered with debris from the final battles.&lt;ref&gt;Koenigsberger Express [http://www.koenigsberger-express.com/index.php?b=1&amp;id=19&amp;a=5&amp;id_article=284 Das Niemandsland gibt ein Geheimnis preis. Koenigsberger Express, ed. 2004/7]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Units==
{{unreferenced section|date=March 2017}}

===Red Army===
The following Soviet units were involved in completing the encirclement of the ''Kessel'':
*[[2nd Belorussian Front]] (Marshal [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]])
**[[5th Guards Tank Army]]
**[[48th Army (Soviet Union)|48th Army]]
**[[Third Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Army]]
**[[50th Army (Soviet Union)|50th Army]]
*[[3rd Belorussian Front]] (General [[Aleksandr Vasilevsky]])
**[[31st Army (Soviet Union)|31st Army]]
**[[28th Army (Soviet Union)|28th Army]]
**[[1st Air Army (Soviet Union)|1st Air Army]]

===Wehrmacht===
German records list the following units with the Fourth Army at the time of the ''Kessel'''s collapse:
*[[VI Corps (Germany)|VI Corps]] (General [[Horst Großmann]])
**[[German 102nd Infantry Division|102nd Infantry Division]]
**[[24th Panzer Division]]
**[[349th Volksgrenadier Division]]
*[[XX Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XX Corps]] (General [[Rudolf Freiherr von Roman]])
**[[131st Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|131st Infantry Division]]
**[[German 61st Volksgrenadier Division|61st Volksgrenadier Division]]
**[[German 21st Infantry Division|21st Infantry Division]]
**[[German 14th Infantry Division|14th Infantry Division]]
**[[292nd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|292nd Infantry Division]]
**[[German 56th Infantry Division|56th Infantry Division]]
*[[XXXXI Panzer Corps (Germany)|XXXXI Panzer Corps]] (General [[Helmuth Weidling]])
**[[170th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|170th Infantry Division]]
**[[Fallschirm-Panzergrenadier Division 2 Hermann Göring]]
**[[Großdeutschland Division|Panzergrenadier Division "Großdeutschland"]]
**[[German 28th Jäger Division|28th Jäger Division]]
**[[German 562nd Grenadier Division|562nd Volksgrenadier Division]]
*[[50th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|50th Infantry Division]]

Nearly all German units would have been at well below divisional strength even at the start of the East Prussian Operation; also some additional units involved (such as the [[299th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|299th Infantry Division]] and [[18th Panzergrenadier Division (Wehrmacht)|18th Panzergrenadier Division]]) were destroyed, disbanded or completely evacuated before the ''Kessel'' collapsed.

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
*[[Antony Beevor|Beevor, Antony]]. ''Berlin: The Downfall 1945'', Penguin Books, 2002, {{ISBN|0-670-88695-5}}
*Duffy, Christopher. ''Red Storm on the Reich: The Soviet March on Germany, 1945'', Routledge, 1991, {{ISBN|0-415-22829-8}}
*Hastings, Max. ''Armageddon: The Battle for Germany, 1944–1945'', Macmillan, 2004, {{ISBN|0-333-90836-8}}
*Lanza, Conrad. ''Perimeters in Paragraphs'', ''[[Field Artillery (magazine)|Field Artillery]]'', May 1945

{{Coord missing|Germany}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1945]]
[[Category:1945 in Germany]]
[[Category:East Prussia]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:Strategic operations of the Red Army in World War II]]
[[Category:Encirclements in World War II]]
[[Category:January 1945 events]]
[[Category:February 1945 events]]
[[Category:March 1945 events]]</text><sha1>ga4cktmgnlcue43u4ul3kc9ciqb2gid</sha1></revision></page>