<page><title>East Pomeranian Offensive</title><ns>0</ns><id>11801356</id><revision><id>964731673</id><parentid>957003473</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-27T07:35:16Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Filiep</username><id>1065306</id></contributor><comment>/* Siege of Danzig */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="13699" xml:space="preserve">{{more citations needed|date=March 2016}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=East Pomeranian Offensive&lt;br/&gt;East Pomeranian Strategic Offensive Operation
|image=Danzigm17.jpg
|image_size=300px
|caption=Soviet Red Army troops manning two [[M16 Multiple Gun Motor Carriage|M17 Multiple Gun Motor Carriage]] (MGMC) self-propelled anti-aircraft vehicles (half-tracks) in Danzig in March of 1945. 
|partof=the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of [[World War II]]
|place=[[Province of Pomerania (1815–1945)|Pomerania]], [[Reichsgau Danzig-West Prussia|Danzig-West Prussia]] inside [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]
|date=24 February – 4 April 1945
|result=Soviet victory
|combatant1={{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|combatant2={{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flagdeco|Poland|1928}} [[Polish Armed Forces in the East|Poland]]
|commander1={{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Walter Weiß]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Dietrich von Saucken]]&lt;br/&gt;([[2nd Army (Wehrmacht)|2nd Army]])
|commander2={{flagicon|USSR|1936}} [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]]&lt;br/&gt;([[2nd Belorussian Front]])
|strength1= Unknown
|strength2=996,100&lt;ref name=glantz&gt;Glantz (1995), p. 300&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties1=Unknown
|casualties2='''234,360'''
*55,315 killed or missing
*179,045 wounded&lt;ref name=glantz/&gt;
'''Materiel destroyed or captured'''
*1,027 tanks and self-propelled guns{{sfn|Liedtke|2008|p=585}}
*1,005 guns and mortars{{sfn|Liedtke|2008|p=585}}
*1,073 aircraft{{sfn|Liedtke|2008|p=585}}
|}}
{{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Campaignbox Poland 1944-1945}}

The '''East Pomeranian Strategic Offensive''' operation ({{lang-ru|Восточно-Померанская наступательная операция}}) was an [[Strategic offensive|offensive]] by the [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] [[Red Army]] against the [[Nazi Germany|German]] ''[[Wehrmacht]]'' on the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]. It took place in [[Pomerania]] and [[West Prussia]] from 10 February – 4 April 1945.

The operation happened in four phases:

:[[Konitz-Köslin Offensive Operation]] 24 February – 6 March 1945
:[[Danzig Offensive Operation]] 7–31 March 1945
:[[Arnswalde-Kolberg Offensive Operation]] 1–18 March 1945
:[[Altdamm Offensive Operation]] 18 March – 4 April 1945 (near Stettin)

It was the East Pomeranian Offensive that prevented [[Georgy Zhukov|Zhukov]] from reaching Berlin in February (the object of the massive [[Vistula–Oder Offensive]]), since it became a priority to clear German forces from Pomerania first. 

==Planning==
[[File:Pomerania and Silesia.jpg|thumb|Pomeranian and Silesian offensives]]
The [[2nd Belorussian Front]]—under [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]]—had initially been tasked with advancing westward north of the [[Vistula]] River toward Pomerania and the major port city of [[Gdańsk|Danzig]], with the primary aim of protecting the right flank of Zhukov's [[1st Belorussian Front]], which was pushing towards Berlin. During the [[East Prussian Offensive]], however, Rokossovsky was ordered to wheel directly north toward [[Elbląg|Elbing]].&lt;ref name=duffyp170&gt;Duffy, p.170&lt;/ref&gt; This left substantial German forces intact in Pomerania, where they threatened the right flank of Zhukov's formations.

As a result, once the initial phase of the East Prussian Offensive was over, the 2nd Belorussian Front was redeployed with the intention of attacking westwards into Pomerania, eliminating the possibility of a German counter-offensive (similarly, the parallel [[Silesian Offensives]] of Konev's [[1st Ukrainian Front]] in the south were in part designed to protect the 1st Belorussian Front's left flank). The need to secure the flanks delayed [[Battle of Berlin|the Soviets' final push towards Berlin]], which was originally planned for February, until April.

[[Joseph Stalin]]'s decision to delay the push toward Berlin from February to April has been a subject of some controversy among both the Soviet generals and military historians, with one side arguing that the Soviets had a chance of securing Berlin much quicker and with much lower losses in February, and the other arguing that the danger of leaving large German formations on the flanks could have resulted in a successful German counter-attack and prolonged the war further: the Germans did in fact mount a surprise counter-attack in Pomerania in mid-February, [[Operation Solstice]]. The delay did, however, allow the Soviets to occupy significant parts of Austria in the [[Vienna Offensive]].

==German intelligence==
As early as 13 February, German intelligence services had deduced that the Soviets would seek to clear Pomerania before advancing on Berlin. The [[2nd Army (Wehrmacht)|2nd Army]]—defending a large and exposed sector running through Pomerania eastward toward the edge of [[East Prussia]] at [[Elbing]] — sought permission to withdraw, but this was denied by [[Adolf Hitler]].&lt;ref name= Duffypp186&gt;Duffy, pp.186–7&lt;/ref&gt; [[Grudziądz|Graudenz]], on the Vistula, was surrounded on 18 February (the garrison, from the [[83rd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|83rd Infantry Division]]—finally surrendered the following month).

==Deployments==

===Wehrmacht===
*[[Army Group Vistula]]
**[[2nd Army (Wehrmacht)|2nd Army]] (Colonel-General [[Walter Weiß]])
***[[XXXXVI Panzer Corps (Germany)|XXXXVI Panzer Corps]]
***[[VII Panzer Corps (Germany)|VII Panzer Corps]]
***[[XXVII Army Corps (Germany)|XXVII Army Corps]]
***[[XXIII Army Corps (Wehrmacht)|XXIII Corps]]
***[[XVIII Mountain Corps (Germany)|XVIII Mountain Corps]]
***Fortress garrisons of [[Grudziądz|Graudenz]] and [[Gdańsk|Danzig]]
**Eastern flank of [[3rd Panzer Army]] (reconstituted) (General [[Erhard Raus]])
***[[III (Germanic) SS Panzer Corps|III SS Panzer Corps]]
***[[X SS Corps]]

The corps of the Second Army were seriously understrength by this time, being composed largely of fragmentary or ''ad hoc'' units. The [[3rd Panzer Army]] had been rebuilt using the ''korps'' of the recently formed [[Eleventh SS Panzer Army|11th SS Panzer Army]], the original formation having been largely destroyed in [[Lithuania]] and East Prussia, where its remnants were now [[Battle of Königsberg|defending]] [[Königsberg]].

===Red Army===
*[[2nd Belorussian Front]] (Marshal [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]])
*Eastern flank of [[1st Belorussian Front]] (Marshal [[Georgy Zhukov]])
**[[3rd Shock Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Shock Army]]
**[[1st Guards Tank Army (Soviet Union)|1st Guards Tank Army]]
**[[2nd Guards Tank Army (Soviet Union)|2nd Guards Tank Army]]

==The offensive==

===Breakthrough===
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-H26409, Pommern, Wollin, Infanterie bei Straßenkämpfen.jpg|thumb|German infantrymen during street fighting in [[Wolin|Wollin]], March 1945]]
Rokossovsky opened the offensive on 24 February using the fresh troops of Kozlov's 19th Army, but after an initial advance of some {{convert|20|km|mi|abbr=on}} they were halted by intense German resistance. On 26 February, he inserted the [[3rd Guards Tank Corps (Soviet Union)|3rd Guards Tank Corps]] east of [[Szczecinek|Neustettin]], where they achieved a penetration of {{convert|40|km|mi|abbr=on}}, and relieved Kozlov of command.&lt;ref name=duffyp187&gt;Duffy, p.187&lt;/ref&gt; The 3rd Guards Tank Corps broke through at [[Biały Bór|Baldenburg]], while Neustettin on the Front's left flank fell to the [[3rd Guards Cavalry Corps (Soviet Union)|3rd Guards Cavalry Corps]] on 27 February.

Weiß had hurriedly assembled the [[VII Panzer Corps (Germany)|VII Panzer Corps]], including the remnants of the [[7th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|7th Panzer Division]], at [[Miastko|Rummelsburg]] to threaten 19th Army's flank. However, after a Soviet breakthrough at [[Koszalin|Köslin]] on 2 March, the 2nd Army found itself completely cut off from the rest of its Army Group.

===1st Belorussian Front joins the attack===
[[File:Radziecki czołg IS-2 na ul. Chrobrego, przy istniejących do dziś zabudowaniach.jpg|thumb|left|Soviet [[IS-2]] in [[Stargard]], 19 March 1945]]
Zhukov's right wing—a grouping of the [[3rd Shock Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Shock Army]] and [[1st Guards Tank Army (Soviet Union)|1st]] and [[2nd Guards Tank Army (Soviet Union)|2nd]] Guards Tank Armies—went over to the offensive on 1 March, striking northward with the main force concentrated at [[Recz|Reetz]]. The entire left wing of 3rd Panzer Army was cut off by their breakthrough, after [[Heinz Guderian|Guderian]] refused Raus' request for withdrawal; the right flank withdrew towards [[Szczecin|Stettin]].&lt;ref name=duffyp188&gt;Duffy, p.188&lt;/ref&gt;

On 4 March, forward Soviet tank units reached the [[Baltic Sea|Baltic]], and the German forces in Pomerania were trapped in a series of encirclements. The 2nd Army began to fall back on the Danzig fortified area, while the X SS Corps of the 3rd Panzer Army had been surrounded at [[Drawsko Pomorskie|Dramburg]].

===The second phase===
Rokossovsky opened the second phase of his offensive on March 6. The [[2nd Shock Army (Soviet Union)|2nd Shock Army]] threatened to cut off the defending forces in the [[Malbork Castle|fortress]] of [[Malbork|Marienburg]], which was evacuated two days later, while in the east Elbing finally fell on 10 March. The defence of Marienburg was conducted by a ''[[Kampfgruppe]]'' under the nominal control of the staff of the [[7th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|7th Infantry Division]], including marine, SS and other units. Weiß, having warned that the Elbing pocket could not be held, was relieved of command on 9 March and replaced by [[Dietrich von Saucken]]. The troops of the German 2nd Army withdrew in disarray into Danzig and [[Gdynia|Gdingen]], where the 2nd Belorussian Front besieged them. Zhukov's forces meanwhile, cleared the remainder of 3rd Panzer Army from the east bank of the lower [[Oder]], driving the Germans from their last positions in a bridgehead at [[Dąbie, Szczecin|Altdamm]].

==Siege of Kolberg==
{{main|Battle of Kolberg (1945)}}

Many civilian refugees from Pomerania had fled into the coastal town of [[Kołobrzeg|Kolberg]], which was surrounded by 4 March. Nevertheless, the town was successfully defended until 18 March, by which time evacuation was almost complete.

==Siege of Danzig==
The [[Gdansk|Danzig]]-[[Gdynia|Gotenhafen (Gdingen)]] Fortified Area—also the main port for refugees from East Prussia escaping to the west—was ordered to be defended for as long as possible by [[Dietrich von Saucken|von Saucken]] in order to keep the evacuation routes open.

Rokossovsky opened his final offensive on 15 March 1945; the main thrust, toward the coast at [[Sopot|Zoppot]] between Gdingen and Danzig, being undertaken by the [[70th Army (Soviet Union)|70th]] and [[49th Army (Soviet Union)|49th]] Army advancing in parallel.&lt;ref name=duffyp223&gt;Duffy, p.223&lt;/ref&gt; The fighting was savage, but by 19 March 1945 the Soviet spearheads had reached the heights over Zoppot, while the [[4th Panzer Division]] had been pushed back to the outskirts of Danzig itself. By 22 March 1945, the 70th Army reached the sea, splitting the German defence. Gdingen was taken on 26 March 1945, its defenders and many civilians retreating to the headland at [[Oksywie|Oxhöft]], from where they were evacuated to the [[Hel Peninsula]].

Danzig finally fell on 30 March 1945, after which the remnants of the 2nd Army withdrew to the Vistula delta southeast of the city. Evacuation of civilians and military personnel from there and from the Hel Peninsula continued until 10 May 1945. The Soviets declared the East Pomeranian Offensive complete a week after the fall of Danzig.

According to Soviet claims, in the Battle of Danzig the Germans lost 39,000 soldiers dead and 10,000 captured.&lt;ref&gt;http://9may.ru/30.03.1945/inform/m4219&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[History of Pomerania (1933–1945)]]
*[[Operation Hannibal]], the evacuation effort by the ''[[Kriegsmarine]]''
*[[Operation Solstice]], the preceding German offensive in Pomerania
*[[East Prussian Offensive]], the parallel offensives of the [[3rd Belorussian Front]] to the east
*The [[Heiligenbeil Pocket]], the parallel defence of the German 4. ''Armee'' east of Elbing
*The [[Pomeranian Wall]], a German line of fortifications overrun largely by the [[First Polish Army (1944–45)|First Polish Army]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|2}}

==References==
*Duffy, Christopher. ''Red Storm on the Reich: The Soviet March on Germany, 1945'', Routledge, 1991, {{ISBN|0-415-22829-8}}
*[[David M. Glantz]]
**[https://web.archive.org/web/20110709141048/http://www.strom.clemson.edu/publications/sg-war41-45.pdf The Soviet-German War 1941–45]: Myths and Realities: A Survey Essay
**Glantz, David M. &amp; House, Jonathan (1995), ''When Titans Clashed: How the Red Army Stopped Hitler'', Lawrence, Kansas: University Press of Kansas, {{ISBN|0-7006-0899-0}}
*[[Antony Beevor|Beevor, Antony]]. ''Berlin: The Downfall 1945'', Penguin Books, 2002, {{ISBN|0-670-88695-5}}
* {{cite journal
| last1 = Liedtke
| first1 = Gregory
| date=3 September 2008
| title = Analyzing World War II eastern front battles
| journal = The Journal of Slavic Military Studies
| volume = 21
| issue = 3
| publisher = Routledge Taylor &amp; Francis Group
| pages = 563–587
| doi = 10.1080/13518040802313852
| ref = harv
}}

{{Commons category|East Pomeranian Offensive}}{{Gdańsk}}{{coord missing|Poland}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1945]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:Strategic operations of the Red Army in World War II]]
[[Category:World War II aerial operations and battles of the Eastern Front]]
[[Category:Invasions of Germany]]
[[Category:February 1945 events]]
[[Category:March 1945 events]]
[[Category:April 1945 events]]
[[Category:1945 in Germany]]</text><sha1>cewk9w7fps4m9io9w6zvojl3s1mdohl</sha1></revision></page>