<page><title>Operation Margarethe</title><ns>0</ns><id>579508</id><revision><id>958687720</id><parentid>953931309</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-25T05:57:17Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Crispas</username><id>12893171</id></contributor><comment>/* Operation Margarethe II (TB +Mareile) */Added content</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="5661" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2019}}
{{More citations needed|date=January 2017}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-669-7340-27, Flugzeuge Me 110 über Budapest.jpg|250px|thumb|German [[Messerschmitt Bf 110|Bf 110s]] flying over [[Budapest]], January 1944.]]
'''Operation Margarethe''' was the occupation of [[Kingdom of Hungary (1920–1946)|Hungary]] by [[Nazi Germany|Nazi German]] forces during [[World War II]],&lt;ref&gt;Andreas Hillgruber, Helmuth Greinert, Percy Ernst Schramm, ''Kriegstagebuch  des Oberkommandos der Wehrmacht (Wehrmachtführungsstab) 1940-1945, Band IV: 1. Januar 1944 – 22. Mai 1945'' (Bernard &amp; Graefe, 1961)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Carlile Aylmer Macartney, ''October Fifteenth: A History of Modern Hungary, 1929–1945'', 2 vols. (Edinburgh University Press, 1956–57), II, 226.&lt;/ref&gt; as it was ordered by Hitler on 12 March 1944. A plan for the occupation of [[Kingdom of Romania|Romania]] was devised under the name Operation Margarethe II but was never carried out.

==Course of events==
Hungarian [[Prime Minister of Hungary|Prime Minister]] [[Miklós Kállay]] (in office from 1942), with the knowledge and approval of Regent [[Miklós Horthy]], secretly sought to negotiate a separate peace with the Allies in early 1944. German dictator [[Adolf Hitler]] wanted to prevent the Hungarians from turning against Germany, as Hungary's oil was desperately needed for the war effort. On 12 March 1944, German troops were ordered by Hitler to capture critical Hungarian facilities.

Hitler invited Horthy to the [[Schloss Klessheim|Palace of Klessheim]], outside of [[Salzburg|Salzburg, Austria]], on 15 March.  As the two heads of state conducted their negotiations, German forces quietly marched from [[Austria under National Socialism|German-occupied Austria]] into Hungary.  The meeting served merely as a German ruse to keep Horthy out of the country and to leave the [[Royal Hungarian Army|Hungarian Army]] without orders.  Negotiations between Horthy and Hitler lasted until the 18th, when Horthy boarded a train to return home.

When Horthy arrived in Budapest, German soldiers were waiting for him at the station. Horthy was told{{by whom|date=November 2017}} that Hungary could only remain sovereign if he removed Kállay in favor of a government that would cooperate fully with the Germans.  Otherwise, Hungary would be subject to undisguised occupation. As such, Horthy appointed [[Döme Sztójay]] as prime minister to appease German concerns. Being a complete surprise, the occupation was quick and bloodless. The initial plan was to immobilize the Hungarian army, but with [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] forces [[Dnieper–Carpathian Offensive|advancing from the north and east]], and with the prospect of British and American forces [[Adriatic Campaign of World War II#Planned allied landings|invading]] the [[Balkans]],&lt;ref&gt;Earl F. Ziemke, [https://books.google.com/books?id=Pr6HhrecbZ8C&amp;pg=PA208 Stalingrad to Berlin: The German Defeat in the East], U.S. Government Printing Office, 1968. "In November [1943] the transfer to the Eastern Front of the divisions allocated for Margarethe and intelligence reports that the Rumanians and Hungarians had secretly ironed out their difficulties and might try to desert the Axis in conjunction with an American-British invasion of the Balkans, complicated the problem."&lt;/ref&gt; the German military decided to retain Hungarian forces in the field, sending a portion to defend the passes through the [[Carpathian Mountains]] against possible invasion.

As a consequence of the Nazi occupation, [[Adolf Eichmann]] arranged the transportation of 550,000 [[Hungarian Jews]] from wartime Hungary (including Jews from territories annexed from Czechoslovakia, Romania, and Yugoslavia) to the [[Extermination camp|Nazi death camps]], with the collaboration of Hungarian authorities.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|last= Cesarani|first= David
|title= Eichmann: His Life and Crimes
|year= 2005|publisher= Vintage
|location= London
|isbn= 978-0-099-44844-0
|pages= 159–195
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;{{qn|date=November 2017}}

==Operation Margarethe II (TB +Mareile)==
Operation Margarethe II was the name for a planned Nazi German invasion of [[Kingdom of Romania|Romania]] by  German forces in conjunction with those of Hungary&lt;ref&gt;(see note 1)&lt;/ref&gt; should the Romanian government decide to surrender to the [[Soviet Union]] and switch sides.&lt;ref name="Sedlar2007"&gt;{{cite book|author=Jean W. Sedlar|title=The Axis Empire in Southeast Europe, 1939-1945|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=DoEhAQAAIAAJ|year=2007|publisher=BookLocker.com|isbn=978-1-60145-297-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Erickson1999"&gt;{{cite book|author=John Erickson|title=Stalin's War with Germany: The road to Berlin|url=https://archive.org/details/stalinswarwithge00eric|url-access=registration|year=1999|publisher=Yale University Press|isbn=978-0-300-07813-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="romania3"&gt;[https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwtwo/killing_hitler_01.shtmlRomania]{{dead link|date=November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; Romania did in fact surrender and switched sides in August 1944 (after [[King Michael's Coup]]), however this operation was never implemented.&lt;ref name="Sedlar2007"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Erickson1999"/&gt;&lt;ref name = "romania3"/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Hungary in World War II]]
* [[Operation Panzerfaust]]
* [[Chance Survivor]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{coord missing|Hungary}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Margarethe, Operation}}
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Eastern Front of World War II]]
[[Category:Military operations of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles involving Hungary]]
[[Category:Battles and conflicts without fatalities]]
[[Category:Germany–Hungary relations]]</text><sha1>f2j8nsi5b4rrmjopkxqscebl0brf0mb</sha1></revision></page>