<page><title>Battle of the Seelow Heights</title><ns>0</ns><id>1753935</id><revision><id>957003307</id><parentid>956963383</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-16T14:15:30Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Denniss</username><id>133598</id></contributor><comment>Undid revision 956963383 by [[Special:Contributions/Doomwings13|Doomwings13]] ([[User talk:Doomwings13|talk]])</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="18365" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|WWII German-Soviet military engagement}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Battle of Seelow Heights
|partof = the [[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]] of the&lt;br/&gt;[[Second World War]]
|image= Gedenkstätte Seelower Höhen Blick ins Oderbruch.JPG
|image_size= 250px
|caption = A modern view over the Oder from&lt;br/&gt;the Seelow Heights
|date = 16–19 April 1945
|place = [[Seelow Heights]], [[Province of Brandenburg]], [[Free State of Prussia|Prussia]], [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]
|coordinates = {{coord|52|31|47.3|N|14|25|33.9|E|region:DE-BB_type:event|display=inline,title}}
|result = Soviet victory, Complete encirclement of German capital
|combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
|combatant1 = {{flag|Soviet Union|1936}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flagdeco|Poland|1928}} [[Polish Armed Forces in the East|Poland]]
|commander2 = {{Flag icon|Nazi Germany}} [[Gotthard Heinrici]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flag icon|Nazi Germany}} [[Ferdinand Schörner]]
|commander1 = {{Flag icon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Georgy Zhukov]]&lt;br&gt;{{Flag icon|Soviet Union|1936}} [[Vasily Chuikov]]
|strength2 = 112,143 men&lt;br/&gt;587 tanks&lt;br/&gt;2,625 guns
|strength1 = 1,000,000 men&lt;br/&gt;3,059 tanks&lt;br/&gt;16,934 guns and mortars
|casualties2 = 12,000  killed{{sfn|Hastings|2005|p=468}}
|casualties1 = 30,000–33,000 killed{{sfn|Hastings|2005|p=468}}{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=244}}&lt;br&gt;
Estimate based on Soviet data: 5,000–6,000 killed and missing out of ~20,000 total casualties{{sfn|Isaev|2010|}}
|campaignbox ={{Campaignbox Axis-Soviet War}}
{{Campaignbox Battle of Berlin}}
}}

The '''Battle of the Seelow Heights''' ({{lang-de|Schlacht um die Seelower Höhen}}) was part of the [[Berlin Offensive|Berlin Strategic Offensive Operation]] (16 April–2 May 1945). A [[pitched battle]], it was one of the last assaults on large [[Field entrenchment|entrenched defensive positions]] of the [[Second World War]]. It was fought over three days, from 16–19 April 1945. Close to 1,000,000 Soviet soldiers of the [[1st Belorussian Front]] (including 78,556 soldiers of the [[First Polish Army (1944-1945)|Communist Polish 1st Army]]), commanded by [[Marshal of the Soviet Union|Marshal]] [[Georgi Zhukov]], attacked the position known as the "Gates of Berlin". They were opposed by about 110,000 soldiers of the [[9th Army (Wehrmacht)|German 9th Army]],{{sfn|Le Tissier|1996|p=273}} commanded by [[General (Germany)|General]] [[Theodor Busse]], as part of the [[Army Group Vistula]].

This battle is often incorporated into the [[Battle of the Oder-Neisse]]. The [[Seelow Heights]] was where some of the most bitter fighting in the overall battle took place, but it was only one of several crossing points along the [[Oder]] and [[Lusatian Neisse|Neisse]] rivers where the Soviets attacked. The Battle of the Oder-Neisse was itself only the opening phase of the [[Battle of Berlin]].

The result was the encirclement of the German 9th Army and the [[Battle of Halbe]].

==Buildup==
On 9 April 1945, [[Königsberg]] in [[East Prussia]] fell to the Soviet Army. This freed the [[2nd Belorussian Front]] under Marshal [[Konstantin Rokossovsky]] to move to the east bank of the Oder. During the first two weeks of April, the Soviets performed their fastest front redeployment of the war. The 2nd Belorussian Front relieved the [[1st Belorussian Front]] along the lower Oder between [[Schwedt]] and the [[Baltic Sea]]. This allowed the 1st Belorussian Front to concentrate in the southern half of its former front, opposite the Seelow Heights. To the south, the [[1st Ukrainian Front]] under Marshal [[Ivan Konev]] shifted its main force from [[Upper Silesia]] north-west to the Neisse River.

The three Soviet fronts together had 2,500,000 men, 6,250 tanks, 7,500 aircraft, 41,600 [[artillery]] pieces and [[Mortar (weapon)|mortar]]s, 3,255 truck-mounted ''[[Katyusha rocket launcher|Katyusha]]'' [[rocket launcher]]s and 95,383 motor vehicles.{{sfn|Ziemke|1968|p=71}}

The 1st Belorussian Front had nine regular and two tank armies consisting of 77 rifle divisions, two cavalry, five tank and two mechanized corps, eight artillery and one guards mortars divisions and a mixture of other artillery and rocket launcher brigades. The front had 3,059 tanks and self-propelled guns and 18,934 artillery pieces and mortars.{{sfn|Goncharov|2007|pp=170, 171, 550}} Eight of the 11 armies were posted along the Oder. In the north, the 61st Army and the [[1st Polish Army]] held the river line from Schwedt to its meeting with the [[Finow Canal]]. On the Soviet bridgehead at [[Küstrin]], the [[47th Army (Soviet Union)|47th Army]], [[3rd Shock Army|3rd]] and [[5th Shock Army|5th Shock armies]], and the [[8th Guards Army]] were concentrated for the attack. The [[69th Army (Soviet Union)|69th Army]] and [[33rd Army (Soviet Union)|33rd Army]] covered the river line south to [[Guben]]. The [[1st Guards Tank Army|1st Guards]] and [[2nd Guards Tank Army|2nd Guards Tank armies]] and the [[3rd Army (Soviet Union)|3rd Army]] were in reserve. The 5th Shock and 8th Guards were posted directly opposite the strongest part of the defences, where the [[Reichsstraße (Deutsches Reich)|Reichsstraße 1]] to Berlin passed through the heights.{{sfn|Goodenough|1982|p=116}}

The German 9th Army held the front from about the [[Finow Canal]] to [[Guben]], an area which included the Seelow Heights. It had 14 divisions, the [[Fortress Division Frankfurt/Oder|"Fortress" (''Festung'') Frankfurt]], 587 tanks (512 operable, 55 in repair, 20 in transit) and 2,625 artillery pieces (including 695 anti-aircraft guns).{{sfn|Isaev|2007|pp=293–295}} Further south, the front was held by the [[Fourth Panzer Army|4th ''Panzerarmee'']], which opposed the 1st Ukrainian Front.

General [[Gotthard Heinrici]] replaced [[Heinrich Himmler]] as commander of Army Group Vistula on 20 March. He correctly predicted that the main Soviet thrust would be made over the River Oder and along the Reichsstraße 1 at Seelow Heights. He decided to defend the riverbank with only a light skirmishing screen, but to strongly fortify the Seelow Heights, which rise about {{convert|48|m|ft|abbr=on}} above the Oder and overlook the river where the Reichsstraße crossed it. He thinned out the line in other areas to put more men on the heights. The Oder's floodplain was already saturated by the spring thaw, but German engineers also released water from a reservoir upstream, which turned the plain into a swamp. Behind the heights, they built three lines of defences, spreading back toward Berlin. The last was the ''Wotan'' Line, {{convert|10|-|15|mi|km|abbr=on}} behind the front line. These lines consisted of anti-tank ditches, anti-tank gun emplacements, and an extensive network of trenches and bunkers.{{sfn|Ziemke|1968|p=76}}{{sfn|Zuljan|2003}}

==Battle==
{{more citations needed|section|date=April 2017}}
[[File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-E0406-0022-012, Sowjetische Artillerie vor Berlin.jpg|300px|thumb|right|Soviet artillery bombarding German positions during the battle]]
In the early hours of April 16th, the offensive began with a massive bombardment by thousands of artillery pieces and ''Katyusha''s. Well before dawn, the 1st Belorussian Front attacked across the Oder and the 1st Ukrainian Front attacked across the Neisse. The 1st Belorussian Front was the stronger force, but it had the more difficult assignment since it was facing the bulk of the German forces.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|p=217}}{{sfn|Ziemke|1968|p=81}}

The assault by the 1st Belorussian Front started with an intense artillery bombardment. According to Beevor and Ziemke, Heinrici and Busse had anticipated the attack and withdrew their defenders from the first line of trenches just before the Soviet artillery would have obliterated them. Whereas according to a report to [[Joseph Stalin|Stalin]], Zhukov wrote  that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;Considering that the enemy moves its infantry from the first to the second and third lines of trenches in the morning, I used a nightly artillery barrage with a high density of fire for 30 minutes, with the use of searchlights to blind the enemy and light up the terrain ahead of the advancing troops... According to the interrogated prisoners, artillery fire was so sudden and overwhelming that the enemy did not have time to move from the first trench line; the second and third lines were at all times under heavy fire from our artillery. As a result of this, the enemy units in the first line of defence suffered heavy casualties.{{sfn|Isaev|2006|pp=394–395}}&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The swampy ground proved to be a great hindrance, and a German counter-barrage caused heavy Soviet casualties. Frustrated by the slow advance, Zhukov threw in his reserves, which according to his earlier plan were to be held back until the expected breakthrough. By early evening, an advance of {{convert|4|-|6|km|mi|abbr=on}} had been achieved (the 77th Rifle Corps from the 3rd Shock Army had advanced {{convert|8|km|mi|abbr=on}}), but the second German defensive line remained intact. Zhukov was forced to report that his battle was not going as planned. However, in the south the attack by Konev's 1st Ukrainian Front was going according to plan. To spur Zhukov on, Stalin told him that he let Konev direct his tank armies north towards Berlin.{{sfn|Beevor|2002|pp=217–233}}{{sfn|Ziemke|1968|p=82}}

On the second day, the 1st Belorussian Front's troops continued to advance in accordance with the initial plan. By nightfall on 17 April, the German second defensive line (''Stein Stellung'') was broken by the 5th Shock Army and 2nd Guards Tank Army. The right flank of the 4th Guards Rifle Corps of the 8th Guards Army, together with the 11th Tank Corps of the 1st Guards Tank Army, had taken advantage of the success of their comrades and also advanced. The 47th and the 3rd shock armies progressed another {{convert|4|-|8|km|mi|abbr=on}}.

To the south however, the 1st Ukrainian Front was pushing back the 4th Panzer Army; the left flank of [[Army Group Centre]] under [[Ferdinand Schörner]] was beginning to crumble. Schörner kept his two reserve [[panzer]] divisions in the south covering his centre, instead of using them to shore up the 4th Panzer Army. This was the turning point in the Berlin Offensive because the positions of both Army Group Vistula and the centre and right sectors of Army Group Centre were becoming untenable. Unless they fell back in line with the 4th Panzer Army, they faced envelopment. In effect, Konev's successful attack on Schörner's relatively poor defences to the south of Seelow Heights was unhinging Heinrici's defence.

On 18 April, both Soviet fronts advanced with heavy losses. The Seelow Heights was bypassed from the north, during which Soviet troops met counterattacks by German reserves: 11th SS Panzergrenadier Division ''Nordland'', 23rd SS Panzergrenadier Division ''Nederland'' and SS-Panzer Abteilung 103 (503rd). By nightfall, an advance of {{convert|3|-|5|km|mi|abbr=on}} on the right flank and {{convert|3|-|8|km|mi|abbr=on}} in the centre had been achieved, and the 1st Belorussian Front had reached the third and final German line of defence.

On 19 April, the 1st Belorussian Front eventually broke through the final defensive line of the Seelow Heights and now nothing but broken German formations lay between them and Berlin. The remnants of the 9th Army and the 4th Panzer Army were enveloped by the 1st Belorussian Front and by elements of the 1st Ukrainian Front which had broken through and turned north. Other armies of the 1st Ukrainian Front raced west towards the Americans. By the close of 19 April, the German eastern frontline had effectively ceased to exist. All that remained were pockets of resistance.{{sfn|Ziemke|1968|p=84}}

==Aftermath and analysis==
[[File:Kriegerdenkmal-Seelower-Hoehe-k.jpg|thumb|right|Soviet monument at the Seelow Heights.]]

The defensive line on the Seelow Heights was the last major defensive line outside Berlin. From 19 April, the road to Berlin—{{convert|90|km|mi|abbr=on}} to the west—lay open. By 23 April, Berlin was fully encircled and the [[Battle in Berlin]] entered its last stage. Within two weeks, [[Adolf Hitler]] was dead and the [[End of World War II in Europe|war in Europe was effectively over]].

As a result of the 1st Belorussian Front's success at the Seelow Heights and the Oder Front in general, most of the forces of the German 9th Army were encircled before they could retreat to Berlin. The city was then defended by broken formations, the ''[[Volkssturm]]'', police, and air defence units, which resulted in the Red Army taking it in 10 days.{{sfn|Isaev|2010|}}{{sfn|Isaev|2006|pp=402–403}}

After the war, Zhukov's critics{{who|date=February 2016}} asserted that he should have stopped the 1st Belorussian Front's attack via the direct line to Berlin along the ''autobahn'' and instead made use of the 1st Ukrainian Front's breakthrough over the Neisse or concentrate its armies on surrounding Berlin from the north. This would have bypassed the strong German defences at Seelow Heights, and avoided many casualties and the delay in the Berlin advance. Zhukov supposedly took the shortest path, the critics contend, so that his troops would be the first ones to enter the city. However, Zhukov chose the main thrust to be through the Seelow Heights not because he thought that was the quickest way to get to Berlin, but because that was the quickest way to link up with Konev's 1st Ukrainian Front and cut off the German 9th Army from the city.{{sfn|Isaev|2006|pp=377–383}} Also, bypassing the Seelow Heights and attacking Berlin from the north would have exposed the northern flank of the 1st Belorussian Front to a potential attack from German forces to the north, which could have pinned Zhukov's forces against the Seelow Heights.{{sfn|Isaev|2006|p=388-389}} Furthermore, in actuality only two of the five armies of the 1st Belorussian Front attacked the Seelow Heights themselves and the heights were eventually bypassed from the north as soon as there was a narrow breakthrough.{{sfn|Isaev|2010|}}{{sfn|Isaev|2007|pp=421, 690}}

Estimates of Soviet casualties during the assault on the Seelow Heights vary from under 10,000 to over 30,000 killed.&lt;ref group="Note"&gt;According to historian Aleksey Isaev, based on archival data the 1st Belorussian Front lost 20,000 men, including 5,000–6,000 killed and missing, while the historians [[Max Hastings]] and [[Antony Beevor]] state that 30–33,000 were killed. {{harvnb|Isaev|2010}}; {{harvnb|Hastings|2005|p=468}};   {{harvnb|Beevor|2002|p=244}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Eastern Front (World War II)|Eastern Front]]
*[[Battle of Halbe]]
*[[Battle of Berlin]]

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group="Note"}}

==References==

===Citations===
{{reflist|colwidth=20em}}

===Bibliography===
*{{cite book | title = [[Berlin: The Downfall 1945]] | last = Beevor | first = Antony | authorlink = Antony Beevor | year = 2002 | publisher = Viking-Penguin Books | location = London | isbn = 978-0-670-03041-5 | ref = harv}}
*{{Cite book|ref=harv |last=Goncharov |first=Vladislav |script-title=ru:Битва за Берлин. Завершающее сражение Великой Отечественной войны |trans-title=Battle for Berlin: The Final Battle of the Great Patriotic War |year=2007 |publisher=AST |location=Moscow |language=Russian |isbn=978-5-17-039116-5}}
*{{Cite book |ref=harv |last=Goodenough |first=Simon |title=War Maps |year=1982 |publisher=Macdonald |isbn=0-312-85584-2 |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/warmapsworldwari0000good }}
*{{Cite book|ref=harv |authorlink=Max Hastings | last = Hastings | first = Max | title = Armageddon: The Battle for Germany, 1944–1945 | publisher = Vintage | year = 2005 | isbn = 978-0-375-71422-1|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uKmeiZmEXJoC}}
*{{cite book |ref=harv |last=Isaev |first=Aleksey |script-title=ru:Георгий Жуков: Последний довод короля |trans-title=Zhukov: The Last Argument of the King |year=2006 |publisher=Yauza |location=Moscow |isbn=5-699-16564-9 |url=https://archive.org/details/georgiizhukovpos00isae |language=Russian |url-access=registration }}
*{{Cite book |ref=harv |last=Isaev |first=Aleksey |script-title=ru:Берлин 45-го: Сражения в логове зверя |trans-title=Berlin of 45: Battles in the Beast's Den |year=2007 |publisher=Yauza, Eksmo |location=Moscow |isbn=978-5-699-20927-9 |url=http://militera.lib.ru/h/isaev_av7/index.html |language=Russian}}
*{{cite interview |ref=harv |last=Isaev |first=Aleksey |interviewer=Vitaly Dymarsky |title=Seelow Heights |url=http://echo.msk.ru/programs/victory/697626-echo |work=Price of Victory |publisher=[[Echo of Moscow]] |location=Moscow |date=26 July 2010  |accessdate=1 December 2012 |language=Russian}}
*{{Cite book|ref=harv |last=Le Tissier |first=Tony |title=Zhukov at the Oder |publisher=Praeger |location=New York |year=1996 |isbn=978-0-275-95230-3}}
*{{Cite book|ref=harv |last=Ziemke |first=Earl F.|title=The Battle for Berlin: End of the Third Reich|year=1968| publisher=Ballantine Books|location=New York|isbn=0-356-02960-3}}
*{{cite web|ref=harv |last=Zuljan |date=1 July 2003 |origyear=1999 |first=Ralph |url=http://www.onwar.com/articles/9905.htm |title=Battle for the Seelow Heights – Part II |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110525014346/http://www.onwar.com/articles/9905.htm |archivedate=25 May 2011 |df=dmy }} Originally published in "World War II" at Suite101.com on 1 May 1999. Revised edition published in "Articles on War" at [https://web.archive.org/web/20110514001340/http://www.onwar.com/faq.htm  OnWar.com] on 1 July 2003.

{{Subject bar
| portal1=Military of Germany
| portal2=World War II
| commons=y
| commons-search=Gedenkstätte Seelower Höhen
}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Seelow Heights}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1945]]
[[Category:1945 in Germany]]
[[Category:Battles involving Poland]]
[[Category:Battles involving the Soviet Union]]
[[Category:20th century in Brandenburg]]
[[Category:Battles in Brandenburg]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of the Soviet–German War]]
[[Category:Battle of Berlin]]
[[Category:Seelow|Battle of the Seelow Heights]]
[[Category:April 1945 events]]
[[Category:Province of Brandenburg]]</text><sha1>qwf81g8evehetawb14xjp8hwnxq3zzu</sha1></revision></page>