<page><title>Action of 27 February 1941</title><ns>0</ns><id>24993311</id><revision><id>961401019</id><parentid>961400672</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-08T07:47:18Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Keith-264</username><id>925588</id></contributor><minor /><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="11976" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Action of 27 February 1941
|partof=the [[Second World War]]
|image=File:Maldives (orthographic projection).svg
|image_size=250px
|caption=Maldive Islands (orthographic projection)
|date=27 February 1941
|place= off [[Maldives]], [[Indian Ocean]]
|coordinates = {{coord|1|0|N|68|30|E|display=inline}}
|territory=
|result= New Zealand victory
|combatant1={{flagcountry|Dominion of New Zealand}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
|commander1=[[Robert Hesketh Bevan|Robert Bevan]]
|commander2=[[Alfredo Bonezzi]]
|strength1=1 [[cruiser]]
|strength2=1 [[auxiliary cruiser]]
|casualties1=1 cruiser slightly damaged
|casualties2=1 auxiliary cruiser sunk&lt;br /&gt;1 killed&lt;br /&gt;103 captured&lt;br /&gt;of whom: 4 wounded&lt;br /&gt;(1 died of wounds)
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Indian Ocean Theatre}}
{{Campaignbox South-East Asian Theatre}}
}}
The '''Action of 27 February 1941''' was a [[single ship action]] between the British [[cruiser]] {{HMS|Leander||6}} and the Italian [[auxiliary cruiser]] {{Ship|Italian ship|Ramb I||2}}. It began when ''Leander'' ordered an un-flagged freighter to stop for an inspection. The freighter raised the Italian colours and engaged ''Leander'' which sank ''Ramb'' I shortly after. Most of the Italian crew were rescued and taken to [[Addu Atoll]], then [[British Ceylon|Ceylon]] (now Sri Lanka). ''Leander'' patrolled southwards to investigate more reports of commerce raiders.

==Background==

===East African Campaign===
{{main article|East African Campaign (World War II)|l1=East African Campaign}}

In January 1941, British forces simultaneously advanced from Sudan and Kenya into Eritrea, Abyssinia and Italian Somaliland, as the navy blockaded and bombarded Italian harbours. The port of Kismayu in Italian Somaliland was occupied on 14 February and sixteen Italian and German ships there were sunk or captured, except for one vessel. Merka and Mogadishu were occupied on 25 February and several hundred Allied merchant sailors were liberated. As Allied forces closed on [[Massawa]], the Italian [[Red Sea Flotilla]] was ordered to break out and run for friendly ports. A group of Italian vessels consisting of the colonial ship [[Eritrea (ship)|''Eritrea'']] and the auxiliary cruisers {{Ship|Italian ship|Ramb I||2}} and {{Ship|Italian ship|Ramb II||2}} attempted to operate as commerce raiders while en route to Japan.{{sfn|Jackson|2006|p=281}} The Italian squadron managed to evade the British blockade on 20 February and scattered into the Indian Ocean, ''Ramb'' I heading for the [[Dutch East Indies]].{{sfn|Waters|1956|p=96}}

===HMS ''Leander''===

{{HMS|Leander||6}} was the leader of the {{sclass-|Leander|cruiser|4||1931}} of cruisers, armed with eight {{cvt|6|in|mm}} guns, ten [[QF 4 inch Mk V naval gun|{{cvt|4|in|mm}} gun]]s, twelve [[Vickers .50 machine gun|{{cvt|.50|in|mm|1}} Vickers]] [[machine gun]]s in quadruple mounts and eight {{cvt|21|in|mm}} [[torpedo tube]]s. ''Leander'' also had armour plating over her turrets, deck and magazines and a top speed of {{cvt|32.5|kn|mph+km/h|lk=in}}.{{sfn|Campbell|1985|p=34}}{{sfn|Lenton|Colledge|1968|p=39}}

===''Ramb'' I===

{{main|East African campaign (World War II)#Massawa|l1=Massawa}}

''Ramb'' I (3,667 [[Gross register tons|GRT]]) was an auxiliary cruiser, a merchant ship adapted for naval service and lacked armour protection. ''Ramb'' I was armed with two {{cvt|120|mm|in|1}} guns and eight {{cvt|13.2|mm|in|2}} [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft machine guns]].{{sfn|Roskill|1957|p=605}} ''Ramb'' I was slower than ''Leander'', with a maximum speed of {{cvt|18.5|kn|mph+km/h}}. The ship had departed Suez on 10 June 1940 for Massawa on the [[Red Sea]] coast, from where the ship made short cruises along the coast of Eritrea but was mainly used for anti-aircraft defence of the port. As British and Commonwealth troops neared the port, ''Ramb'' I and ''Coburg'' (7,400 GRT), a German freighter, escaped from Massawa on the night of 20/21 February 1941 and passed into the [[Gulf of Aden]]. One ship was sighted near the island of [[Socotra]] off the Horn of Africa but it was considered too dangerous a location to attack.{{sfn|Waters|1956|p=98}}{{sfn|Rohwer|Hümmelchen|1992|p=51}}

==Prelude==

[[File:British light cruiser HMS Leander (75) underway at sea in 1945.jpg|thumb|{{centre|HMNZS ''Leander''}}]]
Acting on reports of [[Commerce raiding|commerce raiders]] in the area, ''Leander'' detached from convoy US 9 off Bombay on 22 February.{{sfn|Rohwer|Hümmelchen|1992|p=51}} Passing west of the [[Lakshadweep|Laccadive]] and [[Maldives|Maldive]] islands, to a patrol area west of [[Huvadhu Kandu|One and a Half Degree Channel]]. At {{nowrap|7:00 a.m.}} on 27 February, ''Leander'' was steaming east, about {{cvt|28|nmi}} north of the Equator and {{cvt|320|nmi}} west of the Maldives. The captain, [[Robert Hesketh Bevan|Robert Bevan]] altered course to the north to head for One and a Half Degree Channel, because news of the capture of Mogadishu had been received by radio on the previous day. Italian ships in the port might have sailed along that route for the Far East.{{sfn|Waters|1956|p=96}}

==Action==
At {{nowrap|10:37 a.m.,}} a ship was sighted ahead and ''Leander'' increased speed to {{cvt|23|kn|mph+km/h}}, gradually overhauling the vessel. As ''Leander'' closed, a gun was seen on the ship's forecastle and the silhouette of the ship resembled an Italian ''Ramb''-class fruit carrier. Leander went to action stations at {{nowrap|11:15 a.m.}} and when ordered to identify itself ten minutes later, the vessel hoisted a British merchant flag. When ordered to give its signal letters, the ship hoisted four letters which were not listed in British signal books. ''Leander'' made the ''secret challenge'' but received no reply and the ship maintained its course and speed. A boarding party was standing by and at {{nowrap|11:45 a.m.,}} the ship was ordered to stop instantly but no reply was received. A few minutes later, the ship hoisted the Italian merchant flag and trained its guns on ''Leander''. The cruiser was broad on the beam of the Italian ship and at {{cvt|3000|yd|nmi+mi+km}} was an easy target for its guns and torpedoes. At {{nowrap|11:53 a.m.,}} the Italian ship opened fire and thirty seconds later, ''Leander'' replied. The Italian fire was inaccurate and it was estimated that only about three shells were fired from each gun.{{sfn|Waters|1956|p=97}}

[[File:Ramb1.jpg|thumb|{{centre|''Ramb'' I sinking, February 1941}}]]
A few shell splinters hit ''Leander'', which fired five salvoes in a minute, then ceased fire to observe results. ''Leander'' made the flag signal "Do you surrender?", the Merchant flag was seen to be lowered and the crew began to abandon ship. ''Leander'' had hit the ship several times in the forepart and a fire burned, visible through a large hole in the side. A boat was lowered from ''Leander'' with a boarding party to try to save the ship and two lifeboats were seen leaving the vessel as men jumped overboard or scrambled down the side. An Italian officer in the water called out that the boarding party should not approach the ship, as it was burning and laden with ammunition. The boarding party laid off and as the fire spread, a big explosion before the bridge shot flames and smoke high into the sky, the ship settling bows first. As the fire burned, there was another explosion and five minutes later the ship sank under a cloud of black smoke. ''Leander'' recovered the boarding party and the Italian lifeboats, while edging away.{{sfn|Waters|1956|p=97}}

==Aftermath==
One Italian sailor had been killed by shellfire during the engagement; the Italian captain, ten officers and 92 sailors were rescued, of whom one man was seriously wounded, four were slightly injured.{{sfn|Waters|1956|p=98}}{{sfn|Rohwer|Hümmelchen|1992|p=51}} The seriously wounded man died in surgery during the afternoon and was buried at sunset. The prisoners said that ''Ramb'' I had been badly damaged by the shell hits and as ''Leander'' closed, the order to abandon ship had been given. ''Leander'' proceeded eastward and arrived at [[Addu Atoll]] next morning. The Italian prisoners were transferred to the oiler ''Pearleaf'' with an armed guard of nineteen ratings and an officer; the ship made for [[Colombo]], [[British Ceylon|Ceylon]] (now Sri Lanka). ''Leander'' was sent to investigate wireless direction-finding indications that Axis ships were in the vicinity of the [[Saya de Malha Bank]], several hundred miles south-east of the Seychelles Islands and north-east of [[Madagascar]].{{sfn|Waters|1956|p=98}} ''Coburg'' with a prize, ''Ketty Brovig'', a Norwegian tanker, was spotted south-east of the Seychelles by a spotter aircraft from {{HMAS|Canberra|D33|6}} and both ships were scuttled when ''Canberra'' and ''Leander'' approached them.{{sfn|Rohwer|Hümmelchen|1992|p=51}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Campbell|1985}}
|title=Naval Weapons of World War Two |last=Campbell |first=J. |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, MD |year=1985 |isbn=978-0-87021-459-2}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Jackson|2006}}
|title=The British Empire and the Second World War |last=Jackson |first=A. |publisher=Continuum International |location=New York |year=2006 |isbn=978-1-85285-417-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Lenton|Colledge|1968}}
|title=British and Dominion Warships of World War Two |last1=Lenton |first1=H.T. |last2=Colledge |first2=J. J. |year=1968 |orig-year=1964 |publisher=Doubleday |location=Garden City, NY |edition=orig. pub. Warships of World War II |oclc=440734}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Rohwer|Hümmelchen|1992}}
|first1= Jürgen |last1=Rohwer |first2=Gerhard |last2=Hümmelchen |title=Chronology of the War at Sea, 1939–1945: The Naval History of World War Two |year=1992 |orig-year=1972 |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, MD |edition=2nd rev. |isbn=978-1-55750-105-9}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Roskill|1957}}
|series=History of the Second World War United Kingdom Military Series: The War at Sea 1939–1945 |title=The Defensive |volume=I |last=Roskill |first=S. W. |authorlink=Stephen Roskill |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=J. R. M. |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |year=1957 |orig-year=1954 |publisher=HMSO |location=London |edition=4th impr. |oclc=881709135}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Waters|1956}}
|series=Official History of New Zealand in the Second World War 1939–45 |title=The Royal New Zealand Navy |last=Waters |first=S. D. |authorlink=|year=1956 |publisher=War History Branch, Dept. of Internal Affairs |location=Wellington, NZ |edition=online |via=New Zealand Electronic Text Centre |url=http://nzetc.victoria.ac.nz/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2Navy.html |accessdate=23 February 2016 |oclc=11085179}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |series=Battle Summary |title=Actions with Enemy Disguised Raiders 1940–1941 |number=13 |author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |authorlink= |year=1942 |publisher=Tactical, Torpedo and Staff Duties Division, Historical Section, Naval Staff, Admiralty |location=London |edition= |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/sites/default/files/documents/Battle_Summary_No_13.pdf |accessdate=7 April 2016 |pages=5–6 |oclc=221288026}}
* {{cite book |title= Bitter Victory: The Death of HMAS Sydney |last=Olson |first=Wesley |year=2003 |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, MD |isbn=978-1-59114-066-5}}

==External links==
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/UK-RN-I/index.html Roskill War at Sea Vol. I via Hyperwar]

{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:19410227}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1941]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving New Zealand]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in February 1941]]
[[Category:History of the Maldives]]
[[Category:February 1941 events]]
[[Category:Italy–New Zealand relations]]</text><sha1>63324tsbmd2one5tqldz7ftln3sl7uo</sha1></revision></page>