<page><title>Japanese occupation of the Andaman Islands</title><ns>0</ns><id>3102512</id><revision><id>964862365</id><parentid>961125945</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-28T01:01:51Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Amigao</username><id>11099276</id></contributor><minor /><comment>clean up, [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: km² → km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="15539" xml:space="preserve">[[File:Japanese running to Andaman Islands.jpg|thumb|right|250px|Japanese disembarking in Andaman, March 1942.]]
The '''Japanese occupation of the Andaman Islands''' occurred in 1942 during [[World War II]]. The [[Andaman and Nicobar]] Islands (8,293&amp;nbsp;km&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; on 139 islands), are a group of islands situated in the [[Bay of Bengal]] at about {{convert|1250|km|abbr=on}} from [[Kolkata]],  {{convert|1200|km|abbr=on}} from [[Chennai]] and  {{convert|190|km|abbr=on}} from [[Cape Nargis]] in [[Burma]]. Until 1938 the British government used them as a penal colony for [[India]]n and [[Ethnic groups of Africa|African]] political prisoners, who were mainly put in the notorious [[Cellular Jail]] in [[Port Blair]], the biggest town (port) on the islands. Today they form a [[Union Territory]] of [[India]].

The only military objective on the islands was the city of Port Blair. The garrison consisted of a 300-man Sikh militia with 23 British officers, augmented in January 1942 by a [[Gurkha]] detachment of 4/[[12th Frontier Force Regiment]] of the [[16th Indian Infantry Brigade]]. Following the fall of [[Rangoon]] on March 8, however, the British recognized that Port Blair had become impossible to defend, and on March 10 the Gurkhas were withdrawn to the [[Rakhine State|Arakan]] peninsula.
{{Campaignbox South-East Asia}}
{{Campaignbox Indian Ocean Theatre}}
{{Campaignbox South-East Asian Theatre}}

==Invasion force==
The Japanese, seeking to secure their seaward flank, dispatched a force to seize the islands.  The force was composed of the following units and ships:&lt;ref name="Klemen" /&gt;

'''Distant Cover'''&lt;br&gt;
:*Cruiser (flagship) ''[[Japanese cruiser Chōkai|Chokai]]''
:'''Carrier Division 4'''
:*Carrier ''[[Japanese aircraft carrier Ryūjō|Ryūjō]]'' (although listed, she did not conduct air operations)
:'''Cruiser Division 7''' – Heavy cruisers
:*''[[Japanese cruiser Kumano|Kumano]]''
:*{{ship|Japanese cruiser|Suzuya|1934|2}}
:*''[[Mikuma]]''
:*''[[Japanese cruiser Mogami (1934)|Mogami]]''
:'''Destroyer Division 11'''
:*''[[Japanese destroyer Fubuki (1927)|Fubuki]]''
:*''[[Japanese destroyer Hatsuyuki (1928)|Hatsuyuki]]''
:*''[[Japanese destroyer Shirayuki (1928)|Shirayuki]]''
:*''[[Japanese destroyer Murakami|Murakami]]''
'''Close Cover'''&lt;br&gt;
:'''Destroyer Squadron 3'''
:*Light cruiser ''[[Japanese cruiser Sendai|Sendai]]''
::'''Destroyer Division 19'''
::*''[[Japanese destroyer Isonami (1927)|Isonami]]''
::*''[[Japanese destroyer Uranami (1928)|Uranami]]''
::*''[[Japanese destroyer Ayanami (1929)|Ayanami]]''
::'''Destroyer Division 20'''
::*''[[Japanese destroyer Amagiri (1930)|Amagiri]]''
::*{{ship|Japanese destroyer|Asagiri|1929|2}}
::*''[[Japanese destroyer Yūgiri (1930)|Yugiri]]''
::*''[[Japanese destroyer Shirakumo (1927)|Shirakumo]]''
'''Invasion Force'''&lt;br&gt;
:*Light cruiser ''[[Japanese cruiser Yura|Yura]]'' – escort unit
:*9 Transports
::*1 Battalion from 18th Infantry Division
::*9th Base Force
:*Training cruiser ''[[Japanese cruiser Kashii|Kashii]]''
:*Escort ship ''[[Shumushu]]''
:*Minelayer ''[[Japanese minelayer Hatsutaka|Hatsutaka]]''
:*Converted gunboat ''Eiko Maru''
'''Minesweeper Division 1'''&lt;br&gt;
:*Minesweepers W1, W3, W4
'''Special Minesweeper Division 91'''&lt;br&gt;
:*Minesweepers: ''Choko Maru'', ''Shonan Maru'' #7, ''Shonan Maru'' #5
'''Air Unit'''&lt;br&gt;
:*Seaplane tender ''Sagara Maru'' (operated east of the Nicobars)

==Japanese occupation==

Port Blair was occupied on the 23 March 1942. The garrison offered no resistance to the landings, and were disarmed and interned; many of the Sikh militia later enlisted in the [[Indian National Army]].&lt;ref name="Klemen"&gt;{{cite web|first = Klemen | last = L |url= http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/andaman.html |title= The capture of Andaman Islands, March 1942 |date=1999–2000 |work=Forgotten Campaign: The Dutch East Indies Campaign 1941–1942}}&lt;/ref&gt; The British militia officers were sent to Singapore as POWs,&lt;ref name="Klemen" /&gt; whilst Chief Commissioner Waterfall, Deputy Commissioner Major A.G. Bird and the other British administrative officers were imprisoned. The Japanese released the prisoners held in the jail,&lt;ref name="Klemen" /&gt; one of whom, Pushkar Bakshi, became their principal collaborator. The islands were put under the authority of Colonel Bucho, whilst a number of junior Indian officials in the administration were elevated to more responsible posts. The defence of the islands was assigned to the newly formed fighter squadron of the [[Kanoya Kōkūtai|Kanoya]] [[Kōkūtai]] based at [[Dawei|Tavoy]] in southern [[Burma]]. This fighter squadron was the former "[[Yamada Unit]]" under the control of the [[22d Koku Sentai]], then based at [[Penang]].&lt;ref name="Klemen" /&gt; Six flying boats from the [[Toko Kōkūtai]] were dispatched on March 26, with twelve more arriving shortly thereafter. Within the islands, a Japanese garrison of approximately 600 men, together with the police force, now under Japanese control, were responsible for maintaining order.

'''Japanese Army personnel in Andaman and Nicobar'''

*[[Yoshisuke Inoue]]: Commanding Officer 35th Independent Mixed Brigade, Andaman Islands
*[[Toshio Itsuki]]: Commanding Officer 36th Independent Mixed Brigade, Nicobar Islands
*[[Hideo Iwakuro]]: Japanese Liaison Officer to Indian National Army
*Major-General [[Saburo Isoda]]: Japanese Liaison Officer to Indian National Army

===Japanese atrocities===

The events of the next three years are not easy to establish, as the Japanese destroyed all records when they left. The principal sources are an unpublished report by local resident Rama Krishna: ''The Andaman Islands under Japanese Occupation 1942–5'', another unpublished account by a British Officer, D. McCarthy: ''The Andaman Interlude'' (he was sent on a secret mission to the islands in 1944), together with the memories of the older inhabitants interviewed by historians. All these and the published works that draw upon them are in agreement that the occupation saw numerous atrocities committed by the Japanese against the local population.&lt;ref&gt;N. Iqbal Singh ''The Andaman Story'' (Delhi: Vikas Publ.) 1978&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jayant Dasgupta ''Japanese in Andaman &amp; Nicobar Islands. Red Sun over Black Water'' (Delhi: Manas Publications) 2002 pp. 42, 88–91&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;L.P. Mathur ''Kala Pani. History of the Andaman &amp; Nicobar Islands with a study of India's Freedom Struggle'' (Delhi: Eastern Book Corporation) 1985 pp. 247–55&lt;/ref&gt;

The first victim of the occupation came on the fourth day after the Japanese landings. Angered by soldiers who had pursued some chickens into his house, a young man called Zulfiqar Ali fired an airgun at them. No-one was hurt, but he was forced into hiding. After twenty-four hours he was captured and marched to the ''maidan'' in front of the Browning Club. Here his arms were twisted until they broke, and he was then shot. A cement memorial now stands on the spot.&lt;ref&gt;Dasgupta ''Red Sun over Black Water'' pp. 44–45&lt;/ref&gt; In the early days of the occupation local intellectuals (mostly officials and doctors) were encouraged to join [[Rash Behari Bose]]'s [[Indian Independence League]], and a 'Peace Committee' was formed from its members, headed by Dr [[Diwan Singh]]. Over the next few months they did what they could to mitigate the suffering of the population at the hands of the Japanese, but to little avail: indeed, many of them would later fall victim themselves. In any case, there was little any of them could have done to save Major A.G. Bird, who had not been sent to [[Rangoon]] or [[Singapore]] like the other British captives, and of whom the Japanese were determined to make an example. Pushkar Bakshi persuaded a fellow convict, Sarup Ram, to bear witness at Bird's 'trial' that he had been spying (wireless parts had been planted in the house where he was imprisoned). According to eyewitnesses, a popular man known as "Chirrie" ('Bird' in [[Hindi]]) had his arms and legs twisted and broken, and was then beheaded by Colonel Bucho with his sword.&lt;ref&gt;Dasgupta ''Red Sun over Black Water'' pp. 50–51&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mathur ''Kala Pani'' p. 248; Iqbal Singh ''The Andaman Story'' pp. 241–42&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:The Allied Reoccupation of the Andaman Islands, 1945 SE5226.jpg|thumb|Chinese and Malayan girls forcibly taken from Penang by the Japanese to work as 'comfort girls' for the troops.]]
Korean and Malay women were brought in to act as "[[comfort women]]" for the Japanese garrison. Forced labour was used to build a new airport, and in October 1942 mass arrests of 'spies' took place, with 300 people being confined in the Cellular Jail, where some were tortured. Of these seven were shot, including Narayan Rao, who had been Superintendent of Police under Japanese auspices, Itter Singh, the Deputy Superintendent, Subedar Sube Singh of the Military Police and Dr. Surinder Nag. Realising that the Japanese were targeting influential members of the population, the members of the Indian Independence League grew increasingly nervous, and ceased to engage in much nationalist activity.&lt;ref&gt;Dasgupta ''Red Sun over Black Water'' pp. 52–60&lt;/ref&gt; In 1943 a second reign of terror was unleashed by the new commander of the garrison, Colonel Jochi Renusakai, and chief of police Mitsubashi, both of whom had served at [[Rape of Nanking|Nanking]]. 600 people were arrested and tortured, including Dr. Diwan Singh, who died as a result of his injuries. At this stage, the Japanese decided that Bakshi was no longer useful, and he was imprisoned.&lt;ref&gt;Dasgupta ''Red Sun over Black Water'' pp. 63–67&lt;/ref&gt;

==The Provisional Government of Free India==
On December 29, 1943, political control of the islands was passed to the [[Azad Hind]] government of [[Subhas Chandra Bose]]. Bose visited [[Port Blair]] to raise the tricolour flag of the Indian National Army. During this, his only visit to the Andamans, he was kept carefully screened from the local population by the Japanese authorities. Various attempts were made to inform him of the sufferings of the people of the Andamans, and the fact that many local Indian Nationalists were at that time being tortured in the [[Cellular Jail]]. Bose does not seem to have been aware of this, and the judgment of some is that he "failed his people".&lt;ref&gt;Iqbal Singh ''The Andaman Story'' p. 249&lt;/ref&gt; After Bose's departure the Japanese remained in effective control of the Andamans, and the sovereignty of the Provisional Government of Free India was largely fictional.&lt;ref&gt;[[Christopher Bayly|C. A. Bayly]] &amp; T. Harper ''Forgotten Armies. The Fall of British Asia 1941–5'' (London) 2004 p. 325&lt;/ref&gt; The islands themselves were renamed "Shaheed" and "Swaraj", meaning "martyr" and "self-rule" respectively. Bose appointed General [[A. D. Loganathan]] as the governor of the islands, and had limited involvement with the administration of the territory. During his interrogation after the war Loganathan admitted that he had only had full control over the islands' vestigial education department, as the Japanese had retained control over the police force, and in protest he had refused to accept responsibility for any other areas of Government. He was powerless to prevent the worst Japanese atrocity of the occupation, the [[Homfreyganj massacre]] on 30 January 1944, where 44 Indian civilians were shot by the Japanese on suspicion of spying. Many of them were members of the [[Indian Independence League]].&lt;ref&gt;Dasgupta ''Red Sun over Black Water''  pp. 67, 87, 91–95; Mathur ''Kala Pani'' pp. 249–51&lt;/ref&gt; Notionally this government continued to administer the islands, which were almost the only territory it ever acquired, until the British retook them in 1945, but in practice little had changed.

==The last year==
[[File:The Allied Reoccupation of the Andaman Islands, 1945 SE5213.jpg|thumb|The first members of the Allied forces to land at Port Blair in the Andaman Islands are welcomed by the local population, 1945]]
As food became more scarce in 1945, the Japanese resorted to ever more desperate measures. Between 250 and 700 people (estimates vary) from the Aberdeen area of South Andaman were deported to an uninhabited island to grow food. According to a survivor, a released convict called Saudagar Ali, at least half drowned or were eaten by sharks as they were pushed out of boats in the dark, whilst the remainder either died of starvation or were killed by Burmese pirates. A rescue mission sent to the island after the end of the occupation found just twelve survivors and over a hundred skeletons on the beach.

In all, approximately 2,000 people in the Andamans are thought to have died as a result of the occupation, and at least 501 were tortured by the Japanese. The former figure represents 10% of the pre-war population of Port Blair. Casualties on the more sparsely-populated Nicobar islands were fewer, as the Japanese did not have a garrison there, although in 1943 they created a brief reign of terror on Car Nicobar as they rounded up forced labour amongst the Nicobarese. The occupation left a legacy of lasting bitterness towards the Japanese, and to some extent towards their collaborators in the Provisional Government of Free India, amongst the generation which experienced it.&lt;ref&gt;Dasgupta ''Red Sun over Black Water''  pp. 101, 131, 133; Mathur ''Kala Pani'' pp. 254–55&lt;/ref&gt;

Japanese Vice Admiral Teizo Hara, and Major-General Tamenori Sato surrendered the islands to Brigadier J.A. Salomons, commander of the [[116th Indian Infantry Brigade]], and Chief Administrator Mr. Noel K. Patterson, Indian Civil Service, on 7 October 1945, in a ceremony performed on the Gymkhana Ground, Port Blair.

==See also==
* [[Battle of the Malacca Strait]]
* [[Cocos Islands mutiny]]
* [[India in World War II]]

==Notes==
&lt;references /&gt;

==References==
*{{cite book
| last = Gill
| first = G. Hermon
| year = 1968
| url = http://www.awm.gov.au/histories/chapter.asp?volume=25
| title = Volume II – Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945
| series = [[Australia in the War of 1939–1945]]
| location = Canberra
| publisher = [[Australian War Memorial]]
| accessdate = 2006-11-20
}}
*{{cite web|first=Klemen |last=L |url=http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/index.html |title=Forgotten Campaign: The Dutch East Indies Campaign 1941-1942 |date=1999–2000 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20110726053035/http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/index.html |archivedate=2011-07-26 }}

==External links==
* [http://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?search=The+Allied+Reoccupation+of+the+Andaman+Islands&amp;title=Special%3ASearch&amp;go=Go Commons images of The Allied Reoccupation of the Andaman Islands]

{{Japanese occupations}}
{{Indian National Army}}
{{Indian independence movement}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Japanese Occupation Of The Andaman Islands}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:History of the Andaman and Nicobar Islands]]
[[Category:Military history of India during World War II|Andaman]]
[[Category:Indian independence movement|Andaman]]
[[Category:Azad Hind]]
[[Category:Military history of Japan during World War II|Andaman]]
[[Category:Japanese war crimes|Andaman]]
[[Category:Japanese military occupations|Andaman Islands]]
[[Category:World War II occupied territories]]
[[Category:India–Japan military relations]]
[[Category:Military history of the British Empire and Commonwealth in World War II]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations of World War II]]</text><sha1>f0aoiet483u09hunhfnprcxxrrghbyu</sha1></revision></page>