<page><title>Easter Sunday Raid</title><ns>0</ns><id>12737715</id><revision><id>958576298</id><parentid>956899596</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-24T15:39:00Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Redglblackeye</username><id>29768768</id></contributor><minor /><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="22813" xml:space="preserve">{{Use American English|date = February 2019}}
{{Short description|WWII battle in Ceylon between Britain and Japan}}
{{more citations needed|date=April 2015}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2020}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict          = Easter Sunday Raid on Ceylon
| partof            = the [[Pacific War|Pacific Theatre]] of [[World War II]]
| image             = [[File:Dorsetshire&amp;Cornwall.jpg|300px|center|British heavy cruisers {{HMS|Dorsetshire|40|6}} and {{HMS|Cornwall|56|2}} under Japanese air attack and heavily damaged, off Ceylon, on 5 April 1942]]
| caption           = British heavy cruisers {{HMS|Dorsetshire|40|6}} and {{HMS|Cornwall|56|2}} under Japanese air attack and heavily damaged off the southwest of Ceylon, on Easter Sunday, 5 April 1942
| date              = 5 April 1942
| place             = [[Indian Ocean]] and [[Ceylon]]
| result            = Japanese tactical victory
| combatant1        = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan}} [[Empire of Japan|Japan]]
| combatant2        = *{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[United Kingdom]]
**{{flagicon|Ceylon|colonial}} [[Ceylon]]
| casualties1       = 7 aircraft&lt;ref&gt;Dull, p.114&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2       = 27 aircraft &lt;br&gt;
Two heavy cruisers &lt;br&gt;
Many more killed on the ground.&lt;ref name="sundaytimes.lk"&gt;http://www.sundaytimes.lk/100411/Plus/plus_26.html . Retrieved 19 May 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;
| campaignbox       = {{Campaignbox Indian Ocean Theatre}}
}}

The '''Easter Sunday Raid''' (or '''Battle of Ceylon''') was an air attack by [[aircraft carrier|carrier]]-based aircraft of the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] against [[Colombo]], [[British Ceylon|Ceylon]] (now [[Sri Lanka]]), on [[Easter Sunday]], 5 April 1942, during the [[South-East Asian theatre of World War II|South-East Asian theatre]] of [[World War II]]. This attack was part of the [[Indian Ocean Raid]], and was followed a few days later by a similar attack on [[Trincomalee]]. The targets were [[United Kingdom|British]] warships, harbour installations, and air bases; the object was to disrupt the war effort of [[Commonwealth of Nations|British Commonwealth]] nations and force the [[British Eastern Fleet]] to leave [[Asia]]n waters.

==Background==
The British had been in occupation of the coastal areas of Ceylon since 1796, but the colony had not had a regular garrison of British troops since 1917. The [[Ceylon Defence Force]] and [[Sri Lanka Volunteer Naval Force|Ceylon Navy Volunteer Reserve]] were mobilized and expanded. The [[Royal Navy]] maintained naval installations in Trincomalee and the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) had established an aerodrome in [[China Bay Airport|China Bay]], Trincomalee, long before the war.

With [[Empire of Japan|Japan]]'s entry into the war, and especially after the [[fall of Singapore]], Ceylon became a front-line British base. The Royal Navy's [[East Indies Station]] was moved to Colombo and then to Trincomalee. [[Geoffrey Layton|Admiral Sir Geoffrey Layton]] was appointed commander-in-chief, Ceylon, with [[Air Vice Marshal]] [[John D'Albiac]] as air officer commanding and Admiral Sir [[James Somerville (admiral)|James Somerville]] appointed commander of the British Eastern Fleet.

The fixed land defences consisted of four [[coastal batteries]] at Colombo and five at Trincomalee; these were established just before the war. Air defences were expanded in 1941 with the RAF occupying the civil airfield at [[Ratmalana Airport|Ratmalana]] near Colombo with its station headquarters set up at [[Kandawala]]. Another airbase was rapidly built at [[Koggala airport|Koggala]] near [[Galle]] and several temporary airstrips were built across the country with the largest at [[Colombo Racecourse Airstrip|Colombo Racecourse]] grounds. Several RAF [[Squadron (aviation)|squadrons]] were sent to Ceylon. In March 1942 the 65th HAA Regiment of the Royal Artillery arrived in Ceylon and were stationed in Wellawata.

==The attack on Colombo==
Somerville retreated with the main body of the Eastern Fleet to [[Addu Atoll]] in the [[Maldives]]. He left at Ceylon the [[aircraft carrier]] {{HMS|Hermes|D95|6}} (under repair at Trincomalee), [[heavy cruiser]]s {{HMS|Cornwall|56|6}} and {{HMS|Dorsetshire|40|2}}, and the [[Royal Australian Navy]] destroyer {{HMAS|Vampire|D68|6}}.

After the [[sinking of Prince of Wales and Repulse|sinking of ''Prince of Wales'' and ''Repulse'']] and the [[fall of Singapore]], British morale on the island dropped. The sinking of these two capital ships shocked much of the world; the awareness of the vulnerability of battleships to air power increased dramatically. On Ceylon, there was much anxiety that a Japanese attack appeared to be inevitable. A large [[sea turtle]] which came ashore was reported by an Australian unit as a number of Japanese [[amphibious vehicle]]s. However, actual preparations for defence were lackadaisical, apart from the deployment of an RAF squadron at the Colombo Racecourse. Anti-British sentiment increased within some portions of the indigenous population and their hopes ran high for liberation by the Japanese.{{Citation needed|date=April 2015}}
[[File:Leonard birchall.jpg|thumb|left|[[Leonard Birchall]] spotted the [[Japanese Imperial Navy]] approaching Ceylon and radioed the strength and the position of the Japanese fleet before his [[PBY Catalina]] was shot down by Zero fighter aircraft.]]

The Japanese fleet comprised five aircraft carriers plus supporting ships under the command of Admiral [[Chuichi Nagumo]].&lt;ref name="Klemen"&gt;{{cite web |last = Klemen |first = L |url = http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/nagumo.html |title = Vice-Admiral Chuichi Nagumo |work = Forgotten Campaign: The Dutch East Indies Campaign 1941–1942 |access-date = 3 June 2011 |archive-url = https://web.archive.org/web/20120630044158/http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/nagumo.html |archive-date = 30 June 2012 |url-status = dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 April 1942, the Japanese fleet was located by a [[PBY Catalina]] aircraft flown by [[Royal Canadian Air Force|RCAF]] Squadron Leader [[Leonard Birchall]], out of Koggala. Birchall's Catalina was shot down by six [[Mitsubishi A6M Zero|A6M2 Zero]] fighters from the carrier {{Ship|Japanese aircraft carrier|Hiryū||2}}. He managed to radio in the position of the Japanese fleet and alert Colombo about the impending attack.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lankalibrary.com/geo/30-squadron.htm The Battle of Ceylon – 1942/WW II Japanese air raid on Colombo]&lt;/ref&gt; However, Nagumo's air strike on Colombo the next day achieved near-complete surprise ([[Pearl Harbor]] also was attacked on a weekend). The British [[radar]]s were not operating, they were shut down for routine maintenance.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

The Japanese high command had planned the bombing of Colombo very much like the Pearl Harbor operation (many of the same planes and pilots participated in both strikes); but most of the British Eastern Fleet was at [[Addu Atoll]], so when the Japanese attacked at Colombo there were only three ships there. The survival of the British Eastern Fleet (which included some [[Royal Netherlands Navy]] warships) prevented the Japanese from attempting a major troop landing in Ceylon.{{Citation needed|date=June 2011}}

[[File:HMS Cornwall - 1942 - WWII.jpg|300px|thumb|{{HMS|Cornwall|56|6}}, burning and sinking following Japanese dive bomber attacks, in the Indian Ocean, 5 April 1942]]

The first attack wave of Japanese planes took off in pre-dawn darkness (30 minutes before sunrise) from the aircraft carriers [[Japanese aircraft carrier Akagi|''Akagi'']], [[Japanese aircraft carrier Hiryū|''Hiryu'']], and [[Japanese aircraft carrier Sōryū|''Soryu'']], moving about 200 miles south of Sri Lanka. The first attack wave of 36 fighters, 54 dive bombers, and 90 level bombers was led by Captain [[Mitsuo Fuchida]], the same officer who led the air attack on Pearl Harbor.

The [[Hawker Hurricane]]s of the RAF's [[No. 30 Squadron RAF|No. 30 Squadron]] were on the ground at Ratmalana Airport when the Japanese aircraft passed overhead. The [[auxiliary cruiser]] {{HMS|Hector|F45|6}} and the old destroyer {{HMS|Tenedos|H04|6}} were sunk in the harbour. The RAF and the [[Fleet Air Arm]] (FAA) lost at least 27 aircraft; the Japanese only five. The Japanese also bombed the mental asylum at Angoda, mistaking it for the fuel tanks at nearby [[Kolonnawa]].

After Fuchida and his aircrews returned to the flagship ''Akagi'', a second-wave of 53 [[Aichi D3A]] ''Val'' dive bombers led by Lieutenant Commander Egusa took off to attack the two British cruisers ''Dorsetshire'' and ''Cornwall'', {{convert|320|km|nmi mi|abbr=on}} southwest of Ceylon, and sank the two ships. British losses were 424 men killed; 1,120 survivors spent hours in the water.

The Japanese dive bombers scored hits with close to 90% of their bombs—an enviable rate of accuracy, according to Mitsuo Fuchida in ''Midway: The Battle That Doomed Japan''.&lt;ref name="asiantribune.com"&gt;[http://www.asiantribune.com/node/5216 Air raid 1942: No one was asked to resign]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:RAF Hurricane.jpg|thumb|left|RAF [[Hawker Hurricane]]s were scrambled from the temporary airstrip at the Colombo Racecourse. The Hurricanes were involved in several dogfights with the [[Imperial Japanese Navy Air Service]] Zero fighters and bombers which were attacking the city]]

The Japanese attack began at 07:30 on Easter Sunday morning. Air defence of [[Colombo fort]] and harbour was provided by the 3rd Searchlight/Light Anti-Aircraft Regiment, [[Ceylon Garrison Artillery]] with two batteries based at [[Galle Face Green]] and [[Mutwal]]. Colonel R. M. White and his operations staff officer, Major J. O. Widdows, [[Distinguished Service Order|DSO]] commanded ground units from ground forces headquarters at [[Echelon Barracks]].

[[St Luke's Church, Borella]], was packed for Easter services with both locals and military personnel. According to parishioners, the vicar, Reverend Canon [[Ivan Corea]], was preaching when the RAF Hurricanes engaged the Japanese Zero aircraft high above the church.&lt;ref&gt;[http://vernoncorea.wordpress.com/2006/08/28/vernon-coreas-ceylon/ Vernon Corea's Ceylon – reference to Japanese raid over St Luke's Church Borella]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Sri Lankan writer Ariyadasa Ratnasinghe recalled the Easter Sunday Japanese raid: "Japanese aircraft flew in close formation over Colombo and dropped bombs at different places. The air battle lasted for nearly half an hour. The Allied forces, warned of the danger, were able to shoot down some of the enemy aircraft which fell on land and sea."

Among those shot down, one fell near [[S. Thomas' College, Mount Lavinia|Saint Thomas' College]], one closer to the Bellanwila paddy fields, one near Pita Kotte, one on the racecourse in Colombo, one near Horana and one on the Galle Face Green. A bomb fell off the target and damaged the Mulleriyawa Mental Hospital, killing some inmates. It appeared that the pilot had mistaken the buildings for the Echelon Barracks. One fell near the [[Maradana railway station]], partly damaging it. There were many deaths and more casualties, most of them civilians. To prevent bombs falling on hospitals, it was decided to have a large red cross painted on the roofs.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lankalibrary.com/geo/japan4.htm First Japanese air raid on Colombo]&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Zero Akagi Dec1941.jpg|thumb|Admiral Nagumo's fleet unleashed the [[Mitsubishi A6M Zero]] fighters and bombers on the attack on Colombo on 5 April 1942.]]

In the late afternoon on 5 April 1942, just before sunset, at 16:55 and again at 18:00, two [[Royal Navy|RN]] [[Fairey Albacore]]s operating from the RN [[Fleet Air Arm#Fleet Air Arm|aircraft carriers]] [[HMS Formidable (67)|''Formidable'']] and [[HMS Indomitable (92)|''Indomitable'']] made contact with the IJN carriers. One Albacore was shot down and the other damaged before an accurate sighting report could be made, frustrating [[Admiral Somerville]]'s plans for a retaliatory night strike by his [[List of World War II British naval radar#ASV II|ASV radar]]-equipped Albacore strike bombers. Somerville continued to probe for the IJN carriers on the night of 5 April 1942, but they failed to find the IJN ships, and the RN's only opportunity to launch a strike against enemy aircraft carriers faded away.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naval-history.net/xDKWD-EF1942-Introduction.htm ''REPORT OF PROCEEDINGS (ROP) OF EASTERN FLEET – 1942'']&lt;/ref&gt;

H. G. P. Jayasekera, president of the Ceylon War Veterans Association of World War II, wrote: "The April raids in Colombo were led by Vice Admiral Chuichi Nagumo and Commander Mitsuo Fuchida, the two men who inflicted the biggest damage on the mighty American Pacific Fleet. The Ceylon R.A.F. had only 20 planes as against that of 120 planes of Mitsuo Fuchida. These 20 fighter planes got off from the Racecourse grounds and there was an air battle over Colombo on Easter Sunday morning (5 April). Ceylon Garrison Artillery and Boys of Royal Artillery managed to shoot down many of the Japanese planes."&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.lankalibrary.com/geo/japan5.htm How tiny Ceylon became a target]&lt;/ref&gt;

The Ceylon ''Daily News'' reported the raid on Monday, 6 April 1942: "Colombo and the suburbs were attacked yesterday at 8 o'clock in the morning by 75 enemy aircraft which came in waves from the sea. Twenty-five of the raiders were shot down, while 25 more were damaged. Dive-bombing and low-flying machine-gun attacks were made in the Harbour and Ratmalana areas. A medical establishment in the suburbs was also bombed."&lt;ref name="asiantribune.com"/&gt;

==The attack on Trincomalee Harbour==
[[File:HermesSinking302403.jpg|thumb|The light aircraft carrier HMS ''Hermes'' was sunk off Batticaloa by Japanese dive bombers on 9 April 1942]]
On 9 April, the Japanese attacked the harbour at Trincomalee and the British ships off [[Batticaloa]]. The light aircraft carrier {{HMS|Hermes|D95|6}}, the destroyer {{HMAS|Vampire|D68|6}} and the [[Flower-class]] [[corvette]] {{HMS|Hollyhock|K64|6}} were sunk, and [[SS Sagaing|SS ''Sagaing'']] partially destroyed and set on fire below decks.&lt;ref name="rogersAU"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Rogers|first1=James|title=Huge World War II shipwreck raised from the depths in massive salvage operation|url=http://www.news.com.au/technology/science/archaeology/huge-world-war-ii-shipwreck-raised-from-the-depths-in-massive-salvage-operation/news-story/66d058084186e582172b77f32d517bf9|accessdate=7 April 2018|agency=news.com.au|publisher=news.com.au|date=3 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The RAF lost at least eight Hurricanes and the FAA one [[Fairey Fulmar]]. The Japanese lost five bombers and six fighters, one in a suicide attack on the Trincomalee fuel tanks. Seven hundred people lost their lives in the attack on Trincomalee. According to eye witness Michael Tomlinson (author of ''The Most Dangerous Moment'' and RAF Station Intelligence Officer at Ratmalana and later at China Bay in Trincomalee), one Japanese pilot deliberately crashed his plane into one of the giant fuel tanks just north of China Bay aerodrome. Inside the aircraft were three Japanese—Shigenori Watanabe, Tokya Goto, and Sutomu Toshira. After carefully circling the area, they plunged unerringly into the tank, igniting their own funeral pyre. The resulting fire lasted seven days. Parts of the aircraft's engine and the flattened remains of the fuel storage tank have been placed in a barbed wire enclosure 1½ km from the turn off at the 4th mile post on the Trincomalee–Habarana Road.&lt;ref name="asiantribune.com"/&gt;

HMS ''Hermes'' was undergoing repairs in Trincomalee harbour in April 1942. As a result of the advance warning of the impending attack by the Japanese, ''Hermes'' left Trincomalee, minus the 12 [[Fairey Swordfish]] Mk Is of 814 Naval Air Squadron that had been disembarked in Ceylon.

A Japanese reconnaissance plane from the battleship {{ship|Japanese battleship|Haruna||2}} spotted ''Hermes'' at 8:55&amp;nbsp;a.m. as the ships had turned northward to return to Trincomalee.{{sfn|Gill|1968|p=20}} Though the Japanese sighting report had been intercepted and orders issued to try to protect ''Hermes'', communications breakdowns delayed action.{{sfn|Gill|1968|p=21}} At 9:45&amp;nbsp;a.m. the Japanese carriers launched 85 bombers and 9 fighters which found ''Hermes'', ''Vampire'' and the just joined hospital ship ''Vita'', which had been heading south, off [[Batticaloa]] light.{{sfn|Gill|1968|p=21}} Japanese bombers attacked ''Hermes'' in waves beginning at 10:35&amp;nbsp;a.m. Within ten minutes ''Hermes'' had taken forty direct hits and capsized.{{sfn|Gill|1968|p=21}} ''Vampire'' was next with a direct hit in the boiler room stopping the ship, after which four more hits resulted in an order to abandon ship.{{sfn|Gill|1968|p=21}} ''Vita'' rescued survivors of both ships. The carrier sank with the loss of 308 lives.{{sfn|Gill|1968|p=21}}&lt;ref name="sundaytimes.lk"&gt;http://www.sundaytimes.lk/100411/Plus/plus_26.html . Retrieved 19 May 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Churchill quote on the Battle of Ceylon===
[[Prime Minister]] [[Winston Churchill]] said:

&lt;blockquote&gt;''The most dangerous moment of the War, and the one which caused me the greatest alarm, was when the Japanese Fleet was heading for Ceylon and the naval base there. The capture of Ceylon, the consequent control of the Indian Ocean, and the possibility at the same time of a German conquest of Egypt would have closed the ring and the future would have been black.''
:— From a conversation at the British Embassy, Washington, D.C.&lt;ref&gt;Birchall, Leonard, RCAF (2004). ''Battle for the Skies''. Michael Paterson, David &amp; Charles. IBN 0-7153-1815-2.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==British Commonwealth units in Ceylon at the time of the attack==

===Ground===

====Ceylonese units====
* [[Ceylon Defence Force]]
** [[Ceylon Garrison Artillery]] (CGA) (equipped with {{convert|6|in|mm|abbr=on}} and {{convert|9.2|in|mm|abbr=on}} guns)
** [[Ceylon Light Infantry]] (CLI)
** [[Ceylon Planters Rifle Corps]] (CPRC)
** [[Colombo Town Guard]]

====Commonwealth units====
* 65th Heavy Anti-Aircraft [HAA] Regiment, Royal Artillery.
* [[Indian 34th Infantry Division|34th Indian Division]].
* [[16th Brigade (Australia)|Australian 16th Brigade]] (of the [[7th Division (Australia)|6th Australian Division]]).
* [[17th Brigade (Australia)|Australian 17th Brigade]] (of the 6th Australian Division).
* [[King's African Rifles|24th East African Brigade]].

===Air===

====[[Royal Air Force]]====
* [[No. 222 Group RAF]]
** [[No. 11 Squadron RAF]] ([[Bristol Blenheim]]s) (Colombo Racecourse)
** [[No. 30 Squadron RAF]] ([[Hawker Hurricane]]s) (RAF Ratmalana, Colombo)
** [[No. 258 Squadron RAF]] (Hawker Hurricanes) (Colombo Racecourse)
** [[No. 261 Squadron RAF]] (Hawker Hurricanes) (China Bay, Trincomalee)
** [[No. 273 Squadron RAF]] ([[Fairey Fulmar]]s) (China Bay)
** [[No. 202 Squadron RAF]] ([[PBY Catalina]] one aircraft)
** [[No. 204 Squadron RAF]] (PBY Catalinas)
** [[No. 205 Squadron RAF]] (one PBY Catalina aircraft)
** [[No. 321 Squadron RAF]] (PBY Catalinas) ([[Netherlands|Dutch]] unit under formation at China Bay)
** [[No. 413 Squadron RCAF]] (PBY Catalinas)

====[[Fleet Air Arm]]====
* [[788 Naval Air Squadron]] ([[Fairey Swordfish]])
* [[803 Naval Air Squadron]] ([[Fairey Fulmar]]s)
* [[806 Naval Air Squadron]] (Fairey Fulmars)

==See also==
* [[Ceylon in World War II]]
* [[Sri Lanka Army]]
* [[Sri Lanka Navy]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

===Books===
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Brown|first=David|year=1990|title=Warship Losses of World War Two| publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=1-55750-914-X}}
* {{cite book|last=Dull|first=Paul S.|year=1978|title=A Battle History of the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1941–1945|publisher=Naval Institute Press|isbn=0-87021-097-1|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/battlehistoryofi0000dull}}
* {{cite book |last=Gill |first=G. Hermon |title=Royal Australian Navy 1939-1942 |series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 2 – Navy |volume=2 |year=1968 |publisher=Australian War Memorial |location=Canberra |lccn=76454854 |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/histories/second_world_war/volume.asp?levelID=67911 |accessdate=11 May 2015 |ref=harv |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20130927112028/http://www.awm.gov.au/histories/second_world_war/volume.asp?levelID=67911 |archivedate=27 September 2013}}
* Tomlinson, Michael ''The Most Dangerous Moment: The Japanese Assault on Ceylon 1942'', London: William Kimber &amp; Co Ltd, 1976, {{ISBN|955-564-000-9}}.
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Sister project links}}
* [http://www.bbc.co.uk/ww2peopleswar/stories/38/a4428038.shtml 1941–1945 Eastern Travels Part 4 by cjcallis]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100722085023/http://worldwar2database.com/html/india42.htm The Raids on Ceylon April 1942]
* [http://www.lankalibrary.com/geo/30-squadron.htm The Battle of Ceylon – 1942]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9H2WlD0oTCk A short film on YouTube on the Easter Sunday Raid: The Battle of Ceylon Prelude]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=K3ngDoueaDc A Film Clip on YouTube 'The Saviour of Ceylon' – The Story of Leonard Birchall]
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FzpMCtgGQ60&amp;feature=watch_response A Film on YouTube on the 'Battle of Ceylon – based on a True Story]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20100723201731/http://www.merchant-navy-ships.com/index.php?id=80,0,0,1,0,0 The Battle of Ceylon 1942]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20161117054735/http://www.fleetairarmarchive.net/ships/Hermes.html HMS Hermes I Fleet Aircraft Carrier]
* [http://www.sundaytimes.lk/100411/Plus/plus_26.html Ceylon's Pearl Harbour Attack]
* [http://www.journal.forces.gc.ca/vo7/no4/stuart-eng.asp Leonard Birchall And The Japanese Raid On Colombo]
* [http://www.asiantribune.com/node/5216 Air raid 1942: No one was asked to resign]
* [http://www.serendipity365.com/uploads/Target_Ceylon_1942__Sep_08_.pdf Island at War – Target Ceylon 1942]
* [http://rcaf.com/Gallery/galleryDetail.php?No.-413-Tusker-Squadron-13 Photographs of Ceylon during World War II from Leonard Birchall's 413 Tusker Squadron in 1942]

{{WWIIHistory}}

{{coord missing|Sri Lanka}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:1942 in Ceylon]]
[[Category:South-East Asian theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Military of British Ceylon]]
[[Category:Military history of Japan during World War II]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Canada]]
[[Category:Aerial bombing in Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles involving Sri Lanka]]
[[Category:Military history of Ceylon in World War II]]
[[Category:April 1942 events]]</text><sha1>dq9k44cn6cr1vvinj5k0n8enh5v1emj</sha1></revision></page>