<page><title>Battle of Madagascar</title><ns>0</ns><id>1622242</id><revision><id>965880319</id><parentid>964876907</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-03T23:40:33Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Bonthefox3</username><id>35810938</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="42798" xml:space="preserve">{{for|the 1811 naval battle of Madagascar|Battle of Tamatave}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2017}}
{{Use British English|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Madagascar
| partof      = the [[Indian Ocean in World War II|Indian Ocean theatre]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = Madagascar KAR 1942.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = [[King's African Rifles]]' [[Ordnance QF 25-pounder|25 pdr]] battery in action near [[Ambositra]] in Madagascar against Vichy positions during Operation Steam Line Jane, September 1942.
| date        = {{start and end dates|1942|05|05|1942|11|06|df=y}}
| place       = [[Madagascar]], [[Indian Ocean]]
|coordinates= {{coord|12|16|S|49|17|E|display=inline}}
|map_type=Madagascar
|map_size=100
|map_caption=Location of [[Antsiranana Bay|Diego-Suarez Bay]]
| casus       = Risk of Japanese submarine base threatening supply routes
| territory   = [[Free France|Free French]] administration established in [[French Madagascar|Madagascar]]
| result      = Allied victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
* {{flag|British Raj|name=India}}
* {{nowrap|{{flag|Northern Rhodesia}}}}
* {{nowrap|{{flag|Southern Rhodesia}}}}
* {{flagicon image|Flag of Tanganyika (1923–1961).svg}} [[Tanganyika Territory|Tanganyika]]
{{flag|Union of South Africa|name=South Africa}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Australia}} &lt;small&gt;(naval)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{{flagdeco|Netherlands}} [[Dutch government-in-exile|Netherlands]] &lt;small&gt;(naval)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;{{flagdeco|Poland|1928}} [[Polish government-in-exile|Poland]] &lt;small&gt;(naval)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
| combatant2  = {{flag|Vichy France|name=France}}
* {{flagdeco|Vichy France}} [[French Madagascar|Madagascar]]
&lt;hr&gt;{{flag|Empire of Japan|name=Japan}} &lt;small&gt;(naval)&lt;/small&gt;
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Robert Sturges]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Edward Neville Syfret|Edward Syfret]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Vichy France}} [[Armand Annet]]&lt;hr&gt;{{flagicon|Empire of Japan|naval}} [[Ishizaki Noboru]]
| strength1   = 10,000–15,000 soldiers&lt;br&gt;6 infantry tanks&lt;br&gt;6 light tanks&lt;br&gt;2 aircraft carriers&lt;br&gt;1 seaplane carrier&lt;br&gt;2 battleships&lt;br&gt;6 light cruisers&lt;br&gt;22 destroyers&lt;br&gt;8 corvettes&lt;br&gt;1 monitor&lt;br&gt;1 minelayer&lt;br&gt;4 minesweepers&lt;br&gt;5 assault transports
| strength2   = '''Vichy France''':&lt;br&gt;8,000 soldiers&lt;ref name="Rigge103"&gt;Rigge pp 103-04&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;6 tanks&lt;br&gt;35 aircraft{{sfn|Wessels|1996}}&lt;br&gt;4 warships&lt;ref&gt;Stapleton, Timothy J.  [https://books.google.com/books?id=XvtDAgAAQBAJ&amp;dq=&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s A Military History of Africa] p. 225&lt;/ref&gt; &lt;br&gt;'''Japanese Navy'''&lt;br&gt;2 soldiers &lt;br&gt;4 submarines &lt;br&gt;2 midget submarines
| casualties1 = 107 killed&lt;br&gt;280 wounded&lt;br&gt;108 died from disease{{sfn|Wessels|1996}}&lt;br&gt;1 battleship heavily damaged&lt;br&gt;1 oil tanker sunk
'''Total''':&lt;br&gt;620
| casualties2 = 152 killed&lt;br&gt;500 wounded&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(does not include any casualties caused by disease)&lt;/small&gt;{{sfn|Wessels|1996}}&lt;br&gt;1,000 captured&lt;ref&gt;{{cite hansard |url=http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1942/nov/10/madagascar-operations#column_2259 |house=House of Commons |date=10 November 1942 |title=MADAGASCAR (OPERATIONS) HC Deb 10 November 1942 vol 383 cc2259-60|speaker=Winston Churchill |position=Prime Minister |url-status=live |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140522085121/http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1942/nov/10/madagascar-operations#column_2259 |archivedate=22 May 2014 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;1 midget submarine destroyed&lt;br&gt;1 midget submarine lost at sea
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Indian Ocean Theatre}}
{{Campaignbox Vichy France Military in World War II}}
}}

The '''Battle of Madagascar''' was the [[British Empire|British]] campaign to capture the [[Vichy France|Vichy French]]-controlled island [[French Madagascar|Madagascar]] during [[World War II]]. The seizure of the island by the British was to deny Madagascar's ports to the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] and to prevent the loss or impairment of the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] shipping routes to India, Australia and Southeast Asia. It began with '''Operation Ironclad''', the seizure of the port of [[Antsiranana|Diego-Suarez]] (now Antsiranana) near the northern tip of the island, on 5 May 1942.&lt;ref name="Rigge103"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Grehan (2013), p. 18&lt;/ref&gt;

A subsequent campaign to secure the entire island, '''Operation Stream Line Jane''', was opened on 10 September. The Allies broke into the interior linking up with forces on the coast and secured the island by the end of October. Fighting ceased and an armistice was granted on 6 November.{{sfn|Thomas|1996}} This was the first large-scale operation by the Allies of World War II [[Combined arms|combining]] sea, land and air forces.&lt;ref name="Rigge100"&gt;Rigge p. 100&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Grehan (2013), Ch. 9&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==

===Geopolitical===
[[Antsiranana Bay|Diego-Suarez]] is a large bay with a fine harbour near the northern tip of the island of Madagascar and has an opening to the east through a narrow channel called Oronjia Pass. The naval base of Diego-Suarez lies on a peninsula between two of the four small bays enclosed within Diego-Suarez Bay. Diego-Suarez Bay cuts deeply into the northern tip of Madagascar (Cape Amber), almost severing it from the rest of the island.{{sfn|Turner|Gordon-Cummings|Betzler|1961}}{{RP|133}} In the 1880s, the bay was coveted by France, which claimed it as a [[coaling station]] for steamships travelling to French possessions farther east. The colonization was formalized after the first [[Franco-Hova Wars|Franco-Hova War]] when Queen [[Ranavalona III of Madagascar|Ranavalona III]] signed a treaty on 17 December 1885 giving France a [[protectorate]] over the bay and surrounding territory, as well as the islands of [[Nosy Be]] and [[Ste. Marie de Madagascar|St. Marie de Madagascar]]. The colony's administration was subsumed into that of [[French Madagascar]] in 1897.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | title = History of Madagascar | publisher = History World | url = http://www.historyworld.net/wrldhis/PlainTextHistories.asp?historyid=ad26 | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20101023170532/http://historyworld.net/wrldhis/PlainTextHistories.asp?historyid=ad26 | accessdate = 30 October 2013 | archivedate = 23 October 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

In 1941, Diego-Suarez town, the bay and the channel were well protected by naval [[Coastal artillery|shore batteries]].{{sfn|Turner|Gordon-Cummings|Betzler|1961}}{{RP|133}}

===Axis===
Following the Japanese [[Dutch East Indies campaign|conquest]] of [[Southeast Asia]] east of [[Burma]] by the end of February 1942, [[submarine]]s of the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] were moving freely throughout the north and eastern expanses of the [[Indian Ocean]]. In March 1942, Japanese [[aircraft carrier]]s conducted the [[Indian Ocean raid]] upon shipping in the [[Bay of Bengal]] and bases in [[Colombo]] and [[Trincomalee]] in [[Ceylon]] (now [[Sri Lanka]]). This raid drove the [[British Eastern Fleet]] out of the area and they were forced to relocate to a new base at [[Kilindini]], near [[Mombasa]], in [[Kenya Colony|Kenya]].

The move made the British fleet more vulnerable to attack. The possibility of Japanese naval forces using forward bases in Madagascar had to be addressed. The potential use of these facilities particularly threatened [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] merchant shipping, the supply route to the [[British Eighth Army]] and also the Eastern Fleet.

Japanese submarines had the longest range of any [[Axis powers|Axis]] forces' subs at the time – more than {{convert|10000|mi|km}} in some cases,{{citation needed|date=April 2016}} but being challenged by the [[United States Navy]]'s then-relatively new {{sclass-|Gato|submarine|0}} [[fleet submarine]]s' {{convert|11,000|nmi|lk=in|km}} top range figures. If the Imperial Japanese Navy's submarines were able to utilise bases on Madagascar, Allied [[Line of communication|lines of communication]] would be affected across a region stretching from the [[Pacific]] and [[Australia]], to the [[Middle East]] and as far as the [[South Atlantic]].

On 17 December 1941, [[Kurt Fricke|Vice Admiral Fricke]], Chief of Staff of Germany's [[Seekriegsleitung|Maritime Warfare Command]] (''Seekriegsleitung''), met [[Naokuni Nomura|Vice Admiral Naokuni Nomura]], the Japanese Naval Attaché, in [[Berlin]] to discuss the delimitation of respective operational areas between the German ''[[Kriegsmarine]]'' and Imperial Japanese Navy forces. At another meeting on 27 March 1942, Fricke stressed the importance of the Indian Ocean to the Axis powers and expressed the desire that the Japanese begin operations against the northern Indian Ocean sea routes. Fricke further emphasized that [[British Ceylon|Ceylon]], the [[Seychelles]], and Madagascar should have a higher priority for the Axis navies than operations against [[Australia]].{{sfn|Turner|Gordon-Cummings|Betzler|1961}}{{RP|116}} By 8 April, the Japanese announced to Fricke that they intended to commit four or five submarines and two [[auxiliary cruiser]]s for operations in the western Indian Ocean between [[Aden]] and the [[Cape of Good Hope]], but they refused to disclose their plans for operations against Madagascar and Ceylon, only reiterating their commitment to operations in the area.{{sfn|Turner|Gordon-Cummings|Betzler|1961}}{{RP|117}}
&lt;!-- *** TO DO TEXT ***
''Add:''
* ''synopsis of Battle of France''
* ''Fall of France, creation of Vichy and Free French forces''
* ''Which colonies sided with which?''
---&gt;

===Allies===
The Allies had heard the rumours of Japanese plans for the Indian Ocean and on 27 November 1941, the British Chiefs of Staff discussed the possibility that the [[Vichy France|Vichy government]] might cede the whole of Madagascar to Japan, or alternatively permit the Japanese Navy to establish bases on the island. British naval advisors urged the occupation of the island as a precautionary measure.{{sfn |Turner|Gordon-Cummings|Betzler|1961}}{{RP|131}} On 16 December, General [[Charles de Gaulle]], leader of the [[Free France|Free French]] in London, sent a letter to the British Prime Minister, [[Winston Churchill]], in which he also urged a Free French operation against Madagascar.{{sfn |Churchill |1950}}{{RP|223}} Churchill recognised the risk of a Japanese-controlled Madagascar to Indian Ocean shipping, particularly to the important sea route to [[British Raj|India]] and [[British Ceylon|Ceylon]], and considered the port of [[Diego-Suarez]] as the strategic key to Japanese influence in the Indian Ocean. However, he also made it clear to planners that he did not feel Britain had the resources to mount such an operation and, following experience in the [[Battle of Dakar]] in September 1940, did not want a joint operation launched by British and Free French forces to secure the island.{{sfn |Churchill |1950}}{{RP|223}}
&lt;!--- ***TO DO TEXT ***
Add:
* Anglo-Free French relations. De Gaulle and Churchill, destruction of French Fleet at Mers-El-Kebir,
* [[Battle of Dakar]]
---&gt;

By 12 March 1942, Churchill had been convinced of the importance of such an operation and the decision was reached that the planning of the invasion of Madagascar would begin in earnest. It was agreed that the Free French would be explicitly excluded from the operation. As a preliminary battle outline, Churchill gave the following guidelines to the planners{{sfn|Churchill|1950}}{{RP|225}} and the operation was designated [[Operation Bonus]]:{{sfn|Churchill|1950}}{{RP|225}}
* [[Force H]], the ships guarding the Western Mediterranean, should move south from Gibraltar and should be replaced by an American Task Force
* The 4,000 men and ships proposed by [[Louis Mountbatten, 1st Earl Mountbatten of Burma|Lord Mountbatten]] for the operation, should be retained as the nucleus around which the plan should be built
* The operation should commence around 30 April 1942
* In the event of success, the [[British Commandos|commandos]] recommended by Mountbatten should be replaced by garrison troops as soon as possible{{sfn|Churchill|1950}}{{RP|225}}

On 14 March, Force 121 was constituted under the command of Major-General [[Robert Sturges]] of the [[Royal Marines]] with Rear-Admiral [[Edward Neville Syfret|Edward Syfret]] being placed in command of naval Force H and the supporting sea force.{{sfn|Turner|Gordon-Cummings|Betzler|1961}}{{RP|132}}
&lt;!--- *** TO DO TEXT ***
==Deployment==
===Axis dispositions===
''To be added''
---&gt;

===Allied preparations===
[[File:Battle of Madagaskar.jpg|thumb|Map of the assault]]
Force 121 left the [[River Clyde|Clyde]] in Scotland on 23 March and joined with South African-born Syfret's ships at [[Freetown]] in Sierra Leone, proceeding from there in two convoys to their assembly point at [[Durban]] on the South African east coast. Here they were joined by the 13th Brigade Group of the 5th Division – General Sturges' force consisting of three infantry brigades, while Syfret's squadron consisted of the flag [[battleship]] {{HMS|Ramillies|07|6}}, the aircraft carriers {{HMS|Illustrious|87|6}} and {{HMS|Indomitable|92|6}}, the [[cruiser]]s {{HMS|Hermione|74|6}} and {{HMS|Devonshire|39|6}}, eleven [[destroyer]]s, six [[minesweeper]]s, six [[corvette]]s and auxiliaries. It was a formidable force to bring against the 8,000 men (mostly [[Malagasy people|Malagasy]]) at Diego-Suarez, but the chiefs of staff were adamant that the operation was to succeed, preferably without any fighting.{{sfn|Turner|Gordon-Cummings|Betzler|1961}}{{RP|132}}

This was to be the first British [[amphibious assault]] since the disastrous landings in the [[Gallipoli Campaign|Dardanelles]] twenty-seven years before.{{sfn|Churchill|1950}}{{RP|230}}

During the assembly in Durban, Field-Marshal [[Jan Smuts]] pointed out that the mere seizure of Diego-Suarez would be no guarantee against continuing Japanese aggression and urged that the ports of [[Majunga]] and [[Tamatave]] be occupied as well. This was evaluated by the chiefs of staff, but it was decided to retain Diego-Suarez as the only objective due to the lack of manpower.{{sfn|Turner|Gordon-Cummings|Betzler|1961}}{{RP|132}} Churchill remarked that the only way to permanently secure Madagascar was by means of a strong fleet and adequate air support operating from Ceylon and sent General [[Archibald Wavell]] (India Command) a note stating that as soon as the initial objectives had been met, all responsibility for safeguarding Madagascar would be passed on to Wavell. He added that when the commandos were withdrawn, garrison duties would be performed by two African brigades and one brigade from the Belgian Congo or west coast of Africa.{{sfn|Churchill|1950}}{{RP|231}}

In March and April, the [[South African Air Force]] (SAAF) had conducted reconnaissance flights over Diego-Suarez and No. 32, 36 and 37 Coastal Flights were withdrawn from maritime patrol operations and sent to [[Lindi]] on the Indian Ocean coast of [[Tanganyika Territory|Tanganyika]], with an additional eleven [[Bristol Beaufort]]s and six [[Martin Maryland]]s to provide close air support during the planned operations.{{sfn|Turner|Gordon-Cummings|Betzler|1961}}{{RP|133}}

==Campaign==
Allied commanders decided to launch an [[amphibious assault]] on Madagascar. The task was Operation Ironclad and executed by Force 121. It would include Allied naval, land and air forces and be commanded by Major-General Robert Sturges of the Royal Marines. The [[British Army]] landing force included the [[British 29th Infantry Brigade|29th Independent Infantry Brigade Group]], [[No. 5 Commando|No 5 (Army) Commando]], and two brigades of the [[British 5th Infantry Division|5th Infantry Division]], the latter en route to India with the remainder of their division. The Allied naval contingent consisted of over 50 vessels, drawn from Force H, the [[British Home Fleet]] and the British [[Eastern Fleet]], commanded by Syfret. The fleet included the aircraft carrier ''Illustrious'', her [[sister ship]] ''Indomitable'' and the ageing battleship ''Ramillies'' to cover the landings.
[[File:Débarquement à Tamatave.jpg|thumb|Allied soldiers landing from [[Landing Craft Assault|LCAs]] at [[Tamatave]] in May 1942]]

===Landings (Operation Ironclad)===
Following many reconnaissance missions by the SAAF, the first wave of the British 29th Infantry Brigade and No. 5 Commando landed in [[Landing Craft Assault|assault craft]] on 5 May 1942. Follow-up waves were by two brigades of the 5th Infantry Division and Royal Marines. All were carried ashore by [[landing craft]] to Courrier Bay and Ambararata Bay, just west of the major port of Diego-Suarez, at the northern tip of Madagascar. A diversionary attack was staged to the east. Air cover was provided mainly by [[Fairey Albacore]] and [[Fairey Swordfish]] [[torpedo bomber]]s which attacked Vichy shipping. They were supported by [[Grumman F4F Wildcat|Grumman Martlets]]  fighters from the [[Fleet Air Arm]]. A small number of SAAF planes assisted.

The defending Vichy forces, led by [[Governor General]] [[Armand Léon Annet]], included about 8,000 troops, of whom about 6,000 were Malagasy [[tirailleurs]] (colonial infantry). A large proportion of the rest were [[Senegal]]ese. Between 1,500 and 3,000 Vichy troops were concentrated around Diego-Suarez.&lt;ref name="Rigge103"/&gt; However, naval and air defences were relatively light and/or obsolete: eight coastal batteries, two [[armed merchant cruiser]]s, two [[Sloop-of-war|sloops]], five submarines, 17 [[Morane-Saulnier M.S.406|Morane-Saulnier 406]] fighters and 10 [[Potez 63]] bombers.

[[File:Operation Ironclad.Madagascar1942.jpg|thumb|Captured French troops marching away from their HQ after the British had captured Diego-Suarez on 7 May]]
[[File:SurrenderTreatyconferenceatBHQAntsirane.jpg|thumb|Negotiations for the surrender of Diego-Suarez at the British headquarters in the town]]
The beach landings met with virtually no resistance and these troops seized Vichy coastal batteries and barracks. The Courier Bay force, the [[17th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|17th Infantry Brigade]], after toiling through mangrove swamp and thick bush took the town of Diego-Suarez taking a hundred prisoners. The Ambararata Bay force, the 29th Independent Brigade, headed towards the French naval base of Antisarane.&lt;ref name="Rigge103"/&gt; With assistance from six [[Valentine tank|Valentines]] and six [[Tetrarch tank|Tetrarch]] light tanks of B Special Service Squadron they advanced 21 miles overcoming light resistance with bayonet charges.&lt;ref name="Flint68"&gt;Flint, pp. 68-69&lt;/ref&gt; Antisarane itself was heavily defended with trenches, two redoubts, pillboxes, and flanked on both sides by impenetrable swamps.&lt;ref name="Rigge105"&gt;Rigge pp.105-06&lt;/ref&gt;

On the morning of 6 May 1942 a frontal assault on the defences failed with the loss of three Valentines and two Tetrarchs.&lt;ref name="Flint68"/&gt; Another assault by the [[South Lancashire Regiment|South Lancashires]] worked their way around the defences but the swamps and bad terrain meant they were broken up into groups. Nevertheless, they swung behind the Vichy line and caused chaos. Fire was poured on the Vichy defences from behind and the radio station and a barracks were seized.&lt;ref name="Rigge105"/&gt; In all 200 prisoners were taken, but the South Lancs had to withdraw as communication with the main force was nonexistent after the radio set failed. With the French defence highly effective, the deadlock was broken when the old destroyer {{HMS|Anthony|H40|6}} dashed straight past the harbour defences of Antisarane and landed fifty Royal Marines from ''Ramillies'' amidst the Vichy rear area.&lt;ref name="Rigge105"/&gt; The marines created "disturbance in the town out of all proportion to their numbers" taking the French artillery command post along with its barracks and the naval depot. At the same time the troops of the 17th Infantry Brigade had broken through the defences and were soon marching in the town. The Vichy defence was broken and Antisarane surrendered that evening, although substantial Vichy forces withdrew to the south.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | title = Combined Operations: the Official Story of the Commandos | year = 1943 | publisher =  Combined Operations Command | location = Great Britain | isbn = 9781417987412 | pages = 101–109 | ref = harv}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Japanese submarines {{Jsub|I-10||2}}, {{Jsub|I-16||2}}, and {{Jsub|I-20||2}} arrived three weeks later on 29 May 1942. ''I-10''{{'}}s reconnaissance plane spotted HMS ''Ramillies'' at anchor in Diego-Suarez harbour, but the plane was spotted and ''Ramillies'' changed her berth. ''I-20'' and ''I-16'' launched two [[midget submarine]]s, one of which managed to enter the harbour and fired two [[torpedo]]es while under [[depth charge]] attack from two corvettes. One torpedo seriously damaged ''Ramillies'', while the second sank the 6,993-ton [[oil tanker]] ''British Loyalty'' (later refloated).&lt;ref name="Rigge107"&gt;Rigge pp. 107–108&lt;/ref&gt; ''Ramillies'' was later repaired in [[Durban]] and [[Plymouth]].

The crew of one of the midget submarines, Lieutenant Saburo Akieda and Petty Officer Masami Takemoto, beached their craft (''M-20b'') at Nosy Antalikely and moved inland towards their pick-up point near Cape Amber. They were betrayed when they bought food at the village of Anijabe and both were killed in a firefight with Royal Marines three days later. One marine was killed in the action as well. The second midget submarine was lost at sea and the body of a crewman was found washed ashore a day later.&lt;ref name="Rigge107"/&gt;

===Ground campaign (Operation Stream Line Jane)===
[[File:IWM A 012399 Madagascar.jpg|thumb|19 September 1942. Allied troops disembarking from a [[Landing Craft Assault|LCA]] in [[Tamatave]] harbour.]]

Hostilities continued at a low level for several months. After 19 May 1942 two brigades of the 5th Infantry Division were transferred to India. On 8 June 1942, the [[King's African Rifles|22nd (East Africa) Brigade Group]] arrived on Madagascar{{sfn|Joslen|2003|pp=421–422}} The [[3rd Infantry Division (South Africa)|7th South African Motorized Brigade]] arrived on 24 June 1942.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://books.stonebooks.com/armies/unit/SA110/ |title=Archived copy |accessdate=2012-09-10 |url-status=live |archiveurl=http://archive.wikiwix.com/cache/20120912082325/http://books.stonebooks.com/armies/unit/SA110/ |archivedate=12 September 2012 |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[North Rhodesia|27th (North Rhodesia) Infantry Brigade]] (including forces from [[East Africa]]) landed on 8 August.{{sfn|Joslen|2003|pp=425–426}}

The operation code-named "Stream Line Jane" (sometimes given as "Streamline Jane") consisted of three separate sub-operations code-named Stream, Line and Jane. Stream and Jane were, respectively, the amphibious landings at Majunga on 10 September and Tamatave on 18 September, while Line was the advance from Majunga to the French capital, [[Antananarivo|Tannanarive]], which fell on 23 September.{{sfn|Buckley|1977|pp=191, 202}}{{sfn|Chant|1986|pp=196 (Jane) and 266 (Stream)|ps=. See also [http://codenames.info/operation/stream/ Stream], [http://codenames.info/operation/line/ Line] and [http://codenames.info/operation/jane/ Jane] at ''Codenames: Operations of World War II'' (retrieved 2017-11-18).}}

On 10 September 1942 the 29th Brigade and 22nd Brigade Group made an amphibious landing at Majunga, another port on the west coast of the island. No. 5 Commando spearheaded the landing and faced machine gun fire but despite this they stormed the quayside, took control of the local post office, stormed the governor's residence and raised the [[Union Jack]].&lt;ref name=website2&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.combinedops.com/MADAGASCAR.htm|title=Operation Ironclad: 5–7 May 1942|publisher=www.combinedops.com|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090321114535/http://www.combinedops.com/MADAGASCAR.htm|archivedate=21 March 2009|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt; Having severed communications with Tannanarive, the Allies intended to re-launch the offensive ahead of the [[rainy season]]. Progress was slow for the Allied forces. In addition to occasional small-scale clashes with Vichy forces, they also encountered scores of obstacles erected on the main roads by Vichy soldiers. The Allies eventually captured the capital, [[Tananarive]], without much opposition, and then the town of [[Ambalavao]], but the devoutly Vichy Governor Annet escaped.&lt;ref name="Rigge110"&gt;Rigge pp 110-11&lt;/ref&gt;

Eight days later a British force set out to seize Tamatave. Heavy surf interfered with the operation. As HMS ''Birmingham''{{'}}s launch was heading to shore it was fired at by French shore batteries and promptly turned around. ''Birmingham'' then opened her guns up on the shores batteries and within three minutes the French hauled up the white flag. Tamatave fell into British hands. From there the South Lancashires and the Royal Welch Fusiliers set out to the south to link up with forces there. After they reached Tananarive they pressed on towards [[Moramanga]] and on 25 September 1942 they linked up with the King's African Rifles having secured the British lines of communication around the island. At the same time the East African infantry and South African armoured cars set out to find the elusive Governor Annet.&lt;ref name="Rigge110"/&gt;

The last major action took place on 18 October, at [[Andramanalina]], a U-shaped valley with the meandering Mangarahara River where an ambush was planned for British forces by Vichy troops. The King's African Rifles split into two columns and marched around the 'U' of the valley and met Vichy troops in the rear and then ambushed them. The Vichy troops suffered heavy losses which resulted in 800 of them surrendering.&lt;ref name="Rigge110"/&gt; A week later the King's African Rifles then entered [[Fianarantsoa]] but found Annet gone, this time near [[Ihosy]] 100 miles south. The Africans swiftly moved after him, but they received an envoy from Annet asking for terms of surrender. He had had enough and couldn't escape further. An armistice was signed in [[Ambalavao]] on 6 November 1942, and Annet surrendered two days later.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine | title = World Battlefronts: Madagascar Surrenders | magazine = Time Magazine | date = November 16, 1942 | jstor = 2| url = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,932848,00.html | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20101014152159/http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,932848,00.html | archivedate = 14 October 2010 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Allies suffered about 500 casualties in the landing at Diego-Suarez, and 30 more killed and 90 wounded in the operations which followed on 10 September 1942.

Julian Jackson, in his biography of de Gaulle, observed that the French had held out longer against the Allies in Madagascar in 1942 than they had against the Germans in France in 1940.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Jackson |first1=Julian |title=A Certain Idea of France: the life of Charles de Gaulle |date=2018 |publisher=Allen Lane |location=London |isbn=978-1846143519 |pages=Chapter 9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Westland Lysander - Madagascar WWII.jpg|thumb|December 1942. Four RAF [[Westland Lysander]] aircraft flying over Madagascar following the end of the campaign.]]
With Madagascar in Allied hands, they established military and naval installations across the island. The island was crucial for the rest of the war. Its deep water ports were vital to control the passageway to India and the Persian corridor, and this was now beyond the grasp of the Axis.&lt;ref name="Rigge110"/&gt; This was the first large-scale operation of World War II by the Allies combining sea, land, and air forces. In the makeshift Allied planning of the war's early years, the invasion of Madagascar held a prominent strategic place.&lt;ref name="Rigge100"/&gt;

Free French General [[Paul Legentilhomme]] was appointed High Commissioner for Madagascar. [[decolonisation|Like many colonies]], Madagascar sought its independence following the war. In 1947, the island experienced the [[Malagasy Uprising]], a costly revolution that was crushed in 1948. It was not until 26 June 1960, about twelve years later, that the [[Madagascar|Malagasy Republic]] successfully proclaimed its independence from [[France]].

Campaign service in Madagascar did not qualify for the British and Commonwealth [[Africa Star]]. It was instead covered by the [[1939–1945 Star]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Citation | title = Medals: campaigns, descriptions &amp; eligibility | work = Guidance | publisher = Government | place = [[United Kingdom|UK]] | url = https://www.gov.uk/guidance/medals-campaigns-descriptions-and-eligibility | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20170623150944/https://www.gov.uk/guidance/medals-campaigns-descriptions-and-eligibility | archivedate = 23 June 2017 | df = dmy-all }}.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Order of battle==

===Allied Forces===
[[File:The Royal Navy during the Second World War A9713.jpg|thumb|A [[Grumman F4F Wildcat|Grumman Martlet]] of the [[Fleet Air Arm]] flying over {{HMS|Warspite|03|6}} during the Madagascar operations]]

====Naval forces====
[[File:Jacob van heemskerk light cruiser.jpg|thumb|{{HNLMS|Jacob van Heemskerck|1939|2}}, a Dutch cruiser involved in the operations off Madagascar]]
[[File:Baia di Diego Suarez.JPG|thumb|Modern-day view of the bay]]
;Battleships
:{{HMS|Ramillies|07|6}}
;Aircraft Carriers
:{{HMS|Illustrious|87|6}}
:{{HMS|Indomitable|R92|6}}
;Cruisers
:{{HMS|Birmingham|C19|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist&gt;{{cite web | last=Mason RN | first=Lt Cdr (Rtd) Geoffrey B | title=Dutch HNethMS TJERK HIDDES (G 16), ex-HMS NONPAREIL - N-class Destroyer | work=SERVICE HISTORIES of ROYAL NAVY WARSHIPS in WORLD WAR 2 | year=2003 | url=http://www.naval-history.net/xGM-Chrono-10DD-45N-HMS_Nonpareil.htm | accessdate=9 Nov 2014 | url-status=live | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140326231221/http://naval-history.net/xGM-Chrono-10DD-45N-HMS_Nonpareil.htm | archivedate=26 March 2014 | df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
:{{HMS|Dauntless|D45|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
:{{HMS|Gambia|48|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
:{{HMS|Hermione|74|6}}
:{{HMS|Devonshire|39|6}}
:{{HNLMS|Jacob van Heemskerck|1939|6}}
;Minelayer
:{{HMS|Manxman|M70|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
;Monitor
:{{HMS|Erebus|I02|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
;Seaplane Carrier
:{{HMS|Albatross|I23|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
;Destroyers
:{{HMS|Active|H14|6}}
:{{HMS|Anthony|H40|6}}
:{{HMS|Arrow|H42|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
:{{HMS|Blackmore|L43|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
:{{HMS|Duncan|D99|6}}
:{{HMS|Fortune|H70|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
:{{HMS|Foxhound|H69|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
:{{HMS|Inconstant|H49|6}}
:{{HMS|Hotspur|H01|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
:{{HMS|Javelin|F61|6}}
:{{HMS|Laforey|G99|6}}
:{{HMS|Lightning|G55|6}}
:{{HMS|Lookout|G32|6}}
:{{HMAS|Napier|G97|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
:{{HMAS|Nepal|G25|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
:{{HMAS|Nizam|G38|6}}
:{{HMAS|Norman|G49|6}}
:{{HMS|Pakenham|G06|6}}
:{{HMS|Paladin|G69|6}}
:{{HMS|Panther|G41|6}}
:{{HNLMS|Van Galen|G84|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
:{{HNLMS|Tjerk Hiddes|G16|6}}&lt;ref name=navhist /&gt;
;Corvettes
:{{HMS|Freesia|K43|6}}
:{{HMS|Auricula|K12|6}}
:{{HMS|Nigella|K19|6}}
:{{HMS|Fritillary|K199|6}}
:{{HMS|Genista|K200|6}}
:{{HMS|Cyclamen|K83|6}}
:{{HMS|Thyme|K210|6}}
:{{HMS|Jasmine|K23|6}}
;Minesweepers
:{{HMS|Cromer|J128|6}}
:[[Bangor-class minesweeper|HMS ''Poole'']]
:[[Bangor-class minesweeper|HMS ''Romney'']]
:[[Bangor-class minesweeper|HMS ''Cromarty'']]
;Assault transports
:HMS ''Winchester Castle''
:HMS ''Royal Ulsterman''
:HMS ''Keren''
:HMS ''Karanja''
:{{MS|Sobieski}} (Polish)
;Special ships
:HMS ''Derwentdale'' (LCA)
:HMS ''Bachaquero'' (LST)
;Troop ships
:{{SS|Oronsay|1925|6}}
:{{RMS|Duchess of Atholl}}
:{{RMS|Franconia|1922|6}}
;Stores and MT ships
:[[List of Empire ships (K)|SS ''Empire Kingsley'']]
:M/S ''Thalatta''
:SS ''Mahout''
:SS ''City of Hong Kong''
:SS ''Mairnbank''
:SS ''Martand II''&lt;ref name="Ironclad"&gt;{{cite web | url = http://stonebooks.com/history/madagascar.shtml | title = Operation Ironclad: Invasion of Madagascar | accessdate = 2 November 2010 | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20110514091628/http://stonebooks.com/history/madagascar.shtml | archivedate = 14 May 2011 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

====Ground forces====
[[File:Valentine II in Kubinka.jpg|thumb|A [[Valentine tank]] of the type used during the invasion.]]
[[File:British OP Ironclad 942BEMB.png|thumb|300px|Organization of British ground forces for Operation Ironclad, during the invasion of Madagascar 5 May 1942&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Nafziger|first1=George|title=Operation Ironclad Invasion of Madagascar 5 May 1942|url=http://usacac.army.mil/CAC2/CGSC/CARL/nafziger/942BEMB.pdf|website=United States Army Combined Arms Research Library|accessdate=18 October 2016|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161018235051/http://usacac.army.mil/CAC2/CGSC/CARL/nafziger/942BEMB.pdf|archivedate=18 October 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last1=Nafziger|first1=George|title=British Infantry Brigades 1st thru 215th 1939-1945|url=http://usacac.army.mil/CAC2/CGSC/CARL/nafziger/939BXIE.pdf|website=United States Army Combined Arms Research Library|accessdate=18 October 2016|url-status=live|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20161018234832/http://usacac.army.mil/CAC2/CGSC/CARL/nafziger/939BXIE.pdf|archivedate=18 October 2016|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;]]
;29th Infantry Brigade (independent) arrived via amphibious landing near Diego-Suarez on 5 May 1942
:2nd [[South Lancashire Regiment]]
:2nd [[East Lancashire Regiment]]
:1st [[Royal Scots Fusiliers]]
:2nd [[Royal Welch Fusiliers]]
:455th Light Battery (Royal Artillery)
:MG company
:'B' Special Service Squadron with 6 [[Valentine tank|Valentine]] and 6 [[Light Tank Mk VII Tetrarch|Tetrarch tanks]]
;Commandos arrived via amphibious landing near Diego-Suarez on 5 May 1942
:[[No. 5 Commando]]
;British 17th Infantry Brigade Group (of 5th Division) landed near Diego-Suarez as second wave on 5 May 1942
:2nd Royal Scots Fusiliers
:2nd Northamptonshire Regiment
:6th Seaforth Highlanders
:9th Field Regiment (Royal Artillery)
;British 13th Infantry Brigade (of 5th Division) landed near Diego-Suarez as third wave on 6 May 1942.  Departed 19 May 1942 for India
:2nd Cameronians
:2nd Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers
:2nd [[Wiltshire Regiment]]
;East African Brigade Group arrived 22 June to replace 13 and 17 Brigades
;[[3rd Infantry Division (South Africa)|South African 7th Motorised Brigade]]
;[[Rhodesian Army|Rhodesian 27th Infantry Brigade]] arrived 8 August 1942; departed 29 June 1944
:2nd [[Northern Rhodesia Regiment]]
:3rd Northern Rhodesia Regiment
:4th Northern Rhodesia Regiment
:55th (Tanganyika) Light Battery
:57th (East African) Field Battery&lt;ref name="Ironclad"/&gt;

====Fleet Air Arm====
;Aboard HMS ''Illustrious''
:881 Squadron - 12 [[Grumman F4F-4 Wildcat]] (Martlet Mk.II)
:882 Squadron - 8 [[Grumman F4F-4 Wildcat]] (Martlet Mk.II) 1 Fairey Fulmar
:810 Squadron - 10 [[Fairey Swordfish]]
:829 Squadron - 10 [[Fairey Swordfish]]
;Aboard HMS ''Indomitable''
:800 Squadron - 8 [[Fairey Fulmar]]
:806 Squadron - 4 [[Fairey Fulmar]]
:880 Squadron - 6 [[Hawker Sea Hurricane Mk IA]]
:827 Squadron - 12 [[Fairey Albacore]]
:831 Squadron - 12 [[Fairey Albacore]]&lt;ref name="Ironclad"/&gt;

===Vichy France===

====Naval Forces====

[[File:Japanese submarine I-10 at Penang port in 1942.jpg|thumb|[[Japanese submarine I-10]] in [[Penang]], 1942.]]
:Merchant Cruiser {{ship|French aviso|Bougainville 2||2}}
:Sloop {{ship|French aviso|D'Entrecasteaux|1931|2}}
;Submarines
:{{ship|French submarine|Bévéziers|1935|2}}
:{{ship|French submarine|Héros|Q170|2}}
:{{ship|French submarine|Monge|Q144|2}}&lt;ref name="Ironclad"/&gt;

====Land forces====
The following order of battle represents the Malagasy and Vichy French forces on the island directly after the initial ''Ironclad'' landings.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url = http://france1940.free.fr/vichy/ob_madaf.html | title = Madagascar, Ordres de bataille | accessdate = 30 October 2013 | language = French | url-status = live | archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20131102071826/http://france1940.free.fr/vichy/ob_madaf.html | archivedate = 2 November 2013 | df = dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Midget submarine crews (AWM P00325-001).jpg|thumb|Members of the Japanese imperial navy [[midget submarine]] attack group which included those who carried out the attacks on Diego-Suarez.]]
;West coast
:Two platoons of reservists and volunteers at [[Nosy Be|Nossi-Bé]]
:Two companies of the ''Régiment mixte malgache'' (RMM – Mixed Madagascar Regiment) at [[Ambanja]]
:One battalion of the 1er RMM at [[Mahajanga|Majunga]]
;East coast
:One battalion of the 1er RMM at [[Tamatave]]
:One artillery section (65mm) at Tamatave
:One company of the 1er RMM at [[Brickaville]]
;Centre of the island
:Three battalions of the 1er RMM at [[Tananarive]]
:One motorised reconnaissance detachment at Tananarive
:Emyrne battery at Tananarive
:One artillery section (65mm) at Tananarive
:One engineer company at Tananarive
:One company of the 1er RMM at [[Maevatanana|Mevatanana]]
:One company of the ''Bataillon de [[tirailleur]]s malgaches'' (BTM - Malagasy Tirailleurs Battalion) at [[Fianarantsoa]]
:South of the island
;Other
:One company of the BTM at [[Fort Dauphin (Madagascar)|Fort Dauphin]]
:One company of the BTM at [[Tuléar]]

===Japan===

====Naval forces====
* Submarines ''[[Japanese submarine I-10|I-10]]'' (with reconnaissance aircraft), ''[[Japanese submarine I-16|I-16]]'', ''I-18'' (damaged by heavy seas and arrived late), ''[[Japanese submarine I-20|I-20]]''
* Midget submarines ''M-16b'', ''M-20b''

==See also==
{{portal|Madagascar|World War II}}
* [[Force H]]
* [[Madagascar in World War II]]
{{clear}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book | last = Buckley |first = Christopher | title = Five Ventures: Iraq, Syria, Persia, Madagascar, Dodecanese | publisher = H. M. Stationery Office | year = 1977 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |ref=harv |title=The Encyclopedia of Codenames of World War II |publisher=Routledge |year=1986 |first=Christopher |last=Chant}}
* {{cite book | last = Churchill | first = Winston | authorlink = Winston Churchill | title = The Hinge of Fate | url = https://archive.org/details/hingeoffate00chur | url-access = registration | year = 1950 | publisher = Houghton Mifflin | location = Boston | oclc = 396148 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book| last=Flint| first=Keith| title=Airborne Armour: Tetrarch, Locust, Hamilcar and the 6th Airborne Armoured Reconnaissance Regiment 1938–1950| year=2006| publisher=Helion &amp; Company| isbn= 1-874622-37-X}}
* {{cite book| last=Grehan| first=John| title=Churchill's Secret Invasion: Britain's First Large-scale Combined Operations Offensive 1942| year=2013| publisher=Pen and Sword Military|location = Barnsley| isbn= 9781781593820}}
* {{cite book|last=Jennings|first=Eric T.|title=Vichy in the Tropics: Petain's National Revolution in Madagascar, Guadeloupe, and Indochina, 1940–44|year=2001|publisher=Stanford University Press|location=Stanford|isbn=0804750475}}
* {{cite book | last = Joslen | first = H. F. | authorlink =  | title = Orders of Battle, United Kingdom and Colonial Formations and Units in the Second World War, 1939–1945 | volume = I | year = 2003 | publisher = HM Stationery Office | location = London |edition=repr. Naval &amp; Military Press, Uckfield | isbn = 1843424746 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite book|last1=Rigge|first1=Simon|title=War in the Outposts |volume=24 |series=World War II: Time-Life International|year=1980|publisher=Time-Life Books|isbn=9780809433797}}
* {{cite book |title=Dust Clouds in the Middle East: Air War for East Africa, Iraq, Syria, Iran and Madagascar, 1940–42 |first=Christopher |last=Shores |year=1996 |location=London |publisher=Grub Street}}
* {{cite book|last1=Smith|first1=Colin|title=England's Last War Against France: Fighting Vichy 1940–42|year=2010|publisher=Hachette UK|isbn=9780297857815}}
* {{cite journal  | last = Thomas | first = Martin | title = Imperial Backwater or Strategic Outpost? The British Takeover of Vichy Madagascar, 1942 | journal = The Historical Journal |date=December 1996 | volume = 39 | issue = 4 | pages = 1049–1074 | publisher = Cambridge University Press | jstor = 2639867| ref = harv | doi=10.1017/s0018246x00024754}}
* {{cite book | last = Turner | first = Leonard Charles Frederick | title = War in the Southern Oceans: 1939–1945 | year = 1961 | publisher = Oxford University Press | location = Cape Town |last2=Gordon-Cummings |first2=H. R. |last3=Betzler |first3=J. E. | editor = Turner, L. C. F. | oclc = 42990496 | ref = harv}}
* {{cite journal | last = Wessels | first = André | title = South Africa and the War against Japan, 1941–1945 | journal = Military History Journal | publisher =South African Military History Society |date=June 1996 | volume=10 | issue=3 | url = http://samilitaryhistory.org/vol103aw.html | ref=harv}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite journal  | last = Harrison | first = E.D.R. | title = British Subversion in French East Africa, 1941–42: SOE's Todd Mission | journal = English Historical Review |date=April 1999 | volume = 114 | issue = 456 | pages = 339–369 | jstor = 580082 | doi = 10.1093/enghis/114.456.339 }}
* {{cite journal  | last = Nativel | first = Eric | title = La "guérilla" des troupes vichystes à Madasgar en 1942 | journal = Revue Historique des Armées |date= 1998 | volume = 1 | issue = | pages =  | jstor = }}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{commons category|Operation Ironclad}}
* [http://exordio.com/1939-1945/militaris/batallas/ironclad.html exordio.com, ?, "Operación Ironclad" (Spanish language) ]
* [http://www.combinedfleet.com/Madagascar.htm Outline of Japanese involvement]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20140416175245/http://cdn.bbcmagazinesbristol.com/bbchistory/audio/HistoryExtra_6thSep12.mp3 BBC History Magazine podcast about the Battle of Madagascar]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Madagascar 1942, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:Land battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving South Africa]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:History of Madagascar]]
[[Category:Military battles of Vichy France]]
[[Category:World War II occupied territories]]
[[Category:1942 in France]]
[[Category:1942 in Madagascar]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations involving the United Kingdom]]</text><sha1>bn913ynbu5ql52gtmkog7oymg4mitn3</sha1></revision></page>