<page><title>Indian Ocean raid (1944)</title><ns>0</ns><id>23414320</id><revision><id>964862551</id><parentid>954663947</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-28T01:03:14Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Amigao</username><id>11099276</id></contributor><minor /><comment>/* Aftermath */clean up, [[WP:AWB/T|typo(s) fixed]]: However  → However,</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="17583" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2015}}
{{good article}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Second Indian Ocean raid
|partof = [[Pacific War]]
|image = [[File:Aoba class cruiser;h97733.jpg|300px|alt=Black and white drawing of a World War II-era warship|U.S. Navy recognition drawing for Japanese Aoba-class heavy cruisers]]
|caption =U.S. Navy recognition drawing for Japanese ''Aoba''-class heavy cruisers
|date = 1–16 March 1944
|place = [[Indian Ocean]]
|coordinates =
|map_type =
|latitude =
|longitude =
|map_size =
|map_caption =
|territory =
|result = inconclusive
|status =
|combatant1 = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
|combatant2 = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
|commander1 = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan|naval}} Rear Admiral [[Naomasa Sakonju]]
|commander2 =
|strength1 =3 [[heavy cruiser]]s
|strength2 =
|casualties1 = none
|casualties2 =1 steamer sunk,&lt;br /&gt;3 killed,&lt;br /&gt;unknown wounded
|notes =
* Either 72 or 89 British survivors were executed by Japanese forces after being taken prisoner.
|campaignbox={{Axis naval attacks on Australia}}
{{Campaignbox Indian Ocean Theatre}}
}}

In March 1944, a force of three [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] (IJN) [[heavy cruiser]]s raided [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] shipping in the [[Indian Ocean]]. The cruisers departed Japanese-held territory on 1&amp;nbsp;March with the support of other IJN vessels and aircraft. On 9&amp;nbsp;March, they encountered and sank the British [[Steamboat|steamer]] ''Behar'', with the heavy cruiser {{Ship|Japanese cruiser|Tone|1937|2}} picking up over 100 survivors. Fearing detection, the Japanese force subsequently returned to the [[Netherlands East Indies]] (NEI), arriving on 16&amp;nbsp;March. Two days later, most of ''Behar''{{'}}s crew and passengers were murdered on board ''Tone''. Following the war the commander of the raid, Rear Admiral [[Naomasa Sakonju]], was executed for this [[war crime]] and ''Tone''{{'}}s captain Haruo Mayuzumi ([[:ja:黛治夫]]) was sentenced to seven years imprisonment.

==Background==
In February 1944, the Japanese [[Combined Fleet]] withdrew from its base at [[Chuuk State|Truk]] in the Central [[Pacific Ocean|Pacific]] to [[Palau]] and [[Singapore]]. The appearance of a powerful Japanese naval force at Singapore concerned the Allies, as it was feared that these ships could potentially conduct raids in the Indian Ocean and against [[Western Australia]].&lt;ref&gt;Odgers (1968), pp. 134–135&lt;/ref&gt; In response, the Allies strengthened their naval and air forces in the area by transferring two British [[light cruiser]]s from the [[Atlantic Ocean|Atlantic]] and [[Mediterranean Sea|Mediterranean]] as well as several [[United States Navy|U.S. Navy]] warships from the [[Pacific Ocean|Pacific]]. The number of air units in [[Ceylon]] and the [[Bay of Bengal]] region was also increased.&lt;ref&gt;Gill (1968), p. 387&lt;/ref&gt; Admiral [[James Somerville]], the commander of the British [[Eastern Fleet]], feared that the Japanese would repeat their devastating [[Indian Ocean raid]] of early 1942, and on 25&amp;nbsp;February requested permission to withdraw his fleet from its base at [[Trincomalee]] so that it was not at risk from the larger Japanese force. The [[Admiralty]] rejected this request, and directed that the fleet should remain at Trincomalee unless it was threatened by a superior Japanese force as its withdrawal would affect morale and harm Britain's prestige in the region. It was agreed, however, that the Eastern Fleet should not engage superior Japanese forces and could withdraw if Somerville judged this necessary.&lt;ref name="Gill_388"&gt;Gill (1968), p. 388&lt;/ref&gt;

In late February, Vice-Admiral [[Shiro Takasu]]—the Commander in Chief, [[Southwest Area Fleet]]—ordered the heavy cruisers {{Ship|Japanese cruiser|Aoba||2}}, {{Ship|Japanese cruiser |Chikuma|1938|2}}, and {{Ship|Japanese cruiser|Tone|1937|2}} to raid Allied shipping on the main route between [[Aden]] and [[Fremantle, Western Australia|Fremantle]]. This force was commanded by Rear Admiral Naomasa Sakonju on board ''Aoba''. In his instructions to Sakonju, Vice Admiral Takasu directed that if the force captured Allied merchant seamen all prisoners, other than radio operators and other personnel who might possess useful information, were to be killed.&lt;ref name="Gill_388"/&gt; Sakonju did not question this order. The Japanese cruisers embarked specialised boarding parties for this operation as it was hoped that they could capture merchant ships to alleviate Japan's shipping shortage.&lt;ref&gt;Royal Navy Historical Section (1957), pp. 183–184&lt;/ref&gt;

==Raid==
The three Japanese heavy cruisers departed from the Combined Fleet's anchorage in the [[Lingga Islands]] on 27&amp;nbsp;February.&lt;ref name="Aoba_TROM"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.combinedfleet.com/aoba_t.htm|title=HIJMS Aoba: Tabular Record of Movement|last=Hackett|first=Bob|author2=Kingsepp, Sander|year=2007|publisher=Combinedfleet.com|accessdate=28 June 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; The light cruisers {{Ship|Japanese cruiser|Kinu||2}} and {{ship|Japanese cruiser|Ōi||2}} and three destroyers escorted the force through the [[Sunda Strait]] on 1&amp;nbsp;March. The raiders were supported by 10 medium bombers and three or four [[seaplane]]s based in [[Sumatra]] and west [[Java]] which conducted patrols in the direction of Ceylon. Three or four submarines from the 8th&amp;nbsp;Flotilla also monitored Allied shipping movements near [[Ceylon]], the [[Maldive Islands]] and [[Chagos Archipelago]].&lt;ref name= "Gill_388"/&gt; The Allies did not detect the Japanese force's departure, but [[Western Australian emergency of March 1944|reinforced their forces in Western Australia]] after an American submarine encountered ''Kinu'' and ''Ōi'' operating near the [[Lombok Strait]] on 6&amp;nbsp;March. The presence of these ships was taken to indicate that a hostile force had possibly been dispatched into the Indian Ocean.&lt;ref name="Gill_390"&gt;Gill (1968), p. 390&lt;/ref&gt; On 8&amp;nbsp;March, Somerville directed all Allied ships travelling between 80 and 100° east to divert to the south or west.&lt;ref name="RN_184"/&gt;

After leaving the Sunda Strait, the Japanese heavy cruisers sailed south-west for the main route between Aden and Fremantle. The ships were spread {{convert|50|km|nmi mi|lk=on|abbr=on}} by day and {{convert|20|km|nmi mi|abbr=on}} by night and maintained [[radio silence]].&lt;ref name="RN_184"&gt;Royal Navy Historical Section (1957), p. 184&lt;/ref&gt; On the morning of 9&amp;nbsp;March, they encountered the {{convert|6100|LT|t|abbr=on}} British steamer ''Behar'' at {{coord|20|32|S|87|10|E}}, about midway between Fremantle and [[Colombo]].&lt;ref name="Gill_388"/&gt; The ship was travelling from Fremantle to [[Bombay]] as part of a voyage between [[Newcastle, New South Wales]] and the United Kingdom carrying a cargo of [[zinc]].&lt;ref name="Weaver_12"&gt;Weaver (2000), p. 12&lt;/ref&gt;

Upon sighting the Japanese ships, ''Behar''{{'}}s master, Captain Maurice Symons, ordered that his radio operator transmit the "RRR" code in order to notify other ships and Allied bases that the merchant ship was being attacked by surface raiders. ''Tone''{{'}}s signals room picked up this message, and the cruiser opened fire on ''Behar''.&lt;ref&gt;Lamont-Brown (2002), pp. 110–111&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese cruiser did not attempt to capture the steamer, as it was judged too risky to sail her back to Japanese territory.&lt;ref name= "RN_184"/&gt; ''Tone''{{'}}s gunners scored hits on ''Behar''{{'}}s prow and stern which killed three of her crew. Five minutes after the sighting, ''Behar''{{'}}s crew and passengers abandoned ship. The steamer sank shortly afterwards and either 104 or 108 survivors were rescued by ''Tone''.&lt;ref&gt;Gill (1968), pp. 388–389&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Lamont_Brown_111"&gt;Lamont-Brown (2002), p. 111&lt;/ref&gt;{{ref|def|(I)}}

The ''Behar'' survivors were maltreated by members of ''Tone''{{'}}s crew. Japanese sailors forced the survivors to hand over all their personal belongings of any value, and then used ropes to tie the survivors in painful positions which caused them to have difficulty breathing. The merchant ship's chief officer was beaten after he complained that treating civilians in such a way violated the [[Geneva Conventions|Geneva Convention]]. However, the female survivors later had their ropes removed.&lt;ref name=Lamont_Brown_111 /&gt; When the survivors were taken below decks to be imprisoned they were badly beaten by Japanese sailors.&lt;ref&gt;Lamont-Brown (2002), pp. 111–112&lt;/ref&gt;

Following the attack, Sakonju judged that it was too dangerous to continue the raid as ''Behar''{{'}}s distress message may have alerted the Allies to his force's presence. Accordingly, the Japanese turned back for the NEI that day.&lt;ref name="Gill_389"&gt;Gill (1968), p. 389&lt;/ref&gt; The heavy cruisers were again escorted through the Sunda Strait by ''Kinu'', ''Ōi'' and five destroyers, and arrived back at the NEI on 15&amp;nbsp;March.&lt;ref name= "Gill_388"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Aoba_TROM"/&gt; During this time, the ''Behar'' survivors were held in a small and extremely hot store room on board ''Tone'', and were given little access to food and water, sanitary facilities and exercise.&lt;ref name="Lamont_Brown_112"&gt;Lamont-Brown (2002), p. 112&lt;/ref&gt;

Despite Sakonju's fears, the Allies were not immediately aware of the attack on ''Behar''. Her distress signal had been picked up by only a single Allied merchant ship, which did not report it until she arrived at Fremantle on 17&amp;nbsp;March. In the meantime, Somerville had decided on 16&amp;nbsp;March that surface raiders no longer posed a threat to shipping in the Indian Ocean and allowed Allied vessels to resume their normal routing.&lt;ref name="RN_184"/&gt;

==Massacre==
[[File:Naomasa Sakonju.jpg|thumb|upright|Rear Admiral Naomasa Sakonju]]
Shortly after the ''Behar'' survivors were rescued, Sakonju sent a radio message to ''Tone''{{'}}s commanding officer, Captain Haruo Mayuzumi, reprimanding him for taking non-essential personnel prisoner and not capturing the merchant ship. In this message Sakonju ordered that the survivors be killed. Mayuzumi was unwilling to do so, however, as he felt that this would violate his Christian religious beliefs. His executive officer, Commander Junsuke Mii, also opposed killing the prisoners. Mayuzumi radioed a request to Sakonju that the prisoners be put ashore, but this was rejected. The captain then visited ''Aoba'' to argue his case, but Sakonju remained unmoved and told Mayuzumi to "obey my orders". Despite his misgivings, Mayuzumi decided to kill the prisoners.&lt;ref name=Lamont_Brown_112 /&gt;

On 15&amp;nbsp;March the three heavy cruisers anchored at [[Tanjung Priok]] near Java. Following this, either 15 or 36 survivors were transferred to ''Aoba''.&lt;ref name=Gill_389 /&gt;&lt;ref name=Lamont_Brown_112 /&gt;{{ref|def|(II)}} The party sent to ''Aoba'' included Symonds, the ''Behar''{{'}}s chief officer and several of the senior officers as well as both of the ship's female passengers.&lt;ref name=Lamont_Brown_112 /&gt; All of this group were later landed at Tanjung Priok.&lt;ref name="Lamont_Brown_114"&gt;Lamont-Brown (2002), p. 114&lt;/ref&gt;

The three cruisers sailed from Tanjung Priok bound for Singapore on 18&amp;nbsp;March.&lt;ref name="Aoba_TROM"/&gt; That night, all the prisoners on board ''Tone'' were beheaded by several of the cruiser's officers.&lt;ref name="Gill_389"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Lamont-Brown_112-114"&gt;Lamont-Brown (2002), pp. 112–114&lt;/ref&gt; Mayuzumi watched the killings from the ship's bridge but Mii refused to take part.&lt;ref name=Lamont-Brown_112-114 /&gt;

==Aftermath==

''Aoba'', ''Chikuma'' and ''Tone'' arrived at Singapore on 25&amp;nbsp;March.&lt;ref name="Aoba_TROM"/&gt; The Indian Ocean raid was the last operation conducted by Axis surface raiders during World War II.&lt;ref name="Gill_390"/&gt; As a result, ''Behar'' was the final Allied merchant ship to be sunk by surface raiders during the war.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill (1960), p. 351&lt;/ref&gt;
The raid is notable chiefly for the ''Behar'' massacre; it achieved little militarily. The raid failed to disrupt Allied traffic in the region as the diversions ordered by Somerville on 8 March were rescinded by the 16th. The only tangible result was the sinking of one ship,  the ''Behar''; by contrast Axis submarines [[Indian Ocean in World War II#1944|sank three ships]] in the Indian Ocean during the same period. The raid was also less successful than comparable raids by surface ships in the region, such as that of the [[German cruiser Admiral Scheer|''Admiral Scheer'']] in 1941. The Japanese made no attempt to capitalize on their numerical superiority in the region and by the end of the month it had vanished; reinforcements to the Eastern Fleet enabled Somerville to start  a series of carrier raids, commencing with the [[Operation Cockpit|attack on Sabang]] on 19 April 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Roskill (1960), p. 354-6&lt;/ref&gt;

The party of ''Behar'' survivors who had been landed at Tanjung Priok were initially interned in [[prisoner of war]] camps in Java; the male prisoners were sent to a camp near [[Jakarta|Batavia]] and the women were held in a female camp nearby. After all the members of the group had been interrogated, the survivors were separated and sent to other camps in Java or to work as slave labourers in Japan. All the survivors were freed after the end of the war in August 1945.&lt;ref name=Lamont_Brown_114 /&gt; One of the Survivors Mrs Agnes (Nancy) Shaw had been travelling to India to join her husband. They had been separated when they escaped from Malaya on different ships. She was imprisoned at Camp Makkasar in Batavia (now Java) where she worked in the camp bakery. She was reunited with her husband after Java was liberated. When the British Government negotiated gratuities for Far East Prisoners of War the Foreign and Commonwealth Office disavowed knowledge of her captivity. However, on being shown artefacts from captivity including a pastel sketchbook the gratuity was paid    She died in Aberdeen in February 2002 aged 89.

Following the war, the Allies prosecuted the officers responsible for the murders on board ''Tone''. Vice Admiral Takasu had died from disease in September 1944, but Sakonju was tried by the British in 1947 at [[Hong Kong]] and sentenced to death.&lt;ref&gt;Fuller (1992), p. 284&lt;/ref&gt; Mayuzumi was also convicted for his role in the killings and sentenced to seven years imprisonment.&lt;ref name="Gill_390"/&gt;

==See also==
* [[Japanese raiders in the Indian Ocean]]

==Notes==
* {{note|def|(I)}} The number of ''Behar'' survivors rescued after the ship's sinking differ between sources. Lamont-Brown (2002), p.&amp;nbsp;111 states that 108 of the 111 people on board the ship were rescued while Gill (1968), p.&amp;nbsp;389 states that there were 104 survivors, all of whom were rescued.
* {{note|def|(II)}} Gill (1968), p.&amp;nbsp;389 states that 15 ''Behar'' survivors were landed at Tanjung Priok while Lamont-Brown (2002), p.&amp;nbsp;112 puts the figure at 36.

==Citations==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Fuller|first=Richard|title=Shokan. Hirohito's Samurai|publisher=Arms and Armour Press|location=London|year=1992|isbn=1-85409-151-4|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/shokanhirohitoss00full}}
* {{cite book |last=Gill|first=G. Hermon |authorlink=G. Hermon Gill|title=Royal Australian Navy 1942–1945|url= http://www.awm.gov.au/histories/second_world_war/volume.asp?levelID=67911|series=[[Australia in the War of 1939–1945|Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 2&amp;nbsp;– Navy]]|year=1968|publisher= Australian War Memorial|location=Canberra|OCLC=65475}}
* {{cite book|last=Lamont-Brown|first=Raymond|title=Ships From Hell : Japanese War Crimes on the High Seas|year=2002|publisher=Sutton|location=Stroud, Gloucestershire|isbn=0-7509-2719-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Odgers |first=George |authorlink=George Odgers |title=Air War Against Japan 1943–1945 |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/histories/second_world_war/volume.asp?levelID=67913 |series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 3&amp;nbsp;– Air |year=1968 |edition=reprint |publisher=Australian War Memorial |location=Canberra |OCLC=569568982 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20131014171352/http://www.awm.gov.au/histories/second_world_war/volume.asp?levelID=67913 |archivedate=14 October 2013 |df=dmy-all }}
* {{cite book |last=Roskill |first=S. W. |volume=III |title=The War at Sea 1939–1945: The Offensive Part I 1st June 1943 – 31st May 1944 |publisher=HMSO |location=London |year=1960 |series=History of the Second World War. United Kingdom Military Series |oclc=570500225}}
* {{cite book|last=Royal Navy Historical Section|title=War with Japan Volume IV. The South–East Asian Operations and Central Pacific Advance|publisher=Royal Navy|location=London|year=1957|OCLC=651943668}}
* {{cite journal|last=Weaver|first=Paul|year=2000|title=Behar massacre&amp;nbsp;— a review of a little-known wartime atrocity|journal=Quarterly Newsletter&amp;nbsp;— The Australian Association for Maritime History|issue=80|publisher=The Australian Association for Maritime History|location=Perth|issn=1440-5164|url=http://www.aamh.asn.au/news/0080.pdf|access-date=28 June 2009|archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20091013072342/http://www.aamh.asn.au/news/0080.pdf|archive-date=13 October 2009|url-status=dead}}
{{refend}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:Indian Ocean operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:Japanese war crimes]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:March 1944 events]]
[[Category:Military raids]]
[[Category:Japan–United Kingdom military relations]]</text><sha1>ruxfsp5ph5c7covgeilxctde43bcnh3</sha1></revision></page>