<page><title>Japanese occupation of Attu</title><ns>0</ns><id>29078911</id><revision><id>943628902</id><parentid>943625179</parentid><timestamp>2020-03-03T00:31:35Z</timestamp><contributor><username>XXzoonamiXX</username><id>17080504</id></contributor><minor /><comment>/* Occupation */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="7752" xml:space="preserve">{{more footnotes|date=September 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Japanese occupation of Attu
|partof=the [[American Theater (World War II)|American Theater]] and the [[Pacific War|Pacific Theater]] of [[World War II]]
| image= A6M2-N Rufes Holtz Bay 1942.jpg
| image_size = 300
|caption=''Four Japanese seaplanes landed at Holtz Bay, Attu Island on 7 November 1942. Photo taken by American surveillance aircraft.''
|date=7 June 1942 – 30 May 1943
|place=[[Attu Island|Attu]], [[Aleutian Islands]], [[Pacific Ocean]]
|coordinates= {{coord|52.9241|173.1568|type:event_globe:earth_region:US-AK|display=ti}}
|result=Japanese occupation commences.
|combatant1={{flag|United States|1912}}
|combatant2={{flag|Empire of Japan}}
|commander1=N/A
|commander2={{flagicon|Empire of Japan|army}} [[Matsutoshi Hosumi]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Empire of Japan|army}} [[Yasuyo Yamasaki]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Empire of Japan|naval}} [[Boshirō Hosogaya]]
|strength1=N/A
|strength2=1,140 - 2,900
|casualties1=1 civilian killed&lt;br /&gt;46 civilians captured
|casualties2=unknown
}}
{{Campaignbox Aleutians}}

The '''Japanese occupation of Attu''' was the result of an invasion of the [[Aleutian Islands]] in Alaska during [[World War II]]. [[Imperial Japan]]ese [[Imperial Japanese Army|Army]] troops landed on 7 June 1942 the day after the [[Japanese occupation of Kiska|invasion]] of [[Kiska]]. Along with the Kiska landing, it was the first time that the [[continental United States]] was invaded and occupied by a foreign power since the [[War of 1812]], and was the second of the only two [[Invasion of the United States|invasions of the United States]] during World War II. The occupation ended with the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] victory in the [[Battle of Attu]] on 30 May 1943.

==Occupation==
In May 1942, the Japanese began near-simultaneous campaigns against [[Midway Atoll|Midway]], and the Aleutians, thus beginning the [[Aleutian Islands Campaign]]. During the [[Battle of Midway]], Japanese forces were repulsed in a decisive action, meanwhile, on 7 June, Japanese naval forces under [[Boshirō Hosogaya]] landed troops unopposed at Attu in conjunction with the same forces invading Kiska the previous day. A force consisting of 1,140 [[infantry]] under [[Major]] [[Matsutoshi Hosumi]] took control of the island and captured Attu's population, which consisted of 45 [[Aleut]]s and two white Americans, Charles Foster Jones (1879-1942), an [[amateur radio]] operator and weather reporter, originally from [[St. Paris, Ohio]], and his wife Etta (1879-1965), a teacher and nurse, originally from [[Vineland, New Jersey]].&lt;ref&gt;Mary Breu (2009) ''Last Letters from Attu'', Alaska Northwest Books, {{ISBN|0882408100}}&lt;/ref&gt; The village consisted of several houses around [[Chichagof Harbor]].

The 42 Aleut inhabitants who survived the Japanese invasion were taken to a prison camp near [[Otaru]], [[Hokkaido]]. Sixteen of them died while they were imprisoned.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Attu: The Forgotten Battle|last=Chloe|first=John Haile|publisher=National Park Service|year=2017|isbn=0996583734|location=|pages=32–33}}&lt;/ref&gt; Charles Jones was killed by the Japanese forces immediately after the invasion due to his refusal to fix the radio he previously destroyed to prevent the occupying troops from using it. His wife was subsequently taken to the Bund Hotel, which housed [http://www.montevideomaru.info/Montevideo/html/Nurses%20Camps.htm Australian Rabaul New Britain nurses] who were prisoners of war from the [[Battle of Rabaul (1942)|1942 Battle of Rabaul]] in [[Papua New Guinea]], in [[Yokohama]], [[Japan]]. Sometime later, she and the Australian nurses were taken to the Yokohama Yacht Club and kept there from 1942 to July 1944 when then moved to the old Totsuka Hospital, also in [[Yokohama]]. The hospital served as a civilian prisoner of war camp until the end of the war in August 1945. Etta Jones died in December 1965 at age 86 in [[Bradenton, Florida]].&lt;ref&gt;Mary Breu (2009) ''Last Letters from Attu'', Alaska Northwest Books, {{ISBN|0882408100}}&lt;/ref&gt; 
[[File:Attu village 1937.jpg|left|thumb|''Attu village, occupied by the Japanese and retaken during the Battle of Attu.'']]

After landing, the soldiers began constructing an [[airbase]] and [[fortification]]s. The nearest American forces were on [[Unalaska Island]] at [[Dutch Harbor]] and at an airbase on [[Adak Island]]. Throughout the occupation, American air and naval forces bombarded the island. Initially the Japanese intended to hold the Aleutians only until the winter of 1942; however, the occupation continued into 1943 in order to deny the Americans use of the islands. In August 1942, the [[garrison]] of Attu was moved to Kiska to help repel a suspected American attack. From August to October 1942, Attu was unoccupied until a 2,900-man force under [[Colonel]] [[Yasuyo Yamasaki]] arrived. The new garrison of Attu continued constructing the airfield and fortifications until 11 May 1943, when a 15,000 man army of American troops landed. On 12 May, {{Ship|Japanese submarine|I-31||2}} was forced to surface five miles northeast of [[Chichagof Harbor]], she was then sunk in a surface [[Action of 12 May 1943|engagement]] with {{USS|Edwards|DD-619|6}}.
[[File:Attu Chichagof Harbor with smoke 1943.jpg|upright=1.2|right|thumb|''Chichagof Harbor under attack during the Allied liberation of Attu.'']]

Allied forces under [[General]] [[John L. DeWitt]] took control of the island on 30 May after the remaining Japanese troops conducted a massive [[banzai charge]]. American forces lost 549 killed and 1,148 wounded, another 2,100 evacuated due to weather-related injuries. During the Battle of Attu, all but 29 men of the Japanese garrison were killed. The occupation ended with an American victory and American forces deemed the half-completed airfield as not ideally situated. After building a new airfield the Americans launched [[bomber]] attacks against the Japanese home islands for the remainder of the war &lt;ref&gt;Brian Garfield, The Thousand-Mile War: World War II in Alaska and the Aleutians&lt;/ref&gt;

Attu village was abandoned after the war, and surviving members of Japanese internment were moved to other islands after the war. In 2012, for the 70th anniversary of the occupation, a memorial to Attu village was dedicated at the former site of the town.

==See also==
* [[Attacks on North America during World War II]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}
* {{cite book| author = Fern Chandonnet| title = Alaska at War, 1941-1945| date = 2007-09-15| publisher = University of Alaska Press| isbn = 978-1-60223-013-2 | pages = 23–26}}
* {{cite book| author = Diane Olthuis| title = It Happened in Alaska| date = 2006-07-01| publisher = Globe Pequot Press| isbn = 978-0-7627-3908-0 |page = 119}}
* {{cite web|last=Paulin|first=Jim|title=Memorial placed in Attu honoring villagers|url=http://www.thedutchharborfisherman.com/article/1235memorial_placed_in_attu_honoring_villagers|publisher=The Bristol Bay Times|accessdate=3 March 2014}}
* {{cite book| author = Mary Breu| title = Last Letters from Attu| date = 2009| publisher = Alaska Northwest Books | isbn = 978-0-88240-810-1}}
* Mason, Rachel. "[https://www.nps.gov/akso/nature/science/ak_park_science/PDF/2011Vol10-2/attu-a-lost-village-of-the-aleutians.pdf Attu, A Lost Village of the Aleutians]." Alaska Park Science, Volume 10, Issue 2
{{Alaska history footer}}
{{Japanese occupations}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2017}}

[[Category:1942 in Alaska]]
[[Category:1943 in Alaska]]
[[Category:Aleutian Islands Campaign]]
[[Category:American Theater of World War II]]
[[Category:Japanese military occupations|Attu]]
[[Category:World War II occupied territories]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations of World War II]]</text><sha1>5la8pvfdvj7nqbe7jgtda2ac6z7do4n</sha1></revision></page>