<page><title>Battle of Borneo (1941–42)</title><ns>0</ns><id>7321353</id><revision><id>966803542</id><parentid>966783432</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-09T08:54:10Z</timestamp><contributor><username>AustralianRupert</username><id>8731061</id></contributor><comment>/* Battle */ reword to clarify</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="16873" xml:space="preserve">{{Short description|WWII Battle between Japanese and Dutch and British forces}}

{{EngvarB|date=October 2017}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2017}}
{{for|the campaigns on eastern Borneo|Battle of Tarakan (1942)|Battle of Balikpapan (1942)}}
{{Multiple issues|
{{more footnotes|date=September 2014}}
{{refimprove|date=May 2016}}
}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Borneo
| image       = Japanese paratroopers heading to Borneo, 1941.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = Japanese paratroopers of the [[Japanese marine paratroopers of World War II|2nd Yokosuka Naval Landing Force]] under the command of Lieutenant Colonel Genzo Watanabe (standing on top in the left) inside a transport ship heading to [[Borneo]] prior to their invasion in December 1941.
| partof      = the [[Pacific War|Pacific Theatre]] of [[World War II]]
| date        = 16 December 1941 – March 1942
| place       = [[Borneo|Borneo Island]]
| result      = Japanese victory
| territory   = Japanese occupation of [[Japanese occupation of British Borneo|British Borneo]] and [[Japanese occupation of the Dutch East Indies|Dutch Borneo]]
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
* {{flagicon|Raj of Sarawak}} [[Raj of Sarawak|Sarawak]]
* {{flag|British Raj|name=India}}
* {{flag|North Borneo}}
* {{flag|Brunei|1906}} 
* {{flagicon image|Flag of Labuan (1912–1946).svg}} [[Crown Colony of Labuan|Labuan]]
{{flag|Netherlands}}
* {{flag|Dutch East Indies}}
| commander1  = {{flagdeco|Empire of Japan|army}} [[Kiyotake Kawaguchi]]
| commander2  = {{flagdeco|United Kingdom}} [[Robert Brooke-Popham]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} C.M. Lane&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|Netherlands}} Dominicus Mars
| strength1   = 4,500 infantry&lt;br&gt;2 heavy cruisers&lt;br&gt;1 light cruiser&lt;br&gt;6 destroyers&lt;br&gt;1 submarine chaser&lt;br&gt;1 seaplane tender&lt;br&gt;1 minesweeper&lt;br&gt;1 submarine&lt;br&gt;1 collier&lt;br&gt;10 transports
| strength2   = 1,000 Sarawak Force&lt;br /&gt;1,000 British Punjab Regiment&lt;br /&gt;1,000 KNIL&lt;br /&gt;650 police&lt;br /&gt;5 fighters&lt;br&gt;Unknown bomber strength&lt;br&gt;3 flying boats&lt;br&gt;2 submarines
| casualties1 = 567+ casualties&lt;br&gt;2 destroyers sunk&lt;br&gt;1 minesweeper sunk&lt;br&gt;1 collier sunk&lt;br&gt;2 transports sunk&lt;br&gt;1 transport beached&lt;br&gt;1 transport damaged
| casualties2 = 2,300 casualties&lt;br&gt;1 flying boat destroyed&lt;br&gt;1 submarine sunk
}}
{{Campaignbox Pacific 1941}}
{{Campaignbox Netherlands East Indies}}

The '''Battle of Borneo''' was a successful campaign by [[Empire of Japan|Japanese Imperial]] forces for control of [[Borneo]] island and concentrated mainly on the subjugation of the [[Raj of Sarawak]], [[Brunei]], [[North Borneo]], and the western part of [[Kalimantan]] that was part of the [[Dutch East Indies]]. The Japanese main unit for this mission was the 35th Infantry Brigade led by Major-General [[Kiyotake Kawaguchi]].

== Background ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2020}}
In 1941, Borneo was divided between the [[Dutch East Indies]] and British [[protectorate]]s (North Borneo, Sarawak and Brunei) and [[Crown colony|crown colonies]] (Labuan).

The so-called "[[White Rajahs]]", the Brooke family, had ruled Sarawak, on the northwest of Borneo, for almost a century, first as [[Raja]]hs under the [[Sultanate of Brunei]] (a by then tiny but once powerful state entirely enclosed within the borders of Sarawak), and from 1888 as a protectorate of the [[British Empire]]. The northeast of the island comprised [[North Borneo]], since 1882 another British protectorate under the [[British North Borneo Company]]. Offshore lay the small British [[crown colony of Labuan]].

The rest of the island—collectively known as [[Kalimantan]]—was under Dutch control. The Netherlands were invaded by [[Nazi Germany]] in 1940. However, Free Dutch forces—mainly the [[Royal Netherlands Navy]] and the 85,000-strong [[Royal Netherlands East Indies Army]] (KNIL, including a small air service)—fought on, spread throughout the Dutch East Indies, and by December 1941 under an embryonic and somewhat chaotic joint Allied command which became the short-lived [[American-British-Dutch-Australian Command]] (ABDACOM).

The [[Tripartite Pact]]—between the three Axis powers of Germany, Japan and Italy—guaranteed mutual support, and this paid off for Japan in July 1941 when [[Vichy France|French]] weakness in the wake of [[Battle of France|the fall of France]] to Germany allowed Japan to [[Japanese invasion of French Indochina|occupy]] [[French Indo-China]] (now modern [[Vietnam]], [[Laos]] and [[Cambodia]]). This blocked a supply route for the [[Kuomintang]], against whom Japan had been fighting since 1937, the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]]. It also gave Imperial Japan a seaboard facing Sarawak and North Borneo across the China Sea. In December 1941, Japan attacked US possessions in Hawaii and the Philippines, declaring war on the US and finally precipitating Germany's official declaration of war on America, according to the Pact.

With its rich [[petroleum]] exploitation capacity, for instance at [[Battle of Tarakan (1942)|Tarakan]], [[Battle of Balikpapan (1942)|Balikpapan]] and [[Banjarmasin]], Borneo was a prime target for Japan, and a very poorly guarded one. Chronically short of natural resources, Japan needed an assured supply of fuel to achieve its long-term goal of becoming the major power in the Pacific. Borneo also stood on the main sea routes between Java, Sumatra, Malaya and Celebes. Control of these routes were vital to securing the territory.

== Allied order of battle ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2020}}
[[File:ABDACOM-Area.jpg|thumb|right|Map of the [[American-British-Dutch-Australian Command]] (ABDACOM) area, with Borneo just left of centre.]]
=== Defence in Sarawak and North Borneo ===
The main objectives were the oilfields at [[Miri, Malaysia|Miri]] in [[Sarawak]] region and [[Seria]] in [[Brunei]]. The oil was refined at [[Lutong]] near Miri. Despite rich oil supplies, the Sarawak region had no air or sea forces to defend it. Only in late 1940 did [[Air Chief Marshal]] Sir [[Robert Brooke-Popham]] order the 2nd Battalion, [[15th Punjab Regiment]], a heavy 152 mm (6 in) gun battery from the Hong Kong-Singapore Royal Artillery, and a detachment of the 35th Fortress Company (Royal Engineers) to be positioned at [[Kuching]]. They numbered about 1,050 men. In addition, the Brooke White Rajah government also organised the [[The Sarawak Rangers|Sarawak Rangers]]. This force consisted of 1,515 men who were primarily [[Iban people|Iban]] and [[Dayak people|Dayak]] tribesmen. Altogether these forces were commanded by British Lieutenant Colonel C.M. Lane and was known as "SARFOR" (Sarawak Force).

After having heard of the [[attack on Pearl Harbor]], on 8 December 1941, the Brooke government ordered that the oilfields at Miri and Seria and refinery at Lutong be quickly demolished.

=== Defence in Singkawang and Pontianak (Dutch East Indies) ===
The Dutch forces had an important airfield near the border of British Malaysia (Sarawak) called "Singkawang II", which was defended by about 750 Dutch troops. On 25 November, five [[Brewster F2A Buffalo|Brewster 339 Buffalo]] fighter planes arrived for local defence, followed in the beginning of December by [[Martin B-10]] bombers.

The [[Dutch Naval Aviation]] Group GVT-1, with three [[Dornier Do 24]]K [[flying boat]]s, was located in [[Pontianak, Indonesia|Pontianak]] along with a [[KNIL]] garrison, commanded by Lieutenant Colonel Dominicus Mars, numbering approximately 500 men.

Dutch forces in West Borneo consisted of the following units:
* West Borneo KNIL Garrison Battalion
* ''Stadswacht'' Infantry Company (about 125 men) in Pontianak
* Anti-Aircraft Battery (two {{convert|40|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} guns) plus some AA machine-guns
* Mobile Auxiliary First Aid Platoon
* ''Stadswacht'' Detachment (about 50 men) in [[Singkawang]]
* ''Stadswacht'' Detachment (unknown strength) in [[Sintang]]

== Japanese order of battle ==
{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2020}}
The main Japanese force—led by Major General [[Kiyotake Kawaguchi]]—consisted of units from Canton, southern China:
* 35th Infantry Brigade Headquarters
* 124th Infantry Regiment from [[18th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|Japanese 18th Division]]
* 2nd Yokosuka Naval Landing Force
* 4th Naval Construction Unit
* 1 platoon of the 12th Engineer Regiment
* 1 unit from the 18th Division Signal Unit
* 1 unit from the 18th Division Medical Unit
* 4th Field Hospital, 18th Division
* 1 unit from the 11th Water Supply and Purification Unit

== Battle ==
[[Image:Japanese landing off the west coast of British North Borneo, Labuan.jpg|thumb|right|Additional Japanese troops landing off the west coast of British North Borneo in [[Labuan]], 14 January 1942.]]
On 13 December 1941, a Japanese invasion convoy left [[Cam Ranh Bay]] in [[French Indochina]], escorted by the cruiser {{Ship|Japanese cruiser|Yura||2}} (Rear-Admiral Shintaro Hashimoto), the destroyers of the 12th Destroyer Division ({{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Murakumo|1928|2}}, {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Shinonome|1927|2}}, {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Shirakumo|1927|2}} and {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Usugumo|1927|2}}), the submarine chaser [[Japanese submarine chaser CH-7 (1938)|''CH-7'']], and the seaplane tender [[Japanese seaplane tender Kamikawa Maru|''Kamikawa Maru'']]. Ten transport ships ([[Imperial Japanese Army]] transports ''Katori Maru'', ''Hiyoshi Maru'', ''Myoho Maru'', ''Kenkon Maru'', ''Nichiran Maru''; and [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] transports [[Japanese transport ship Hokkai Maru|''Hokkai Maru'']], ''Tonan Maru No 3'', ''Unyo Maru No. 2'', ''Kamikawa Maru'', ''Mitakesan Maru'') carried the Japanese 35th Infantry Brigade HQ under the command of Major-General [[Kiyotake Kawaguchi]]. The Support Force—commanded by Rear-Admiral [[Takeo Kurita]]—consisted of the cruisers {{Ship|Japanese cruiser|Kumano||2}} and {{Ship|Japanese cruiser|Suzuya|1934|2}} and the destroyers {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Fubuki|1927|2}} and {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Sagiri||2}}.

Part of the Japanese force was allocated to capture [[Miri, Malaysia|Miri]] and [[Seria]], while the rest would capture [[Kuching]] and nearby airfields. The convoy escaped detection and, at dawn on 16 December 1941, two landing units secured Miri and Seria, encountering very little resistance from British forces. A few hours later, [[Lutong]] was captured as well.

Dutch Martin B-10 bombers attacked Japanese shipping from their base, 'Singkawang II' at Miri, on 17 December, but their attempt failed. The three [[Dornier Do 24#Variants|Dornier Do 24Ks]] followed up with their own attack, but one was shot down, possibly by a floatplane from ''Kamikawa Maru''.&lt;ref name= cox&gt;{{cite book| last = Cox| first = Jeffrey| title = Rising Sun, Falling Skies: The disastrous Java Sea Campaign of World War II| publisher = Osprey Publishing| edition = illustrated| date = November 2015| pages =| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=SckfAwAAQBAJ&amp;dq=&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s | isbn = 9781472808349}}&lt;/ref&gt; The remaining two, benefiting from cloud cover, were never seen by the Japanese. One flying boat scored two 200&amp;nbsp;kg bomb hits on {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Shinonome|1927|2}}, causing a massive explosion, while a near miss ruptured its hull plating. The destroyer's stern broke off and the ship sank within minutes.&lt;ref name= cox/&gt; The last flying boat dropped its bombs on a freighter, but missed. The B-10 bombers made attacks at Miri 18 and 19 December, but retired to [[Sumatra]] on 23 December since Singkawang II airfield was discovered by the Japanese, who began attacking it the same day.

On 22 December, a Japanese convoy left Miri for [[Kuching]], but was spotted by the Dutch flying boat ''X-35'', which radioed a warning to the Dutch submarine [[HNLMS K XIV|HNLMS ''K XIV'']], under the command of Lieutenant Commander Carel A. J. van Groeneveld. At 20:40 on 23 December, ''K XIV'' infiltrated the convoy and began its attack. The army transports ''Hiyoshi Maru'' and {{SS|Katori Maru|1913|2}} were sunk with the loss of hundreds of troops. ''[[Japanese transport ship Hokkai Maru|Hokkai Maru]]'' was beached to prevent it from sinking, and an additional transport was less seriously damaged.&lt;ref name= cox/&gt; The rest of the troops were able to land. Although 2nd Battalion, [[15th Punjab Regiment]], resisted the attack, they were soon outnumbered and retreated up the river. By the afternoon, Kuching was in Japanese hands.

On the night of 23–24 December, HNLMS ''K XVI'' torpedoed the Japanese destroyer ''Sagiri'' {{convert|30|mi|km}} north of Kuching, becoming the first Allied submarine in the Pacific to sink a warship. ''K XVI'' was lost with all hands during the day by a torpedo from Japanese submarine ''I66''.&lt;ref name= cox/&gt;

On 24 and 28 December, B-10 bombers from a different unit flew missions against Kuching from Singapore, Sembawang. On 26 December, B-10s operating out of [[Samarinda]] sank a Japanese minesweeper and a collier.&lt;ref name= cox/&gt;

Meanwhile, on 31 December 1941, the force under Lieutenant Colonel Watanabe moved northward to occupy [[Brunei]], [[Crown colony of Labuan|Labuan Island]], and Jesselton (now called [[Kota Kinabalu]]). On 18 January 1942, using small fishing boats, the Japanese landed at [[Sandakan]], the seat of government of British [[North Borneo]]. The North Borneo Armed Constabulary, with only 650 men, hardly provided any resistance to slow down the Japanese invasion. On the morning of 19 January, Governor [[Charles Robert Smith]] surrendered British North Borneo and was interned with other staff.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

At about 16:40 on 25 December, Japanese troops successfully captured Kuching airfield. The Punjab regiment retreated through the jungle to the Singkawang area. After Singkawang was secured as well on 29 December, the rest of the British and Dutch troops retreated southward further into the jungle, trying to reach [[Sampit]] and [[Pangkalanbun]], where a Dutch airfield at Kotawaringin was located. South and central [[Kalimantan]] were taken by the Japanese Navy following attacks from east and west. The town of Pontianak was finally occupied by the [[Imperial Japanese Army|Imperial Japanese forces]] on 29 January 1942. After ten weeks in the jungle-covered mountains, Allied troops surrendered on 1 April 1942.{{Citation needed|date=March 2020}}

== References ==
* [[Steven Runciman|Runciman, S.]], ''The White Rajahs: A History of Sarawak from 1841 to 1946'', particularly 252–5. [[Cambridge University Press]], 1960.
* [[Arthur Ernest Percival|Percival, Arthur Ernest]] ''The War in Malaya'', (especially Chapter XII: Operations in Borneo.) London, [[Eyre &amp; Spottiswoode]], 1949.
* L., Klemen, 1999–2000, ''The Netherlands East Indies 1941–42'', "[http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/sarawak.html  The Invasion of British Borneo in 1942]".
* L., Klemen, 1999–2000, ''The Netherlands East Indies 1941–42'', "[http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/sandakan.html  The Japanese occupation of Sandakan, January 1942]".
* [http://www.worldstatesmen.org/Malay_states.htm Governors of North Borneo], [http://worldstatesmen.org./ World Statesmen].

=== Citations ===
&lt;references /&gt;

{{History of East Malaysia}}
{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Borneo (1941-42)}}
[[Category:British Borneo|Battle of Borneo (1941-42)]]
[[Category:British North Borneo|Battle of Borneo (1941-42)]]
[[Category:Dutch East Indies|Battle of Borneo (1941-42)]]
[[Category:British Malaya in World War II|Battle of Borneo (1941-42)]]
[[Category:Indonesia in World War II|Battle of Borneo (1941-42)]]
[[Category:Japanese occupation of the Dutch East Indies|.]]
[[Category:South West Pacific theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Japan|Borneo (1941-42)]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the Netherlands|Borneo (1941-42)]]
[[Category:Land battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Military history of Malaya during World War II]]
[[Category:Wars involving pre-independence Malaysia|Battle of Borneo (1941-42)]]
[[Category:1941 in British Malaya]]
[[Category:1942 in British Malaya]]
[[Category:1941 in the Dutch East Indies]]
[[Category:1942 in the Dutch East Indies]]
[[Category:1941 in the Japanese colonial empire]]
[[Category:1942 in the Japanese colonial empire]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1941]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:History of Borneo|Battle of Borneo (1941-42)]]
[[Category:History of Brunei|Battle of Borneo (1941-42)]]
[[Category:History of North Borneo|Battle of Borneo (1941-42)]]
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Pacific theatre]]
[[Category:December 1941 events]]
[[Category:January 1942 events]]
[[Category:February 1942 events]]
[[Category:March 1942 events]]</text><sha1>lo5qlwogzpphhcd7yi12yyjzhj6vlsd</sha1></revision></page>