<page><title>Battle of Balikpapan (1942)</title><ns>0</ns><id>8043332</id><revision><id>965791889</id><parentid>965738349</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-03T12:52:33Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Deacon Vorbis</username><id>29330520</id></contributor><minor /><comment>mass rollback of a large number of inappropriate image additions by Joy Ayara; see their talk page for more details</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="11867" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=First Battle of Balikpapan
|image=
|caption=
|partof=[[World War II]], [[Pacific War]]
|date=23–24 January 1942
|place=[[Balikpapan]], [[Borneo]]
|result=Japanese land victory&lt;br&gt;Allied tactical naval victory
|combatant1={{flag|Netherlands}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United States|1912}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
|commander1={{flagicon|Netherlands}} Cornelis van den Hoogenband&lt;hr&gt;{{nowrap|{{flagdeco|United States|1912}} [[William A. Glassford]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |first=Klemen |last=L |url=http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/glassford.html |title=Rear-Admiral William A. Glassford, Jr. |date=1999–2000 |work=Forgotten Campaign: The Dutch East Indies Campaign 1941–1942 |access-date=2011-07-13 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120522044839/http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/glassford.html |archive-date=2012-05-22 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|United States|1912}} [[P. H. Talbot|Paul H. Talbot]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Empire of Japan}} Shizuo Sakaguchi&lt;ref name="sakaguchi-DEI"&gt;{{cite web| last = Klemen |first = L |url= http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/sakaguchi.html |title=Major-General Shizuo Sakaguchi |date=1999–2000|work= Forgotten Campaign: The Dutch East Indies Campaign 1941–1942}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;hr&gt;{{flagicon|Empire of Japan|naval}} [[Shoji Nishimura]]&lt;ref name="nishimura-DEI"&gt;{{cite web|last = Klemen |first = L |url= http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/nishimura.html |title= Rear-Admiral Shoji Nishimura |date=1999–2000 |work=Forgotten Campaign: The Dutch East Indies Campaign 1941–1942}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|strength1=1,100 infantry&lt;br&gt;4 destroyers&lt;br&gt;1 submarine&lt;br&gt;29 aircraft
|strength2=5,500 infantry&lt;br&gt;1,100 naval infantry&lt;br&gt;3 patrol boats&lt;br&gt;12 transport ships
|casualties1=unknown&lt;br&gt;1 destroyer lightly damaged&lt;br&gt;1 submarine heavily damaged
|casualties2=unknown&lt;br&gt;50+ naval casualties&lt;br&gt;1 patrol boat sunk&lt;br&gt;6 transports sunk
}}
{{Campaignbox Netherlands East Indies}}
{{Campaignbox Pacific 1941}}

''This article concerns the naval and land battles of Balikpapan in 1942. For information on the 1945 landings by Australian forces in the same area, see [[Battle of Balikpapan (1945)|Second Battle of Balikpapan]].''

The '''First Battle of Balikpapan''' took place on 23–24 January 1942, off the major [[petroleum|oil]] producing town and port of [[Balikpapan]], on [[Borneo]], in the [[Netherlands East Indies]]. After capturing the destroyed oilfield at [[Tarakan Island|Tarakan]] from the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] in the [[Battle of Tarakan (1942)|Battle of Tarakan]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last = Klemen |first = L |url = http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/tarakan.html |title = The capture of Tarakan Island, January 1942 |date = 1999–2000 |work = Forgotten Campaign: The Dutch East Indies Campaign 1941–1942 |url-status = dead |archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20110726052724/http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/tarakan.html |archivedate = 2011-07-26 }}&lt;/ref&gt; the [[Empire of Japan|Japanese]] force—the Sakaguchi Detachment (named for its commander, [[Major General]] [[Shizuo Sakaguchi]])&lt;ref name="sakaguchi-DEI"/&gt;-moved on to Balikpapan with the hope that the oilfields there had not been destroyed.

In the ensuing conflict, the Japanese successfully landed and seized the oil facilities. A short time later an American destroyer task force ambushed the Japanese invasion convoy and sank multiple transports.

==Background==
The Dutch army in Balikpapan numbered approximately 1,100 troops, under the command of [[KNIL]] [[Lieutenant Colonel]] [[Cornelis van den Hoogenband]].&lt;ref name="balikpapan-DEI"&gt;{{cite web|last = Klemen |first = L |url= http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/balikpapan.html |title= The capture of Balikpapan, January 1942 |date=1999–2000|work= Forgotten Campaign: The Dutch East Indies Campaign 1941–1942}}&lt;/ref&gt; The city itself was protected by coast, anti-aircraft, and field batteries. The entrance of the harbor was protected by a minefield laid by the minelayer ''Soemenep'' under the command of Lt. T. Jellema.&lt;ref name="balikpapan-DEI"/&gt;

On 18 January, the Dutch commander ordered the destruction of oil installations in Balikpapan and started to evacuate his staff to [[Samarinda]]. However, the destruction was not complete; the only serious damage was to tanks, pipes and special quays in the harbor area.&lt;ref name="balikpapan-DEI"/&gt;

==Battle==

===Land engagement===
On 22 January, the Japanese fleet was sighted moving south by an American [[Consolidated PBY Catalina|PBY flying boat]], and on 23 January formations of Dutch bombers attacked the convoy. Despite this, the Japanese unit successfully landed approximately {{convert|5|km|mi|abbr=on}} southeast of Balikpapan airfield on the evening of 24 January. The assault unit landed without meeting enemy resistance and, by dawn, had occupied the airfield. The southward advance moved slowly as the bridges had been destroyed, and the unit reached the northern outskirts of Balikpapan City on the night of 25 January. The Dutch garrison troops had been withdrawn and the Japanese entered the city without a fight.&lt;ref name="balikpapan-DEI"/&gt;

A portion of the Sakaguchi Detachment called the Surprise Attack Unit proceeded up the river in camouflaged landing craft, evaded detection, and landed just south of the reservoir at 04:30 on the 25th. It proceeded to the village of Banoeabaroe, arriving there at 14:40, thus cutting off the Dutch line of retreat. While the unit was advancing along the road to Balikpapan City, it ran into a Dutch military column, commanded by Lieutenant Colonel C. van den Hoogenband, attempting to escape from Balikpapan. After defeating this Dutch column, the Surprise Attack Unit proceeded to Balikpapan City.&lt;ref name="balikpapan-DEI"/&gt;

After Balikpapan was occupied, a new detachment was formed led by Lt. Col. Kume. He was ordered to secure and protect the oil fields. The main force moved forward along the Balikpapan City-Samboaja-Sangasanga-Samarinda-Road, mopping up the remaining Dutch troops in the vicinity of Samarinda.&lt;ref name="balikpapan-DEI"/&gt;

===Naval Engagement===
[[File:Brewster B-339 Buffalo.jpg|thumb|Replica Brewster B339C. The Dutch used the fighter also as a light dive bomber against Japanese convoys.]]
In the afternoon of 23 January, nine Dutch [[Martin B-10]] bombers, escorted by 20 [[Brewster F2A Buffalo|Brewster Buffaloes]] from [[2-VLG-V (ML-KNIL)|2-VLG-V]] and [[3-VLG-V (ML-KNIL)|3-VLG-V]], attacked the Japanese convoy. The transport ship ''Tatsugami Maru'' was damaged and {{ship|MS|Nana Maru||2}} sunk. Near Balikpapan, the Dutch submarine {{HNLMS|K XVIII||6}}, under [[Lieutenant Commander]] van Well Groeneveld, attacked and sank the transport ''Tsuruga Maru'' and reportedly damaged the patrol boat ''P-37'' by midnight, but was later heavily damaged itself by depth charges and forced to withdraw to [[Surabaya]].&lt;ref name="dutchsubmarines.com"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.dutchsubmarines.com/boats/boat_kxviii.htm|title=Dutch Submarines: The submarine K XVIII|work=dutchsubmarines.com|accessdate=17 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

While the Japanese invasion force was landing at Balikpapan, on the early morning of 24 January, at around 02:45, the 59th U.S. Navy Destroyer Division under [[Rear Admiral]] [[William A. Glassford]] and [[Commander]] [[P. H. Talbot|Paul H. Talbot]], acting on orders from [[Thomas C. Hart|Admiral Hart]], attacked the Japanese navy escort led by Rear Admiral [[Shoji Nishimura]] for about four hours.&lt;ref name="PacWar"&gt;Costello (1981), p. 191.&lt;/ref&gt; The U.S. Destroyer Division composed of {{USS|Paul Jones|DD-230|6}}, {{USS|Parrott|DD-218|2}}, {{USS|Pope|DD-225|2}} and {{USS|John D. Ford|DD-228|2}} attacked the twelve transport ships and the three patrol boats (World War I-era destroyers) escorting them. The Japanese destroyer escorts were undertaking a search for the Dutch submarine which had been sighted earlier.&lt;ref name="PacWar"/&gt; At least four transport ships—''Kuretake Maru'',  ''Nana Maru'', ''Sumanoura Maru'' and ''Tatsukami Maru''—and patrol boat ''P-37'' were sunk in torpedo attacks. Two other transports were damaged by gunfire or torpedoes.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|first=Dan |last=Muir |url= http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/BalikpapanRaid.html |title=The Balikpapan Raid |date=1999–2000 |work=Forgotten Campaign: The Dutch East Indies Campaign 1941–1942}}&lt;/ref&gt; Gunfire from one of the armed transports damaged the ''John D. Ford''. The ''Ford'' returned fire, inflicting 50 casualties on the transport.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title= World War II at Sea: An Encyclopedia|editor-last1= Tucker|editor-first1= Spencer| last = O'Hara| first = Vincent P.| publisher = ABC-CLIO| volume = 1| edition = illustrated, reprint| date = 30 November 2011| pages = 81-83| url = https://books.google.com/books?id=N0nrSWUHx6sC&amp;dq=&amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s| isbn = 9781598844573}}&lt;/ref&gt; At 04:00 the ''Ford'' withdrew.

==Aftermath==

=== Analyses ===
The battle was the first surface engagement in Southeast Asia that the U.S. Navy had participated in since the [[Battle of Manila Bay (1898)|Battle of Manila Bay]] in 1898.&lt;ref name="PacWar"/&gt; The American destroyers expended all of their torpedoes with only a few hits, mostly because of the as yet unrealized problems with the [[Mark 15 torpedo]] running too deep.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=mszT93YXPFMC&amp;pg=PA91 |pages=91–92 |last=Roscoe |first=Theodore |title=United States Destroyer Operations in World War II |publisher=Naval Institute Press |year=1953 |isbn=0870217267}}&lt;/ref&gt; Because the landing had taken place around 21:30, the raid was too late to stop the capture of Balikpapan.&lt;ref name="balikpapan-DEI"/&gt;

While the various attacks on the Japanese transports did little to prevent the fall of Balikpapan, it proved that Admiral Hart's conservative strategy could be effectively used against Japanese forces until Allied forces in the Southeast Asia area could be bolstered.&lt;ref name="krex.k-state.edu"&gt;Jeffrey C. Nelson. (1994).  [http://krex.k-state.edu/dspace/bitstream/handle/2097/13618/JeffreyNelson2012.pdf?sequence=1 ABDACOM: AMERICA’S FIRST COALITION EXPERIENCE IN WORLD WAR II]&lt;/ref&gt; It was under his orders that the destroyers conducted the raid and sank the four transports. Crucial to the success of the destroyer raid was also the fact that it had been conducted by an all American force, operating under the same doctrine and protocol, whereas other [[ABDACOM]] engagements of combined forces (the [[Battle of the Java Sea]], notably) suffered from much confusion.&lt;ref name="krex.k-state.edu"/&gt; Hart was later relieved of command and replaced with the much bolder [[Conrad Helfrich]].

Balikpapan remained under Japanese control until July 1945, when the Japanese force was defeated by an Australian-led force in the [[Battle of Balikpapan (1945)|1945 Battle of Balikpapan]].

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
*Costello, John (2002), "The Pacific War", Perennial – [[HarperCollins]], {{ISBN|0-688-01620-0}}
* {{cite web|first=Klemen|last=L |url= http://www.dutcheastindies.webs.com/index.html |title= Forgotten Campaign: The Dutch East Indies Campaign 1941–1942 |date=1999–2000}}

{{Coord|1|14|46|S|116|49|18|E|display=title|region:ID_type:event}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Balikpapan (1942)}}
[[Category:South West Pacific theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the Netherlands|Balikpapan (1942)]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the Netherlands]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Japan|Balikpapan (1942)]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United States|Balikpapan (1942)]]
[[Category:Japanese occupation of the Dutch East Indies]]
[[Category:1942 in Japan]]
[[Category:1942 in the Dutch East Indies]]
[[Category:January 1942 events]]</text><sha1>qb9kbftqd4tmsnzni4aihfkidrui7ah</sha1></revision></page>