<page><title>Attack on Sydney Harbour</title><ns>0</ns><id>3232610</id><revision><id>965972803</id><parentid>964650110</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-04T14:52:19Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Siegfried Nugent</username><id>11450424</id></contributor><comment>/* Aftermath */ contemporary news reports give the location as Eastern Suburbs Crematorium, not Rookwood</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="70793" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|World War II attack by Japan}}
{{Use Australian English|date=March 2013}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2020}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Attack on Sydney Harbour
| partof      = the [[Axis naval activity in Australian waters]] during World War II
| image       = Ko-hyoteki Sydney.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = A Japanese ''Ko-hyoteki'' class midget submarine, believed to be midget No. 14, is raised from Sydney Harbour the day after the attack.
| date        = 31 May – 8 June 1942
| place       = [[Port Jackson|Sydney Harbour]], [[Sydney]], [[Australia]]
| result      = Indecisive
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Australia}} &lt;br&gt; {{flagcountry|United States|1912}} &lt;br&gt; {{flagcountry|United Kingdom}} &lt;br&gt; {{flagdeco|Netherlands}} [[Dutch government-in-exile|Netherlands]] &lt;br&gt; {{flagcountry|British India}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
| commander1  = {{flagdeco|UK|naval}} [[Gerard Muirhead-Gould|Gerard Muirhead]]
| commander2  = {{flagdeco|Empire of Japan|naval}} [[Hankyu Sasaki]]
| strength1   = 2 heavy cruisers &lt;br&gt; 1 light cruiser &lt;br&gt; 2 merchant cruisers &lt;br&gt; 2 destroyers &lt;br&gt; 3 corvettes &lt;br&gt; 2 submarine chasers &lt;br&gt; 1 submarine &lt;br&gt; 6 patrol boats &lt;br&gt; 1 depot ship
| strength2   = 5 submarines &lt;br&gt; 3 midget submarines &lt;br&gt; 2 seaplanes
| casualties1 = 71 killed &lt;br&gt; 10 wounded &lt;br&gt; 1 depot ship sunk &lt;br&gt; 1 airplane destroyed &lt;br&gt; 3 merchantmen sunk&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Nichols|first=Robert|title=Sydney Under Attack: Japanese Midget Submarine 31 May – 1 June 1942 |url=http://www.awm.gov.au/atwar/remembering1942/midget_submarine/transcript.asp |work=Remembering 1942 |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=9 February 2014 |date=31 May 2002}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = 6 killed &lt;br&gt; 2 midget submarines sunk &lt;br&gt; 1 midget submarine scuttled &lt;br&gt; 2 seaplanes destroyed
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox South West Pacific}} &lt;br&gt; {{Axis naval attacks on Australia}}
}}

In late May and early June 1942, during [[World War II]], [[Imperial Japanese Navy submarines|submarines belonging to the Imperial Japanese Navy]] made a series of attacks on the cities of [[Sydney]] and [[Newcastle, New South Wales|Newcastle]] in [[New South Wales]], Australia. On the night of 31 May – 1 June, three [[Ko-hyoteki class submarine|''Ko-hyoteki''-class]] [[midget submarine]]s, (M-14, M-21 and M-24) each with a two-member crew, entered [[Sydney Harbour]], avoided the partially constructed [[Sydney Harbour anti-submarine boom net]], and attempted to sink Allied warships. Two of the midget submarines were detected and attacked before they could engage any Allied vessels. The crew of M-14 [[scuttling|scuttled]] their submarine, whilst m-21 was successfully attacked and sunk. The crew of M-21 killed themselves. These submarines were later recovered by the Allies. The third submarine attempted to torpedo the heavy cruiser {{USS|Chicago|CA-29|6}}, but instead sank the converted ferry {{HMAS|Kuttabul|ship|6}}, killing 21 sailors. This midget submarine's fate was unknown until 2006, when amateur scuba divers discovered the wreck off [[Northern Beaches (Sydney)|Sydney's northern beaches]].

Immediately following the raid, the five Japanese fleet submarines that carried the midget submarines to Australia embarked on a campaign to disrupt merchant shipping in eastern Australian waters. Over the next month, the submarines attacked at least seven merchant vessels, sinking three ships and killing 50 sailors. During this period, between midnight and 02:30 on 8 June, two of the submarines bombarded the ports of Sydney and Newcastle.

The midget submarine attacks and subsequent bombardments are among the best-known examples of [[Axis naval activity in Australian waters]] during World War II, and are the only occasion in history when either city has come under attack. The physical effects were slight: the Japanese had intended to destroy several major warships, but sank only an unarmed depot ship and failed to damage any significant targets during the bombardments. The main impact was psychological; creating popular fear of an impending [[Proposed Japanese invasion of Australia during World War II|Japanese invasion]] and forcing the Australian military to upgrade defences, including the commencement of [[Convoy#Naval convoys|convoy]] operations to protect merchant shipping.

==Forces==
[[File:Midget submarine crews (AWM P00325-001).jpg|thumb|left|The crews of the Japanese midget submarines that attacked Sydney and [[Antsiranana|Diego Suarez]]]]

===Japanese===
The [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] originally intended to use six submarines in the attack on Sydney Harbour: [[B1 type submarine|B1-type]] submarines {{Ship|Japanese submarine|I-21||2}}, {{Ship|Japanese submarine|I-27||2}}, {{Ship|Japanese submarine|I-28||2}}, and {{Ship|Japanese submarine|I-29||2}}, and [[Type C submarine|C1-type]] submarines {{Ship|Japanese submarine|I-22|1938|2}} and {{Ship|Japanese submarine|I-24|1939|2}}.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|161}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.combinedfleet.com/type_b1.htm |title=Type B1 |accessdate=7 August 2007 |publisher=CombinedFleet.com| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070814042329/http://www.combinedfleet.com/type_b1.htm| archivedate= 14 August 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.combinedfleet.com/type_c1.htm |title=Type C1 |accessdate=7 August 2007 |publisher=CombinedFleet.com| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070814042203/http://www.combinedfleet.com/type_c1.htm| archivedate= 14 August 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; The six submarines made up the Eastern Attack Group of the [[8th Submarine Squadron (Imperial Japanese Navy)|8th Submarine Squadron]], under the command of Captain [[Hankyu Sasaki]].{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|161}}{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|59}}

On 8 June 1942, ''I-21'' and ''I-29''—each carrying a [[Yokosuka E14Y]]1 "Glen" [[floatplane]] for aerial reconnaissance—scouted various [[Australasia]]n harbours to select the ones most vulnerable to attack by midget submarines.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|61}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|163}} ''I-21'' scouted [[Nouméa|Nouméa in New Caledonia]], [[Suva|Suva in Fiji]], then [[Auckland|Auckland in New Zealand]], while ''I-29'' went to Sydney, Australia.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|162}}

On 11 May, ''I-22'', ''I-24'', ''I-27'', and ''I-28'' were ordered to proceed to the Japanese naval base at [[Chuuk State|Truk Lagoon]], in the [[Caroline Islands]], to each receive a [[Ko-hyoteki class submarine|''Ko-hyoteki''-class midget submarine]].{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|61}} ''I-28'' failed to reach Truk; she was torpedoed on the surface by the US submarine {{USS|Tautog|SS-199|6}} on 17 May.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|61–62}} The three remaining submarines left Truk around 20 May for a point south of the [[Solomon Islands]].{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|62}} ''I-24'' was forced to return a day later when an explosion in her midget submarine's battery compartment killed the midget's navigator and injured the commander.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|164}} The midget submarine intended for ''I-28'' replaced the damaged midget.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|164}}

===Allies===
[[File:USS Chicago (P00279-004).jpg|thumb|USS ''Chicago'' in Sydney Harbour on 31 May 1942]]

The naval officer-in-charge of Sydney Harbour at the time of the attack was [[Rear Admiral]] [[Gerard Muirhead-Gould]] of the Royal Navy.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|30}} On the night of the attack, three major vessels were present in Sydney Harbour; the [[heavy cruiser]]s {{USS|Chicago|CA-29|6}} and {{HMAS|Canberra|D33|6}}, and the [[light cruiser]] {{HMAS|Adelaide|1918|6}}.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|193–94}} Other warships in the harbour included: destroyer tender {{USS|Dobbin|AD-3|6}}, auxiliary minelayer {{HMAS|Bungaree||6}}, corvettes {{HMAS|Whyalla|J153|6}}, {{HMAS|Geelong|J201|6}}, and {{HMIS|Bombay|1941|6}}, armed merchant cruisers {{HMS|Kanimbla||6}} and {{HMAS|Westralia|1939|6}}, and Dutch submarine [[HMAS K9|''K-IX'']].{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|193–94}} A converted ferry—HMAS ''Kuttabul''—was alongside at [[Garden Island, New South Wales|Garden Island]] where she served as a temporary barracks for sailors transferring between ships.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|143}} The [[MS Oranje|hospital ship ''Oranje'']] had also been in the harbour, but departed an hour before the attack.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|190}}

==Harbour defences==
At the time of the attack, the static [[Sydney Harbour defences]] consisted of eight [[anti-submarine indicator loop]]s—six outside the harbour, one between [[North Heads|North Head]] and [[South Head, New South Wales|South Head]], and one between South Head and [[Sydney Heads#Middle Head|Middle Head]], as well as the partially constructed [[Sydney Harbour anti-submarine boom net]] between George's Head on Middle Head and Laing Point (formerly known as Green Point) on Inner South Head.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|65}}{{sfn|Stevens, ''A Critical Vulnerability''}}{{rp|192–94}} The central section of the net was complete and support piles were in place to the west, but {{convert|400|m|ft|abbr=on}} wide gaps remained on either side.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|65}}{{sfn|Stevens, ''A Critical Vulnerability''}}{{rp|193}} Material shortages prevented the completion of the boom net prior to the attack.{{sfn|Stevens, ''A Critical Vulnerability''}}{{rp|194}} On the day of the attack, the six outer indicator loops were inactive; two were not functioning and there were not enough trained personnel to man both the inner and outer loop monitoring stations.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|6}}{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|177}} The North Head&amp;nbsp;– South Head indicator loop had been giving faulty signals since early 1940, and as civilian traffic regularly passed over the loop, readings were often ignored.{{sfn|Fullford, ''We Stood And Waited''}}{{rp|190}}

Harbour defence craft included the anti-submarine vessels {{HMAS|Yandra}} and ''Bingera''; the auxiliary minesweepers HMAS ''Goonambee'' and {{HMAS|Samuel Benbow||2}}; pleasure [[Launch (boat)|launches]] converted to channel patrol boats (and armed with [[depth charge]]s), namely {{HMAS|Yarroma}}, ''Lolita'', ''Steady Hour'', {{HMAS|Sea Mist||2}}, ''Marlean'', and {{HMAS|Toomaree||2}}; and four unarmed Naval Auxiliary Patrol boats.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|66}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|194}}

==Prelude==
[[File:Fujita&amp;Glen.jpg|thumb|[[Nobuo Fujita]] with a plane of the type he flew over Sydney on 17 February 1942. The seaplanes aboard ''I-29'' and ''I-21'' were of the same type.]]

The Japanese Navy used five ''Ko-hyoteki''-class midget submarines in an unsuccessful operation against US battleships during the [[attack on Pearl Harbor]]. The navy hoped that upgrades to the submarines, intensified crew training, and the selection of a less well defended target would lead to better results and an increased chance of the crews of the midgets to return alive from their mission.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|58}} Therefore, on 16 December 1941, the navy initiated plans for a second midget submarine operation.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|58}}

The plans called for two simultaneous attacks against Allied naval vessels in the [[Indian Ocean|Indian]] and South Pacific oceans.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|59}} These attacks were intended as diversions ahead of the [[Battle of Midway|attack on Midway Island]] in the North Pacific, with the Japanese hoping to convince the Allies that they intended to attack to the south or west of their conquests.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Morison |first=Samuel Eliot |authorlink=Samuel Eliot Morison |title= History of United States Naval Operations in World War II. Volume 4. Coral Sea, Midway and Submarine Actions. May 1942 – August 1942 |origyear=1949 |year=2001 |publisher=[[University of Illinois Press]] |location=Champaign, Illinois |isbn=0-252-06995-1 |page=68}}&lt;/ref&gt; Eleven submarines of the 8th Submarine Squadron were to carry out the two attacks, the five submarines of the Western Attack Group in the Indian Ocean, and the six submarines of the Eastern Attack Group in the Pacific Ocean.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|194}} The submarine groups were to select a suitable port of attack, based on their own reconnaissance.

The Western Attack Group selected the port of [[Antsiranana|Diégo-Suarez]] in [[French Madagascar|Madagascar]].{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|162}} This attack—which occurred at nightfall on 30 May and resulted in the damaging of the battleship {{HMS|Ramillies|07|6}} and the sinking of the tanker ''British Loyalty''—came 22 days after the British captured the port from [[Vichy France]] at the beginning of the [[Battle of Madagascar]].{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|65}}

The four potential targets for the Eastern Attack Group were Nouméa, Suva, Auckland, and Sydney.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|163}} Identified by reconnaissance flights conducted by Warrant Flying Officer Nobuo Fujita of the Imperial Japanese Navy flying from ''I-25''; commencing 17 February over Sydney Harbour, and the eastern Australian harbours of Melbourne and Hobart (1 March), followed by the New Zealand harbours of Wellington (8 March) and Auckland (13 March).{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|130–48}} ''I-21'' and ''I-29'' were sent to select the final target, with ''I-29'' sailing to Sydney.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|65}} On the evening of 16 May, ''I-29'' fired on the {{convert|5135|LT|t|lk=on|abbr=on}} Soviet merchant vessel ''Wellen'', {{convert|30|mi|nmi km|abbr=on}} from [[Newcastle, New South Wales]].{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|65}} Although ''Wellen'' escaped with minimal damage, shipping between Sydney and Newcastle was halted for 24 hours while aircraft and all available anti-submarine ships from Sydney, including Dutch light cruiser [[HNLMS Tromp (1937)|HNLMS ''Tromp'']], Australian destroyer {{HMAS|Arunta|I30|6}} and US destroyer {{USS|Perkins|DD-377|6}}, searched unsuccessfully for the submarine.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|62}} Muirhead-Gould concluded that the submarine had operated alone and had left the area immediately after the attack.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|87}}

''I-29''{{'}}s floatplane made a reconnaissance flight over Sydney on 23 May.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|62}} A secret radar unit set up in [[Iron Cove (New South Wales)|Iron Cove]] detected the flight, but authorities dismissed its report as a glitch, as there were no Allied aircraft operating over Sydney.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|63–64}} The aircraft was damaged or destroyed on landing, although its two crew survived.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|64}} They reported the presence of several [[capital ship]]s, including two battleships or large cruisers, five other large warships, several minor war vessels and patrol boats, and prolific merchant shipping.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|170–71}} The report, which the Allied [[FRUMEL]] [[signals intelligence]] network partially intercepted, resulted in the Japanese Navy selecting Sydney as the target.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|170–71}}{{sfn|Stevens, ''A Critical Vulnerability''}}{{rp|192}} The three midget-carrying submarines rendezvoused with ''I-29'' and ''I-21'' approximately {{convert|35|mi|nmi km|abbr=on}} north-east of [[Sydney Heads]], with all five submarines in position by 29 May.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|64}}

==Midget submarine operation==

===Final reconnaissance===
Before dawn on 29 May,{{efn-ur|Some sources give the date of the reconnaissance flight as 30 May}} ''I-21''{{'}}s floatplane, piloted by Ito Susumu,&lt;ref name=Dulhunty&gt;{{cite book|last=Dunhunty|first=Philip|title=Never a Dull Moment|publisher=Philip Dulhunty|date=2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|340}} performed a final reconnaissance flight over Sydney Harbour, with the mission of mapping the locations of the major vessels and of the anti-submarine net.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|71}}{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|87}} Multiple observers spotted the floatplane but assumed it was a US Navy [[Curtiss SOC Seagull|Curtiss Seagull]].{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|64}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|189–93}} No alarm was raised until 05:07, when it was realised that the only ship in the area carrying Seagulls was the U.S. cruiser ''Chicago'', and all four of her aircraft were on board.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|64}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|189–93}} [[RAAF Base Richmond|Richmond Air Force Base]] launched [[Royal Australian Air Force|RAAF]] [[CAC Wirraway|Wirraway]] fighters, which failed to locate ''I-21'' or the floatplane.{{sfn|Stevens, ''A Critical Vulnerability''}}{{rp|193}} Therefore, the reconnaissance flight did not result in the authorities in Sydney taking any special defence measures.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|64}} The floatplane was seriously damaged on landing and had to be scuttled, but both aircrew survived.{{sfn|Stevens, ''A Critical Vulnerability''}}{{rp|192}}

===Plan of attack===
The Japanese planned to launch the midgets one after the other between 17:20 and 17:40, from points {{convert|5|-|7|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}} outside Sydney Harbour.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|205}} The first midget was to pass through the Heads just after 18:30, but heavy seas delayed her by over an hour.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|205}} The other two midgets followed at twenty-minute intervals and were similarly delayed.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|205}}

The choice of targets was left up to the midget commanders, with advice that they should primarily target aircraft carriers or battleships, with cruisers as secondary targets.&lt;ref name= Sasaki&gt;Sasaki, ''Telegraphic Order 3''. (Reproduced in {{harvnb|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|66}})&lt;/ref&gt; The midgets were to operate to the east of the Harbour Bridge, although if no suitable targets were to be found in this area they were to move under the Bridge and attack a battleship and large cruiser believed to be in the inner harbour.&lt;ref name=Sasaki/&gt; When the second reconnaissance flyover revealed that the expected British battleship—{{HMS|Warspite|03|6}}—was nowhere to be found, USS ''Chicago'' became the priority target.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|75,79}}

After completing their mission, the midgets were to depart Sydney Harbour and head south for {{convert|20|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}} to the recovery point off Port Hacking.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|79}} Four of the mother submarines would be waiting in an east–west line {{convert|16|km|nmi mi|abbr=on}} long, with the fifth waiting {{convert|6|km|nmi mi|abbr=on}} further south.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|79}}

===Attack===
Midget submarine ''M-14''—launched from ''I-27''—was the first to enter Sydney Harbour.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|67}} The Middle Head&amp;nbsp;– South Head loop detected it at 20:01, but dismissed the reading due to heavy civilian traffic.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|206}} At 20:15, a Maritime Services Board watchman spotted the midget after it passed through the western gap, collided with the Pile Light, then reversed and trapped its stern in the net.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|105}} The submarine's bow broke the surface; the watchman rowed toward it to determine what it was and then rowed to the nearby patrol boat {{HMAS|Yarroma}} to report his finding.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|106}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|208}} Despite efforts by ''Yarroma'' to pass on this information, Sydney Naval Headquarters did not receive the report until 21:52.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|208}}{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|108}} HMAS ''Yarroma'' and {{illm|HMAS Lolita{{!}}''Lolita''|pl|HMAS Lolita}} were dispatched to investigate.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|208}} Upon confirming that the object in the net was a "baby submarine", ''Lolita'' dropped two [[depth charge]]s while ''Yarroma''{{'}}s commander requested permission from Sydney Naval Headquarters to open fire.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|115}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|209}} The depth charges failed to detonate, as the water was too shallow for the hydrostatic fuse setting.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|209}} At 22:35, while ''Yarroma'' was waiting for permission to fire, and ''Lolita'' was setting up to deploy a third depth charge, the two crewmen on ''M-14'' activated one of the submarine's scuttling charges, killing themselves and destroying the submarine's forward section.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|209}}{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|116–17}}

Muirhead-Gould gave the general alarm, along with orders for ships to take anti-submarine measures, at 22:27; the alarm was repeated at 22:36 with advice for ships to take precautions against attack, as an enemy submarine might be in the harbour.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|210}}{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|119}} At the time of the first alarm, Sydney Harbour was closed to external traffic, but Muirhead-Gould ordered ferries and other internal traffic to continue, as he believed that having multiple ships travelling around at speed would help force any submarines to remain submerged.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|119}}

Midget submarine ''M-24''{{efn-ur|As this midget submarine was the only one not recovered, its specific designation is unknown, and is referred to differently in the various sources. Gill refers to it as ''Midget A'', Jenkins identifies it as ''Ban's midget'' (after the midget's commander, Sub–Lieutenant Katsuhisa Ban), and Carruthers uses ''I-24'', naming it after the mother submarine. Numerous sources discussing the 2005 and 2006 findings (such as newspaper articles) refer to it as ''M-24'' or ''M24''. This article uses the ''M-24'' designation for consistency with the identified midget submarines and to avoid confusion with the mother submarine.}} was the second to enter the harbour. [[Falie|HMAS ''Falie'']] grazed ''M-24''{{'}}s hull and reported the contact to command.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Rickard |first=Dave |title=Is the Falie Finished? |journal=Afloat |issue=229 |date=8 November 2008 |url=http://www.afloat.com.au/afloat-magazine/2008/november-2008/Is_Failie_Finished |access-date=1 December 2008 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120211152825/http://www.afloat.com.au/afloat-magazine/2008/november-2008/Is_Failie_Finished |archive-date=11 February 2012 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; The report was not followed up. ''M-24'' crossed the indicator loop undetected at 21:48, and at approximately 22:00 followed a Manly ferry through the anti-submarine net.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|67}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|210}} At 22:52, ''M-24'' was spotted by a ''Chicago'' searchlight operator less than {{convert|500|m|ft|abbr=on}} to the moored cruiser's starboard, and on a course roughly parallel to the ship's facing.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|210}}{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|123}} ''Chicago'' opened fire with a {{convert|5|in|mm|abbr=on}} gun and a quadruple machinegun mount, but inflicted minimal damage as the weapons could not [[wikt:depress|depress]] far enough.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|211}} Some of the {{convert|5|in|mm|abbr=on}} shells [[Stone skipping|skipped off the water]] and hit [[Fort Denison]]'s [[Martello tower]], while fragments were later found in the suburbs of [[Cremorne, New South Wales|Cremorne]] and [[Mosman, New South Wales|Mosman]].{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|125}} The senior officer present aboard ''Chicago'' ordered the crew to begin preparing for departure, and for USS ''Perkins'' to begin an anti-submarine screening patrol around the cruiser, orders that were revoked by the sceptical Captain Howard Bode when he arrived on board at around 23:30.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|127, 133}}

{{HMAS|Whyalla|J153|6}} and {{HMAS|Geelong|J201|2}} also fired upon ''M-24'' as it fled west toward the [[Sydney Harbour Bridge]], before the midget was able to submerge and escape.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|212}} When it returned to periscope depth, the midget found itself west of [[Fort Denison]].{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|212}} It turned and sailed east for about {{convert|1|nmi|mi km|abbr=on}}, then took up a firing position south-west of [[Bradley's Head (New South Wales)|Bradley's Head]], from where its commander could see ''Chicago''{{'}}s stern silhouetted against the construction floodlights at Garden Island's new Captain Cook Graving Dock.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|212–14}}

Midget submarine ''M-21''—from ''I-22''—probably entered the harbour at the same time that USS ''Chicago'' opened fire on ''M-24''.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|68}} The unarmed Naval Auxiliary Patrol boat ''Lauriana'' (later commissioned HMAS ''Lauriana'') spotted ''M-21'' and illuminated the submarine's conning tower, while sending an alert signal to the Port War Signal Station at South Head, and the nearby anti-submarine vessel HMAS ''Yandra''.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|68}} ''Yandra'' attempted to ram the submarine, lost contact, regained contact at 23:03, and fired a full pattern of six depth charges.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|last=Carruthers|title=Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942|publisher=Casper Publications|year=2006|isbn=0977506304|location=|pages=133}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|213}} At the time of the attack, it was assumed that the depth charges had destroyed or disabled the midget, but ''M-21'' survived.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|213}} Historians believe that the midget took refuge on the harbour floor and waited until the Allied vessels had moved away before it resumed the attack.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|213}}

At 23:14, Muirhead-Gould ordered all ships to observe [[blackout (wartime)|blackout]] conditions.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|213–14}} Just after 23:30, he set off on a barge towards the boom net, to make a personal inspection.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|135}} The Admiral reached ''Lolita'' at about midnight and indicated to her crew that he did not take the reports of enemy submarines seriously, reportedly saying: "What are you all playing at, running up and down the harbour dropping depth charges and talking about enemy subs in the harbour? There's not one to be seen."{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|135}} The crew reiterated that a submarine had been seen, but Muirhead-Gould remained unconvinced and before he left, added sarcastically: "If you see another sub, see if the captain has a black beard. I'd like to meet him."{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|136}}
[[File:Kuttabul (AWM 042975).jpg|thumb|left|HMAS ''Kuttabul'' following the Japanese attack]]

Despite the blackout order, the Garden Island floodlights remained on until 00:25.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|213–14}} About five minutes later, ''M-24'' fired the first of its two torpedoes; it delayed firing the second torpedo for several minutes as the midget submarines would lose longitudinal stability immediately after firing a torpedo.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|214}} Historians are divided as to the exact paths of the torpedoes relative to ''Chicago'', although all agree that the US cruiser was the intended target. Both torpedoes missed ''Chicago'', while one torpedo may have also passed close to ''Perkins''' starboard bow.{{sfn|Warner &amp; Seno, ''The Coffin Boats''|page=130}}{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|139}} One of the torpedoes continued underneath the Dutch submarine [[HMAS K9|''K-IX'']] and HMAS ''Kuttabul'', then hit the breakwater ''Kuttabul'' was tied up against.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|139}} The explosion broke ''Kuttabul'' in two and sank her, and damaged ''K-IX''.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|143}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|215}} The attack killed 19 [[Royal Australian Navy]] and two [[Royal Navy]] sailors, and wounded another 10.&lt;ref name="Elbourne"/&gt; The explosion shook residences in the area and damaged Garden Island's lights and telecommunications.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|215}} The other torpedo ran aground on the eastern shore of Garden Island without exploding.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|215}} ''M-24'' then dived and moved to leave the harbour.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|216}}
[[File:Sydney torpedo (305024).jpg|thumb|upright|The unexploded torpedo at [[Garden Island, New South Wales|Garden Island]] several days after the attack]]

A crossing over the indicator loop that was recorded at 01:58 was initially believed to be another midget submarine entering the harbour, although later analysis showed that the reading indicated an outbound vessel and was therefore most likely represented ''M-24''{{'}}s exit.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|70}} ''M-24'' did not return to its mother submarine, and [[#M-24|its fate]] remained unknown until 2006.&lt;ref name=Foundit/&gt;{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|189}}

Ships were ordered to make for the open ocean. ''Chicago'' left her anchorage at 02:14, leaving a sailor behind on the [[Mooring (watercraft)|mooring]] buoy in her haste to depart.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|216}} ''Bombay'', ''Whyalla'', ''Canberra'', and ''Perkins'' began their preparations to depart.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|153–54}}

Just before 03:00, as ''Chicago'' was leaving the harbour, the lookouts spotted a submarine periscope passing alongside the cruiser.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|218}} At 03:01, the indicator loop registered an inbound signal; ''M-21'' was re-entering Sydney Harbour after recovering from the attack four hours previously.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|218}} {{HMS|Kanimbla||6}} fired on ''M-21'' in [[Neutral Bay, New South Wales|Neutral Bay]] at 03:50, and at 05:00, three auxiliary patrol boats—HMAS ''Steady Hour'', ''Sea Mist'', and ''Yarroma''—spotted the submarine's conning tower in Taylors Bay.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|218}} The patrol boats had set their depth charge fuses to {{convert|15|m|ft|abbr=on}}, and when ''Sea Mist'' passed over where the submarine had just submerged and dropped a depth charge, she had only five seconds to clear the area.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|218}} The blast damaged ''M-21'', which inverted and rose to the surface before sinking again.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|219}} ''Sea Mist'' dropped a second depth charge, which damaged one of her two engines in the process and prevented her from making further attacks.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|219}} ''Steady Hour'' and ''Yarroma'' continued the attack, dropping seventeen depth charges on believed visual sightings and instrument contacts of the midget over the next three and a half hours.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|219}} At some point during the night, the crew of ''M-21'' killed themselves.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|219}}

At 04:40, HMAS ''Canberra'' recorded that the Japanese may have fired torpedoes at her.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|160–62}} This may have been one of many false alarms throughout the night. However, ''M-21'' had attempted to fire its two torpedoes, but failed because of damage to the bow either from HMAS ''Yandra''{{'}}s ramming or depth charges, or a possible collision with USS ''Chicago'', making it possible that ''M-21'' attempted to attack the cruiser.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|160–62}} The observer aboard ''Canberra'' may have seen bubbles from the compressed air released to fire the torpedoes.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|160–62}}

==Secondary missions==
As per the operation plan, the five mother submarines waited off [[Port Hacking]] on the nights of 1 and 2 June for the midget submarines to return.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|225}}{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|188–89}} FRUMEL picked up wireless traffic between the five submarines, leading the [[Royal Australian Air Force|RAAF]] to task three [[Lockheed Hudson]]s and two [[Bristol Beaufort]]s with finding the source of the communications.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|225}} They were unsuccessful.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|225}} On 3 June, Sasaki abandoned hope of recovering the midget submarines, and the submarines dispersed on their secondary missions.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|189}}

===Attacks on Allied merchant shipping===
Four of the submarines began operations against Allied merchant shipping. ''I-21'' patrolled north of Sydney, while ''I-24'' patrolled south of Sydney.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|239}} ''I-27'' began searching off [[Gabo Island]] for ships departing Melbourne, and ''I-29'' travelled to Brisbane.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|239}} ''I-22'' left the group to conduct reconnaissance operations, first at Wellington and Auckland in New Zealand, and then at Suva in Fiji.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|239}}

Between 1 and 25 June, when the four submarines arrived at [[Kwajalein]] Atoll in the [[Marshall Islands]] to re-supply before proceeding to Japanese shipyards for maintenance, the four submarines attacked at least seven Allied merchant vessels.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|254}} Three of these were sunk: ''[[SS Iron Chieftain (1937)|Iron Chieftain]]'' by ''I-24'' on 3 June, ''Iron Crown'' by ''I-27'' on 4 June, and ''Guatemala'' by ''I-21'' on 12 June.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|241,244,253}} The first two attacks resulted in 12 and 37 fatalities respectively, though the third attack killed no one.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|191,193,199}} The attacks forced the authorities to institute changes in merchant traffic; travel north of Melbourne was restricted until a system of escorted convoys was established.{{sfn|Stevens, ''A Critical Vulnerability''}}{{rp|195}}

''I-21'' was the only submarine to return to Australian waters, where she sank three ships and damaged two others during January and February 1943.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|254, 260–61}} During her two deployments, ''I-21'' sank {{convert|44000|LT|t|abbr=on}} of Allied shipping, which made her the most successful Japanese submarine to [[Axis naval activity in Australian waters|operate in Australian waters]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |editor=Stevens, David |title=The Royal Australian Navy |series=The Australian Centenary History of Defence |year=2001 |publisher=Oxford University Press |location=South Melbourne, VIC |isbn=0-19-555542-2 |oclc=50418095 |at=opp. p 112}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bombardment===
{{further|Shelling of Newcastle}}
[[File:Sydney shell damage (AWM 012593).jpg|thumb|A house in [[Eastern Suburbs (Sydney)|Sydney's Eastern Suburbs]] damaged by a Japanese shell]]

On the morning of 8 June, ''I-24'' and ''I-21'' briefly bombarded Sydney and [[Newcastle, New South Wales|Newcastle]].{{sfn|Stevens, ''A Critical Vulnerability''}}{{rp|194}} Just after midnight, ''I-24'' surfaced {{convert|9|mi|km|abbr=on}} south-south-east of [[Macquarie Lighthouse]].{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|247}} The submarine's commander ordered the gun crew to target the [[Sydney Harbour Bridge]].{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|247}} They fired 10 shells over a four-minute period; nine landed in the [[Eastern Suburbs (Sydney)|Eastern Suburbs]] and one landed in water.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|248}} ''I-24'' then [[crash dive]]d to prevent successful retaliation by coastal artillery batteries.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|248–49}} Only one shell detonated, and the only injuries inflicted were cuts and fractures from falling bricks or broken glass when the unexploded shells hit buildings.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|249}} A [[United States Army Air Forces]] pilot, 1st Lieutenant George Cantello, based at [[Bankstown Airport]] disobeyed orders and took off to try and locate the source of the shelling, but was killed when engine failure caused his [[Bell P-39 Airacobra|Airacobra]] to crash in a paddock at [[Hammondville, New South Wales|Hammondville]].&lt;ref name=PacificWreck&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pacificwrecks.com/aircraft/p-400/cantello.html |title=P-400 Serial Number ? |accessdate=7 August 2007 |work=Pacific Wreck Database}}&lt;/ref&gt; In 1988, following efforts by residents and the US Consulate in Sydney, the [[Liverpool, New South Wales|City of Liverpool]] established a memorial park, the Lt. Cantello Reserve, with a monument in his honour.&lt;ref name=PacificWreck/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/P05600.002/ |title=Portrait of 1st Lieutenant (Lt) George Leo Cantello... |publisher=Australian War Memorial |accessdate=19 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.warmemorialsregister.nsw.gov.au/content/lt-cantello-memorial |title=Register of War Memorials in NSW Lt Cantello Memorial |publisher=New South Wales Government |accessdate=19 July 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

At 02:15, ''I-21'' [[Shelling of Newcastle|shelled Newcastle]], from {{convert|9|km|nmi mi|abbr=on}} north-east of [[Stockton, New South Wales|Stockton Beach]].{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|250}} She fired 34 shells over a 16-minute period, including eight [[star shell]]s.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|250}} The target of the attack was the [[BHP Billiton|BHP]] steelworks in the city.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|197}} However, the shells landed over a large area, causing minimal damage and no fatalities: the only shell to detonate damaged a house on Parnell Place, while an unexploded shell hit a [[Trams in Newcastle, New South Wales|tram terminus]].{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|197}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|251}} [[Fort Scratchley]] returned fire, the only time an Australian land fortification has fired on an enemy warship during wartime, but the submarine escaped unscathed.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|251}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite speech|title=Fort Scratchley Dedication Dinner |first=Dana |last=Vale |date=31 May 2002 |location=Newcastle, New South Wales |url=http://minister.dva.gov.au/speeches/2002/05_may/fort_scratchley.htm |accessdate=7 August 2007 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20070828230133/http://minister.dva.gov.au/speeches/2002/05_may/fort_scratchley.htm |archivedate=28 August 2007 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Analysis==
The attack on Sydney Harbour ended in failure on both sides, and revealed flaws in both the Allied defences and the Japanese tactics. During the primary attack, the Japanese lost all three midget submarines in exchange for the sinking of a single barracks ship. The subsequent operations were no more successful as the five large Japanese submarines sank only three merchant ships and caused minimal property damage during the two bombardments. The performance of the Allied defenders was equally poor. However, one historian states that the lack of damage in Sydney Harbour was due to "a combination of good luck and aggressive counter-attack".{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|74}}

The main impact of the midget submarine attack and subsequent operations was psychological; dispelling any belief that Sydney was immune to Japanese attack and highlighting Australia's proximity to the [[Pacific War]].{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|225}}{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|74}} There was no official inquiry into the attacks, despite demand from some sections of the media, as there was concern that an inquiry would lead to [[defeatism]] and reduce faith in [[John Curtin]]'s government, particularly after the damaging inquiry into Australian defences that had followed the [[Bombing of Darwin (February 1942)|Japanese aerial attack on Darwin]] three months earlier.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|169,176}}

===Failures in Allied defences===
The Allies failed to respond adequately to several warnings of Japanese activity off the east coast of Australia prior to the attack; they simply ignored the warnings or explained them away. They attributed the unsuccessful attack on the freighter ''Wellen'' on 16 May to a single submarine, and assumed it had departed Australian waters immediately after the attack.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|174}} The first reconnaissance flight went unnoticed, and although [[FRUMEL]] intercepted the report and distributed it to Allied commanders on 30 May, Muirhead-Gould apparently did not react.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|170–71}} [[New Zealand]] naval authorities detected radio chatter between the Japanese submarines on 26 and 29 May, and although they could not decrypt the transmissions, [[Direction finding|radio direction finding]] indicated that a submarine or submarines were approaching Sydney.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|174}} The Allies considered dispatching an anti-submarine patrol in response to the 29 May fix, but were unable to do so as all anti-submarine craft were already committed to protecting a northbound troop convoy.{{sfn|Stevens, ''A Critical Vulnerability''}}{{rp|192}} The only response to the second reconnaissance flight on 29 May was the launching of search planes.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|193}} No other defence measures were put into place.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|193}} Although the midget attack on [[Antsiranana|Diego Suarez]] in Madagascar occurred on the morning of 31 May (Sydney time), the Allies sent no alert to other command regions, as they believed that [[Vichy France|Vichy French]] forces had launched the attack.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|198}}
[[File:Muirhead-Gould.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Muirhead-Gould in May 1941]]

Historians have questioned the competence of the senior Allied officers. Muirhead-Gould had been hosting a dinner party on the night of the attack, and one of the main guests was the senior United States Navy officer in Sydney Harbour, Captain [[Howard Bode]] of USS ''Chicago''.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|87}} Both officers were sceptical that any attack was taking place.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|135}} Muirhead-Gould arrived aboard HMAS ''Lolita'' at approximately midnight, an action he described as attempting to learn about the situation. But members of ''Lolita'''s crew later recounted that when Muirhead-Gould came aboard he immediately chastised the patrol boat's skipper and crew, and quickly dismissed their report.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|135}}{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|136}} Junior officers on ''Chicago'' provided similar descriptions of Bode's return on board, and members of both crews later claimed that Muirhead-Gould and Bode were intoxicated.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|133–35}} It was only after the destruction of HMAS ''Kuttabul'' that both officers began to take the attack seriously.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|142–43}}

During the attack, there were several delays between events and responses to them. Over two hours passed between the observation of ''M-14'' in the boom net and Muirhead-Gould's first order for ships to commence anti-submarine actions.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|72}} It took another two hours to mobilise the auxiliary patrol boats, which did not leave their anchorage for a further hour.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|72}} Part of these delays was due to a lack of effective communications.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|73}} None of the auxiliary patrol craft in the harbour had radio communications, so all instructions and reports came from signal lights via the Port War Signal Station or Garden Island, or by physical communication via [[Launch (boat)|launches]].{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|73}}{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|176}} In Muirhead-Gould's preliminary report on the attack, he stated that the Port War Signal Station was not designed for the volume of communications traffic the attack caused.&lt;ref&gt;Reproduced in {{harvnb|Carruthers, ''Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942''}}{{rp|244}}.&lt;/ref&gt; Telephone communications with Garden Island were unreliable during the early part of the attack, and then the first torpedo explosion disabled them completely.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|211}}{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|73}}

The need to keep information secret may also have contributed to the delays and the defenders' scepticism.{{sfn|Fullford, ''We Stood And Waited''}}{{rp|194–95}} As the auxiliary patrol boat crews, the indicator loop staff, and other personnel manning defensive positions would have been outside 'need to know' and would not have been informed about any of the incidents prior to the attack, they would not have been alert, contributing to the disbelief demonstrated in the early hours of the attack.{{sfn|Fullford, ''We Stood And Waited''}}{{rp|194–95}}

===Flaws in Japanese tactics===
[[File:I-21 being raised.jpg|thumb|''M-21'' being raised by a floating crane on 10 June 1942]]
[[File:Mid21may.jpg|thumb|The wreckage of ''M-21'']]

The main flaw in the Japanese plans was the use of midget submarines for the primary attack. Midget submarines were originally intended to operate during fleet actions: they would be released from modified [[Seaplane tender|seaplane carriers]] to run amok through the enemy fleet.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|68}} This concept went out of favour as changing Japanese naval thinking and experience led to recognition that naval warfare would centre around [[Aircraft carrier|carrier]]-supported aerial combat.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|71}} As a result, the midget program's focus changed to the infiltration of enemy harbours, where they would attack vessels at anchor.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|71}} This concept failed completely during the [[attack on Pearl Harbor]], where the midgets had no effect, and tying up 11 large submarines for six weeks in support of further midget submarine attacks on Sydney and Diego Suarez proved a waste of resources.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|58}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|291}}

Moreover, the failures at Sydney Harbour and Diego Suarez demonstrated that the improvements to the midget submarines made after Pearl Harbor had not increased the overall impact of the midget program.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|58}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|291}} The modifications had various effects. The ability to man and deploy the midgets while the mother ships were submerged prevented the Army coastal radars from detecting the mother submarines.{{sfn|Fullford, ''We Stood And Waited''}}{{rp|188}} However, the midgets were still difficult to control, unstable, and prone to surfacing or diving uncontrollably.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|70}} These manoeuvrability issues contributed to ''M-14''{{'}}s entanglement in the anti-submarine net, and the repeated detection of ''M-21'' and ''M-24''.

Beyond the use of the unreliable midgets, historians have identified areas in the plan of attack where the Japanese could have done significantly more damage. If the Japanese midget submarines had conducted a simultaneous, co-ordinated attack, they would have overwhelmed the defences.{{sfn|Fullford, ''We Stood And Waited''}}{{rp|188}} A chance for more damage came following the destruction of ''Kuttabul'', when several naval vessels headed to sea, including USS ''Chicago'', USS ''Perkins'', Dutch submarine ''K-IX'', HMAS ''Whyalla'', and HMIS ''Bombay''.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|70}} The five mother submarines were already en route to the [[Port Hacking]] recovery position, and although Sasaki's plan at Pearl Harbor had been to leave some submarines at the harbour mouth to pick off fleeing vessels, he did not repeat this tactic.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|155}}

===USS ''Chicago''{{'}}s survival===
Several factors beyond the control of any of the combatants contributed to the survival of USS ''Chicago''. At the time of ''M-24''{{'}}s attack on ''Chicago'', the latter had spent some time preparing to depart from Sydney Harbour, and although still moored and stationary, was producing large volumes of white smoke as the boilers warmed up.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|137}} This smoke, streaming aft under the influence of the wind, and contrasting against the dark, low-lying cloud, may have given the impression that ''Chicago'' was moving, causing ''M-24'' to [[Deflection (military)|lead the target]] when firing its torpedoes, and consequently sending its torpedoes across the bow.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|137–39}} Another factor that may have influenced ''Chicago''{{'}}s survival was the extinguishing of Garden Island's floodlights minutes before ''M-24'' fired its first torpedo, impeding targeting.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|73}}

===Bombardment impact===
[[File:Sydney shelling damage.jpg|thumb|A crowd looking at a shell hole at [[Woollahra, New South Wales|Woollahra]] on 8 June 1942]]

The bombardments failed to cause significant physical damage, but had a major psychological impact on the residents of Sydney and Newcastle. Due to the inaccuracy of the submarines' range-finding equipment, coupled with the unstable firing platform of a submarine at sea, specific targeting was impossible.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|250}} The intention of the submarine bombardment was to frighten the population of the target area.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|250}}

The failure of the majority of the shells to detonate may have had various causes. As the submarines fired [[Armor-piercing shot and shell|armour-piercing]] shells, intended for use against steel ship hulls, the relatively softer brick walls may have failed to trigger the impact fuses.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|249}} Sea water may have degraded the shells, which the Japanese had stored in deck lockers for several weeks.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|249}} The age of the shells may also have been a factor; some of the shells recovered from the Newcastle bombardment were found to be of English manufacture: surplus munitions from World War I.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|197}}

In Sydney, fear of an impending Japanese invasion caused people to move west; housing prices in the [[Eastern Suburbs (Sydney)|Eastern Suburbs]] dropped, while those beyond the [[Blue Mountains (Australia)|Blue Mountains]] rose significantly.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|258}} The attack also led to a significant increase in the membership of volunteer defence organisations, and strengthening of defences in Sydney Harbour and Port Newcastle.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Nichols |first=Robert |year=2006 |title=The Night the War Came to Sydney |journal=Wartime |volume= |issue=33 |pages=28–29 |url= |accessdate= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
The papers did not publish news of the submarine attack until 2 June, as most of the attack occurred after the newspapers went to press on the morning of 1 June.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|225}} Instead, on the morning after the attack, the front pages carried news of [[Bombing of Cologne in World War II|Operation Millennium]], the [[Royal Air Force]]'s first 1,000-bomber raid, although several newspapers included a small interior article mentioning the [[#Final reconnaissance|final reconnaissance flyover]].{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|225}} The Federal Censor ordered total censorship of the events, issuing an official statement on the afternoon of 1 June which reported that the Allies had destroyed three submarines in Sydney Harbour, and described the loss of ''Kuttabul'' and the 21 deaths as the loss of "one small harbour vessel of no military value".{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|156, 187}} ''[[Smith's Weekly]]'' finally released the real story on 6 June, and follow-up material in 13 June issue caused more political damage, prompting the [[Royal Australian Navy]] to attempt to charge the newspaper with releasing defence information.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|212, 223–27}}
[[File:Submariners funeral (AWM 012580).jpg|thumb|left|The burial service for the Australian sailors killed during the raid on Sydney.]]

It was several days before the 21 dead sailors aboard ''Kuttabul'' could all be recovered.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|151}} On 3 June, Muirhead-Gould and over 200 Navy personnel attended a burial ceremony for these sailors.{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|151}} On 1 January 1943, the Navy base at Garden Island was commissioned as {{HMAS|Kuttabul|naval base|6}} in commemoration of the ferry and the lives lost.&lt;ref name=Elbourne&gt;{{cite news|last=Elbourne |first=Sean |title=Wonderful Kuttabul – a long history of service |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/w/images/Sea_Talk_2006-winter.pdf |work=Sea Talk (Winter 2006) |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |pages=11–19 |date=Winter 2006 |accessdate=7 September 2008 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20091019113436/http://www.navy.gov.au/w/images/Sea_Talk_2006-winter.pdf |archivedate=19 October 2009 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Australians recovered the bodies of the four Japanese crew of the two midget submarines sunk in Sydney Harbour and had them cremated at [[Eastern Suburbs Memorial Park|Eastern Suburbs Crematorium]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article48869769 |title=Naval Honors At Burial Of Submarine Crews |newspaper=[[The Advertiser (Adelaide)|The Advertiser]] |location=South Australia |date=10 June 1942 |accessdate=5 July 2020 |page=1 |via=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article247989311 |title=NAVAL HONORS FOR JAP SAILORS |newspaper=The Daily Telegraph|location=New South Wales, Australia |date=9 June 1942 |accessdate=5 July 2020 |page=2 |via=National Library of Australia}}&lt;/ref&gt; For the cremation, the Allies draped the Japanese flag over each coffin and rendered full naval honours.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|72}} Muirhead-Gould was criticised for this, but defended his actions as respecting the courage of the four submariners, regardless of their origin.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|230}} Australian politicians also hoped that the Japanese Government would notice the respect paid to the sailors and improve the conditions Australian prisoners-of-war were experiencing in Japanese internment camps.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|231}} Japanese authorities noted the funeral service, but this did not lead to any major improvement in conditions for Australian POWs.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|231}} Following the use of the midget submariners' funeral by the Japanese for propaganda purposes, the Australian High Command forbade similar funerals for enemy personnel in the future.{{sfn|Warner &amp; Seno, ''The Coffin Boats''|page=130}}

An exchange of Japanese and Allied diplomatic personnel stranded in the opposing nations occurred in August 1942, which allowed [[Tatsuo Kawai (diplomat)|Tatsuo Kawai]], the Japanese ambassador to Australia, to return home with the ashes of the four Japanese submariners.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|232–33}} When the exchange ship ''[[Kamakura Maru]]'' arrived in [[Yokohama]], several thousand people were present to honour the four men.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|232–33}}
[[File:Kamakura Maru.jpg|thumb|left|upright|Relatives of four of the Japanese sailors killed in the midget submarines which raided Sydney Harbour greet ''Kamakura Maru'' as she arrives at [[Yokohama]] with the ashes of the four submariners in October 1942.]]

The two main targets of the attack, USS ''Chicago'' and HMAS ''Canberra'', were both lost within the next year: ''Canberra'' sinking on 9 August 1942 during the [[Battle of Savo Island]], and ''Chicago'' on 30 January 1943 following the [[Battle of Rennell Island]].{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|61, 150–53, 273}} None of the Japanese submarines involved in the attack survived the war. {{USS|Charrette|DD-581|6}} and {{USS| Fair|DE-35|2}} sank ''I-21'' on 5 February 1944 off the [[Marshall Islands]].{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|216}} An American torpedo boat sank ''I-22'' on 25 December 1942 off [[New Guinea]].{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|216}} An American patrol craft sank ''I-24'' on 10 June 1943 near the [[Aleutian Islands]].{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|216}} {{HMS|Paladin|G69|6}} and {{HMS|Petard|G56|2}} sank ''I-27'' on 12 February 1943 off the [[Maldives]].{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|216}} Lastly, {{USS|Sawfish|SS-276|6}} sank ''I-29'' on 26 July 1944 in the [[Philippines]].{{sfn|Carruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}{{rp|216}}

===''M-14'' and ''M-21''===
[[File:Midget sub AWM 1.JPG|thumb|The composite midget submarine at the [[Australian War Memorial]] in 2007.]]

The Allies located and recovered ''M-21'' on 3 June and ''M-14'' on 8 June.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|209,219}} Although both were damaged during the attack, it was possible to assemble a complete submarine from the two vessels.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|72}} The centre section of the rebuilt submarine was mounted on a trailer and taken on a {{convert|4000|km|mi|abbr=on}} tour throughout southern New South Wales, Victoria, and western South Australia.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|72}}{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|250}} The purpose of the tour was twofold; it allowed Australians to see a Japanese midget submarine up close, and was used to raise A£28,000 for the Naval Relief Fund and other charities.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|72}}{{sfn|Warner &amp; Seno, ''The Coffin Boats''|page=169}} The submarine arrived at the [[Australian War Memorial]] in Canberra on 28 April 1943, flying the [[White Ensign]] and a [[Decommissioning pennant|paying-off pennant]].{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|72}} The submarine was originally displayed outside the museum in three separate pieces,{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|251}} but was moved inside in the 1980s due to heavy vandalism; on one occasion in 1966, a group of university students painted it bright yellow in response to [[The Beatles]]' song ''[[Yellow Submarine (song)|Yellow Submarine]].''{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|253–55}} The composite submarine was restored and remains on display inside the Memorial as part of a permanent exhibition on the attack, next to the recovered wheelhouse of HMAS ''Kuttabul''.'{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|253–55}} The conning tower from ''M-21'' is on display at the [[Royal Australian Navy Heritage Centre]] on Garden Island.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|251}} Leftover material from ''M-21'' was melted down and made into souvenirs following the construction of the combined vessel.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|253}}

===''M-24''===
{{main|M24 Japanese Midget Submarine wreck site}}
[[File:Submarine Conning Tower M 22 'Battle of Sydney' (3).jpg|thumb|left|Submarine M-22 Conning Tower on display at the [[RAN Heritage Centre]], Sydney]]
Over the 64 years following the disappearance of ''M-24'' after the attacks, more than 50 people approached the Royal Australian Navy claiming to have found the submarine.&lt;ref name=McNicoll/&gt; All of these claims were found to be false.&lt;ref name=McNicoll/&gt; One early theory about the midget's fate was that it was damaged or destroyed, along with ''M-21'', in or around Taylors Bay, which would account for reports from ''Steady Hour'' and ''Yarroma'' of multiple submarines during their three-hour attack against ''M-21''.{{sfn|Gill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}{{rp|71}}{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|217}} A second theory was that the midget attempted to return to the mother submarines but exhausted its battery power before reaching the Port Hacking recovery point and would therefore be outside and to the south of Sydney Heads.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|217}} The third theory was that the midget's crew decided to avoid endangering the five larger submarines during the recovery process, and either ran straight out to sea or headed north.{{sfn|Jenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}{{rp|184}}

A group of seven amateur scuba divers solved the mystery in November 2006, when they found a small submarine sitting upright on the seabed, {{convert|55|m}} below sea level and approximately {{convert|5|km|nmi mi}} from [[Bungan Head, New South Wales|Bungan Head]], off [[Northern Beaches (Sydney)|Sydney's Northern Beaches]].&lt;ref name=Foundit&gt;{{cite episode |title=Found it! |series=60 Minutes |serieslink=60 Minutes (Australian TV program) |credits=[[Liam Bartlett]] (reporter), Stephen Taylor &amp; Julia Timms (producers) |network=[[Nine Network]] |airdate=26 November 2006 |url=http://video.msn.com/?mkt=en-au&amp;brand=ninemsn&amp;tab=m163&amp;mediaid=28587&amp;from=39&amp;vid=5a450894-8216-4807-8d5f-c116fb30f3a3&amp;playlist=videoByTag:mk:en-AU:vs:0:tag:aunews_au60minutes:ns:MSNVideo_Top_Cat:ps:10:sd:-1:ind:1:ff:8A }}{{Dead link|date=November 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Hasham/&gt; Commander Shane Moore, the officer responsible for the [[Royal Australian Navy]]'s heritage collection, confirmed that the wreck was ''M-24'' after viewing footage from multiple dives, along with measurements the group had taken.&lt;ref name=Foundit/&gt; The wreck had several bullet holes in it, most likely from ''Chicago''{{'}}s quadruple machine-gun mount.&lt;ref name="Foundit"/&gt; The location of the wreck was kept secret by both the divers and the navy, with Defence Minister [[Brendan Nelson]] promising to have the wreck protected as a [[war grave]].&lt;ref name=Foundit/&gt; The wreck was [[gazette]]d on 1 December 2006 as a heritage site.&lt;ref name=HO&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.heritage.nsw.gov.au/07_subnav_01_2.cfm?itemid=5060289 |title=M24 Japanese Midget Submarine wreck site |accessdate=7 August 2007 |work=State Heritage Inventory Database |publisher=New South Wales Heritage Office| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20070829225815/http://www.heritage.nsw.gov.au/07_subnav_01_2.cfm?itemid=5060289| archivedate= 29 August 2007 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; A {{convert|500|m|ft|abbr=on}} exclusion zone was established around the wreck site, and any vessel entering the zone is liable to a fine under New South Wales law of up to A$1.1&amp;nbsp;million, with additional fines and confiscation of equipment under Commonwealth law.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|255}} Shore- and buoy-mounted surveillance cameras and a sonar listening device further protect the site.{{sfn|Grose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}{{rp|255}}

On 7 February 2007, during [[Japan Maritime Self-Defense Force|JMSDF]] Admiral [[Eiji Yoshikawa (admiral)|Eiji Yoshikawa]]'s visit to Australia, Yoshikawa and RAN Vice Admiral [[Russ Shalders]] presided over a ceremony held aboard {{HMAS|Newcastle|FFG 06|6}} to honour ''M-24''{{'}}s crew.&lt;ref name=Wurth&gt;{{cite news |first=Bob |last=Wurth |title=Fallen submariners honored in Australia |url= http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20070224f1.html |work=[[The Japan Times]] |page=3 |date= 24 February 2007 |accessdate=7 August 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Relatives of the midget submarines' crews, one of the survivors from ''Kuttabul'', and dignitaries and military personnel from Australia and Japan attended another ceremony on 6 August 2007 at HMAS ''Kuttabul''.&lt;ref name=McNicoll&gt;{{cite news |first=D.D. |last=McNicoll |authorlink= |title=Ceremony ends missing sub saga |url=http://www.theaustralian.com.au/news/nation/ceremony-ends-missing-sub-saga/story-e6frg6nf-1111114124882 |work= [[The Australian]] |publisher=News Corporation |date=7 August 2007 |accessdate=7 August 2007}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{HMAS|Melbourne|FFG 05|6}} then carried relatives of ''M-24''{{'}}s crew to the wreck site, where they poured [[sake]] into the sea before being presented with sand taken from the seabed around the submarine.&lt;ref name=McNicoll/&gt;

In May 2012, the NSW state government announced that, with the approval of the Japanese government and the submariners' families, divers would be allowed to observe the ''M-24'' wreck for a short period of time.&lt;ref name=Hasham&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.smh.com.au/nsw/depths-of-knowledge-divers-to-explore-secrets-of-submarine-site-20120527-1zd75.html |title=Depths of knowledge: divers to explore secrets of submarine site |last=Hasham |first=Nicole |date=28 May 2012 |work=The Sydney Morning Herald |accessdate=28 May 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt; Divers would enter a ballot for places on controlled dives run on several days.&lt;ref name=Hasham/&gt; If successful, opening the site would become an annual event to commemorate the attack.&lt;ref name=Hasham/&gt;

== See also ==
{{Portal|Military of Australia}}
* [[Air raids on Australia, 1942–43]]
* [[Military history of Australia during World War II]]

==Footnotes==
{{notelist-ur}}

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* Blunt, William (2020). Lolita and the Hollywood Fleet.  Available online at http://www.lolitaandthehollywoodfleet.com
* {{cite book |last=Carruthers |first=Steven |title=Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942: A maritime mystery |origyear=1982 |edition=Revised |year=2006 |publisher=Casper Publications |location=Narrabeen, NSW |isbn=0-9775063-0-4 |oclc=|ref=CITEREFCarruthers, Japanese Submarine Raiders 1942}}
* {{cite book |last=Fullford |first=Richard |title=We Stood And Waited: Sydney's anti-ship defences 1939–1945 |year=1994 |publisher=Royal Australian Artillery Historical Society |location=North Fort |isbn=0-646-04599-7 |oclc=|ref=CITEREFFullford, ''We Stood And Waited''}}
* {{cite book |last=Gill |first=George Hermon |title=Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945 |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070208/ |series=[[Australia in the War of 1939–1945]], Series 2, Volume II |publisher=Australian War Memorial |location=Canberra |chapter=Australia's Coast Raided – Her Flanks Strengthened |chapterurl=https://www.awm.gov.au/images/collection/pdf/RCDIG1070272--1-.pdf |year=1968 |isbn=0-00-217480-4|ref=CITEREFGill, ''Royal Australian Navy, 1942–1945''}}
* {{cite book |last=Grose |first=Peter |title=A Very Rude Awakening |year=2007 |publisher= Allen &amp; Unwin |location=Crows Nest |isbn=978-1-74175-219-9 |oclc= |ref=CITEREFGrose, ''A Very Rude Awakening''}}
* {{cite book |last=Jenkins |first=David |title=Battle Surface! Japan's Submarine War Against Australia 1942–44 |year=1992 |publisher=Random House Australia |location=Milsons Point |isbn=0-09-182638-1 |ref=CITEREFJenkins, ''Battle Surface''}}
* {{cite book |last=Stevens |first=David |title=A Critical Vulnerability: The Impact of the Submarine Threat on Australia's Maritime Defence (1915–1954) |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/w/images/PIAMA15.pdf |accessdate=7 September 2008 |series=Papers in Australian Maritime Affairs (No. 15) |date=June 2005 |publisher=Sea Power Centre |location=Canberra |isbn=0-642-29625-1 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081004040951/http://www.navy.gov.au/w/images/PIAMA15.pdf |archivedate=4 October 2008 |url-status=dead |ref=CITEREFStevens, A Critical Vulnerability  }}
* {{cite book |last=Warner |first=Peggy |author2=Seno, Sadao |title=The Coffin Boats |year=1986 |publisher=Leo Cooper in association with Secker &amp; Warburg |location=London |isbn=0-436-56330-4 |ref=CITEREFWarner &amp; Seno, ''The Coffin Boats''}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Attack on Sydney Harbour}}
{{Commons category|Sydney Harbour defences}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070812024409/http://www.ww2australia.gov.au/underattack/sydharbour.html Australia's War 1939–1945: Australia Attacked – Sydney Harbour] Overview of the events. Includes an animation showing the events immediately prior to and during the attack.
* [http://www.combinedfleet.com/Sydney.htm Midget Submarines at Sydney, Australia 1942] at Combinedfleet.com.

{{featured article}}

{{coord|33|51|30|S|151|14|00|E|type:event_region:AU|display=title}}

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sydney Harbour}}
[[Category:Military history of Sydney during World War II|Attack on Sydney Harbour]]
[[Category:Sydney Harbour|Attack on Sydney Harbour]]
[[Category:Submarine warfare in World War II]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:1942 in Australia|Attack on Sydney Harbour]]
[[Category:Military attacks against Australia]]
[[Category:Shipwrecks of New South Wales]]
[[Category:South West Pacific theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:History of Sydney|Attack on Sydney Harbour]]
[[Category:1940s in Sydney|Attack on Sydney Harbour]]</text><sha1>t1optq1wbsth2d2b0mvyddh41ulzi38</sha1></revision></page>