<page><title>Battle of the Mareth Line</title><ns>0</ns><id>3833461</id><revision><id>960899053</id><parentid>960898748</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-05T14:21:05Z</timestamp><contributor><username>GELongstreet</username><id>16567817</id></contributor><minor /><comment>consistency</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="30592" xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=November 2017}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of the Mareth Line
| partof      = the [[Tunisia Campaign]] of the [[Second World War]]
| image       = File:The British Army in Tunisia 1943 NA1397.jpg
| image_size = 250px
| caption     = A British [[Ordnance QF 25-pounder|25-pounder]] field gun in action at night, during the assault on the Mareth Line
| date        = 16–31 March 1943
| place       = Southern [[Tunisia]]
|coordinates = {{coord|33|38|N|10|18|E|display=inline|region:TN_type:city_source:GNS-enwiki}}
| territory   =
| result      = British victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
* {{flag|British India}}
{{flagcountry|Dominion of New Zealand}}
{{flag|Free France}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagcountry|Kingdom of Greece|1935}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flagcountry|Nazi Germany}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Bernard Montgomery, 1st Viscount Montgomery of Alamein|Bernard Montgomery]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Giovanni Messe]]
|units1 = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]]
|units2 = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[First Army (Italy)|1st Army]]
| strength1   = 90,000 of 123,690 men{{sfn|Stevens|1962|p=173}}
| strength2   = 73,500 of 115,000 men&lt;br /&gt;455 guns&lt;br /&gt;139–220 tanks&lt;br /&gt;480 anti-tank guns&lt;br /&gt;seventy-five 88 mm guns{{sfn|Stevens|1962|p=173}}
| casualties1 = 4,000 casualties
| casualties2 = 7,000{{POW}}
| notes   =
| campaignbox =
{{Campaignbox Tunisia Campaign}}
{{Campaignbox North Africa}}
}}
The '''Battle of the Mareth Line''' or the '''Battle of Mareth''' was an attack in the [[Second World War]] by the British [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]] ([[General (United Kingdom)|General]] [[Bernard Montgomery, 1st Viscount Montgomery of Alamein|Bernard Montgomery]]) in [[Tunisia Campaign|Tunisia]], against the [[Mareth Line]] held by the Italo-German [[First Army (Italy)|1st Army]] (General [[Giovanni Messe]]). It was the first big operation by the Eighth Army since the [[Second Battle of El Alamein]] {{frac|4|1|2}} months previously. On 19 March 1943, Operation Pugilist, the first British attack, established a bridgehead but a break-out attempt was defeated by Axis counter-attacks. Pugilist established an alternative route of attack and Operation Supercharge II, an outflanking manoeuvre via the [[Tebaga Gap]] was planned. Montgomery reinforced the flanking attack, which from 26 to 31 March, forced the 1st Army to retreat to [[Wadi Akarit]], another {{cvt|40|mi|km}} back in Tunisia.

==Background==
===Axis retreat from El Alamein===
The retreat of Panzer Army Africa (known as the {{lang|de|[[Panzer Army Africa|Deutsch-Italienische Panzerarmee]]}}/{{lang|it|Armata Corazzata Italo-Tedesca}} from October 1942) took place from {{nowrap|5 November 1942 – 15 February 1943.}}{{efn|On 23 February 1943 the name of the {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} was changed for the last time, to [[1st Italian Army]] (General [[Giovanni Messe]]). This was the first time that German units came under Italian command, albeit with a German "liaison" officer, Major-General [[Fritz Bayerlein]].}} On 8 November, [[Operation Torch]] began in Morocco, Algeria and Tunisia, as {{lang|de|Panzeramee Afrika]] in Egypt managed to evade British outflanking moves but traffic jams, fuel shortages, poor weather and air attacks reduced the speed of the retreat to {{cvt|6|–|7|mi|km}} per day. {{lang|it|Comando Supremo}} in Rome and OKW in Berlin took an optimistic view of the situation and {{lang|it|Comando Supremo}} chose the [[Brega|Mersa-el-Brega]]–[[El Agheila]] position as the terminus of the retreat, despite the position having a front of {{cvt|110|mi|km}}, strong points up to {{cvt|5|mi|km}} apart, which was too far for mutual support and only {{nowrap|30,000 mines.}} When the {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} arrived, the {{lang|de|[[Afrika Korps]]}} had only {{nowrap|5,000 men,}} {{nowrap|35 tanks,}} {{nowrap|16 armoured cars,}} {{nowrap|12 anti-tank guns,}} {{nowrap|12 field howitzers}} and deliveries of only {{cvt|50|LT|t}} of the {{cvt|400|LT|t}} of supplies needed daily.{{sfn|Cooper|1978|pp=388–389}}

[[File:General Messe.jpg|thumb|left|upright=0.75|{{centre|General [[Giovanni Messe]]}}]]
Rommel wanted to retreat to [[Wadi Akarit]] in the Gabès area, {{cvt|120|mi|km}} further west, where the non-motorised troops could defend a narrow gap between the Mediterranean and the [[Chott Djerid]]. The tanks and motorised infantry would join the [[5th Panzer Army]] (Colonel-General Hans-Jürgen von Arnim) further north, drive back the British [[First Army (United Kingdom)|First Army]] from Tunisia into [[Algeria]], then swiftly return to force back the Eighth Army. At a meeting with Hitler on 28 November, Rommel discussed the proposal but only received a promise of more supplies. On the night of {{nowrap|11/12 December,}} the British attacked and on the following evening, the {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} resumed its retreat and despite the chronic fuel shortage, evaded another outflanking move. The {{lang|de|Panzerarmee}} took up a defensive position at Buerat on 29 December but this was poorly fortified, wide open to an outflanking manoeuvre and vulnerable to an attack on [[Gabès]] by the First Army in southern Tunisia. The supply situation was a little better, with {{cvt|152|LT|t}} tons of the {{cvt|400|LT|t|adj=on}} daily requirement being delivered but {{nowrap|95 percent}} of the fuel was used distributing supplies or for withdrawals.{{sfn|Cooper|1978|pp=389–392}}

The [[Long Range Desert Group]] (LRDG) attacked Axis supply lines and hundreds of lorries were stranded along roads for lack of fuel, while the Eighth Army massed fuel and ammunition for its next attack. On 13 January 1943, the infantry of 21st Panzer Division were sent north to the 5th Panzer Army to protect Gabès and on 15 January, the Eighth Army attacked with {{nowrap|450 tanks}} against {{nowrap|36 German}} and {{nowrap|57 Italian}} tanks. In the evening Rommel ordered another withdrawal; lack of fuel and apprehension about the threat to Gabès, led to the retreat passing beyond the Tarhuna–Homs line. Tripoli was occupied by the British on 23 January, the Axis retreat from El Alamein having covered {{cvt|1400|mi|km}}. On 13 February, the last Axis soldiers left Libya and on 15 February, the rearguard reached the Mareth Line, {{cvt|80|mi|km}} inside Tunisia. {{lang|it|Comando Supremo}} intended that the line would be held indefinitely but Rommel considered it to be too vulnerable to another flanking move, unlike the Wadi Akarit position further back.{{sfn|Cooper|1978|pp=392–394}}

===Terrain===
The [[badlands|broken terrain]] of southern Tunisia, with difficult rocky ridge lines and desert, limited manoeuvre; opposite the [[Bight (geography)|bight]] where the north–south coast opens to the east, a semi-arid, scrub covered coastal plain is met inland by the [[Matmata Hills]] which lie south to north. Across the plain in a line roughly south-west to north-east was the Mareth Line, fortifications built by the French in the 1930s. In the north, the hills and line of forts terminated at the [[Tebaga Gap]], a [[mountain pass|low pass]] between the Matmata Hills and the Djebel Tebaga, another line of high ground to the west of the gap running east–west.{{efn|Also known as the Gabès gap, the coastal strip from Gabès to Wadi Akarit from the sea to the Chott el Fedjadj and the northwards ridges extending to the heights of Djebel Tebaga Fatnassa.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=315}}}} North and west of this feature is the [[Chott el Djerid]] and west of the Matmata Hills, dry [[Jebel Dahar]] country and then the impassable sand of the [[Grand Erg Oriental]]. Gabès lies on the coast, where the plain meets the route from the Tebaga Gap. North of Gabès, the road to Sfax passes between the sea and the Chotts, was the only route north for the Eighth Army and was blocked by the Mareth Line.{{sfn|Stevens|1962|p=154}}

The Mareth Line followed the line of [[Wadi Zigzaou]], a natural tank obstacle with steep banks rising up to {{cvt|70|ft|m}}; the north-west side had been fortified by the French and subsequently reinforced. The wadi crosses the coastal plain from Zarat to Toujane and into the Matmata Hills beyond. In 1938, the French judged Jebel Dahar to be impassable to motorised transport and so had not extended the Mareth Line any further inland but in 1943, motor vehicles had much better performance. The British had an advantage because General [[Georges Catroux]], the designer and garrison commander of the Mareth Line in the 1930s, was available in Algiers, to provide information and advice for the attack.{{sfn|Howard|1972|p=347}} In the original plan, Montgomery wrote "...the object of Operation Pugilist is to destroy the enemy now opposing Eighth Army in the Mareth Line and to advance and capture [[Sfax]]".{{sfn|Stevens|1962|p=133}}

==Prelude==

===Battle of Medenine===
{{main|Battle of Medenine}}

The Battle of Medenine ({{lang|de|Unternehmen Capri}}/Operation Capri), was an [[Axis powers|Axis]] spoiling attack at [[Medenine]] in [[Tunisia]] on 6 March 1943. The operation was intended to delay an attack by the British [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]] on the [[Mareth Line]]. The British had been forewarned by [[Ultra]] decrypts of German wireless communications and rushed reinforcements from Tripoli and Benghazi before the Axis attack, which was a costly failure. General [[Erwin Rommel]], the commander of [[Army Group Africa]] ({{lang|de|Heeresgruppe Afrika}}), could not afford to lose forces needed for the defence of the Mareth Line and the effort was abandoned at dusk. During the night, the Eighth Army remained alert in case of another Axis attempt and sent forward patrols to reconnoitre and to demolish knocked-out Axis tanks. During the day the {{lang|de|[[Luftwaffe]]}} and {{lang|it|[[Regia Aeronautica]]}} had made a maximum effort with little effect against the Allied anti-aircraft defence and the [[Desert Air Force]]. On 7 March, the Axis forces began a withdrawal northwards towards the Mareth Line, the Eighth Army pursuit being slowed by rain. The Battle of Medenine was the last battle commanded by Rommel in the North African Campaign, who returned to Europe for good soon afterwards.{{sfn|Stevens|1962|p=175}}

==Battle==
===Operation Pugilist===
[[File:Zero Hour- the Mareth Offensive, 1943. Cameron Highlanders Art.IWMARTLD3398.jpg|thumb|{{centre|''Zero Hour''{{snds}} Painting of the [[Queen's Own Cameron Highlanders]] advancing during the Battle of the Mareth Line, 1943}}]]
On 19 March 1943, [[XXX Corps (United Kingdom)|XXX Corps]] (Lieutenant-General [[Oliver Leese]]) of the Eighth Army commenced Operation Pugilist. The [[50th (Northumbrian) Infantry Division]] (Major-General [[John Nichols (British Army officer)|John Nichols]]) managed to penetrate the line held by the [[136th Armoured Division Giovani Fascisti|136th Armoured Division "Giovani Fascisti"]] near [[Zarat, Tunisia|Zarat]].&lt;ref&gt;[https://adviceandresearch.blogspot.com/2019/06/division-giovani-fascisti-in-1943.html Young Italians in the Battle of Mareth]&lt;/ref&gt; The terrain and rain prevented the deployment of tanks, aircraft and anti-tank guns, which left the infantry isolated. A counter-attack by [[33rd Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|15th Panzer Division]] and the 136th Armoured Division "Giovani Fascisti" on 22 March, recaptured much of the [[bridgehead]] capturing 35 British tanks and 200 prisoners. British forces kept their positions until darkness. On 24 March all elements were recalled.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/USA-MTO-NWA/USA-MTO-NWA-24.html#fn44 |title=North West Africa: Seizing the Initiative in the West |first=George F. |last=Howe}}&lt;/ref&gt; XXX Corps prepared a new attack towards Tallouf, in which the [[4th Infantry Division (India)|4th Indian Infantry Division]] (Major-General [[Francis Tuker]]) was to make a night attack on {{nowrap|23/24 March,}} around the inland end of the line. This would coincide with the wide left hook manoeuvre Montgomery was planning.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=337–342}}

====Left hook====
In early January 1943, a LRDG patrol had found a pass into the Jebel Dahar, which was given the name Wilder's Gap. A later patrol penetrated to the Tebaga Gap and proved that the route was practicable. The patrol demonstrated the weakness of the Axis defences by going further north to [[Gafsa]] and on 2 February, made contact with the First Army which was advancing from the west. Montgomery reinforced the [[2nd New Zealand Division]] (Lieutenant-General [[Bernard Freyberg, 1st Baron Freyberg|Bernard Freyberg]]) and renamed it the New Zealand Corps, for an attack through the [[Matmata, Tunisia|Matmata]] Hills, via Wilder's Gap, into the Jebel Dahar, with the assembly concealed from Axis reconnaissance. Staff from [[X Corps (United Kingdom)|X Corps]] (Lieutenant-General [[Brian Horrocks]]) were seconded to provide adequate HQ personnel for the new New Zealand Corps, which caused some friction between the two generals.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=343–344}}

The New Zealand Corps advance was planned in three stages, from 19 March, a {{cvt|20|mi|km}} night march to Wadi bel Krecheb, a second night march of {{cvt|40|mi|km}} to just short of the Tebaga Gap and then the capture of the entrance to the gap at first light on 21 March or as soon as possible afterwards. The corps would then advance to [[El Hamma]], which overlooked the coast road north of Gabès. The flank of the advance was to be protected by [[Free France|Free French]] forces ([[Army general (France)|General]] [[Philippe Leclerc de Hauteclocque|Philippe Leclerc]]) and the [[1st King's Dragoon Guards]]. An attack by X Corps from El Hamma to Gabès would cut off the 1st Army defending the Mareth positions and provide the New Zealand Corps with the opportunity to advance to Sfax {{cvt|80|mi|km}} up the coast from Gabès and the landing grounds on the west side of the town.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=337}}
[[File:MarethMap1943 en.png|thumb|{{centre|Mareth Line and attacks by Eighth Army on it during March 1943}}]]

During planning, emphasis was laid on the need for surprise and the ability to {{lang|de|Blitz}} Axis positions. The corps had relatively few infantry and was reliant on its artillery to break Axis troop concentrations and morale. Extensive efforts were made to co-ordinate air support by fighter and bomber aircraft. A simultaneous frontal attack by XXX Corps on the Mareth Line would divide enemy attention and hamper an Axis counter-attack. The [[II Corps (United States)|II US Corps]] of the First Army, advancing from the west through [[El Guettar, Tunisia|El Guettar]] was to threaten Axis communications and pin down reinforcements from the Sfax area.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=329, 331}}

===Tebaga Gap===
The New Zealand Corps engaged the Axis troops in the Tebaga Gap on 21 March but progress over the next four days against the [[164th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|164th Light ''Afrika'' Division]] and [[21st Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|21st Panzer Division]] was very slow, although the entrance to the gap was secured. On the Mareth Line, XXX Corps made some progress but there was no breakthrough. On 23 March, Montgomery ordered the [[1st (United Kingdom) Division|1st Armoured Division]] (Major-General [[Raymond Briggs (British Army officer)|Raymond Briggs]]) of X Corps to reinforce the New Zealand Corps from reserve, where it was waiting to exploit the anticipated breakthrough either by XXX Corps or the New Zealand Corps and Horrocks, with the X Corps Headquarters to take control of operations in the Tebaga Gap.{{sfn|Stevens|1962|pp=178–191}}

===Operation Supercharge II===
Operation Supercharge II was planned to start on the afternoon of 26 March, with a preliminary operation on the night of {{nowrap|25/26 March}} to capture Height 184. The New Zealand Corps was to attack into the Tebaga Gap on a two-brigade front and capture the Axis defences from Djebel Tebaga to Djebel Melab, which would be exploited by the 1st Armoured Division.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|p=347}} After assembling during the night and lying in concealed positions all day, the [[5th Infantry Brigade (New Zealand)|5th New Zealand Brigade]] was to attack on the right and the [[6th Infantry Brigade (New Zealand)|6th New Zealand Brigade]] on the left, preceded by the [[8th Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|8th Armoured Brigade]] and a creeping barrage by the New Zealand and X Corps artillery. The attacking troops were to move to high ground {{cvt|2000|yd|m}} forward and then to a second objective at a wadi {{cvt|2500|yd|m}} further on. The 1st Armoured Division, led by the [[2nd Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|2nd Armoured Brigade]], was to move through at {{nowrap|6:15 p.m.}} to an area {{cvt|3000|yd|m}} beyond the New Zealand Corps final objective and as soon as the moon rose (at about {{nowrap|11:15 p.m.),}} advance on El Hamma.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=347–348}}

[[File:An Italian pilot about to enter into a Macci 202 during the battle.jpg|thumb|{{centre|An Italian pilot climbs into a Macchi 202 during the battle}}]]
RAF heavy bombers would begin harassment of the Axis defenders led by General Messe the night before, with attacks on transport and communications until {{nowrap|3:30 p.m.}} Day bombers would then begin low-altitude pattern bombing, to add to Axis disorganisation, followed by relays of fighter-bombers every {{nowrap|15 minutes}} for {{frac|2|1|2}} hours. [[Supermarine Spitfire|Spitfires]] would escort the bombers and fighter-bombers and the remainder of the [[Northwest African Tactical Air Force]] (NATAF) would bomb Axis airfields. An RAF forward observation officer was to brief pilots by nominating landmarks, marking targets with red and blue smoke; friendly troops were to use orange smoke and the artillery would fire smoke shells to signal to the aircrews. On 24 March, Arnim doubted that an Eighth Army attack was likely and was more concerned about Maknassy further north. Despite the slow advance in the south, Arnim wanted the 1st Army to withdraw to Wadi Akarit on 25 March but Liebenstein and Messe preferred to counter-attack with the 15th Panzer Division. The threat to Maknassy and the possibility of the II US Corps reaching Gabès and cutting off the 1st Army, meant that they had to retire from Mareth and then from Tebaga.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=347–349}}

Height 184 fell at {{nowrap|2:50 a.m.}} to the [[21st Battalion (New Zealand)|21st New Zealand Battalion]] and the Allied artillery commenced firing at {{nowrap|4:00 p.m.}}. The attack began with the 8th Armoured Brigade, followed by infantry battalion [[Universal Carrier|carriers]] and then infantry on foot. It appeared that the 164th Light and 21st Panzer divisions had not expected a daylight assault and had been surprised; the setting sun, wind and dust had made observation difficult. The British tanks had been ordered to press on and the infantry also managed a quick pace, arriving on the first objective and then kept going, despite increasing resistance and delays. An armoured regiment pressed on to Wadi Aisoub beyond the second objective, followed by the [[23rd Battalion (New Zealand)|23rd New Zealand Battalion]]. On the left, a minefield covered by anti-tank guns was bypassed on both sides to close up to the second objective, clearing a gap for the 1st Armoured Division, despite many Axis posts holding out in the vicinity.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=350–351}}

[[File:The British Army in Tunisia 1943 NA1638.jpg|thumb|{{centre|[[Crusader tank]]s of the 1st Armoured Division enter El Hamma, 29 March 1943}}]]
By dark a gap in the defences had been made; pausing until moonrise at {{nowrap|11:00 p.m.,}} the 1st Armoured Division advanced through the gap and rapidly moved on El Hamma, {{cvt|20|mi|km}} to the north-east, halfway to Gabès on the coast. On the morning of 27 March, the 15th Panzer Division was brought out of reserve to counter-attack the New Zealand Corps on their right flank. By {{nowrap|9:00 a.m.,}} the attack had been repulsed and the New Zealand Corps advanced into the hills on their right. By the evening of 27 March, German resistance had been broken and the line of communication forward to the 1st Armoured Division secured, the division having been halted by the defences of El Hamma, while the tanks had waited for the moonlight. Freyberg persuaded Horrocks that the New Zealand Corps, en route to El Hamma to link with the 1st Armoured Division, should branch off to the right to avoid the Axis defences at El Hamma and head across the broken ground direct to Gabès.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=351–353}}

By 28 March, General Messe gave the order that all Axis forces on the Mareth Line be withdrawn to face the X and New Zealand corps on their right flank but by holding up the 1st Armoured Division at El Hamma, managed to avoid encirclement. On 29 March, the New Zealand Corps took Gabès, which forced a further Axis withdrawal to a new line {{cvt|15|mi|km}} to the rear of Gabès at Wadi Akarit, while the 164th Light, 15th Panzer and 21st Panzer divisions fought rearguard actions. El Hamma was evacuated on 29 March, leaving the way open for the 1st Armoured Division to advance northward with the New Zealand Corps on their right.{{sfn|Playfair|2004|pp=353–354}}

==Aftermath==
===Casualties===
[[File:The British Army in Tunisia 1943 NA1344.jpg|thumb|upright=0.75|{{centre|A captured German and a wounded British soldier share a cigarette after the battle}}]]
On 31 March, Operation Supercharge II was terminated, having cost the Eighth Army {{nowrap|4,000 casualties,}} many from the 50th Division and a large number of tanks; the New Zealand Corps lost {{nowrap|51 tanks}} and {{nowrap|945 men.}}{{sfn|Brooks|1991|p=211}} The corps was disbanded and its elements were distributed between X and XXX corps.{{sfn|Stevens|1962|pp=248–249}} On 30 March, Montgomery sent the following message to Freyberg,

{{quote|My very best congratulations to NZ Corps and 10 Corps on splendid results achieved by the left hook. These results have led to the complete disintegration of the enemy resistance and the whole Mareth position. Give my congratulations to all your officers and men, and tell them how pleased I am with all they have done.|Montgomery{{sfn|Stevens|1962|p=248}}}}

The Axis forces, despite withdrawing in relatively good order, lost over {{nowrap|7,000 prisoners,}} of whom {{nowrap|2,500 were}} German.{{sfn|Schmid|1955|p=228}} The 15th Panzer Division had suffered many losses, the 164th Light Afrika Division lost most of its weapons and vehicles. The 80th Infantry Division "La Spezia" suffered losses of nearly 50 percent and the 16th Infantry Division "Pistoia" was almost annihilated; several Italian divisions were amalgamated.&lt;ref name=ax&gt;{{cite web |title=Italian Army |last=Wendel |first=Marcus |accessdate=2009-10-04 |publisher=Axis History |url=http://www.axishistory.com/index.php?id=8573}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Axis Order of Battle 10 June 1940 - The Italian Invasion of France |last=Mulholland |first=John |accessdate=2009-10-04 |url=http://www.axishistory.com/index.php?id=6466 |publisher=Axis History |archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/5gTrg0sPN?url=http://www.axishistory.com/index.php?id=6466 |archivedate=2009-05-02 |url-status=live }}&lt;/ref&gt; The 1st Army withdrew in good order to Wadi Akarit.

==Order of battle==
[[File:Royal Air Force Operations in the Middle East and North Africa, 1939-1943. CM4908.jpg|thumb|{{centre|[[RAF]] [[Martin Baltimore]]s taking off from [[Ben Gardane]] to bomb the Mareth Line}}]]
'''Eighth Army'''
* (General Sir Bernard Montgomery)
'''XXX Corps''' ([[Lieutenant-general (United Kingdom)|Lieut.-General]] Oliver Leese)
* [[50th (Northumbrian) Infantry Division]]
* [[51st (Highland) Division|51st (Highland) Infantry Division]]
* [[4th Infantry Division (India)|4th Indian Infantry Division]]
* [[22nd Guards Brigade|201st Guards Brigade]]
* [[23rd Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|23rd Armoured Brigade]]
'''New Zealand Corps''' (Lieut.-General Bernard Freyberg)
* [[2nd New Zealand Division]]
* [[8th Armoured Brigade (United Kingdom)|8th Armoured Brigade]]
* [[1st King's Dragoon Guards]]
* 64th Medium Regiment, [[Royal Artillery]]
* 57th Anti-Tank Regiment, Royal Artillery
* One Battery 53rd Light Anti-Aircraft Regiment, Royal Artillery
* [[Philippe Leclerc de Hauteclocque|Leclerc Force]] (with the Greek [[Sacred Band (World War II)|Sacred Squadron]])
'''X Corps''' (Lieut.-General Brian Horrocks)
* [[1st (United Kingdom) Division|1st Armoured Division]]
* [[7th Armoured Division (United Kingdom)|7th Armoured Division]] (including [[4th Infantry Brigade and Headquarters North East|4th Light Armoured Brigade]], less King's Dragoon Guards)
* Free French Flying Column
----
'''1st Italian Army'''
(General Giovanni Messe)

'''[[Italian XX Corps]]'''
* [[136 Infantry Division Giovani Fascisti]]
* [[101 Motorised Division Trieste]]
* [[90th Light Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|90th Light ''Afrika'' Division]]

'''[[Italian XXI Corps]]'''
* [[80 Infantry Division La Spezia (Airlanding)]]
* [[16 Motorised Division Pistoia]]
* [[164th Infantry Division (Wehrmacht)|164th Light ''Afrika'' Division]]

'''Reserve'''
* [[15th Panzer Division]]

Tebaga
* Saharan Group

Uncommitted
* [[21st Panzer Division]]

Gafsa front
* [[10th Panzer Division (Wehrmacht)|10th Panzer Division]]
* [[131 Armoured Division Centauro|''Centauro'' Group]]

The 19th Flak Division, with sixteen {{nowrap|88 mm}} batteries and several {{nowrap|20 mm}} anti-aircraft batteries, was on the coast, the 1st Luftwaffe Brigade, little stronger than a battalion, was behind ''Giovani Fascisti'' and Africa Panzer Grenadier Regiment watched the main Gabès–Mareth road. These and the 164 Light Division, were the only mobile infantry groups available.

==See also==
{{Portal|World War II}}
* [[Tunisia Campaign]]
* [[North African Campaign timeline]]
* [[List of World War II Battles]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Brooks|1991}}
|last=Brooks |first=S. |title=Montgomery and the Eighth Army |year=1991 |publisher=The Bodley Head (for the Army Records Society) |location=London |isbn=978-0-370-31723-6}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Cooper|1978}}
|last=Cooper |first=Matthew |title=The German Army 1933–1945: its Political and Military Failure |publisher=Stein and Day |year=1978 |location=Briarcliff Manor, NY |isbn=978-0-8128-2468-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Howard|1972}}
|title=Grand Strategy: August 1942 – September 1943 |volume=IV |series=History of the Second World War United Kingdom Military Series |last=Howard |first=M. |authorlink=Michael Howard (historian) |year=1972 |publisher=[[HMSO]] |location=London |edition= |isbn=978-0-11-630075-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Playfair|2004}}
|first1=Major-General I. S. O. |last1=Playfair |author1-link=Ian Stanley Ord Playfair |first2=Brigadier C. J. C. |last2=and Molony |first3=Captain F. C. |last3=Flynn RN |first4=Group Captain T. P. |last4=Gleave |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=J. R. M. |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |title=The Mediterranean and Middle East: The Destruction of the Axis Forces in Africa |volume=IV |series=History of the Second World War United Kingdom Military Series |orig-year=1st. pub. [[HMSO]] 1966 |year=2004 |location=London |publisher=HMSO |edition=Naval &amp; Military Press, Uckfield |isbn=978-1-84574-068-9 |display-authors=1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Schmid|1955}}
|last=Schmid |first=Heinz Werner |title=With Rommel in the Desert |series=Panther Books |number=508 |date=1955 |publisher=Hamilton |location=London |oclc=67441147}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Stevens|1962}}
|last=Stevens |first=Major-General W. G. |authorlink=|title=Bardia to Enfidaville |series=The Official History of New Zealand in the Second World War 1939–1945 |publisher=War History Branch, Department of Internal Affairs |location=Wellington, NZ |year=2016 |orig-year=1962 |url=http://nzetc.victoria.ac.nz/tm/scholarly/tei-WH2Bard.html |edition=online |accessdate=10 March 2015 |oclc=4377202}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|first=Charles R.|last=Anderson|url=http://www.history.army.mil/brochures/tunisia/tunisia.htm|title=Tunisia 17 November 1942 to 13 May 1943|series=The US Army Campaigns of WWII|publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]] |location=Washington, DC|year=1990|id=CMH Pub 72-12|oclc=835850360}}
* {{cite news|last=Anderson|first=Lt.-General Kenneth|author-link=Kenneth Arthur Noel Anderson|year=1946|title=Official despatch by Kenneth Anderson, GOC-in-C [[First Army (United Kingdom)|First Army]] covering events in NW Africa, 8 November 1942 – 13 May 1943|publisher=London Gazette|location=London|issn=0374-3721}} published in {{London Gazette |issue=37779 |supp=y |pages=5449–5464|date=5 November 1946 |ref=none}}
* {{cite book |last=Battistelli |first=Pier Paolo |title=Italian Soldier in North Africa 1941–43 |year=2013 |publisher=Osprey |location=Oxford |isbn=978-1-78096-855-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Ford|first=Ken|title=The Mareth Line 1943: The End in Africa|year=2012|publisher=Osprey|location=Oxford |isbn=978-1-78200-299-4}}
* {{cite book|last=Lewin|first=Ronald|authorlink=Ronald Lewin|title=Rommel as Military Commander|publisher=[[Pen &amp; Sword]]|year=2004|location=[[Barnsley]]|isbn=978-1-84415-040-3|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/rommelasmilitary0000lewi_e9y5}}
* {{cite book|first=Giuseppe|last=Mugnone|title=I ragazzi di Bir el Gobi|trans-title=The Lads at Bir el Gobi|language=Italian |year=1962|publisher=Editrice La Lucciola|location=Padova|edition=4th|oclc=81301705}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commonscat|Mareth Line}}
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/USA-MTO-NWA/USA-MTO-NWA-27.html Northwest Africa, Chapter XXVII, Mareth to Enfidaville]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mareth Line, Battle}}
[[Category:Tunisian Campaign]]
[[Category:Code names|Pugilist]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving New Zealand]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Greece]]
[[Category:March 1943 events]]</text><sha1>rq6ip4lptc3vsf3njb8qbfh1wmvra26</sha1></revision></page>