<page><title>Operation Vengeance</title><ns>0</ns><id>4274699</id><revision><id>967036735</id><parentid>966242031</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-10T19:03:21Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Pearlharborandmidway</username><id>33982631</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="32588" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|American military operation to kill Japanese Admiral Isoroku Yamamoto}}
{{use mdy dates |date=March 2020 }}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Operation Vengeance
| partof      = the [[Pacific War|Pacific Theater]] of [[World War II]]
| image       = Yamamoto last image alive.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = Japanese Admiral [[Isoroku Yamamoto]], a few hours before his death, saluting Japanese naval pilots at Rabaul, April 18, 1943
| date        = April 18, 1943
| place       = near [[Panguna]], [[Bougainville Island|Bougainville]], [[Solomon Islands]]
| result      = Operation successful;&lt;br/&gt;Admiral Yamamoto killed
| combatant1  = {{flag|United States|1912}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|Empire of Japan|name=Imperial Japan}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[William F. Halsey, Jr.]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[John W. Mitchell (United States Air Force)|John W. Mitchell]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan|naval}} [[Isoroku Yamamoto]]{{KIA}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|Empire of Japan|naval}} [[Matome Ugaki]]{{WIA}}
| units1      = [[Thirteenth Air Force|13th Air Force]]
* [[347th Fighter Group]]
** [[339th Flight Test Squadron|339th Fighter Squadrons]]
| units2      = [[11th Air Fleet (Imperial Japanese Navy)|11th Air Fleet]]
* 26th Air Flotilla
** [[204 Air Group|204th Naval Air Group]]
** [[Misawa Naval Air Group|705th Naval Air Group]]
| strength1   = 18 [[Lockheed P-38 Lightning|P-38G]] fighter aircraft
| strength2   = 2 G4M1 [[bomber]]s,&lt;br/&gt;6 A6M2 [[fighter aircraft]]
| casualties1 = 1 P-38G fighter aircraft lost,&lt;br /&gt;1 pilot killed
| casualties2 = 2 bombers destroyed,&lt;br/&gt;1 fighter damaged,&lt;br/&gt;19 killed inc. Admiral Yamamoto
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Solomons}}
}}
'''Operation Vengeance''' was the American military operation to kill Admiral [[Isoroku Yamamoto]] of the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] on April 18, 1943, during the [[Solomon Islands campaign]] in the [[Pacific Ocean theater of World War II|Pacific Theater]] of [[World War II]]. Yamamoto, commander of the Combined Fleet of the Imperial Japanese Navy, was killed on [[Bougainville Island]] when his transport [[bomber]] aircraft was shot down by [[United States Army Air Forces]] [[fighter aircraft]] operating from [[Kukum Field]] on [[Guadalcanal]].

The mission of the U.S. aircraft was specifically to kill Yamamoto and was based on [[United States Navy]] intelligence on Yamamoto's itinerary in the [[Solomon Islands]] area. The death of Yamamoto reportedly damaged the morale of Japanese naval personnel, raised the morale of the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] forces, and was intended as revenge by U.S. leaders, who blamed Yamamoto for the [[attack on Pearl Harbor]] that initiated the war between [[Empire of Japan|Imperial Japan]] and the United States.

The U.S. pilots claimed to have shot down three twin-engined bombers and two fighters during the mission, but Japanese sources show only two bombers were shot down. There is a controversy over which pilot shot down Yamamoto's plane, but most modern historians credit Lieutenant [[Rex T. Barber]].

== Background ==
{{Location map+|Papua New Guinea
 |caption = New Guinea, the Bismarck Archipelago and the Solomon Islands; Yamamoto's planned two-hour flight on 18th April 1943, from [[Rabaul]] on [[New Britain]] to the small island of [[Balalae]] near [[Bougainville Island]]
  |float = left
  |width=300
  | places ={{Location map~|Papua New Guinea| label = Rabaul| mark =Red_pog.svg|lat=-4.20|long=152.18|position=left|float=}}
{{Location map~|Papua New Guinea| label = &lt;div style="position: relative; top: 1.2em; left: -0.5em;"&gt;Balalae&lt;/div&gt;
  | mark =Red_pog.svg
  |position=below|lat=-7|long=155.86|caption= |float=}}
{{Location map~ |Papua New Guinea |label=Bougainville |position=right |lat=-5.5 |long=154.5 |mark=Steel pog.svg |marksize=1}}
}}
Admiral [[Isoroku Yamamoto]], commander of the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]], scheduled an inspection tour of the [[Solomon Islands]] and [[New Guinea]]. He planned to inspect Japanese air units participating in [[Operation I-Go]] that had begun April 7, 1943; in addition, the tour would boost Japanese morale following the disastrous [[Guadalcanal Campaign]] and its subsequent [[Operation Ke|evacuation]] during January and February. On April 14, the U.S. naval intelligence effort code-named "[[Magic (cryptography)|Magic]]" intercepted and decrypted orders alerting affected Japanese units of the tour.

The original message, NTF131755, addressed to the commanders of Base Unit No. 1, the 11th Air Flotilla, and the 26th Air Flotilla, was encoded in the [[Japanese naval codes#JN-25|Japanese Naval Cipher JN-25D]], and was picked up by three stations of the "Magic" apparatus, including [[Fleet Radio Unit]] Pacific Fleet. The message was then deciphered by Navy cryptographers (among them future Supreme Court Justice [[John Paul Stevens]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |url=https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2010/03/22/after-stevens|title=After Stevens|first=Jeffrey|last=Toobin|date=March 15, 2010|magazine=[[The New Yorker|New Yorker]]}}&lt;/ref&gt;); it contained time and location details of Yamamoto's itinerary, as well as the number and types of planes that would transport and accompany him on the journey.

The decrypted text revealed that on April 18 Yamamoto would be flying from [[Rabaul]] to [[Balalae Airport|Balalae Airfield]], on an island near [[Bougainville Island|Bougainville]] in the Solomon Islands. He and his staff would be flying in two medium bombers ([[Mitsubishi G4M|Mitsubishi G4M Bettys]] of the [[Misawa Naval Air Group|Kōkūtai 705]]), escorted by six navy fighters ([[A6M Zero|Mitsubishi A6M Zero]] fighters of the [[204 Air Group|Kōkūtai 204]]), to depart Rabaul at 06:00 and arrive at Balalae at 08:00, Tokyo time.

President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] may have authorized [[Secretary of the Navy]] [[Frank Knox]] to "get Yamamoto," but no official record of such an order exists&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite journal|first= Adonis C|last=Arvanitakis|date=2015-03-24|title=Killing a Peacock: A Case Study of the Targeted Killing of Admiral Isoroku Yamamoto|url=http://www.dtic.mil/docs/citations/ADA623450|language=en |publisher=[[Defense Technical Information Center]] }}&lt;/ref&gt; and sources disagree whether he did so.&lt;ref name=Maffeo&gt;{{Cite book|title=U.S. Navy codebreakers, linguists, and intelligence officers against Japan, 1910-1941 : a biographical dictionary|last=Maffeo|first=Steven|publisher=|isbn=9781442255647|location=Lanham, MD|pages=493|oclc=914224225|date = 2015-12-16}}&lt;/ref&gt;  Knox essentially let Admiral [[Chester W. Nimitz]] make the decision.&lt;ref name=Maffeo /&gt; Nimitz first consulted Admiral [[William F. Halsey, Jr.]], Commander, South Pacific, and then authorized the mission on April 17.

== Interception ==
{{Location map+|Solomon Islands
 |caption = The Solomon Islands; [[Kukum Field]] on Guadalcanal, the interception flight's base, and the crash-site of Yamamoto's aircraft on [[Bougainville Island]]&lt;ref name="Wheeler" /&gt; |float = right
  |width=300
  |places ={{Location map~|Solomon Islands| label = &lt;div style="position: relative; top: 1.7em; left: -2em;"&gt;Kukum Field&lt;/div&gt;
  | mark =Blue_pog.svg
  |position=below|lat=-9.5|long=160|caption= |float=}}
{{Location map~|Solomon Islands| label = &lt;div style="position: relative; top: -1.4em; left: 0.5em;"&gt;Crash-site&lt;/div&gt;
  | mark =Red_pog.svg
  |position=below|lat=-6.7861|long=155.5523|caption= |float=}}
}}
[[File:P-38 2.jpg|thumb|300px|[[Lockheed P-38 Lightning|P-38G Lightning]]s were the aircraft chosen to carry out the mission.]]
To avoid detection by radar and Japanese personnel stationed in the Solomon Islands along a straight-line distance of about {{convert|400|mi}} between U.S. forces and Bougainville, the mission entailed an over-water flight south and west of the Solomons. This roundabout approach was plotted and measured to be about {{convert|600|mi}}. The fighters would, therefore, travel 600 miles out to the target and 400 miles back. The 1,000-mile flight, with extra fuel allotted for combat, was beyond the range of the [[F4F Wildcat]] and [[F4U Corsair]] fighters then available to Navy and [[United States Marine Corps|Marine]] squadrons based on [[Guadalcanal]]. The mission was instead assigned to the [[339th Flight Test Squadron|339th Fighter Squadron]], [[347th Fighter Group]], whose [[P-38 Lightning|P-38G Lightning]] aircraft, equipped with [[drop tanks]], had the range to intercept and engage.

339th Squadron Commander Major John W. Mitchell, already an ace pilot, was chosen to lead the flight. For better navigation, Mitchell asked for a navy compass, which was provided by Marine Corps Lt. Col. Luther S. Moore, and installed in Mitchell's P-38 the day before the attack. All of the P-38 fighters mounted their standard armament of one [[Hispano-Suiza HS.404|20&amp;nbsp;mm]] cannon and four [[M2 Browning machine gun#Aircraft guns|.50-caliber]] (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) machine guns, and were equipped to carry two {{convert|165|gal|L|adj=on}} [[drop tank]]s under their wings. A limited supply of {{convert|330|gal|L|adj=on}} tanks was flown up from New Guinea, sufficient to provide each Lightning with one large tank to replace one of the small tanks. Despite the difference in size, the tanks were located close enough to the aircraft's center of gravity to avoid any performance problems.

Eighteen P-38s were assigned the mission. One flight of four was designated as the "killer" flight, while the remainder, which included two spares, would climb to {{convert|18000|ft|-2}} to act as "top cover" for the expected reaction by Japanese fighters based at [[Kahili Airfield|Kahili]]. A flight plan was prepared by the Command Operations Officer, Marine Major John Condon, but this was discarded by Mitchell, who thought the airspeeds and time estimates were not best for intercepting Yamamoto.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Glines|1990|p=30}}&lt;/ref&gt; With several of his pilots assisting, Mitchell calculated an intercept time of 09:35, based on the itinerary, to catch the bombers descending over Bougainville, 10 minutes before landing at Balalae. He worked back from that time and drew four precisely calculated legs, with a fifth leg curving in a search pattern in case Yamamoto was not seen at the chosen point. In addition to heading out over the [[Coral Sea]], the 339th would "wave-hop" all the way to Bougainville at altitudes no greater than 50 feet (15&amp;nbsp;m), maintaining radio silence.

Although the 339th Fighter Squadron officially carried out the mission, 10 of the 18 pilots were drawn from the other two squadrons of the 347th Group. The Commander [[AirSols]], Rear Admiral [[Marc A. Mitscher]], selected four pilots to be designated as the "killer" flight: 
* Capt. [[Thomas G. Lanphier, Jr.]]
* Lt. [[Rex T. Barber]]
* Lt. Jim McLanahan (dropped out with flat tire)
* Lt. Joe Moore (dropped out with faulty fuel feed)

The remaining pilots would act as reserves and provide air cover against any retaliatory attacks by local Japanese fighters:

{{colbegin|colwidth=20em}}
* Maj. [[John Mitchell (United States Air Force)|John Mitchell]]
* Lt. William Smith
* Lt. Gordon Whittiker
* Lt. Roger Ames
* Capt. Louis Kittel
* Lt. Lawrence Graebner
* Lt. Doug Canning
* Lt. Delton Goerke
* Lt. Julius Jacobson
* Lt. Eldon Stratton
* Lt. Albert Long
* Lt. Everett Anglin
* Lt. Besby F. Holmes (replaced McLanahan)
* Lt. Raymond K. Hine (replaced Moore)
{{colend}}

A briefing included a cover story for the source of the intelligence stating that a [[coastwatchers|coastwatcher]] had spotted an important high-ranking officer boarding an aircraft at Rabaul. Several historians say that the pilots were not specifically briefed on the identity of their target,&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Davis|1969|p=9}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Glines|1990|p=7}}&lt;/ref&gt; but Thomas Alexander Hughes wrote that Mitscher told the assembled pilots it was Yamamoto, to "provide additional incentive" to the fliers.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=dwUEDAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA267 |page=267 |last=Hughes |first=Thomas Alexander |date=2016 |title=Admiral Bill Halsey: A Naval Life |publisher=[[Harvard University Press]] |isbn=9780674969292}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The specially fitted P-38s took off from [[Kukum Field]] on Guadalcanal beginning at 07:25 on April 18. Two of the Lightnings assigned to the killer flight dropped out of the mission at the start, one with a tire flattened during takeoff (McLanahan) and the second when its drop tanks would not feed fuel to the engines (Moore).

In Rabaul, despite urgings by local Japanese commanders to cancel the trip for fear of ambush, Yamamoto's airplanes took off as scheduled for the trip of {{convert|315|mi}}. They climbed to {{convert|6500|ft|-2}}, with their fighter escort at their 4&amp;nbsp;o'clock position and {{convert|1500|ft|-1}} higher, split into two V-formations of three planes.

Mitchell's flight of four led the squadron at low altitude, with the killer flight, now consisting of Lanphier, Barber, and spares 1st Lt. Besby F. Holmes and 1st Lt. Raymond K. Hine, immediately behind. Mitchell, fighting off drowsiness, navigated by flight plan and the navy compass. This has been called the longest-distance fighter-intercept mission of the war.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=weO6CwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA56 |page=56 |last=Stille |first=Mark |title=Yamamoto Isoroku |date=2012 |publisher=Bloomsbury |isbn=9781849087322}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Mitchell and his force arrived at the intercept point one minute early, at 09:34, just as Yamamoto's aircraft descended into view in a light haze. The P-38s jettisoned the auxiliary tanks, turned to the right to parallel the bombers, and began a full power climb to intercept them.

The tanks on Holmes's P-38 did not detach and his element turned back toward the sea. Mitchell radioed Lanphier and Barber to engage, and they climbed toward the eight aircraft. The nearest escort fighters dropped their own tanks and dived toward the pair of P-38s. Lanphier, in a sound tactical move, immediately turned head-on and climbed towards the escorts while Barber chased the diving bomber transports. Barber banked steeply to turn in behind the bombers and momentarily lost sight of them, but when he regained contact, he was immediately behind one and began firing into its right engine, rear [[fuselage]], and [[empennage]]. When Barber hit its left engine, the bomber began to trail heavy black smoke. The Betty rolled violently to the left and Barber narrowly avoided a mid-air collision. Looking back, he saw a column of black smoke and assumed the Betty had crashed into the jungle. Barber headed towards the coast at treetop level, searching for the second bomber, not knowing which one carried the targeted high-ranking officer.

[[File:Yamamoto's airplane crash.jpg|thumb|300px|The crashed remains of Yamamoto's Mitsubishi "Betty" bomber in a [[Bougainville Island|Bougainville]] jungle]]
Barber spotted the second bomber, carrying Chief of Staff Vice Admiral [[Matome Ugaki]] and part of Yamamoto's staff, low over the water off Moila Point, trying to evade an attack by Holmes, whose wing tanks had finally come off. Holmes damaged the right engine of the Betty, which emitted a white vapor trail, but his closure speed carried him and his wingman Hine past the damaged bomber. Barber attacked the crippled bomber and his bullet strikes caused it to shed metal debris that damaged his own aircraft. The bomber descended and [[water landing|crash-landed in the water]]. Ugaki and two others survived the crash and were later rescued. Barber, Holmes and Hine were attacked by Zeros, Barber's P-38 receiving 104 hits.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last=Grant |first=Rebecca |date=March 2006 |volume=89 |number=3 |page=62 |title=Magic and Lightning |journal=[[Air Force Magazine]] |publisher=Air Force Association |location=Arlington, Virginia}}&lt;/ref&gt; Holmes and Barber each claimed a Zero shot down during this [[Dogfight|melee]], although Japanese records show that no Zeros were lost. The top cover briefly engaged reacting Zeros without making any kills. Mitchell observed the column of smoke from Yamamoto's crashed bomber. Hine's P-38 had disappeared by this point, presumably crashed into the water. Running close to minimum fuel levels for return to base, the P-38s broke off contact, with Holmes so short of fuel that he was forced to land in the [[Russell Islands]]. Hine was the only pilot who did not return. Lanphier's actions during the battle are unclear as his account was later disputed by other participants, including the Japanese fighter pilots. In his landing, Lanphier's plane was so short on fuel that one engine quit during the landing rollout.  Immediately on landing he put in a claim for shooting down Yamamoto.

== Japanese-American involvement ==
{{Main|Japanese-American service in World War II}}

The [[Military Intelligence Service]] (MIS) was made of mostly [[Nisei]] (second-generation [[Japanese Americans]]). They were trained in interpreting, interrogation, and translation with materials ranging from standard textbooks to captured documents, in the war against Japan.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=McNaughton |first1=James C. |title=Nisei Linguists — Central Intelligence Agency |url=https://www.cia.gov/library/center-for-the-study-of-intelligence/csi-publications/csi-studies/studies/vol-52-no-4/nisei-linguists.html |website=www.cia.gov |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A major MIS contribution in the Solomons campaign was the ambush of Yamamoto. MIS soldier Harold Fudenna intercepted a radio message indicating the whereabouts of Admiral Yamamoto. Although this message was first met with disbelief that the Japanese would be so careless, other MIS linguists in Alaska and Hawaii had also intercepted the same message, confirming its accuracy.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |title=Northern Solomons Campaign |url=http://www.goforbroke.org/history/history_historical_campaigns_mis_northern.asp |website=www.goforbroke.org |publisher=Go For Broke National Education Center |archivedate=April 13, 2014 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140413130259/http://www.goforbroke.org/history/history_historical_campaigns_mis_northern.asp |url-status=dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Aftermath ==
[[File:Yamamoto's ashes on Musashi.jpg|thumb|Yamamoto's ashes return to Japan at [[Kisarazu]] aboard battleship [[Japanese battleship Musashi|''Musashi'']] on May 23, 1943]]
[[File:Japan-State-Funeral-for-Marshal-Admiral-Isoroku-Yamamoto (cropped).png|thumb|right|Yamamoto's state funeral, 5 June 1943]]

The crash site and body of Yamamoto were found on April 19, the day after the attack, by a Japanese search-and-rescue party. The crash site was located in the jungle north of the coastal site of the former Australian patrol post and Catholic mission of [[Buin, Papua New Guinea|Buin]] (which was re-established after the war several kilometers inland).

The retrieval party noted Yamamoto had been thrown clear of the plane's wreckage, his white-gloved hand grasping the hilt of his [[katana]] sword, his body still upright in his seat under a tree. Hamasuna said Yamamoto was instantly recognizable, his head tilted down as if deep in thought. A [[post-mortem]] of Yamamoto indicated two bullet wounds, one to the back of his left shoulder, and a separate wound to his left lower jaw that appeared to exit above his right eye. The Japanese navy doctor examining Yamamoto's body determined the head wound killed Yamamoto. These more violent details of Yamamoto's death were hidden from the Japanese public, and the medical report whitewashed, this secrecy "on orders from above" according to biographer [[Hiroyuki Agawa]].

In Japan, Yamamoto's killing became known as the "Navy ''kō'' incident" ([[:ja:海軍甲事件]]). It raised morale in the United States and shocked the Japanese, who were officially told about the incident only on May 21, 1943. In the United States, in order to cover up the fact that the Allies were reading Japanese codes, American news agencies were given the same cover story used to brief the 339th Fighter Squadron&amp;mdash;that civilian coastwatchers in the Solomons observed Yamamoto boarding a bomber and relayed the information by radio to American naval forces in the immediate area. This conveyed to the Japanese military that it was only through a stroke of luck that the Americans carried out the successful attack.

== The crash site today ==
The crash site of Yamamoto's aircraft, ''323'' is at a position {{coord|06|23.165|S|155|22.137|E}}.&lt;ref name="Wheeler" /&gt; This is an area of jungle, around {{convert|9|mi|km}} from the town of [[Panguna]],&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.lonelyplanet.com/papua-new-guinea/island-provinces/bougainville |title=Bougainville |publisher=[[Lonely Planet]] |accessdate=5 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; and an hour's walk from the nearest road.&lt;ref name="pacificwrecks"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.pacificwrecks.com/aircraft/g4m/2656.html |title=G4M1 Model 11 Betty Manufacture Number 2656 Tail T1-323 |publisher=Pacific Wrecks |accessdate=5 January 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although the aircraft has been heavily scavenged by souvenir hunters, its main parts remain where they were when it crashed. The crash site is on private land; access was previously difficult, for the ownership of the land was disputed.&lt;ref name="Wheeler"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://tonywheeler.com.au/yamamotos-aircraft-wreck/ |title=Yamamoto's Aircraft Wreck |publisher=Tony Wheeler’s Travels |date=February 25, 2012 |accessdate=5 January 2016 |author=Wheeler, Tony |authorlink=Tony Wheeler}}&lt;/ref&gt; However, {{as of|2015|lc=y}}, it is possible for visitors to gain access to the site by prior arrangement.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.abc.net.au/news/2015-05-13/historic-wwii-crash-site-opened-for-the-first-time-in-years/6466058 |title=Historic WWII crash site opened to tourists in Bougainville for first time in more than five years |publisher=[[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]] |date=23 May 2015 |accessdate=5 January 2016 |author=Bolitho, Sam}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Part of one wing has been removed and is displayed, on permanent loan, at the Isoroku Yamamoto Family Museum in [[Nagaoka, Niigata|Nagaoka]], Japan. One of the aircraft's doors is at the [[Papua New Guinea National Museum and Art Gallery]].&lt;ref name="pacificwrecks" /&gt;

== Credit controversy ==
Although Operation Vengeance was notable for its target, there has been controversy about who shot down the admiral's aircraft.

The issue began immediately after the mission when the US military credited Thomas Lanphier with the kill. The captain claimed in his report that after turning to engage the escort Zeros and shooting the wings off one, he had flipped upside down as he circled back towards the two bombers. On seeing the lead bomber turning in a circle below him, he came out of his turn at a right angle to the circling bomber and fired, blowing off its right wing. The plane then crashed into the jungle. Lanphier also reported that he saw Lt. Rex Barber shoot down another bomber which also crashed into the jungle.

From the report, US intelligence assumed that three bombers had been downed because Lt. Besby F. Holmes claimed the "Betty" that crashed into the sea. None of the remaining pilots were debriefed after the mission because no formal interrogation procedures existed on Guadalcanal at that time. Likewise, Lanphier's claim of the kill was never officially witnessed. Many of the mission's other pilots soon became skeptical about the official US Army version.

Six months later, unauthorized details about the operation leaked into the press. In October 1943, an issue of ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine featured an article about ''Vengeance'' and mentioned Lanphier by name. An outraged US Navy considered it a serious breach of security. As a result Major [[John Mitchell (United States Air Force)|John Mitchell]], who had been nominated for the [[Medal of Honor]], was downgraded to the [[Navy Cross (United States)|Navy Cross]]; this was the same award subsequently presented to all the pilots of the killer flight.

The controversy did not subside after the war because of the testimony of the surviving Japanese escort pilot who witnessed the mission. Zero pilot [[Kenji Yanagiya]], who had been in Yamamoto's fighter escort, told John Mitchell he might have been responsible for the loss of Lt. Raymond Hine because he had heavily damaged a P-38 (escorting another Lightning that had not dropped its fuel tanks), although neither he nor any of the other Zero pilots had claimed a P-38 that day. The cause of Hine's disappearance is still officially undetermined. Yanagiya also affirmed that none of the escorting Japanese fighters were shot down, only one was damaged enough that it required a half day of repair at Buin. These details contradicted Lanphier's claim for a Zero. Likewise Japanese military records confirmed that only two Mitsubishi G4M bombers had been shot down on the day. Eventually Lanphier and Barber were officially awarded half credits for the destruction of the bomber that crashed into the jungle, and half credits to Barber and Holmes for the bomber that crashed at sea. Several ground inspections of Yamamoto's crash site have determined that the path of the bullet impacts validated Barber's account because "all visible gunfire and shrapnel damage was caused by bullets entering from immediately behind the bomber" not from the right.&lt;ref&gt;{{harvnb|Glines|1990|pp=192–195}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Subsequently, Barber petitioned the [[Air Force Review Boards Agency|Air Force Board for Correction of Military Records]] to have his half credit on the bomber shared with Lanphier changed to a whole credit. In September 1991, the Air Force History Office advised the board that "enough uncertainty" existed in both Lanphier's and Barber's claims for them both to be accepted; the board's decision was split on Barber's petition. [[Secretary of the Air Force]] [[Donald B. Rice]] ruled to retain the shared credit. Barber then applied to the [[U.S. 9th Circuit Court of Appeals]] to have the ruling of the Secretary of the Air Force overturned and the opposing claims re-investigated, but the court refused to intervene.

In May 2006, ''[[Air Force Magazine]]'' published a letter by Doug Canning, a former pilot of the 347th Fighter Group who flew on Operation Vengeance (he escorted Lieutenant Holmes back to the [[Russell Islands]]). Canning, who was friends with both Lanphier and Barber, stated that Lanphier had written the official report, medal citations, and several magazine articles about the mission. He also claimed Barber had been willing to share the half credit for shooting down Yamamoto until Lanphier had given him an unpublished manuscript he had written claiming he alone had shot down the admiral. Canning agreed that Barber had a strong case for his claim citing the testimony of another pilot from Yamamoto's Zero escort, Kenji Yanagiya, who saw Yamamoto's "Betty" crash 20 to 30 seconds after being hit from behind by fire from a P-38. Likewise the second Betty carrying Ugaki crashed 20 seconds after being struck by aircraft fire. Canning stated categorically that the P-38Gs flown that day did not have [[aileron]] boost to assist in turning (as did later models) making it physically impossible for Lanphier's aircraft to have made the 180 degree turn fast enough to intercept Yamamoto's plane in less than 30 seconds.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite magazine |url=http://www.airforcemag.com/MagazineArchive/Pages/2006/May%202006/0506letters.aspx |author=Douglas S. Canning |title=Who Shot Down Yamamoto? |date=May 2006 |magazine=Air Force Magazine}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Air Force later disqualified Lanphier's claim for shooting down a Zero in the battle, meaning that Lanphier lost his "[[Flying ace|ace]]" status as his total number of air-to-air kills dropped from five to four.

In spite of criticism from Barber and other surviving pilots from the mission, Lanphier continued to claim credit for downing Yamamoto until his death in 1987. Most newspaper obituaries reporting Lanphier's death credited him with killing Yamamoto. Rex Barber continued to contest Lanphier's claim, mainly in military circles and publications, until his death in 2001.&lt;ref name=NYT&gt;{{cite news |url=https://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/01/us/rex-t-barber-pilot-who-downed-yamamoto-dies-at-84.html |author=Richard Goldstein |title=Rex T. Barber, Pilot Who Downed Yamamoto, Dies at 84 |date=1 Aug 2001 |publisher=The New York Times Company |accessdate=27 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Lt. Julius Jacobson, another pilot on the mission, remarked in 1997, "There were 15 of us who survived, and as far as who did the effective shooting, who cares?"{{r|NYT}} [[Donald Rice]], the then secretary of the Air Force, commented in 1993, "Historians, fighter pilots and all of us who have studied the record of this extraordinary mission will forever speculate as to the exact events of that day in 1943. There is glory for the whole team."{{r|NYT}}

== Notes ==
{{reflist}}

== References ==
* {{cite book |last=Davis |first=Burke |authorlink= |year=1969 |chapter= |title=Get Yamamoto |url=https://archive.org/details/getyamamoto00davi |url-access=registration |publisher=[[Random House]] |location=New York |asin=B0006BZ2OC |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |last=Davis |first=Donald A. |authorlink= |year=2005 |chapter= |title=Lightning Strike: The Secret Mission to Kill Admiral Yamamoto and Avenge Pearl Harbor |publisher=[[St. Martin's Press]] |location=New York |isbn=0-312-30906-6}}
* {{cite book |last=Glines |first=Carroll V. |authorlink= |year=1990 |chapter= |title=Attack on Yamamoto |publisher=[[Crown Publishing Group|Crown]] (1st edition) |location=New York |isbn=0-517-57728-3 |ref=harv |url-access=registration |url=https://archive.org/details/attackonyamamoto00glin}}
* {{cite book |last=Hall |first=R. Cargill |authorlink= |year=1991 |chapter= |title=Lightning Over Bougainville |publisher=Smithsonian Institution Press |location=Washington, D.C. |isbn=1-56098-012-5}}
* {{cite book |last=Hammel |first=Eric |authorlink=Eric M. Hammel |year=1992 |chapter= |title=Aces Against Japan: The American Aces Speak |publisher=Pacifica Press |location= |isbn=0-935553-43-6}} - contains interview with Besby Frank Holmes.
* {{cite book |last=Hammel |first=Eric |authorlink=Eric M. Hammel |year=1996 |chapter= |title=Aces Against Japan II: The American Aces Speak |publisher=Pacifica Press |location= |isbn=0-935553-14-2}} - contains another interview with Besby Frank Holmes.
* {{cite web |last=Kyodo News |authorlink=Kyodo News |date=September 29, 2008 |url=http://search.japantimes.co.jp/cgi-bin/nn20080929a3.html |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120919142626/http://www.japantimes.co.jp/text/nn20080929a3.html |archivedate=19 September 2012 |title=Use of outdated code led to ambush that killed Yamamoto, U.S. files show |format=Newspaper article |work=[[The Japan Times]] |pages= |publisher= |language= |accessdate=September 29, 2008}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite magazine |last=Canning |first=Douglas S. |authorlink= |date=2006 |title=Who Shot Down Yamamoto?, letter |magazine=[[Air Force Magazine]] |publisher=Air Force Association |location=Arlington, Virginia |id= |volume=89 |number=5 |pages=7–8}}
* {{cite news |last=Holley |first=Joe |authorlink= |date=July 27, 2006 |title=Besby Frank Holmes; WWII Fighter Pilot |newspaper=[[The Washington Post]] |publisher= |location=Washington, DC}} - obituary on the death of Lt. Col. Frank Holmes.
* {{cite book |last=Kahn |first=David |authorlink= |year=1996 |chapter=Chapter 17: The Scrutable Orientals; pp 595-601 |title=The Codebreakers: The Comprehensive History of Secret Communication from Ancient Times to the Internet, Revised and Updated |publisher=Scribner |location=New York |isbn=0-684-83130-9}}

==External links==
{{Commons|Isoroku Yamamoto}}
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4Q_Io28IO3w Yamamoto's Plane Wreck] footage of wreck published in 2015 (YouTube)
{{Spoken Wikipedia|En-OperationVengeance-article.ogg|2017-12-16}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Vengeance, Operation}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1943]]
[[Category:Imperial Japanese Navy]]
[[Category:Military history of Japan during World War II]]
[[Category:Pacific Ocean theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:1943 in the Solomon Islands]]
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the Solomon Islands]]
[[Category:20th-century aircraft shootdown incidents]]
[[Category:Military assassinations]]
[[Category:April 1943 events]]</text><sha1>ac5c2v232mp9vseh0wyvavqc7315lhv</sha1></revision></page>