<page><title>Battle of Kolombangara</title><ns>0</ns><id>545536</id><revision><id>966476582</id><parentid>966476485</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-07T10:15:50Z</timestamp><contributor><username>AustralianRupert</username><id>8731061</id></contributor><comment>fix ref</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="23774" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Battle of Kolombangara
| image = USS St. Louis (CL-49) and HMNZS Leander firing during the Battle of Kolombangara, 13 July 1943 (80-G-342763).jpg
| image_size = 300
|caption = The cruisers {{USS|St. Louis|CL-49|6}} and {{Ship|HMNZS|Leander}} firing
|partof = the [[Pacific War|Pacific Theater]] of [[World War II]]
|date = 12/13 July 1943
|place = [[Kolombangara]] in the [[Solomon Islands]]
|result = Japanese tactical victory
|combatant1 = {{flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br/&gt;{{flag|New Zealand}}
|combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
|commander1 = {{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Walden L. Ainsworth|Walden Ainsworth]]
|commander2 = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan|naval}} [[Shunji Isaki]]{{KIA}}
|strength1 = 3 light cruisers,&lt;br/&gt;10 destroyers
|strength2 = 1 light cruiser,&lt;br/&gt;5 destroyers &lt;br/&gt;4 destroyer-transports
|casualties1 = 1 destroyer sunk,&lt;br/&gt;3 light cruisers damaged (one heavily),&lt;br/&gt;89 killed&lt;ref name=Morison186&amp;189&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks'', p. 186 &amp; 189.&lt;/ref&gt;
|casualties2 = 1 light cruiser sunk,&lt;br/&gt;482 killed&lt;ref name=Japaneselosses&gt;Hackett, Bob; Kingsepp, Sander, [http://www.combinedfleet.com/jintsu_t.htm ''Jintsu''], ''combinedfleet.com''. Retrieved 31 May 2020; Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks'', p. 184.&lt;/ref&gt;
|campaignbox=
{{Campaignbox New Georgia}}
{{Campaignbox Solomons}}
}}
The '''Battle of Kolombangara''' (Japanese:  コロンバンガラ島沖海戦) (also known as the '''Second Battle of Kula Gulf'''&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.fold3.com/document/269658505/ |title=USS ''St Louis'': Second Battle of Kula Gul, 7/12-13/43 |work=World War II War Diaries, 1941–1945 |publisher=NARA|via=Fold3 |accessdate=31 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt;) was a [[naval battle]] of the [[Pacific War|Pacific campaign]] of [[World War II]], fought on the night of 12/13 July 1943, off the northeastern coast of [[Kolombangara]] in the [[Solomon Islands]]. The battle took place during the early stages of the [[New Georgia campaign]] when an [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] force, carrying reinforcements south to [[Vila, Solomon Islands]], was intercepted by a task force of U.S. and New Zealand [[light cruiser]]s and [[destroyer]]s. In the ensuing action, the Japanese sunk one Allied destroyer and damaged three cruisers. They were also able to successfully land 1,200 ground troops on the western coast of Kolombangara but lost one light cruiser sunk with all hands in the process.

==Background==
The Allied campaign in New Georgia had begun on 30 June as part of their advance through the central Solomon Islands towards [[Rabaul]] under the guise of [[Operation Cartwheel]]. In the initial phase of the operation, [[Landings on Rendova|Rendova]] had been captured to provide a staging point for U.S. forces assigned to capture the Japanese airfield at [[Munda, Solomon Islands|Munda Point]], which was one of the campaign's key objectives. On 2 July, troops of the U.S. [[43rd Infantry Division (United States)|43rd Infantry Division]] landed on [[New Georgia]] to [[Drive on Munda Point|attack Munda]], while three days later a battalion [[Marine Raiders]] and two U.S. Army battalions were landed at Rice Anchorage on New Georgia's northern shore to [[Battle of Enogai|seize Bairoko]].&lt;ref name=Stille42-44&gt;Stille, ''The Solomons 1943–44'', pp. 42–44, 48–52&lt;/ref&gt;

In response to the Allied landings, the Japanese sought to reinforce New Georgia to shore up the southern flank to their base around Rabaul.&lt;ref&gt;Stille, ''The Solomons 1943–44'', backcover&lt;/ref&gt; On the night of 12 July 1943, a  Japanese "[[Tokyo Express]]" naval reinforcement force made a run down "[[New Georgia Sound|The Slot]]" from the [[Rabaul]] to land troops at [[Vila, Solomon Islands|Vila]] on Kolombangara by way of the [[Kula Gulf]]. This force was commanded by [[Rear Admiral]] (少将 ''shōshō'') [[Shunji Isaki]] and consisted of the [[light cruiser]] {{Ship|Japanese cruiser|Jintsū||2}}, the [[destroyer]]s {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Mikazuki|1926|2}}, {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Yukikaze|1939|2}}, {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Hamakaze|1940|2}}, {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Kiyonami||2}} and {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Yūgure|1934|2}},&lt;ref name=Stille49map/&gt; as well as the [[destroyer transport]]s {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Satsuki|1925|2}}, {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Minazuki|1926|2}}, {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Yūnagi|1924|2}}, and {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Matsukaze|1923|2}}. These four ships carried 1,200 ground troops which were to be landed on Kolombangara as part of efforts to reinforce area in response to the Allied [[New Georgia campaign|landings in New Georgia]].&lt;ref&gt;Stille, ''The Solomons 1943–44'', p. 49&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese ships of Isaki's force had been drawn from a number of different numbered elements, but the core was formed by Destroyer Squadron 2.&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', p. 181&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:SolomonsNewGeorgiaPacificWarMap.jpg|thumb|left|350px|Map of Solomon Islands]]

The movement of Japanese ships was detected by [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] [[coastwatchers]] and reported. In response Admiral [[William Halsey]] ordered a naval task force to intercept the Japanese ships. The Allied naval force, designated Task Force 18, was commanded by Rear Admiral [[Walden L. Ainsworth]]. It consisted of two [[United States Navy]] light cruisers, {{USS|Honolulu|CL-48|6}} and {{USS|St. Louis|CL-49|2}} and the [[Royal New Zealand Navy]] light cruiser {{HMNZS|Leander}}, and the destroyers {{USS|Nicholas|DD-449|6}}, {{USS|O'Bannon|DD-450|2}}, {{USS|Taylor|DD-468|2}}, {{USS|Jenkins|DD-447|2}}, {{USS|Radford|DD-446|2}}, {{USS|Ralph Talbot|DD-390|2}}, {{USS|Buchanan|DD-484|2}}, {{USS|Maury|DD-401|2}}, {{USS|Woodworth|DD-460|2}}, and {{USS|Gwin|DD-433|2}}.&lt;ref name=Morison178181-182/&gt;

In battle these Allied vessels deployed in a single column with five destroyers in the van followed by the light cruisers and then by five destroyers in the rear.&lt;ref name=Stille49map&gt;Stille, ''The Solomons 1943–44'', p. 49 (map)&lt;/ref&gt; Each group of five destroyers formed a [[Squadron (naval)|squadron]]. The first of these, designated Destroyer Squadron 21, was commanded by Captain [[Francis X. McInerney]]. The second destroyer squadron was Captain [[Thomas J. Ryan (admiral)|Thomas J. Ryan]]'s Destroyer Squadron 12; it had only recently been assigned to Ainworth's task force, as had the New Zealand cruiser which had been assigned to Ainsworth's force following the loss of {{USS|Helena}} during the [[Battle of Kula Gulf]] on 6 July. Together, the three cruisers were grouped together as Cruiser Division 9.&lt;ref name=Morison178181-182&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', pp. 178, 181–182&lt;/ref&gt; Ainsworth's mission was to prevent Japanese troops and supplies from landing as part of efforts to stem the flow of reinforcements towards Munda.&lt;ref name=Stille42-44&gt;Stille, ''The Solomons 1943–44'', pp. 42–44, 48–52&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=remembering/&gt;

==Battle==
The U.S. task force sailed from its base around [[Tulagi]] at 17:00 on 12 July, amidst clear skies and calm seas. Passing [[Savo Island]], Ainsworth steered a course along the west coast of [[Santa Isabel Island]], hoping to use it to hide his force from Japanese reconnaissance aircraft. His plan for the attack was to use the first squadron of five destroyers that formed his vanguard to fire torpedoes while his cruisers maneuvered into a position to use their main guns. After laying down a heavy barrage the cruisers would maneuver again to avoid return torpedoes from the Japanese destroyers.&lt;ref name=Morison180&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', p. 180&lt;/ref&gt; Having gone to [[general quarters]] due to concerns about being spotted in the bright moonlight of the clear night sky, around midnight the U.S task force altered course towards Visu Visu. They then increased their speed following reports from Allied reconnaissance aircraft that had spotted Isaki's force about {{convert|26|mi}} away. Hamstrung by their slowest ship, ''Leander'', Ainsworth's task group was only able to make {{convert|28|kn}} while Isaki's force was estimated to cruising at {{convert|30|kn}}.&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', pp. 182–183&lt;/ref&gt;

As the skies began to grow overcast, at 01:00 on 13 July, the Allied ships established radar contact about {{convert|20|mi|nmi km|lk=on|abbr=on}} east of the northern tip of [[Kolombangara]] at {{coord|7|50|S|157|21|E|type:landmark|display=inline,title}}. Ainsworth assumed he had a complete surprise as the Japanese lacked radar, but in reality, the Japanese had been aware of the Allied force for almost two hours. Despite not possessing radar, the Japanese ships had the ability to detect the electric impulses of the Allied radar systems, and from this, the Japanese crews were able to gain an accurate plot of Ainsworth's dispositions. After sighting the Japanese force at 01:03, the U.S. destroyers of McInerney's squadron increased speed to engage the Japanese force with their torpedoes while the cruisers turned to deploy their main batteries and engage to starboard. Unknown to Ainsworth, the Japanese destroyers had already launched [[Long Lance torpedo]]es, which had a longer range than the Allied torpedoes. After firing their salvoes between 01:08 and 01:14, the Japanese destroyers turned away to regroup.&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', pp. 183–184&lt;/ref&gt; 

[[File:USS St. Louis (CL-49) at Tulagi, after she was torpedoed in the Battle of Kolombangara, 20 July 1943 (80-G-259410).jpg|thumb|''St Louis'' at Tulagi after being torpedoed during the battle]]

The first U.S. torpedoes hit the water about a minute after their Japanese counterparts, with ''Nicholas'' engaging ''Jintsū'' at a range of just under {{convert|10,000|yd}}. ''Jintsū'' turned on her searchlight and engaged the Allied ships, but was subjected to concentrated Allied fire from a range of around {{convert|9,000|yd}}, with 2,630 rounds being fired under the direction of spotting aircraft overhead. After minor corrections to their fall of shot, the Japanese cruiser was heavily damaged. After losing steerage around 01:17, ''Jintsū'' came to a dead stop. It was eventually reduced to a wreck, broken in two by several torpedo hits, and sank at about 01:45, with the loss of nearly her entire crew, including Isaki.&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', pp. 184–185&lt;/ref&gt; On the Allied side, ''Leander'' was hit by a shell from ''Jintsū''. The damage was light, but severed radio communications. Several Japanese torpedoes were spotted, and the Allied ships began evasive action. These counter maneuvers were hampered by faulty communications and thick gunsmoke that reduced visibility. Consequently, several ships turned wide to avoid collisions, including ''Leander'', which was struck by one of the Japanese torpedoes. Severely damaged, the New Zealand cruiser retired from the battle escorted by ''Radford'' and ''Jenkins''.&lt;ref name&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', p. 186&lt;/ref&gt; 

Amidst the confusion of the initial battle, Ryan's destroyer squadron began its torpedo run from a distance of {{convert|7,900|yd}}, firing his first salvo around 01:12. McInerney's destroyers, except ''Radford'' and ''Jenkins'', were detached from the task force by Ainsworth at 01:31 to pursue contacts to the west following a reconnaissance report from the supporting aircraft that indicated several destroyers were withdrawing in that direction. Meanwhile, the four Japanese destroyer-transports began to withdraw along the coast, while the four Japanese escort destroyers temporarily retired north under the command of Captain Yoshima Shimai to use the cover of a rain squall to reload their torpedo tubes, doing so in only 18 minutes. Ainsworth then pursued the Japanese destroyers with Ryan's destroyers and his own three cruisers, altering course to the northwest.&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', p. 187&lt;/ref&gt; 

Radar contact was reestablished by the U.S. ships at 01:56, but there was uncertainty about the identity of the ships among Ainsworth's advisers. Believing that they may have been McInerney's destroyers, the U.S. ships initially held their fire while they sought to confirm the location of three detached destroyers. At 02:03, [[Shell (projectile)#Illumination|starshell]]s were fired to illuminate the contacts that had begun to withdraw. Shortly afterward, Ainsworth deployed his ships to begin firing with their main batteries, maneuvering to starboard. In the process, they moved into the path of a number of torpedoes that had been fired by the Japanese destroyers before they had turned about. In the process, ''St. Louis'' and ''Honolulu'' were both struck by torpedoes and damaged, although this was not mortal. The destroyer ''Ralph Talbot'' managed to reply with a salvo of four torpedoes, but these failed to hit anything. A minute later the destroyer ''Gwin'' was also struck by a torpedo amidships, inflicting heavy damage. Despite efforts to save the ship by its crew, ''Gwin'' was scuttled at 09:30. A total of 61 men were killed on ''Gwin'' as a result of the torpedo attack. Its surviving crew were subsequently evacuated on ''Ralph Talbot''.&lt;ref&gt;Stille, ''The Solomons 1943–44'', pp. 50–52&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', pp. 187–189&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:JintsuSurvivor.jpg|thumb|right|''Jintsū'' survivors aboard USS ''Nicholas''.]]
Following the battle, Ainsworth's force withdrew back to Tulagi.&lt;ref name=remembering&gt;{{cite web |url=http://navymuseum.co.nz/remembering-the-battle-of-kolombangara/ |title=Remembering the Battle of Kolombangara |publisher=National Museum of the Royal New Zealand Navy  |accessdate=31 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; Sailing through The Slot in daylight risked air attack from the Japanese. As a result, Ainsworth requested air support and a strong fighter force was provided from bases in the [[Russell Islands]] to cover the withdrawal. Early on 13 July, a force of 18 Japanese [[dive bomber]]s, escorted by 20 [[Fighter aircraft|fighter]]s, was dispatched to attack the Allied ships, but they were turned back after clashing off Visu Visu.&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', pp. 189–190&lt;/ref&gt; 

Except for ''Jintsū'', which went down with 482 men,&lt;ref&gt;Stille, ''The Solomons 1943–44'', p. 51&lt;/ref&gt; the Japanese force escaped damage. After withdrawing along the coast, the four destroyer transports had diverted through the Vella Gulf and successfully landed 1,200 men at Sandfly Harbor, on the western coast of Kolombangara. They completed unloading at 03:40 after which the Japanese ships searched for survivors from ''Jintsū'' and then returned to [[Buin, Papua New Guinea|Buin]].&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', p. 190&lt;/ref&gt; A total of 21 survivors from ''Jintsū'' were subsequently rescued by {{Jsub|I-180}}; a few others were rescued by American ships.&lt;ref name="combinedfleetI-180"&gt;{{cite web |url= http://www.combinedfleet.com/I-180.htm |title=IJN Submarine I-180: Tabular Record of Movement |first1=Bob |last1=Hackett |first2=Sander |last2=Kingsepp |work=combinedfleet.com |year=2012|accessdate=20 January 2012}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', p. 190&lt;/ref&gt; Allied losses amounted to one destroyer sunk, and three light cruisers damaged, one heavily. A total of 89 Allied sailors were killed, including 28 New Zealanders from ''Leander''.&lt;ref name=Morison186&amp;189&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks'', p. 186 &amp; 189.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Honolulu'' and ''St. Louis'' were out of action for several months, while ''Leander'' was under repair for a year and never returned to action during World War II.&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', p. 190 (note)&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://nzhistory.govt.nz/war/hmnzs-leander/last-days |title=HMNZS ''Leander'': Last days |publisher=New Zealand Government |accessdate=30 May 2020}}&lt;/ref&gt; 

The Japanese had won a tactical victory, and had demonstrated that they possessed superior night-fighting techniques,&lt;ref&gt;Dull, ''A Battle History of the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1941–1945'', p. 276&lt;/ref&gt; but of the action the naval historian [[Samuel Eliot Morison]] wrote: "A string of such victories add[ed] up to defeat."&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', p. 197&lt;/ref&gt; Paul Dull further describes the battle as one in a "series of Pyrrhic victories for the Japanese" as they were unable to match the capacity of US industry to replace their losses.&lt;ref&gt;Dull, ''A Battle History of the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1941–1945'', p. 277&lt;/ref&gt; Ainsworth's force was unable to prevent the flow of Japanese reinforcements south as the lines between Bairoko and the Diamond Narrows remained open.&lt;ref&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', p 198&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, strategically, the battle forced a change in Japanese tactics. Combined with the earlier Battle of Kula Gulf, the engagement eventually deterred the Japanese from future use of the Kula Gulf to reinforce Munda. The Allied naval commander, Admiral [[Chester Nimitz]], also changed tactics, deciding that the use of cruisers in the confined waters around the Solomon Islands was too dangerous and ineffective. Meanwhile, for the Japanese destroyer losses necessitated the use of ''Daihatsu'' barges to move reinforcements between the Shortland Islands and the Kula Gulf. Consequently, the U.S. Navy concentrated responsibility for its interdiction efforts on its destroyer force and [[PT boat]]s.&lt;ref name=Morison207-212&gt;Morison, ''Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', pp. 207–212&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Stille526366/&gt;

Throughout July and into early August, a series of nightly actions took place involving by U.S. destroyers, PT boats and aircraft against the Japanese reinforcement efforts. The most significant action during this time came on the night of 19/20 July, when a force of 11 ships, consisting of cruisers and destroyers under Rear Admiral Shoji Nishimura, was detected by US aircraft in The Slot. At least one destroyer, ''Yugure'', was sunk, and the cruiser ''Kumano'' was damaged, while four US aircraft were lost.  After this, the Japanese chose to use the [[Vella Gulf]] and the [[Blackett Strait]] along the western coast of Kolombangara rather than the direct route through the Kula Gulf. This resulted in the [[Battle of Vella Gulf]] and [[Battle off Horaniu]] in early August.&lt;ref name=Morison207-212/&gt;&lt;ref name=Stille526366&gt;Stille, ''The Solomons 1943–44'', p. 52 &amp; 63, 66&lt;/ref&gt; In late September and early October, the Japanese began evacuating their ground troops from Kolombangara. A series of interdiction actions took place during which the U.S. Navy claimed to have sunk 46 barges, killing thousands of Japanese troops. Another action was fought between Japanese and U.S. destroyers off Kolombangara on the night of 2–3 October during which both sides ineffectively exchanged torpedoes and gunfire.&lt;ref&gt;Stille, ''The Solomons 1943–44'', pp. 68–69&lt;/ref&gt;

{{Commons|Battle of Kolombangara}}

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
*{{cite book | last = Dull | first = Paul S. | authorlink =  | year = 1978 | chapter =  | title = A Battle History of the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1941–1945 | publisher = Naval Institute Press | location =  | isbn = 0-87021-097-1 | url-access = registration | url = https://archive.org/details/battlehistoryofi0000dull }}
*{{cite book | last = Morison | first = Samuel Eliot | authorlink = Samuel Eliot Morison | year = 1958 | chapter = | title = Breaking the Bismarcks Barrier'', vol. 6 of ''[[History of United States Naval Operations in World War II]] | publisher = Castle Books | location = | isbn = 0-7858-1307-1 }}
* {{cite book |last=Stille |first=Mark |year=2018 |title=The Solomons 1943–44: The Struggle for New Georgia and Bougainville |publisher=Osprey |location=Oxford |isbn=978-1-47282-447-9}}

==Further reading==
*{{cite book | last = Brown | first = David | authorlink = | year = 1990 | title = Warship Losses of World War Two | publisher = Naval Institute Press | location = | isbn = 1-55750-914-X }}
*{{cite book | last = Crenshaw | first = Russell Sydnor | authorlink = | year = 1998 | chapter = | title = South Pacific Destroyer: The Battle for the Solomons from Savo Island to Vella Gulf | publisher = Naval Institute Press | location = | isbn = 1-55750-136-X }}
*{{cite book | last = D'Albas | first = Andrieu | authorlink = | year = 1965 | title = Death of a Navy: Japanese Naval Action in World War II | publisher = Devin-Adair Pub | location = | isbn = 0-8159-5302-X }}
*{{cite book | last = Hara | first = Tameichi | authorlink = Tameichi Hara | year = 1961 | title = Japanese Destroyer Captain | publisher = Collins Bros | location = Auckland &amp; London | isbn = }}
*{{cite book | last = Harker | first = Jack S. | authorlink = | year = 1971| title = Well Done Leander | publisher = [[Ballantine Books]] | location = New York &amp; Toronto | isbn = 0-345-27894-1 }}
*{{Cite book | last = Hone | first = Thomas C.|year = 1981 | title = The Similarity of Past and Present Standoff Threats | editor-last = | periodical = Proceedings of the U.S. Naval Institute | publication-place = Annapolis, Maryland | issue = Vol. 107, No. 9, September 1981 | publisher = | pages = 113–116 | issn = 0041-798X }}
*{{cite book | last = Lacroix | first = Eric | authorlink = |author2=Linton Wells | year = 1997 | chapter = | title = Japanese Cruisers of the Pacific War | publisher = Naval Institute Press | location = | isbn = 0-87021-311-3 }}
*{{cite book | last = Kilpatrick | first = C. W. | authorlink = | year = 1987 | chapter = | title = Naval Night Battles of the Solomons | publisher = Exposition Press | location = | isbn = 0-682-40333-4 }}
*{{cite book | last = McGee | first = William L. | authorlink = | year = 2002 | chapter = Operation Toenails | title = The Solomons Campaigns, 1942–1943: From Guadalcanal to Bougainville—Pacific War Turning Point, Volume 2 (Amphibious Operations in the South Pacific in WWII) | publisher = BMC Publications | location = | isbn = 0-9701678-7-3 }}
*{{cite book | last = Parkin | first = Robert Sinclair | authorlink = | year = 1995 | title = Blood on the Sea: American Destroyers Lost in World War II | publisher = Da Capo Press | location = | isbn = 0-306-81069-7 }}
*{{cite book | last = Roscoe | first = Theodore | authorlink =  | year = 1953 | chapter =  | title = United States Destroyer Operations in World War Two | publisher = Naval Institute Press | location =  | isbn = 0-87021-726-7 | url = https://archive.org/details/unitedstatesdest0000rosc }}

==External links==
*{{cite web | last = Parshall | first = Jon |author2=Bob Hackett |author3=Sander Kingsepp |author4=Allyn Nevitt  | url = http://www.combinedfleet.com/kaigun.htm | title = Imperial Japanese Navy Page |website=Combinedfleet.com | accessdate = 14 June 2006 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20060613172444/http://www.combinedfleet.com/kaigun.htm| archivedate= 13 June 2006 | url-status= live}}
*[http://www.microworks.net/pacific/battles/kolombangara.htm Battle of Kolombangara], by Vincent O'Hara
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20060323031827/http://www.ww2db.com/battle_spec.php?battle_id=8 Solomons Campaign], by C. Peter Chen, ''World War II Database''
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2017}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1943|Kolombangara]]
[[Category:Pacific Ocean theatre of World War II|Kolombangara]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Japan|Kolombangara]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving New Zealand|Kolombangara]]
[[Category:1943 in Japan]]
[[Category:1943 in the Solomon Islands]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the Solomon Islands|Kolombangara]]</text><sha1>erjkqxgrh0ouei7d4mpchx50yw0labm</sha1></revision></page>