<page><title>Battle of Morotai</title><ns>0</ns><id>15441402</id><revision><id>967086471</id><parentid>966139718</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-11T02:03:59Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Nick-D</username><id>415269</id></contributor><comment>remove 'native' - my bad</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="46470" xml:space="preserve">{{Coord|02|01|52|N|128|17|26|E|display=title}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict   = Battle of Morotai
| partof     = the [[Western New Guinea campaign]], [[World War II]]
| image      = [[File:Morotai LSTs.jpg|300px|alt=A peninsula with eight ships beached on the shore in the foreground and over eleven ships anchored off the opposite shore. Smoke is rising from the peninsula.|LSTs landing supplies at Blue Beach, Morotai]]
| caption    = [[Tank landing ship|LSTs]] landing supplies at Blue Beach, Morotai
| date       = 15 September – 4 October 1944 (initial period), intermittent fighting continued until the end of the war
| place      = [[Morotai]], off [[North Halmahera]], [[Maluku Islands]]
| result     = Allied victory
| combatant1 = {{flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Australia}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Netherlands}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}
| combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
| commander1 = Clarence Martin (land)&lt;br /&gt;[[Daniel E. Barbey]] (naval)
| commander2 = Takenobu Kawashima&lt;br&gt;(initial commander)&lt;br&gt;
Kisou Ouchi{{POW}}&lt;br&gt;(from 12 October)&lt;ref&gt;33rd Infantry Division Historical Committee (1948), p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength1   = 57,020 (initial force)
| strength2   = ~500 at the time of&lt;br&gt;the Allied invasion,&lt;br&gt;later reinforced
| casualties1 = 
| casualties2 = 
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Western New Guinea}}{{Campaignbox New Guinea}}
}}
The '''Battle of Morotai''', part of the [[Pacific War]], began on 15 September 1944, and continued until the end of the war in August 1945. The fighting started when United States and Australian forces landed on the southwest corner of [[Morotai]], a small island in the [[Dutch East Indies|Netherlands East Indies]] (NEI), which the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] needed as a base to support the [[Philippines campaign (1944–45)|liberation of the Philippines]] later that year. The invading forces greatly outnumbered the island's [[Empire of Japan|Japanese]] defenders and secured their objectives in two weeks. Japanese reinforcements landed on the island between September and November, but lacked the supplies needed to effectively attack the Allied defensive perimeter. Intermittent fighting continued until the end of the war, with the Japanese troops suffering heavy loss of life from disease and starvation.

Morotai's development into an Allied base began shortly after the landing, and two major airfields were ready for use in October. These and other base facilities played an important role in the [[Philippines Campaign (1944–45)|Liberation of the Philippines]] during 1944 and 1945. Torpedo boats and aircraft based at Morotai also harassed Japanese positions in the NEI. The island's base facilities were further expanded in 1945 to support the Australian-led [[Borneo Campaign (1945)|Borneo Campaign]], and Morotai remained an important logistical hub and command center until the Dutch reestablished their colonial rule in the NEI.

==Background==
[[File:The Western Pacific, New Guinea And The Philippine Islands.jpg|thumb|left|300px|alt=Map showing the strategic situation in the Western Pacific region, including the location of military units and military operations described in the article|Allied operations and major Japanese garrisons in the Western Pacific between July and September 1944]]
Morotai is a small island located in the [[Halmahera]] group of eastern [[Indonesia]]'s [[Maluku Islands]]. Most of the island's interior is rugged and covered in thick [[jungle]]. The Doroeba Plain in Morotai's south-west corner is the largest of the island's few [[lowland]] areas. Prior to the outbreak of war, Morotai had a population of 9,000 and had not been commercially developed. It formed part of the Netherlands East Indies and was ruled by the Dutch through the [[Sultanate of Ternate]]. The Japanese occupied Morotai in early 1942 during the [[Netherlands East Indies campaign]] but did not garrison or develop it.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), pp. 456–457.&lt;/ref&gt;

In early 1944, Morotai became an area of importance to the Japanese military when it started developing the neighbouring larger island of [[Halmahera]] as a focal point for the defence of the southern approaches to the Philippines.&lt;ref name="Smith 1953, pp. 460"&gt;Smith (1953), p. 460.&lt;/ref&gt; In May 1944, the [[Imperial Japanese Army]]'s [[32nd Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|32nd Division]] arrived at Halmahera to defend the island and its nine airstrips.&lt;ref name="Smith 1953, pp. 460" /&gt; The division had suffered heavy losses when the convoy carrying it from China (the [[Take Ichi convoy]]) was attacked by US [[submarine]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Willoughby (1966), p. 273.&lt;/ref&gt; Two battalions from the 32nd Division's 211th Infantry Regiment were initially deployed to Morotai to develop an airstrip on the Doroeba Plain. Both battalions were withdrawn to Halmahera in mid-July, however, when the airstrip was abandoned because of drainage problems.&lt;ref name="Willoughby 1966 pp. 348"&gt;Willoughby (1966), pp. 348–349.&lt;/ref&gt; Allied [[Cryptanalysis|code breakers]] detected the Japanese build up at Halmahera and Morotai's weak defenses, and passed this information on to the relevant planning staff.&lt;ref name ="Drea_153"&gt;Drea (1992), p. 153.&lt;/ref&gt;

In July 1944, General [[Douglas MacArthur]], the [[South West Pacific Area (command)|commander of the South West Pacific Area]], selected Morotai as the location for air bases and naval facilities needed to support the liberation of [[Mindanao]] in the Philippines, which at the time was planned for 15 November. While Morotai was undeveloped, it was preferred over Halmahera as the larger and much better-defended island was judged too difficult to capture and secure.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), pp. 450–451.&lt;/ref&gt; The occupation of Morotai was designated Operation Tradewind. The landing was scheduled to take place on 15 September 1944, the same day as the [[1st Marine Division (United States)|1st Marine Division's]] [[Battle of Peleliu|landing at Peleliu]]. This schedule allowed the main body of the [[United States Pacific Fleet]] to simultaneously protect both operations from potential Japanese counter-attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Taaffe (1998), p. 218.&lt;/ref&gt;

As little opposition was expected at Morotai, Allied planners decided to land the invasion force close to the airfield sites on the Doroeba Plain. Two beaches in the south-west coast of the island were selected as suitable landing sites, and were designated Red Beach and White Beach. The Allied plan called for all three infantry regiments of the 31st Division to be landed across these beaches on 15 September and swiftly drive inland to secure the plain. As Morotai's interior had no military value, the Allies did not intend to advance beyond a perimeter needed to defend the airfields.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), pp. 475–477.&lt;/ref&gt; Planning for the construction of airfields and other base installations was also conducted prior to the landing, and tentative locations for these facilities had been selected by 15 September.&lt;ref name="Chief_Engineer_272"&gt;Office of the Chief Engineer, General Headquarters, Army Forces Pacific (1951), p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==

===Opposing forces===
At the time of the Allied landings, Morotai was defended by approximately 500 Japanese soldiers. The main unit was the 2nd Provisional Raiding Unit, which had gradually arrived on the island between 12–19 July 1944, to replace the 32nd Division's battalions when they were withdrawn. The 2nd Provisional Raiding Unit comprised four [[Company (military unit)|companies]] and was manned by Japanese officers and [[Taiwan|Formosan]] soldiers. Small elements of several other infantry, [[military police]] and support units were also present on the island. The 2nd Provisional Raiding Unit's commander, Major Takenobu Kawashima, deployed the unit in the south-west sector of the island and used the smaller units to establish lookout posts and detachments around Morotai's coastline.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), p. 460 and Willoughby (1966), pp. 349–350.&lt;/ref&gt; The largest of these outposts was on the island's north-east end at Cape Sopi, which consisted of about 100 men.&lt;ref&gt;Rottman (2002), p. 253.&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese force was too small and widely dispersed to be able to mount an effective defense, so the 32nd Division ordered it to build dummy camps and use other deceptions in an attempt to trick the Allies into thinking that Morotai was strongly held.&lt;ref name="Willoughby 1966 pp. 348" /&gt;
[[File:Landing craft 017615.jpg|thumb|left|alt=A group of World War II-era ships at sea photographed from another ship. Two men wearing helmets are in the foreground.|A long line of Allied landing craft and transports approaching Morotai]]

The Allied force assigned to Morotai outnumbered the island's defenders by more than one hundred to one. The Tradewind Task Force was established on 20 August under the command of Major General [[Charles P. Hall]] and numbered 40,105 U.S. Army soldiers and 16,915 [[United States Army Air Forces]] (USAAF) and [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF) personnel. The Tradewind Task Force came under the overall command of the [[Sixth United States Army|United States Sixth Army]]; its main combat elements were the [[XI Corps (United States)|XI Corps]] headquarters, the [[31st Infantry Division (United States)|31st Infantry Division]] and the [[126th Cavalry Regiment|126th]] [[Regimental combat team|Regimental Combat Team]] (RCT) from the [[32nd Infantry Division (United States)|32nd Infantry Division]]. These units were supported by engineers and a large anti-aircraft group. The Tradewind Task Force also included large numbers of construction and other line of communications units whose role was to swiftly develop the island into a major base. The [[6th Infantry Division (United States)|6th Infantry Division]] was designated the force reserve but remained on the mainland of New Guinea.&lt;ref&gt;Krueger (1979), p. 126 and Smith (1953), p. 463.&lt;/ref&gt; General MacArthur accompanied the force on board {{USS|Nashville|CL-43|6}} but was not in direct command of the operation.&lt;ref&gt;Manchester (1978), p. 337.&lt;/ref&gt;

The landing force was supported by powerful air and naval forces. The United States [[Fifth Air Force]] provided direct support while the [[Thirteenth Air Force]] and [[Australian First Tactical Air Force|No. 10 Operational Group RAAF]] conducted strategic missions in the NEI and Philippines.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), p. 464.&lt;/ref&gt; The naval force was designated [[Task Force 77 (United States Navy)|Task Force 77]] and was organised into two attack groups, four reinforcement groups, a support group and an [[escort carrier]] group. The attack and reinforcement groups were responsible for transporting the assault force and subsequent support units and comprised twenty-four [[destroyer]]s, four [[frigate]]s, two Australian [[Landing ship infantry|LSIs]], five [[High speed transport|APDs]], one [[Dock landing ship|LSD]], twenty-four [[Landing Craft Infantry|LCIs]], forty-five [[Landing Ship, Tank|LSTs]], twenty [[Landing craft tank|LCTs]] and eleven LCIs armed with rockets. The support group was made up of two Australian [[heavy cruiser]]s, three US [[light cruiser]]s and eight US and two Australian destroyers. The escort carrier group comprised six escort carriers and ten [[destroyer escort]]s and provided [[Anti-submarine warfare|anti-submarine]] and [[combat air patrol]]. [[Fast Carrier Task Force|Task Force 38.4]] with two [[Aircraft carrier|fleet carriers]], two [[light aircraft carrier]]s, one heavy cruiser, one light cruiser and thirteen destroyers was also available to support Task Force 77 if required.&lt;ref&gt;Morison (2002), pp. 21–22, Krueger (1979), p. 127 and Royal Navy Historical Section (1957), pp. 173 and 257.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Preliminary attacks===
Preliminary air attacks to suppress the Japanese air forces in the vicinity of Morotai began in August 1944. At this time, the Allied intelligence services estimated that there were 582 Japanese aircraft within {{convert|400|mi|km}} of Morotai, 400 of which were in the objective area. The Allied air forces conducted heavy raids on airfields in the [[Halmahera]]s, [[Sulawesi|Celebes]], [[Seram Island|Ceram]], [[Ambon Island|Ambon]], [[Buru|Boeroe]] and other areas. US Navy carrier-borne aircraft also attacked Japanese air units based at Mindanao and mounted further attacks on Halmahera and Celebes. These attacks were successful, and by 14 September it was estimated that only 60 aircraft remained in the vicinity of Morotai.&lt;ref&gt;Royal Navy Historical Section (1957), p. 175 and Taaffe (1998), p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt;

To preserve surprise, the Allies did not bombard Morotai prior to the invasion and conducted only a few photographic reconnaissance flights over the island.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), pp. 482–483.&lt;/ref&gt; An [[Allied Intelligence Bureau]] patrol had been landed in the island in June but the information it collected was not passed on to the Sixth Army. Although the Tradewind Taskforce had little information on the invasion beaches or Japanese positions, the Sixth Army did not land any of its own reconnaissance patrols on Morotai, as it was feared that these could warn the island's defenders that an attack was imminent.&lt;ref&gt;Krueger (1979), p. 125.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Tradewind Taskforce embarked onto the invasion convoy at several bases in north-west [[New Guinea]], and conducted landing rehearsals at [[Aitape]] and [[Wakde Island]] in early September. The convoy gathered at [[Maffin Bay]] on 11 September and set out for Morotai the next day. Its voyage was uneventful, and the convoy arrived off Morotai on the morning of 15 September without having been detected by Japanese forces.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), pp. 481–482.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Allied landings==
[[File:Morotai landings 15 September 1944.jpg|thumb|300px|alt=A map of south-west Morotai illustrating the locations where the three US Army regiments landed on 15 September, their D-Day objectives and the locations of the landing beaches and airfields named in the text.|Locations of the Allied landings on 15 September 1944]]

The battle of Morotai began at 6:30 on the morning of 15 September. Allied warships conducted a two-hour-long bombardment of the landing area to suppress any Japanese forces there. This bombardment set several villages on fire, but caused few Japanese casualties as they did not have many troops in the area.&lt;ref&gt;Taaffe (1998), p. 219.&lt;/ref&gt;

The first wave of American troops landed on Morotai at 8:30 and did not encounter any opposition. The 155th and 167th RCTs landed at Red Beach and the 124th RCT at White Beach. Once ashore, the assault troops assembled into their tactical units and rapidly advanced inland. By the end of the day the 31st Division had secured all of its [[D-Day (military term)|D-Day]] objectives and held a perimeter {{convert|2000|yd|m}} inland. There was little fighting and casualties were very low on both sides.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), pp. 483 and 487.&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese 2nd Provisional Raiding Unit was unable to offer any resistance to the overwhelming Allied force, and withdrew inland in good order. Japanese 7th Air Division aircraft based at Ceram and Celebes began a series of nightly air raids on Morotai on 15 September, but these had little effect on the Allied force.&lt;ref name="Willoughby_350"&gt;Willoughby (1966), p. 350.&lt;/ref&gt;

The lack of resistance was fortunate for the Allies due to unexpectedly poor beach conditions.&lt;ref&gt;Heavey (1947), p. 128&lt;/ref&gt; While the limited pre-invasion intelligence suggested that Red and White beaches were capable of supporting an amphibious landing, they were in fact highly unsuitable for this purpose. Both beaches were muddy and difficult for landing craft to approach owing to rocky ridges and [[coral reef]]s. As a result, soldiers and equipment had to be landed through deep surf. This delayed the operation and caused a large quantity of equipment to be damaged.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), pp. 483–485.&lt;/ref&gt; Like many of his soldiers, General MacArthur was forced to wade through chest-high surf when he came ashore.&lt;ref&gt;Manchester (1978), p. 388.&lt;/ref&gt; On the morning of D-Day a survey party determined that a beach on the south coast of Morotai was much better suited to LSTs. This beach, which was designated Blue Beach, became the primary Allied landing point from 16 September.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), p. 487.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:US troops landing into deep water Morotai 017591.jpg|thumb|left|alt=Men wearing military uniforms and carrying equipment walking down ramps from a ship into the sea|Infantrymen disembark into deep water on 15 September.]]

The 31st Division continued its advance inland on 16 September. The division met little opposition and secured the planned perimeter line around the airfield area that afternoon.&lt;ref name="Smith 1953, pp. 488" /&gt; From 17 September, the 126th Infantry Regiment landed at several points on Morotai's coastline and offshore islands to establish radar stations and observation posts. These operations were generally unopposed, though patrols landed in northern Morotai made numerous contacts with small Japanese parties.&lt;ref name="Smith 1953, pp. 488"&gt;Smith (1953), p. 488.&lt;/ref&gt; The 2nd Provisional Raiding Unit attempted to infiltrate into the Allied perimeter on the night of 18 September but was not successful.&lt;ref name="Willoughby_350" /&gt;

A detachment from the [[Netherlands Indies Civil Administration]] (NICA) was responsible for [[civil affairs]] on Morotai. This detachment came ashore on 15 September, and reestablished Dutch sovereignty over Morotai's civilian population. Many local civilians subsequently provided NICA with intelligence on Japanese dispositions on Morotai and Halmahera and others acted as guides for American patrols.&lt;ref name="Smith_490"&gt;Smith (1953), pp. 490–491.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Morotai 1944 - reports of Gen MacArthur.jpg|thumb|300px|upright|alt=A topographic map of Morotai depicting the landings of US units in September, the Allied perimeter in the south-west of the island, concentrations of Japanese forces and routes used by the Japanese to withdraw from the Allied beachhead.|The movements of Allied and Japanese forces during the first weeks of the battle]]

On 20 September, the 31st Division advanced further inland to secure an expanded perimeter. This was necessary to provide room for additional [[Military camp|bivouacs]] and supply installations after General MacArthur's headquarters decided to expand airfield construction on the island. The advance met little resistance and was completed in one day.&lt;ref name="Smith 1953, pp. 488" /&gt; On 22 September, a Japanese force attacked the headquarters of the 1st Battalion, [[167th Infantry Regiment (United States)|167th Infantry Regiment]] but was easily repulsed. The following day, a company from the [[126th Infantry Regiment (United States)|126th Infantry Regiment]] unsuccessfully attacked a fortified Japanese unit near Wajaboeta on the island's west coast. The 126th resumed its attack on 24 September and secured the position. US forces continued intensive patrolling until 4 October when the island was declared secure.&lt;ref&gt;Krueger (1979), p. 130.&lt;/ref&gt; U.S. casualties during the initial occupation of Morotai numbered 30 dead, 85 wounded, and one missing. Japanese casualties were much higher, numbering over 300 dead and 13 captured.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), p. 489.&lt;/ref&gt;

The American ground troops did not require the heavy air support available to them, and the fast carrier group was released for other duties on 17 September. The six escort carriers remained in support, but their aircraft saw little action. Four of the CVEs were released on 25 September, and the remaining two departed on 4 October.&lt;ref name="Craven_Cate_312_314"&gt;Craven and Cate (1953), pp. 312–314.&lt;/ref&gt; The destroyer escort {{USS|Shelton|DE-407|6}} was sunk by Japanese submarine [[Japanese submarine RO-41|''RO-41'']] on 3 October while escorting the CVE group.&lt;ref&gt;Royal Navy Historical Section (1957), pp. 175–176.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.history.navy.mil/research/histories/ship-histories/danfs/s/shelton-i.html|title=Shelton|work=Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships|publisher=US Navy|accessdate=5 February 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt; Several hours later a [[Grumman TBF Avenger|TBF Avenger]] from the escort carrier [[USS St. Lo (CVE-63)|USS ''Midway'']] attacked {{USS|Seawolf|SS-197|6}} {{convert|20|mi|km}} north of where ''Shelton'' had been torpedoed, in the mistaken belief that she was the submarine responsible. After dropping two bombs, the TBF Avenger guided {{USS|Richard M. Rowell|DE-403|6}} to the area and the destroyer escort sank ''Seawolf'' after five attempts, killing all the submarine's crew. It was later determined that while ''Seawolf'' was traveling in a designated "submarine safety lane", the CVE pilots had not been properly briefed on the lane's existence and location, and that the submarine's position had not been provided to USS ''Richard M. Rowell''.&lt;ref&gt;Morrison (2002), pp. 27–28.&lt;/ref&gt;

The U.S. Navy established a [[PT boat]] base at Morotai on 16 September when the tenders {{USS|Mobjack|AGP-7|6}} and {{USS|Oyster Bay|AGP-6|6}} arrived with motor torpedo boat squadrons 9, 10, 18 and 33 and their 41 boats. The PT boats' primary mission was to prevent the Japanese from moving troops from Halmahera to Morotai by establishing a blockade of the {{convert|12|mi|km|adj=on}}-wide strait between the two islands.&lt;ref&gt;Bulkley (2003), p. 368.&lt;/ref&gt;

Elements of the 31st Division embarked from Morotai in November to capture several islands off New Guinea from which Japanese outposts could observe Allied movements. On 15 November 1,200 troops from the 2nd Battalion, 167th Infantry Regiment and attached units were landed at [[Pegun Island]] in the [[Mapia islands]]; the next day, [[Bras Island]] was attacked. The Mapia Islands were declared secure on 18 November after resistance from 172 Japanese troops of the [[36th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|36th Infantry Division]] was overcome. On 19 November, a force of 400 US troops built around F Company, [[124th Infantry Regiment (United States)|124th Infantry Regiment]] occupied the undefended [[Asia Islands]].&lt;ref&gt;Royal Navy Historical Section (1957), p. 176 and 31st Infantry Division (1993), pp. 23 and 101.&lt;/ref&gt; These were the first offensive operations overseen by the [[Eighth United States Army]], and the naval commander for both operations was Captain [[Baron Ashbourne|Lord Ashbourne]] of the [[Royal Navy]] on board {{HMS|Ariadne|M65|6}}. Radar and [[LORAN]] stations were subsequently established on the islands.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), p. 451.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Base development==
[[File:Wama airstrip April 1945 OG1934.jpg|thumb|alt=An aerial photo of two parallel airstrips with a body of water at the right|Wama Drome in April 1945]]

The rapid development of Morotai into a major military base was a key goal of the operation. Pre-invasion plans called for the construction of three large airstrips within forty-five days of 15 September, with the first to be operational immediately after the landing. The plans also included accommodation and supply facilities for 60,000 air force and army personnel, a 1,900-bed hospital, bulk fuel storage and handling installations and ship docking facilities.&lt;ref name="Chief_Engineer_270"&gt;Office of the Chief Engineer, General Headquarters, Army Forces Pacific (1951), p. 270.&lt;/ref&gt; To construct these facilities, the Tradewind Task Force included 7,000 engineer service troops, of whom 84 percent were American and the remainder Australian.&lt;ref name="Chief_Engineer_272" /&gt;

Work began on base facilities before Morotai was secured. [[Surveying|Survey]] parties began transit surveys of the airfield sites on 16 September, which determined that their planned alignment was unworkable.&lt;ref name="Chief_Engineer_272" /&gt; Plans to complete the Japanese airfield were also abandoned, as it would have interfered with larger airfields to be built to the east. It was instead cleared and used as an emergency "crash strip." Work on the first new airstrip (called Wama Drome) began on 23 September after the site was cleared. By 4 October Wama Drome's runway was operable for {{convert|5000|ft}} and was supporting [[heavy bomber]] raids on [[Balikpapan]] in [[Borneo]]. Construction of the even larger [[Pitu Airport|Pitu Drome]], which was to have two runways parallel to Wama Drome, began in late September and by 17 October it had a usable {{convert|7000|ft|adj=on}} runway.&lt;ref&gt;Office of the Chief Engineer, General Headquarters, Army Forces Pacific (1951), pp. 276–277.&lt;/ref&gt; Construction work was accelerated from 18 October after the [[United States Third Fleet]] was withdrawn from providing direct support to the planned [[Battle of Leyte|landing at Leyte]].&lt;ref&gt;Craven and Cate (1953), p. 313.&lt;/ref&gt; When the two airstrips were completed in November they boasted three large runways and hardstandings for 253 aircraft, including 174 heavy bombers.&lt;ref&gt;Office of the Chief Engineer, General Headquarters, Army Forces Pacific (1951), p. 277.&lt;/ref&gt; Although the air base construction required the destruction of villages, the American and Australian airfield engineers were assisted from 1 October by about 350 laborers locally recruited by the NICA detachment.&lt;ref name="Smith_490" /&gt;

Other base facilities were erected concurrently with the construction of the airstrips. Work on fuel storage facilities began shortly after the landing, and the first was ready on 20 September. A jetty for [[oil tanker]]s and a larger [[Oil depot|tank farm]] were completed in early October, and storage facilities continued to be expanded until November, when capacity for {{convert|129000|oilbbl|m3}} of fuel was available. Several docks capable of accommodating [[liberty ship]]s were constructed on Morotai's west coast, and the first was completed on 8 October. In addition, twenty LST landings were constructed on Blue Beach to facilitate the loading and unloading of these ships. Other major construction projects included an extensive road network, a naval installation, {{convert|28000|sqft}} of warehousing, and clearing land for supply dumps and bivouacs. A 1,000-bed hospital was also built after the original plans for a 1,900-bed facility were revised. The main difficulties encountered were overcoming the mud caused by unusually heavy rains and finding sufficient water supplies.&lt;ref&gt;Office of the Chief Engineer, General Headquarters, Army Forces Pacific (1951), pp. 277–280&lt;/ref&gt;

A revision to Allied plans meant that Morotai played a much greater role in the liberation of the Philippines than had been originally envisioned. The invasion of Mindanao was postponed in September 1944 in favour of a landing at [[Leyte]] in the central Philippines in late October. The air bases at Morotai were the closest Allied air strips to Leyte, and fighters and bombers based on the island attacked targets in the southern Philippines and NEI in support of the landing at Leyte on 25 October.&lt;ref&gt;Smith (1953), pp. 491–493.&lt;/ref&gt; After airfields were completed at Leyte, Morotai was also used as a staging point for fighters and bombers traveling to the Philippines.&lt;ref name="Morison 2002, pp. 25"&gt;Morison (2002), p. 25.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Subsequent fighting==

===Japanese response===
The Japanese military recognized that its forces in the Philippines would be threatened if the Allies developed airfields on Morotai. In an attempt to disrupt the airfield construction program, the Japanese Army commanders on Halmahera sent large numbers of reinforcements to Morotai between late September and November. These troops included the main body of the 211th Infantry Regiment, the 3rd Battalion of the 210th Infantry Regiment and three raiding detachments.&lt;ref name="Willoughby_350" /&gt; The commander of the 211th Infantry Regiment, Colonel Kisou Ouchi, assumed command of the Japanese forces on Morotai on 12 October.&lt;ref&gt;Lee (1966), p. 525 and 33rd Infantry Division Historical Committee (1948), p. 73.&lt;/ref&gt; Allied codebreakers were often able to warn the forces at Morotai of attempts to run the blockade,&lt;ref name="Drea_153" /&gt; and PT boats destroyed a large number of the barges the Japanese used to transport troops from Halmahera. The Allies were, however, unable to completely stop the Japanese buildup.&lt;ref&gt;33rd Infantry Division Historical Committee (1948), p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Japanese forces Morotai.jpg|thumb|upright|300px|left|alt=A topographic map of Morotai showing the locations where the Japanese reinforcements mentioned in the text landed and the subsequent movements of these forces, as well as the Allied perimeter in the island's south-west and movements of Allied forces.|Locations of Japanese reinforcement landings]]

The Japanese counter-offensive on Morotai was not successful. The troops brought to the island suffered from high rates of disease and it proved impossible to bring sufficient supplies through the Allied air and naval blockade. As a result, while the 2nd Provisional Raiding Unit raided the US perimeter on several occasions, the reinforcements were unable to mount larger attacks and did not impede Allied airfield construction activities. The Japanese force subsequently withdrew into central Morotai where many soldiers died from disease or starvation.&lt;ref&gt;Hayashi (1959), pp. 120–121 and Willoughby (1966), pp. 350–352.&lt;/ref&gt; The last Japanese supply barges from Halmahera reached Morotai on 12 May 1945.&lt;ref name="Bulkley_442" /&gt;

In late December 1944, the [[33rd Infantry Division (United States)|US 33rd Infantry Division's]] [[136th Infantry Regiment (United States)|136th Infantry Regiment]] was brought to Morotai from New Guinea to attack the Japanese 211th Infantry Regiment in the west of the island. After landing on the island's west coast, the American regiment moved into Japanese-held territory on 26 December and advanced on the Japanese position from the south-west and north. The 136th was supported by a battalion of the [[130th Infantry Regiment (United States)|130th Infantry Regiment]] advancing overland from the Doroeba Plain, artillery units stationed on islands off Morotai's coast and one hundred civilian [[Porter (carrier)|porters]].&lt;ref&gt;33rd Infantry Division Historical Committee (1948), pp. 68–77.&lt;/ref&gt; The 3rd Battalion of the 167th Infantry Regiment also participated in this operation and made a difficult march from Morotai's south coast into the interior to prevent the Japanese from scattering into small groups in the island's mountains.&lt;ref&gt;31st Infantry Division (1993), p. 101.&lt;/ref&gt;

In early January 1945, the American force determined that two battalions of the Japanese 211th Regiment were at Hill 40, about four miles (6&amp;nbsp;km) north of the Allied perimeter. The attack on this position began on 3 January 1945 when the 136th Infantry Regiment's 1st and 2nd battalions advanced from the south-west and encountered strong resistance. The regiment used a large quantity of ammunition in this attack, and [[Airdrop|aerial resupply]] was needed to replenish its supplies. Both American battalions resumed their attack the next day with the support of a highly effective artillery bombardment, and reached the main Japanese position in the afternoon. During this period the 3rd Battalion of the 136th Regiment advanced on Hill 40 from the north, and destroyed the 211th Regiment's 3rd Battalion in a series of battles. This Japanese battalion had been stationed on the coast to receive supplies from Halmahera and mounted several unsuccessful attacks on the American battalion's [[beachhead]] after it landed in December.&lt;ref&gt;33rd Infantry Division Historical Committee (1948), pp. 74–81&lt;/ref&gt;

The 136th Infantry Regiment completed its attack on Hill 40 on 5 January. The Regiment's 1st and 2nd Battalions advanced from the west and south-west and the 3rd Battalion from the north, meeting little resistance. The 1st and 2nd Battalions continued north to pursue Japanese remnants until 14 January, by which time the regiment claimed to have killed 870 Japanese soldiers and captured ten for a loss of 46 killed and 127 wounded and injured.&lt;ref&gt;33rd Infantry Division Historical Committee (1948), pp. 80–83.&lt;/ref&gt; The 3rd Battalion, 167th Infantry Regiment linked up with the 136th on 7 January after overrunning the main Japanese radio station on the island on 4 January.&lt;ref&gt;31st Infantry Division (1993), p. 102.&lt;/ref&gt; In mid-January, the 136th Regiment was withdrawn to the Allied perimeter where it rejoined the 33rd Division, which was staging through Morotai en route for the [[Battle of Luzon|Allied landing in Luzon]].&lt;ref&gt;33rd Infantry Division Historical Committee (1948), pp. 85–87.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Air attacks and Allied mopping up===
The Japanese 7th Air Division continued to raid Morotai for months after the Allied landing. The air division conducted 82 raids on Morotai involving 179 sorties between 15 September 1944 and 1 February 1945. The aircraft used in these raids flew from Ceram and the Celebes and landed at airfields on Halmahera before proceeding to their targets. While 54 of the raids caused no damage, the others resulted in the destruction of forty-two Allied aircraft and damage to another thirty-three. Allied casualties from air attack were 19 killed and 99 wounded. The most successful raid was conducted on the night of 22 November when 15 Allied planes were destroyed and eight damaged. The regular Japanese air raids ceased at the end of January 1945, though a final attack took place on 22 March. USAAF [[night fighter]]s had only limited success as raiders were normally detected only shortly before they entered anti-aircraft gun defended zones; these guns shot down most of the 26 Japanese aircraft lost over Morotai.&lt;ref&gt;Craven and Cate (1953), pp. 315–316.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[official history]] of the USAAF's night fighter force states that Morotai "was probably the most difficult task undertaken by American night fighters during World War II" due to the difficulty of detecting incoming raiders.&lt;ref&gt;McFarland (1998), p. 37&lt;/ref&gt;

The PT boat force at Morotai was reduced to a single squadron by February 1945 but remained active until the end of the war. As well as patrolling around Morotai, the boats operated in the eastern NEI to raid Japanese positions and support Australian and Dutch scouting parties. In May 1945 PT boats and the Australian [[Z Special Unit]] rescued the Sultan of Ternate along with his court and harem during an operation codenamed [[Project Opossum]] after he was mistreated by the Japanese.&lt;ref&gt;Morison (2002), pp. 28–29.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|last=Allard|first=Tom |title=Diggers snatch sultan to safety|url=http://www.theage.com.au/national/diggers-snatch-sultan-to-safety-20100423-tjc6.html|accessdate=30 December 2010|newspaper=The Age|date=24 April 2010|author2=Murdoch, Lindsay}}&lt;/ref&gt; By the end of the war the PT boats had conducted nearly 1,300 patrols and destroyed 50 barges and 150 small craft off Morotai and Halmahera.&lt;ref&gt;Bulkley (2003), p. 373.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 31st Division remained at Morotai until 12 April 1945 when it departed to participate in the [[Battle of Mindanao|liberation of Mindanao]], and was replaced by the [[93rd Infantry Division (United States)|93rd Infantry Division]].&lt;ref&gt;Stanton (1984), p. 111.&lt;/ref&gt; The 93rd Division was a segregated African American unit, and was mainly used for security and labor tasks during the war.&lt;ref&gt;Bielakowski (2007), p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt; Once established on Morotai the division conducted intensive patrols with the aim of destroying the remaining Japanese force on the island. At this time most of the Japanese on Morotai were located along the island's west coast, and generally stayed close to civilian gardens. The 93rd Division landed patrols along Morotai's west and north coasts from April onwards, and these fought scattered skirmishes with small Japanese forces. One of the division's main goals was to capture Colonel Ouchi, and this was achieved by a patrol from the [[25th Infantry Regiment (United States)|25th Infantry Regiment]] on 2 August. Ouchi was one of the highest-ranked Japanese officers to be captured before the end of the war. The American force also used propaganda broadcasts and leaflets to encourage Japanese soldiers on Morotai to surrender, with some success.&lt;ref&gt;Lee (1966), pp. 525–527.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Japanese surrender party Morotai.jpg|thumb|alt=A group of men wearing military uniforms with a ship in the background|The Japanese commanding officers at Halmahera land at Morotai to surrender to the 93rd Division.]]

Morotai remained an important Allied base after Leyte was secured. Aircraft of the Thirteenth Air Force and Australian First Tactical Air Force (formerly No. 10 Operational Group RAAF) were based at Morotai and attacked targets in the NEI and southern Philippines until the end of the war. From April 1945, the island was also used by the [[I Corps (Australia)|Australian I Corps]] to mount the [[Borneo campaign (1945)|Borneo Campaign]].&lt;ref name="Morison 2002, pp. 25" /&gt; Australian Army engineers expanded the base facilities at Morotai to support this operation. Due to overcrowding, some Australian camp sites were located outside the American perimeter.&lt;ref&gt;Stanley (1997), p. 48.&lt;/ref&gt;

Morotai was the scene of a number of surrender ceremonies following the [[surrender of Japan]]. About 660 Japanese troops on Morotai capitulated to Allied forces after 15 August.&lt;ref&gt;Lee (1966), p. 528.&lt;/ref&gt; The 93rd Division also accepted the surrender of the 40,000 Japanese troops at Halmahera on 26 August after the Japanese commander there was brought to Morotai on a US Navy PT boat.&lt;ref name="Bulkley_442"&gt;Bulkley (2003), p. 442.&lt;/ref&gt; On 9 September 1945, Australian General [[Thomas Blamey]] accepted the surrender of the [[Japanese Second Army]] at a ceremony held on the I Corps' sports ground at Morotai.&lt;ref&gt;Long (1963), p. 553.&lt;/ref&gt; Private [[Teruo Nakamura]], the last confirmed [[Japanese holdout]] on Morotai or elsewhere, was captured by [[Indonesian Air Force]] personnel on 18 December 1974.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,917064,00.html?iid=chix-sphere|title=The Last Last Soldier?|date=13 January 1975|work=Time|accessdate=1 September 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Post et al. (2010), pp. 429–430&lt;/ref&gt;

The facilities on Morotai continued to be heavily used by the Allies in the months after the war. The Australian force responsible for the occupation and military administration of the eastern NEI was headquartered at Morotai until April 1946, when the Dutch colonial government was reestablished.&lt;ref&gt;Hasluck (1970), pp. 602–607&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Post et al. (2010), p. 29&lt;/ref&gt; The island was also one of the sites where the Australian and NEI militaries conducted war crimes trials of Japanese personnel.&lt;ref&gt;Post et al. (2010), pp. 408–409&lt;/ref&gt;

{{clear}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|25em}}

==References==
{{Commons category|Battle of Morotai}}
{{Refbegin}}
* {{Cite book|last=31st Infantry Division|title=History of the 31st Infantry Division in the Pacific|publisher=The Battery Press|location=Nashville|origyear=1946|year=1993 |series=The Divisional Series|isbn=0-89839-190-3}}
* {{Cite book|last=33rd Infantry Division Historical Committee|title=The Golden Cross: A History of the 33d Infantry Division in World War II|url=https://archive.org/details/TheGoldenCross|publisher=Infantry Journal Press|location=Washington D.C.|year=1948|isbn=0-89839-302-7}}
* {{Cite book|last=Bielakowski|first=Alexander M.|title=African American Troops in World War II|publisher=Osprey Publishing|location=Botley|year=2007|isbn=1-84603-072-2|url=https://archive.org/details/africanamericant00biel}}
* {{Cite book|last=Bulkley|first=Robert J.|title=At Close Quarters. PT Boats in the United States Navy|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis|year=2003|isbn=1-59114-095-1|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USN/CloseQuarters/index.html}}
* {{Cite book|editor1-last=Craven|editor1-first=Wesley|editor2-last=Cate|editor2-first=James|title=The Pacific: Matterhorn to Nagasaki|publisher=The University of Chicago Press|location=Chicago|year=1953|series=The Army Air Forces in World War II|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/AAF/V/index.html}}
* {{Cite book|last=Department of the Navy Bureau of Yards and Docks|title=Building the Navy's Bases in World War II|publisher=United States Government Printing Office|location=Washington DC|year=1947|series=History of the Bureau of Yards and Docks and the Civil Engineer Corps 1940–1946. Volume I|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USN/Building_Bases/index.html}}
* {{Cite book|last=Drea|first=Edward J.|title=MacArthur's ULTRA. Codebreaking and the war against Japan, 1942–1945|publisher=University of Kansas Press|location=Lawrence|year=1992|isbn=0-7006-0504-5|url=https://archive.org/details/macarthursultra00drea}}
* {{Cite book |last=Hasluck |first=Paul |authorlink=Paul Hasluck |title=The Government and the People 1942–1945 |url=https://archive.org/details/governmentpeople0000hasl |series=Australia in the War of 1939–1945 Series 4 – Civil |year=1970 |publisher=Australian War Memorial |location=Canberra |isbn=0-642-99367-X |url-access=registration }}
* {{Cite book|last=Hayashi|first=Saburo|year=1959|chapter=|title=Kogun: The Japanese Army in the Pacific War|publisher=Marine Corps Association|location=Westport|isbn=0-313-20291-5}}
* {{Cite book|last=Heavey|first=William F.|title=Down Ramp! The Story of the Army Amphibian Engineers|publisher=Infantry Journal Press|location=Washington D.C.|year=1947}}
* {{Cite book|last=Krueger |first=Walter |authorlink=Walter Krueger |title=From Down Under to Nippon. The Story of Sixth Army in World War II |origyear=1953 |year=1979 |publisher=Combat Forces Press |location=Washington |isbn=0-89201-046-0 }}
* {{Cite book|last=Lee|first=Ulysses|title=The Employment of Negro Troops|publisher=Center of Military History|location=Washington DC|year=1966|series=United States Army in World War II|url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/11-4/index.htm|oclc=835790673}}
* {{Cite book|last=Long |first=Gavin |authorlink=Gavin Long |title=The Final Campaigns |url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070206/|series=[[Australia in the War of 1939–1945|Australia in the War of 1939–1945. Series 1 – Army]] |year=1963 |publisher=Australian War Memorial |location=Canberra |isbn= }}
* {{Cite book|title=Leyte |last=Morison |first=Samuel Eliot |authorlink=Samuel Eliot Morison |series=[[History of United States Naval Operations in World War II|History of United States Naval Operations in World War II Vol. 12]] |origyear=1958 |year=2002 |publisher=University of Illinois Press |location=Champaign |isbn=0-252-07063-1 }}
* {{Cite book|title=The Campaigns of MacArthur in the Pacific |last=MacArthur |first=Douglas |authorlink=Douglas MacArthur |series=Reports of General MacArthur |year=1966 |url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/MacArthur%20Reports/MacArthur%20V1/index.htm  |publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]] |location=Washington DC }}
* {{Cite book|last=McFarland|first=Stephen L|title=Conquering the Night. Army Air Forces Night Fighters at War|publisher=Air Force History and Museums Program|year=1998|series=The U.S. Army Air Forces in World War II|url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/AAF/AAF-Night/index.html}}
* {{Cite book|title=[[American Caesar|American Caesar. Douglas MacArthur 1880–1964]] |last=Manchester |first=William |authorlink=William Manchester |year=1978 |publisher=Hutchinson |location=London |isbn=0-09-920780-X }}
* {{Cite book|last=Office of the Chief Engineer, General Headquarters, Army Forces Pacific|title=Airfield and Base Development |publisher=US Government Print. Office|location=Washington DC|year=1951|series=Engineers of the Southwest Pacific 1941–1945; v. 6}}
*{{Cite book |editor1-last=Post, Peter|others= |title=The Encyclopedia of Indonesia in the Pacific War|series=Handbook of Oriental Studies. Section 3, Southeast Asia; Volume 19 |year=2010 |publisher=Brill |location=Leiden &amp; Boston |isbn=978-90-04-16866-4 |display-editors=etal}}
* {{Cite book|title=World War II Pacific Island Guide. A Geo-Military Study |last=Rottman |first=Gordon L. |year=2002 |publisher=Greenwood Press |location=Westport |isbn=0-313-31395-4 }}
* {{Cite book|last=Royal Navy Historical Section|title=War with Japan Volume IV. The South-East Asian Operations and Central Pacific Advance|publisher=Royal Navy|location=London|year=1957}}
* {{Cite book|title=The Approach to the Philippines |last=Smith |first=Robert Ross |series=United States Army in World War II: The War in the Pacific |year=1953 |url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/USA-P-Approach/index.html |publisher=[[United States Army Center of Military History]] |location=Washington DC |isbn= }}
* {{Cite book|last=Stanley |first=Peter |authorlink=Peter Stanley |title=Tarakan. An Australian Tragedy |year=1997 |publisher=Allen &amp; Unwin |location=Sydney |isbn=1-86448-278-8 }}
* {{Cite book|last=Stanton|first=Shelby L.|title=Order of Battle, U.S. Army, World War II|publisher=Presidio|location=Novato|year=1984|isbn=0-89141-195-X|url=https://archive.org/details/orderofbattleusa00stan}}
* {{Cite book|title=MacArthur's Jungle War. The 1944 New Guinea Campaign |last=Taaffe |first=Stephen R. |year=1998 |publisher=University Press of Kansas |location=Lawrence |isbn=0-7006-0870-2 }}
* {{Cite book|last=Willoughby |first=Charles A. (editor in chief)|others= |title=Japanese Operations in the Southwest Pacific Area Volume II – Part I|origyear= |url=http://www.history.army.mil/books/wwii/MacArthur%20Reports/MacArthur%20V2%20P1/macarthurv2.htm |edition= |series=Reports of General MacArthur |year=1966 |publisher=United States Government Printing Office |location=Washington DC }}
{{Refend}}

{{Featured article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=January 2014}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Morotai, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:1944 in Indonesia]]
[[Category:South West Pacific theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Australia]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations of World War II]]
[[Category:1944 in the Dutch East Indies]]
[[Category:September 1944 events]]
[[Category:October 1944 events]]
[[Category:Amphibious operations involving the United States]]</text><sha1>io9tlk0fhrezuoxfr9fpomt09h2petb</sha1></revision></page>