<page><title>Battle of Ormoc Bay</title><ns>0</ns><id>2447857</id><revision><id>935065311</id><parentid>935065239</parentid><timestamp>2020-01-10T06:58:47Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>2601:601:9C00:3810:A82D:2677:12FB:9B92</ip></contributor><comment>/* Aftermath */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="15180" xml:space="preserve">{{more citations needed|date=February 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Ormoc Bay
|image=Battle of Leyte map 3.jpg
|image_size=300px
|caption=Leyte campaign, November–December 1944
|partof=the [[Pacific War|Pacific Theatre]] of [[World War II]]
|date=11 November–21 December 1944
|place=[[Camotes Sea]], [[Philippines]]
|result=American victory
|combatant1={{flag|United States|1912}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Douglas MacArthur]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Empire of Japan}} [[Tomoyuki Yamashita]]
|strength1=  
|strength2=
|casualties1=3 ships sunk
|casualties2=29 ships sunk&lt;br&gt;1 submarine sunk&lt;br&gt;1 patrol boat sunk
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Philippines}}
}}

The '''Battle of Ormoc Bay''' was a series of air-sea battles between [[Imperial Japan]] and the United States in the [[Camotes Sea]] in the [[Philippines]] from 11 November-21 December 1944, part of the [[Battle of Leyte]] in the [[Pacific War|Pacific campaign]] of [[World War II]]. The battles resulted from Japanese operations to reinforce and resupply their forces on [[Leyte (island)|Leyte]] and U.S. attempts to interdict them.

==Background==
After gaining naval control over the Western Pacific in mid-1944, the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] attacked the Philippines in October, landing troops at [[Leyte Gulf]] on the east side of Leyte on 20 October 1944. The island of Leyte was defended by about 20,000 Japanese; American General [[Douglas MacArthur]] thought that the occupation of Leyte would be only a prelude to the major engagement on [[Luzon]]. For the Japanese, maintaining control of the Philippines was essential because their loss would enable the Allies to sever their oil supply lines from [[Borneo]] and [[Sumatra]].

The [[Imperial Japanese Navy]] responded to this attack with a combined fleet attack that led to the [[Battle of Leyte Gulf]] from 23–26 October. In this massive naval engagement, the Japanese Navy was destroyed as a strategic force. However, this was not at first clear, and the Japanese commander in the Philippines, General [[Tomoyuki Yamashita]], believed that the [[United States Navy]] had suffered severe casualties and that the Allied land forces might be vulnerable. Accordingly, he began to reinforce and resupply the garrisons on Leyte; over the course of the battle the Japanese ran nine [[convoy]]s to the island, landing around 34,000 troops from the 1st, 8th, 26th, 30th, and 102nd divisions. [[Ormoc City]] at the head of [[Ormoc Bay]] on the west side of Leyte was the main port on the island and the main destination of the convoys.

Decryption of messages sent using the [[PURPLE]] cipher alerted the Allies to the concentration of Japanese shipping around Leyte, but they initially interpreted this as an evacuation. However, by the first week of November the picture was clear, and the Allies began to interdict the convoys.&lt;ref name="anderson"&gt;{{cite book| first = Charles R.| last = Anderson| url = http://www.history.army.mil/brochures/leyte/leyte.htm| title = Leyte| series = The U.S. Army Campaigns of World War II| publisher = [[United States Army Center of Military History]] | accessdate = 2006-05-25 | id = CMH Pub 72-27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Operations==

===TA-3 and TA-4 (Japanese)===
On 8–9 November, the Japanese dispatched two convoys from [[Manila]] to Ormoc Bay.&lt;ref name="convoys"&gt;{{cite web|url = http://pacific.valka.cz/forces/ijn/ta.htm#ta3|title = Leyte Reinforcement Convoys 23 October to 13 December 1944: Operations "TA-1" to "TA-9"|accessdate = 2006-01-06}}&lt;/ref&gt; The convoys were spaced one day apart so that the [[destroyer]]s escorting the first convoy could double back and escort the second. However, the convoys were spotted on November 9 and attacked by land-based aircraft of the [[Fifth Air Force]]. On 10 November the [[38th Bombardment Group|38th Bomb Group]], based on [[Morotai]], sent 32 [[B-25 Mitchell]]s escorted by 37 [[P-47 Thunderbolt]]s to attack TA-4 near Ponson Island. Reaching the convoy just before noon, the B-25s attacked at minimum altitude in pairs, sinking the two largest transports, ''Takatsu Maru'' and ''Kashii Maru'', disabling a third, and sinking two of the patrol craft escorts at a cost of seven bombers, for which the group was awarded the [[United States Distinguished Unit Citation|Distinguished Unit Citation]].
But the Japanese transports had been able to put ashore the 10,000 soldiers they had been carrying, be it with only a fraction of the supplies.

On 11 November, [[United States Third Fleet|U.S. 3rd Fleet]] commander Admiral [[William F. Halsey]] ordered an attack by 350 planes of [[Fast Carrier Task Force|Task Force 38]] on the combined convoys.

Four destroyers – {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Shimakaze|1942|2}}, {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Wakatsuki||2}}, {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Hamanami||2}} and {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Naganami||2}} – and four [[transport (ship)|transport]]s ''Mikasa Maru'', ''Taizan Maru'', ''Seiho Maru'' and ''Tensho Maru'' were sunk, with many of the 4,000 soldiers on board killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.combinedfleet.com/Celebes_t.htm|author =Bob Hackett and Erich Muehlthaler|title = CELEBES MARU : Tabular Record of Movement|accessdate = 2016-11-05}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Rear Admiral [[Mikio Hayakawa]] went down with ''Shimakaze'', and some 1,000 sailors from the 8 ships were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.combinedfleet.com/shimak_t.htm|author = Allyn D. Nevitt|title = ''Shimakaze'': Tabular Record of Movement|accessdate = 2006-01-06| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20060209234037/http://www.combinedfleet.com/shimak_t.htm| archivedate= 9 February 2006 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===TA-5 (Japanese)===
Convoy TA-5 left Manila on 23 November for [[Port Cataingan]] and [[Port Balancan]]. Of the six transports, five were sunk by air attack (''T-111'', ''T-141'', ''T-160'', ''T-6'' and ''T-10'') .&lt;ref name="convoys"/&gt;

===U.S. destroyer sweeps===
Bad weather in late November made air interdiction less effective, and the U.S. Navy began to send destroyers into Ormoc Bay. [[Canigao Channel]] was swept for [[Naval mine|mine]]s by the [[minesweeper]]s {{USS|Pursuit|AM-108|2}} and {{USS|Revenge|AM-110|2}}, and the four destroyers of [[Destroyer Squadron 22]] (DesRon&amp;nbsp;22) under the command of Captain Robert Smith &lt;!-- Do not use wikilink to [[Robert H. Smith (naval officer)]] because that particular officer died almost 2 years before this battle --&gt; ({{USS|Waller|DD-466|2}}, {{USS|Pringle|DD-477|2}}, {{USS|Renshaw|DD-499|2}} and {{USS|Saufley|DD-465|2}}) entered the bay on 27 November, where they shelled the docks at Ormoc City.&lt;ref name=Prefer&gt;Prefer, N.N., 2012, Leyte 1944, Havertown: Casemate Publishers, {{ISBN|9781612001555}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|176–177}}

An Allied patrol plane radioed a message to the division noting that a surfaced Japanese [[submarine]] ([[Type C submarine#Class variants|''I-46'']]) was south of [[Pacijan Island]] and heading for Ormoc Bay. The division headed south to intercept; and, at 01:27 on 28 November, ''Waller''{{'}}s radar picked up the target just off the northeast coast of [[Ponson Island]].&lt;ref name=Prefer/&gt;{{rp|177}} ''Waller'' disabled ''I-46'' with her first shots and, unable to submerge, she could only return fire with her deck guns until she sank at 01:45.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/w2/waller.htm |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20040317221615/http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/w2/waller.htm |url-status=dead |archive-date=2004-03-17 |title=Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''Waller'' |author=US Department of the Navy: Naval Historical Center |accessdate=2006-01-06 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

===TA-6 (Japanese)===
Two transports, ''Shinsho Maru'' and ''Shinetsu Maru'', escorted by three patrol vessels, Subchasers Nos. 45 and 53 and Patrol Boat No. 105, left [[Manila]] on 27 November. They were attacked by American [[PT boat]]s in Ormoc Bay on the night of 28 November and by air attack as the survivors left the area. All five ships were sunk, but not before they were able to unload most of their badly-needed supplies to the troops on Leyte.&lt;ref name="convoys"/&gt;

Another U.S. destroyer sweep on the night of 29–30 November in search of a reported convoy resulted only in the destruction of a few barges.

===TA-7 (Japanese)===
A convoy of three transports departed Manila on 1 December, escorted by destroyers [[Matsu-class destroyer#Ships of the classes|''Take'']] and [[Matsu-class destroyer#Ships of the classes|''Kuwa'']] under the command of Lieutenant Commander [[Masamichi Yamashita]]. Two groups of transport submarines also took part in the operation.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.combinedfleet.com/kuwa_t.htm|author = Allyn D. Nevitt|title = ''Kuwa'': Tabular Record of Movement|accessdate = 2006-01-06| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20051203110331/http://www.combinedfleet.com/kuwa_t.htm| archivedate= 3 December 2005 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The convoy was docked at Ormoc City when it was engaged at 00:09 on 3 December by three ships of U.S. Destroyer Division 120 (DesDiv&amp;nbsp;120) under the command of Commander John C. Zahm ({{USS|Allen M. Sumner|DD-692|2}}, {{USS|Cooper|DD-695|2}} and {{USS|Moale|DD-693|2}}).&lt;ref name=Prefer/&gt;{{rp|179}}

The U.S. ships sank the transports as they were unloading but came under heavy attack from [[Yokosuka P1Y]] "Frances" bombers, shore batteries, submarines that were known to be in the harbor, and the Japanese destroyers. ''Kuwa'' was sunk and Commander Yamashita was killed. ''Take'' attacked ''Cooper'' with [[torpedo]]es and escaped, though with some damage. ''Cooper'' sank at about 00:15 with the loss of 191 lives (168 sailors were rescued from the water on 4 December by [[Consolidated PBY Catalina]] [[flying boat]]s). At 00:33, the two surviving U.S. destroyers were ordered to leave the bay, and the victorious Japanese successfully resupplied Ormoc Bay once more. This phase of the Battle of Ormoc Bay has gone down in history as the only naval engagement during the war in which the enemy brought to bear every type of weapon: naval gunnery, naval torpedoes, air attack, submarine attack, shore gunnery, and mines.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/c13/cooper.htm|title = Dictionary of American Naval Fighting Ships: ''Cooper''|author = US Department of the Navy: Naval Historical Center|accessdate = 2006-01-06|url-status = dead|archiveurl = https://web.archive.org/web/20050321091202/http://www.history.navy.mil/danfs/c13/cooper.htm|archivedate = 2005-03-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Ormoc Bay U.S. troop landings===
[[Image:USS Lamson (DD-367) at Ormoc Bay.jpg|thumb|{{USS|Lamson|DD-367|2}} on fire in Ormoc Bay on 7 December 1944, after she was hit by a ''[[kamikaze]]''. The tug assisting with firefighting is probably '''ATR-31'''.]]

On 7 December, the [[77th Infantry Division (United States)|77th Infantry Division]], commanded by Major General [[Andrew D. Bruce]], made an amphibious landing at [[Albuera, Leyte|Albuera]], {{convert|3.5|mi|km|abbr=on}} south of Ormoc City. The 77th Division's 305th, 306th, and 307th Infantry Regiments came ashore unopposed, but naval shipping was subjected to ''kamikaze'' attacks, resulting in the loss of destroyers {{USS|Ward|DD-139|2}} and {{USS|Mahan|DD-364|2}}.&lt;ref name="anderson"/&gt;

===TA-8 (Japanese)===
This convoy carried 4,000 troops destined for Ormoc Bay, but which were unloaded at San Isidro, 30 miles north of Ormoc, after receiving news of the U.S. troop landings near Ormoc. All five transports, ''Akagisan Maru'', ''Hakuba Maru'', ''Shinsei Maru No. 5'', ''Nichiyo Maru'' and ''T-7'' were sunk on 7 December by air attack, and the escorting destroyers [[Matsu-class destroyer#Ships of the classes|''Ume'']] and [[Matsu-class destroyer#Ships of the classes|''Sugi'']] were damaged. Some 350 sailors were killed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://www.combinedfleet.com/taops3.htm|title = The TA Operations to Leyte, Part III|author = Allyn D. Nevitt|accessdate = 2016-11-06}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===TA-9 (Japanese)===
Convoy TA-9 landed some 4,000 troops at Palompon, but escorting destroyers entered the bay on 11 December where two, {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Yūzuki||2}} (by air attacks) and {{Ship|Japanese destroyer|Uzuki|1925|2}} (by PT boats), were sunk and the third, [[Matsu-class destroyer#Ships of the classes|''Kiri'']], was damaged.&lt;ref name="convoys"/&gt;

==Aftermath==
By fighting this series of engagements in Ormoc Bay, the U.S. Navy was eventually able to prevent the Japanese from further resupplying and reinforcing their troops on Leyte, contributing significantly to the victory in the land battle. The final tally of ships lost in Ormoc Bay is: U.S. – three destroyers, one [[high speed transport]], and two LSMs; Japan – six destroyers, 20 small transports, one submarine, one patrol boat and three escort vessels.

Historian Irwin J. Kappes argued that naval historians have unjustly neglected the importance of these engagements, writing:

"In the end, it was the rather amorphous Battle of Ormoc Bay that finally brought Leyte and the entire Gulf area under firm Allied control. From 11 November 1944 until 21 December, the combined efforts of Third Fleet carrier planes, Marine fighter-bomber groups, a pincer movement by the Army’s 77th Division and the [[1st Cavalry Division (United States)|First Division]] plus a motley assortment of destroyers, amphibious ships and PT boats trounced the now semi-isolated Japanese in a series of skirmishes and night raids. And because of poor weather conditions air support for most of these surface actions was almost non-existent."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url = http://dd-692.com/a%20new%20look%20at%20leyte%20gulf.htm|first = Irwin J. |last = Kappes|title = A New Look at the Battle for Leyte Gulf|accessdate = 2011-11-21}}&lt;/ref&gt;

[[Fires on the Plain (novel)]] is a renowned book by the Japanese writer [[ Ooka Shohei]] which describes the final conditions of the Japanese army on the island of Leyte and the desperate flight of some its isolated soldiers after their units have been defeated by US armed forces, as they try to reach [[Palompon]] on Leyte's West coast in the hope of re-embarking on Japanese vessels.

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
*{{cite book | last = Griggs | first = William L. | title = Preludes to Victory: The Battle of Ormoc Bay in WWII | year = 1997 | isbn = 0-9659837-0-6 }} (280-page book)

==External links==
*[http://pacific.valka.cz/forces/tf38.htm Task Force 38]
*[http://www.combinedfleet.com/taops3.htm The TA Operations to Leyte, Part III]

{{coord missing|Philippines}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ormoc Bay, Battle of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:1944 in the Philippines]]
[[Category:South West Pacific theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Military history of the Philippines during World War II]]
[[Category:History of Leyte (province)]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Ormoc]]
[[Category:November 1944 events]]
[[Category:December 1944 events]]

[[tl:Labanan sa Gulpo ng Leyte]]</text><sha1>frhxmz9vnv15znfmmpvm8bu2eysem0q</sha1></revision></page>