<page><title>Battle of Manila (1945)</title><ns>0</ns><id>2457665</id><revision><id>964877530</id><parentid>961021878</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-28T03:20:33Z</timestamp><contributor><username>InternetArchiveBot</username><id>27015025</id></contributor><comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0.1</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="30783" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2020}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Battle of Manila
|partof = the [[Philippines Campaign (1944–45)|1944–1945 Philippine Campaign]] and the [[Pacific War|Pacific Theater]] of [[World War II]]
|image = Manila Walled City Destruction May 1945.jpg
|image_size = 300px
|caption = An aerial view of the destroyed walled city of Intramuros taken in May 1945
|date = 3 February – 3 March 1945
|place = [[Manila]], Philippines
|coordinates = {{Coord|14|35|N|120|58|E|type:event|display=inline,title}}
|map_type =
|latitude =
|longitude =
|map_size =
|map_caption =
|map_label =
|territory =
|result = Allied victory
|status =
|combatant1 = {{flag|United States|1912}}
* {{flag|Commonwealth of the Philippines}}
|combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
* {{flag|Second Philippine Republic}}
|commander1 = {{flagdeco|United States|1912}} [[Douglas MacArthur]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagdeco|United States|1912}} [[Oscar Griswold]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagdeco|United States|1912}} [[Robert S. Beightler]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagdeco|United States|1912}} Verne D. Mudge&lt;br /&gt;{{flagdeco|United States|1912}} [[Joseph M. Swing]]
|commander2 = {{flagdeco|Empire of Japan|naval}} [[Sanji Iwabuchi]]{{KIA|Suicide}}
|units1 =
|units2 =
|strength1 = 35,000 US troops&lt;br /&gt;3,000 Filipino guerrillas
|strength2 = 12,500 sailors and marines&lt;br /&gt;4,500 soldiers&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|73}}
|casualties1 = 1,010 killed&lt;br /&gt;5,565 wounded&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|195}}
|casualties2 = 16,665 killed (counted dead)&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|174}}
|casualties3 = Estimated 100,000–240,000 Filipino civilians killed&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|174}}&lt;ref name="rappler.com"&gt;http://www.rappler.com/newsbreak/iq/82850-americans-destroyed-manila-1945&lt;/ref&gt;
|notes =
|campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Philippines}}&lt;br&gt;{{Campaignbox South West Pacific theatre}}
}}
{{multiple image
| align     = right
| direction = horizontal
| width     = 250
| image1    = Jonesbridgebefore.jpg
| caption1  = Jones Bridge before
| image2    = Legislative Building, Manila.jpg
| caption2  = Legislative Building in Manila before the liberation
}}

The '''Battle of Manila''' ([[Filipino language|Filipino]]: ''Labanan sa Maynila'';  {{daterangedash|1945-02-03|1945-03-03|dmy}}) was a major battle of the [[Philippines Campaign (1944–45)|Philippine campaign of 1944–45]], during the [[Second World War]]. It was fought by American forces from both the U.S. mainland and the [[Commonwealth of the Philippines|Philippines]] against Japanese troops in [[Manila]], the capital city of the Philippines. The month-long battle, which resulted in the death of over 100,000 civilians and the complete devastation of the city, was the scene of the worst [[urban warfare|urban fighting]] in the [[Pacific War|Pacific theater]]. Japanese forces committed [[Manila massacre|mass murder]] against Filipino civilians during the battle. Along with massive loss of life, the battle also destroyed architectural and cultural heritage dating back to the city's founding, and Manila became one of the most devastated capital cities during the entire war, alongside [[Berlin]] and [[Warsaw]]. The battle ended the almost three years of Japanese military occupation in the Philippines (1942–1945). The city's capture was marked as General [[Douglas MacArthur]]'s key to victory in the campaign of reconquest. It is the last of the many [[Battle of Manila (disambiguation)|battles fought within Manila's history]].

==Background==
{{Battles of Manila}}
{{History of the Philippines}}

On 9 January 1945, the [[Sixth United States Army|Sixth U.S. Army]] under Lt. Gen. [[Walter Krueger]] waded ashore at [[Lingayen Gulf]] and began a rapid drive south in the [[Battle of Luzon]]. On 12 Jan., MacArthur ordered Krueger to advance rapidly to Manila.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|83}} The [[37th Infantry Division (United States)|37th Infantry Division]], under the command of Major Gen. [[Robert S. Beightler]], headed south.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|84}}

After landing at [[San Fabian]] on 27 Jan., the [[1st Cavalry Division (United States)|1st Cavalry Division]], under the command of Major Gen. Vernon D. Mudge, was ordered by MacArthur on 31 Jan., to "Get to Manila! Free the internees at Santo Tomas. Take [[Malacanang Palace]] and the Legislative Building.".&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|83–84}}

On 31 January, the [[Eighth United States Army]] of Lt. Gen. [[Robert L. Eichelberger]], consisting of the 187th and 188th Glider Infantry Regiments of Col. Robert H. Soule, and components of the U.S. [[11th Airborne Division]] under Maj. Gen. [[Joseph Swing]], landed unopposed at [[Nasugbu]] in southern [[Luzon]] and began moving north toward Manila.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|182}} Meanwhile, the 11th A/B Division's 511th Regimental Combat Team, commanded by Col. [[Orin D. Haugen|Orin D. "Hard Rock" Haugen]], parachuted onto [[Tagaytay]] Ridge on 4 February.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|85–87}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://cda.morris.umn.edu/~webbrl/Haugen/ ''Col. Orin D. "Hard Rock" Haugen'']&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.thedropzone.org/units/511thHISTORY.html History of the 511th Airborne Regiment] {{webarchive |url=https://web.archive.org/web/20071015085402/http://www.thedropzone.org/units/511thHISTORY.html |date=15 October 2007 }}&lt;/ref&gt; On 10 Feb., the 11th Airborne Division came under the command of the Sixth Army, and seized [[Fort William McKinley]] on 17 Feb.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|89}}

Swing was joined by the [[Hunters ROTC]] Filipino [[Guerilla warfare|guerrillas]], under the command of Lt. Col. Emmanuel V. de Ocampo, and by 5 Feb., they were on the outskirts of Manila.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|87}}

===Japanese defense===
As the Americans converged on Manila from different directions, they found that most of the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] troops defending the city had been withdrawn to [[Baguio City]], on the orders of General [[Tomoyuki Yamashita]], commander in chief of Japanese Army forces in the Philippines. Yamashita planned to engage Filipino and U.S. forces in northern Luzon in a co-ordinated campaign, with the aim of buying time for the build-up of defences against the pending Allied invasion of the Japanese home islands. He had three main groups under his command: 80,000 men of the Shimbu Group in the mountains east of Manila, 30,000 of the Kembu Group in the hills north of Manila, and 152,000 in the Shobu Group in northeastern Luzon.&lt;ref name=Connaughton&gt;Connaughton, R., Pimlott, J., and Anderson, D., 1995, The Battle for Manila, London: Bloomsbury Publishing, {{ISBN|0891415785}}&lt;/ref&gt;{{rp|72}}

General Yamashita did not declare Manila an [[open city]], although General [[Douglas MacArthur]] had done so before its capture in 1941.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ephraim|first=Frank |title=Escape to Manila: from Nazi tyranny to Japanese terror|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=Jdo9V9Y1ofcC|year=2003|publisher=University of Illinois Press|isbn=978-0-252-02845-8|pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=Jdo9V9Y1ofcC&amp;pg=PA87 87]}}&lt;/ref&gt; Yamashita had not intended to defend Manila; he did not think that he could feed the city's one million residents&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|72}} and defend a large area with vast tracts of flammable wooden buildings.

Yamashita did order the commander of Shimbu Group, Gen. [[Shizuo Yokoyama]], to destroy all bridges and other vital installations and then evacuate the city as soon as any large American forces made their appearance. However, [[Rear Admiral]] [[Sanji Iwabuchi]], commander of the [[Imperial Japanese Navy]]'s 31st Naval Special Base Force, was determined to fight a last-ditch battle in Manila, and, though nominally part of the Shimbu Army Group, repeatedly ignored Army orders to withdraw from the city. The naval staff in Japan agreed to Iwabuchi's scheme, eroding a frustrated Yamashita's attempts at confronting the Americans with a concerted, unified defense.&lt;ref&gt;Sandler, Stanley – ''World War II in the Pacific: An Encyclopedia'', p.469; Taylor &amp; Francis, 2001; {{ISBN|0815318839}}, 9780815318835&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|72–73}} Iwabuchi had 12,500 men under his command, designated the Manila Naval Defence Force,&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|73}} augmented by 4,500 army personnel under Col. Katsuzo Noguchi and Capt. Saburo Abe.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|73}} They built defensive positions in the city, including [[Intramuros]], cut down the palm trees on [[Roxas Boulevard|Dewey Blvd.]] to form a runway, and set up barricades across major streets.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|73}} Iwabuchi formed the Northern Force under Noguchi, and the Southern Force under Capt. Takusue Furuse.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|74}}

Iwabuchi had been in command of the battleship {{Ship|Japanese battleship|Kirishima||2}} when she was [[Naval Battle of Guadalcanal|sunk by a US Navy task force]] off Guadalcanal in 1942, a blot on his honor which may have inspired his determination to fight to the death. Before the battle began, he issued an address to his men:

&lt;blockquote&gt;We are very glad and grateful for the opportunity of being able to serve our country in this epic battle. Now, with what strength remains, we will daringly engage the enemy. Banzai to the Emperor! We are determined to fight to the last man.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pwencycl.kgbudge.com/I/w/Iwabuchi_Sanji.htm The Pacific War Online Encyclopedia: Iwabuchi Sanji]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

==Battle==

===Santo Tomas internees liberated===
{{Main|Santo Tomas Internment Camp}}
[[File:ManilaEscape.jpg|thumb|Citizens of Manila run for safety from suburbs burned by Japanese soldiers, 10 February 1945]]
[[File:Manila capture.jpg|thumb|left|200px|Map of the capture of Manila]]
On 3 February, elements of the U.S. [[1st Cavalry Division (United States)|1st Cavalry Division]] under Maj. Gen. Verne D. Mudge pushed into the northern outskirts of Manila and seized a vital bridge across the [[Tullahan River]], which separated them from the city proper, and quickly captured Malacanang Palace.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|91}} A [[Squadron (army)|squadron]] of Brig. Gen. [[William C. Chase]]'s [[8th Cavalry Regiment (United States)|8th Cavalry]], the first unit to arrive in the city, began a drive toward the sprawling campus of the [[University of Santo Tomas]], which had been turned into the [[Santo Tomas Internment Camp]] for civilians and the US Army and Navy nurses sometimes known as the "[[Angels of Bataan]]".

Since 4 January 1942, a total of thirty-seven months, the university's [[Main Building (University of Santo Tomas)|main building]] had been used to hold civilians. Out of 4,255 prisoners, 466 died in captivity, three were killed while attempting to escape on 15 February 1942, and one made a successful breakout in early January 1945.

Capt. Manuel Colayco, a [[USAFFE]] guerrilla officer, became an allied casualty of the city's liberation, after he and his companion, Lt. Diosdado Guytingco, guided the American First Cavalry to the front gate of Santo Tomas.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|91}} Struck by Japanese bullets, Colayco died seven days later in Legarda Elementary School, which became a field hospital. At 9 PM, five tanks of the 44th Tank Battalion, headed by "Battlin' Basic", headed into the compound.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|93}}

The Japanese, commanded by Lt. Col. Toshio Hayashi, gathered the remaining internees together in the Education Building as hostages, and exchanged pot shots with the Americans and Filipinos.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|95}} The next day, 5 February, they negotiated with the Americans to allow them to rejoin Japanese troops to the south of the city, carrying only individual arms.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|95}} The Japanese were unaware the area they requested, was the now American-occupied [[Malacañan Palace]], and soon afterwards were fired upon and several were killed including Hayashi.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|95}}

On 4 February, the [[37th Infantry Division (United States)|37th Infantry Division]] freed more than 1,000 [[Prisoner of war|prisoners of war]], mostly former defenders of [[Bataan]] and [[Corregidor]], held at [[Bilibid Prison]], which had been abandoned by the Japanese.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|96}}

===Encirclement and massacres===
Early on 6 February, General MacArthur announced that "Manila had fallen";&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|97}} in fact, the battle for Manila had barely begun. Almost at once the 1st Cavalry Division in the north and the 11th Airborne Division in the south reported stiffening Japanese resistance to further advances into the city.

General [[Oscar Griswold]] continued to push elements of the [[XIV Corps (United States)|XIV Corps]] south from Santo Tomas University toward the [[Pasig River]]. Late on the afternoon on 4 February, he ordered the 2nd Squadron, [[5th Cavalry Regiment]], to seize [[Quezon Bridge]], the only crossing over the Pasig that the Japanese had not destroyed. As the squadron approached the bridge, Japanese heavy machine guns opened fire from a formidable roadblock thrown up across [[Quezon Boulevard]], forcing the cavalry to stop its advance and withdraw until nightfall. As the Americans and Filipinos pulled back, the Japanese blew up the bridge.

On 5 February, the [[37th Infantry Division (United States)|37th Infantry Division]] began to move into Manila, and Griswold divided the northern section of the city into two sectors, with the 37th responsible for advancing to the south, and the 1st Cavalry Division responsible for an envelopment to the east.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|101}} The Americans secured the northern bank of the Pasig River by 6 February, and had captured the city's water supply at the [[Novaliches]] Dam, [[Balara Filters Park|Balara Water Filters]], and the San Juan Reservoir.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|103}}

On 7 February, Gen. Beightler ordered the [[148th Infantry Regiment (United States)|148th Regiment]] to cross the Pasig River and clear [[Paco, Manila|Paco]] and [[Pandacan]].&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|109}} The bitterest fighting for Manila – which proved costliest to the [[129th Infantry Regiment (United States)|129th Regiment]] – was in capturing the steam-driven power plant on Provisor Island, where the Japanese held out until 11 February.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|103,122}} By the afternoon of 8 February, 37th Division units had cleared most of the Japanese from their sector, but the residential districts were damaged extensively. The Japanese added to the destruction by demolishing buildings and military installations as they withdrew. Japanese resistance in [[Tondo, Manila|Tondo]] and [[Malabon]] continued until 9 February.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|104}}

Trying to protect the city and its civilians, MacArthur had stringently restricted U.S. artillery and air support.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|103}} Yet, by 9 February, American shelling had set fire to a number of districts.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|114}} "If the city were to be secured without the destruction of the 37th and the 1st Cavalry Divisions, no further effort could be made to save buildings, everything holding up progress would be pounded."&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|122}} Iwabuchi's sailors, marines, and Army reinforcements, having initially had some success resisting American infantrymen armed with [[flamethrower]]s, [[grenade]]s and [[bazooka]]s, soon faced direct fire from tanks, tank destroyers, and [[howitzer]]s, which blasted holes in one building after another, often killing both Japanese and civilians trapped inside, without differentiation.&lt;ref name=Manila&gt;Echevarria de Gonzalez, Purita. ''Manila – A Memoir of Love and Loss'', Hale &amp; Iremonger, 2000. {{ISBN|0-86806-698-2}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

Subjected to incessant pounding and facing certain death or capture, the beleaguered Japanese troops took out their anger and frustration on the civilians caught in the crossfire, committing multiple acts of severe brutality, which later would be known as the [[Manila Massacre]].&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|96,107}} Violent mutilations, rapes,&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|114–120}} and [[wikt:massacre|massacres]] of the populace accompanied the battle for control of the city. Massacres occurred in schools, hospitals and convents, including [[San Juan de Dios Hospital]], [[Colegio de Santa Rosa - Intramuros|
Santa Rosa College]], [[Santo Domingo Church]], [[Manila Cathedral]], [[Paco Church]], St. Paul's Convent, and St. Vincent de Paul Church.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|113}}

[[File:Manila001.jpg|thumb|U.S. troops at the [[Rizal Stadium|Rizal Baseball Stadium]], Manila, 16 February 1945]]
By 12 February Iwabuchi's artillery and heavy mortars had been destroyed, and with no plan for withdrawal or regrouping, "each man had his meager supply of rations, barely sufficient arms and ammunition, and a building in which his life would end..."&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|144}} The 1st Cavalry Division reached Manila Bay on 12 February, but it was not until 18 February that they took [[Rizal Stadium]], which the Japanese had turned into an [[ammunition dump]], and [[Fort San Antonio Abad]].&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|144}} On 17 February, the 148th Regiment took the [[Philippine General Hospital]], freeing 7,000 civilians, the [[University of the Philippines]] Padre Faura campus, and [[Assumption College San Lorenzo]]'s original Herran-Dakota campus.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|150}}

Iwabuchi was ordered by Gen. [[Shizuo Yokoyama]], commander of the Shimbu Group, to break out of Manila on the night of 17–18 February, in coordination with counter-attacks on Novaliches Dam and Grace Park.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|142}} The breakout failed and Iwabuchi's remaining 6,000 men were trapped in Manila.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|142}} The destruction of Manila, a quarter of a million civilian casualties, and the subsequent execution of General Yamashita for war crimes after the war was the result.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|143}} 1,010 Americans, 16,665 Japanese and 100,000 to 240,000 civilians were killed.&lt;ref name="rappler.com"&gt;http://www.rappler.com/newsbreak/iq/82850-americans-destroyed-manila-1945&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|151}} There was no animosity amongst the liberated Filipinos, claiming, "We were with the Americans! We were safe! We were liberated!"&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|150}}

By 20 February, the New Police Station, St. Vincent de Paul Church, San Pablo Church, the Manila Club, City Hall and the General Post Office were in American hands.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|156–157}} The Japanese retreated into Intramuros on the night of 19 February, and the [[Manila Hotel]] was liberated on 22 Feb., but MacArthur found his penthouse in ashes.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|155–156}} Only Intramuros, plus the Legislative, Finance, and Agricultural Buildings, remained in Japanese hands.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|157}}

===Intramuros devastated===
[[File:ManilaIntramuros.jpg|thumb|left|U.S. troops fighting in the Walled City, Manila, 27 February 1945]]
The assault on Intramuros started at 07:30 on 23 February, with a 140 gun artillery barrage, followed by the 148th attacking through breaches made in the walls between the Quezon and [[Gates of Intramuros|Parian Gates]], and the 129th crossing the Pasig River, then attacking near the location of the Government Mint.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|164–167}}

The fighting for Intramuros continued until 26 February.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|171}} Fewer than 3,000 civilians escaped the assault, mostly women and children who were released on the afternoon of 23 February.&lt;ref&gt;Robert Ross Smith, ''Triumph in the Philippines'', United States Army in World War II, [[Office of the Chief of Military History]], Department of the Army, 1961, p.299&lt;/ref&gt; Colonel Noguchi's soldiers and sailors killed 1,000 men and women, while the other hostages died during the American shelling.&lt;ref&gt;Raphael Steinberg, ''Return to the Philippines'', Time-Life, p.143;&lt;br /&gt;^ Robert Ross Smith, ''Triumph in the Philippines'', p.294, 299.&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Manila Cathedral after.jpg|thumb|250px|Manila Cathedral after the war]]

Iwabuchi and his officers committed ''seppuku'' (ritual suicide) at dawn on 26 February.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|171}} The 5th Cavalry Regiment took the Agricultural Building by 1 March, and the 148th Regiment took the Legislative Building on 28 Feb. and the Finance Building by 3 March.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|171–173}}

Army Historian Robert R. Smith wrote:

''"Griswold and Beightler were not willing to attempt the assault with infantry alone. Not expressly enjoined from employing artillery, they now planned a massive artillery preparation that would last from 17 to 23 February and would include indirect fire at ranges up to 8,000 yards as well as direct, point-blank fire from ranges as short as 250 yards. They would employ all available corps and division artillery, from 240mm howitzers down. (...) Just how civilian lives could be saved by this type of preparation, as opposed to aerial bombardment, is unknown. The net result would be the same: Intramuros would be practically razed."&lt;ref&gt;Robert Ross Smith, ''Triumph in the Philippines'', United States Army in World War II, [[Office of the Chief of Military History]], Department of the Army, 1961, p.294&lt;/ref&gt; "That the artillery had almost razed the ancient Walled City could not be helped. To the XIV Corps and the 37th Division at this state of the battle for Manila, American lives were understandably far more valuable than historic landmarks. The destruction stemmed from the American decision to save lives in a battle against Japanese troops who had decided to sacrifice their lives as dearly as possible."''&lt;ref&gt;Robert Ross Smith, ''Triumph in the Philippines'', United States Army in World War II, [[Office of the Chief of Military History]], Department of the Army, 1961&lt;/ref&gt;

Before the fighting ended, MacArthur summoned a provisional assembly of prominent Filipinos to Malacañan Palace and in their presence declared the [[Commonwealth of the Philippines]] to be permanently reestablished. ''"My country kept the faith,"'' he told the gathered assembly. ''"Your capital city, cruelly punished though it be, has regained its rightful place—citadel of democracy in the East."''&lt;ref&gt;{{Harvnb|Morison|2002|p=[https://books.google.com/books?id=nICvzYNBKiUC&amp;pg=RA1-PA198&amp;lpg=RA1-PA198&amp;dq=%22Your+capital+city,+cruelly+punished+though+it+be,+has+regained+its+rightful+place%E2%80%94citadel+of+democracy+in+the+East%22&amp;source=web&amp;ots=dc8P4dNCXM&amp;sig=elwWd-gQEUBtCxHL4Y0p6pGhh5o&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;resnum=1&amp;ct=result 198]}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:Damage to the Manila Post Office 1945.jpg|thumb|left|250px]]
[[File:Fire Damage to the Manila Post Office 1945.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Damage The Manila Post Office sustained fire damage in 1945.]]
[[File:Manila003.jpg|thumb|Legislative Building|250px]]
[[File:Jonesbridgeafter.jpg|thumb|Jones Bridge after the liberation|250px]]
[[File:Bombing campaign. Southeast Asia &amp; the Pacific - NARA - 292587.jpg|thumb|left|250px|Like many other buildings in Manila, the Legislative Building was not spared from heavy shelling and bombing.]]
For the rest of the month the Americans and Filipino guerrillas mopped up resistance throughout the city. With Intramuros secured on 4 March, Manila was officially liberated, albeit completely destroyed with large areas levelled by American bombing. The battle left 1,010 U.S. soldiers dead and 5,565 wounded. An estimated 100,000 to 240,000 Filipinos civilians were killed, both deliberately by the Japanese in the [[Manila massacre]] and from artillery and aerial bombardment by U.S. and Japanese forces. 16,665 Japanese dead were counted within Intramuros alone.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|author1=Russell Wilcox Ramsey|author2=Russell Archibald Ramsey|title=On Law and Country: The Biography and Speeches of Russell Archibald Ramsey|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=TD1mNmgB2DoC|date=February 1993|publisher=Branden Books|isbn= 978-0-8283-1970-6|pages=[https://books.google.com/books?id=TD1mNmgB2DoC&amp;pg=PA41 41]}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="rappler.com"&gt;http://www.rappler.com/newsbreak/iq/82850-americans-destroyed-manila-1945&lt;/ref&gt;

===Destruction of the city===
The battle for Manila was the first and fiercest urban fighting in the entire [[Pacific War]]. Few battles in the closing months of [[World War II]] exceeded the destruction and the brutality of the massacres and savagery of the fighting in Manila.&lt;ref name=Connaughton/&gt;{{rp|186,200}} In Manila's business district only two buildings were not damaged and those two were looted of their plumbing.&lt;ref name="TimeMag1945"&gt;{{cite news|title=War Scars|url=http://content.time.com/time/subscriber/article/0,33009,775542,00.html|accessdate=17 March 2016|work=Time|date=16 April 1945}}&lt;/ref&gt;

A steel flagpole still stands today at the entrance to the old U.S. Embassy building in Ermita, pockmarked by numerous bullet and shrapnel hits, a testament to the intense, bitter fighting for the walled city. In this category, Manila is second to [[Stalingrad]] as being the city with the fiercest urban fighting during the war.&lt;ref&gt;http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/lifestyle/artandculture/247396/battle-of-manila-remembered/story/&lt;/ref&gt;

Filipinos lost an irreplaceable cultural and historical treasure in the resulting carnage and devastation of Manila, remembered today as a national tragedy. Countless government buildings, universities and colleges, convents, monasteries and churches, and their accompanying treasures dating to the founding of the city, were ruined. The cultural patrimony (including art, literature, and especially architecture) of the Orient's first truly international melting pot – the confluence of Spanish, American and Asian cultures – was eviscerated. Manila, once touted as the "Pearl of the Orient" and famed as a living monument to the meeting of Asian and European cultures, was virtually wiped out.{{Citation needed|date=October 2014}}

Most of the buildings damaged during the war were demolished after the Liberation, as part of rebuilding Manila, replacing European style architecture from the Spanish and early American era with modern American style architecture. Only a few old buildings remain intact.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=C7rRCwAAQBAJ|title=Feeding Manila in Peace and War, 1850–1945|publisher=University of Wisconsin Pres|first=Daniel F. |last=Doeppers|pages=333–335}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Commemoration==
[[File:Manilajf8547 10.JPG|thumb|125px|Battle of Manila (1945) Historical Marker, Malacañang Palace]]

On 18 February 1995, the Memorare-Manila 1945 Foundation dedicated a memorial called the Shrine of Freedom to honor the memory of the over 100,000 civilians killed in the battle. It is also known as the Memorare Manila Monument and is located at Plaza de Santa Isabel in [[Intramuros]]. The inscription for the memorial was penned by [[National Artist of the Philippines|National Artist for Literature]] [[Nick Joaquin]] and reads:

''"This memorial is dedicated to all those innocent victims of war, many of whom went nameless and unknown to a common grave, or even never knew a grave at all, their bodies having been consumed by fire or crushed to dust beneath the rubble of ruins."''

''"Let this monument be the gravestone for each and every one of the over 100,000 men, women, children and infants killed in Manila during its battle of liberation, 3 February – 3 March 1945. We have not forgotten them, nor shall we ever forget."''

''"May they rest in peace as part now of the sacred ground of this city: the Manila of our affections."''

==See also==
* [[Battle of Bataan (1945)]]
* [[History of the Philippines]]
* [[Military history of Japan]]
* [[Military history of the Philippines during World War II]]
* [[Military history of the United States]]

==Notes==
:{{ACMH}}
{{Reflist}}

==References==
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=kzYOAAAACAAJ&amp;dq=ISBN0891417710&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=VUFzUebXKOiNiAfKvYGwDQ&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA Battle of Manila Footnotes: Battle for Manila] by Richard Connaughton, John Pimlott and Duncan Anderson (2002) Presidio Press {{ISBN|0-89141-771-0}}
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=K-027Yrx12UC&amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;dq=ISBN0815318839&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=Q0FzUYKqLKLwiQfrlYGIDg&amp;ved=0CDEQ6AEwAA World War II in the Pacific: An Encyclopedia] (Military History of the United States) by S. Sandler (2000) Routledge {{ISBN|0-8153-1883-9}}
* [https://www.google.com/search?tbs=bks:1&amp;q=ISBN9718521100 By sword and fire: The Destruction of Manila in World War II], 3 February – 3 March 1945 (Unknown Binding) by Alphonso J. Aluit (1994) National Commission for Culture and the Arts {{ISBN|971-8521-10-0}}
* {{wikicite|reference=[https://www.google.com/search?tbs=bks:1&amp;q=ISBN025207064X History of United States Naval Operations in World War II. Vol. 13: The Liberation of the Philippines—Luzon, Mindanao, the Visayas, 1944–1945] by Samuel Eliot Morison (2002) University of Illinois Press  {{ISBN|0-252-07064-X}}|ref={{harvid|Morison|2002}}}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book| url = http://www.history.army.mil/brochures/luzon/72-28.htm | series = The U.S. Army Campaigns of World War II| title = Luzon | first = Dale| last = Andrade| id = CMH Pub 72-28| publisher = [[United States Army Center of Military History]]}}

==External links==
{{Commons category}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20161014045555/http://www.battleofmanila.org/ The Battle of Manila Scrapbook]
* {{YouTube|Wq21np7y5Ig|The Battle of Manila – a 1959 documentary with newsreel footages}}
* [http://cda.morris.umn.edu/~webbrl/Haugen/ Col. Orin D. "Hard Rock" Haugen]
* [http://dev.rogue.ph/18-photos-that-show-manila-before-and-after-world-war-ii/ 18 photos that show Manila before and after World War II]
* [https://www.silverlensgalleries.com/artists/teodulo-protomartir Silverlens:  Teodulo Protomartir], photos of war-damaged Manila 
* [http://www.mikesturm.com/dad/manila.htm Manila Photo Album – Mike Sturm], American photos of war-damaged Manila
* [https://blogs.lib.unc.edu/morton/index.php/2011/02/battle-of-manila/ A View to Hugh:  Battle of Manila], American photos of war-damaged Manila

{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Manila (1945), Battle of}}
[[Category:1945 in the Philippines]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving the Philippines]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving the United States]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1945]]
[[Category:Urban warfare]]
[[Category:20th century in Manila]]
[[Category:Japan–United States military relations]]
[[Category:Japan–Philippines military relations]]
[[Category:Philippines–United States military relations]]</text><sha1>n3w1lymkbrqbrkinuroihtznr6q8vsb</sha1></revision></page>