<page><title>Operation Ichi-Go</title><ns>0</ns><id>1898698</id><revision><id>965884974</id><parentid>958833437</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-04T00:24:41Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Koreiy</username><id>39663704</id></contributor><minor /><comment>Grammatical correction</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="23067" xml:space="preserve">{{Expand German|date=February 2018}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Operation Ichi-Go
| partof      = the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]], [[World War II]]
| image       = Ichigo plan.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = Japanese plan for Operation Ichi-Go
| date        = 19 April – 31 December 1944&lt;ref&gt;Davison, John ''The Pacific War: Day By Day'', pg. 37, 106&lt;/ref&gt;
| place       = [[Henan]], [[Hunan]] and [[Guangxi]]
| result      = Japanese victory
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Republic of China (1912–1949)}}&lt;br /&gt; {{flag|United States|1912}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan|army}} [[Shunroku Hata]]&lt;br/&gt; {{flagicon|Empire of Japan|army}} [[Yasuji Okamura]]&lt;br/&gt; {{flagicon|Empire of Japan|army}} [[Isamu Yokoyama]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Republic of China (1912–1949)|army}} [[Tang Enbo]]&lt;br/&gt; {{flagicon|Republic of China (1912–1949)|army}} [[Xue Yue]]&lt;br/&gt; {{flagicon|Republic of China (1912–1949)|army}} [[Bai Chongxi]]&lt;br/&gt; {{flagicon|USA|1912}} [[Joseph Stilwell]]
| strength1   = 500,000&lt;br&gt; 15,000 vehicles&lt;br&gt; 6,000 artillery pieces&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://memim.com/operation-ichi-go.html |title=Archived copy |access-date=2015-11-16 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151117022958/http://memim.com/operation-ichi-go.html |archive-date=2015-11-17 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt; 800 tanks&lt;br&gt; 100,000 horses&lt;ref&gt;Hastings, Retribution pg. 210&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 1,000,000 (400,000 in northern China)&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=3Yt6TTRdUzwC&amp;dq=china%27s+bitter+victory&amp;q=Ichigo+30%2C000#v=onepage&amp;q=Ichigo&amp;f=false Hsiung, China's Bitter Victory pgs. 162-165]&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties1 = 100,000 killed&lt;ref name="中国慰霊"&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?hl=zh-CN&amp;id=u2AzAQAAIAAJ&amp;focus=searchwithinvolume&amp;q=+%E6%88%A6%E6%AD%BB+%E6%88%A6%E7%97%85%E6%AD%BB] 記者が語りつぐ戦争 16 中国慰霊 読売新聞社 (1983/2) P187&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt; heavy [[materiel]] losses&lt;ref&gt;[http://memim.com/operation-ichi-go.html "Operation Ichi-Go"] {{Webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20151117022958/http://memim.com/operation-ichi-go.html |date=2015-11-17 }} Retrieved 16 Nov. 2015&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = 500,000-600,000 casualties &lt;small&gt;(according to "China's Bitter Victory: War with Japan, 1937-45")&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=3Yt6TTRdUzwC&amp;dq=china%27s+bitter+victory&amp;q=Ichigo+30%2C000#v=onepage&amp;q=Ichigo&amp;f=false Hsiung, China's Bitter Victory pg. 165]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br/&gt;700,000 wounded, dead or missing according to Cox&lt;ref name="Cox, 1980 pp. 2"&gt;[http://www.dtic.mil/dtic/tr/fulltext/u2/a272727.pdf Cox, 1980 pp. 2] Retrieved 9 March 2016&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="Sandler, Stanley p. 431"&gt;Sandler, Stanley. "World War II in the Pacific: an Encyclopedia" p. 431&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
| casualties4 = 500,000+ Chinese civilians&lt;ref&gt;Pike, Francis. Hirohito's War: The Pacific War, 1941-1945&lt;/ref&gt;
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Second Sino-Japanese War}}
}}'''Operation Ichi-Go''' (一号作戦 ''Ichi-gō Sakusen'', lit. "Operation Number One") was a campaign of a series of major battles between the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] forces and the [[National Revolutionary Army]] of the [[Republic of China (1912-49)|Republic of China]], fought from April to December 1944. It consisted of three separate battles in the Chinese provinces of [[Henan]], [[Hunan]] and [[Guangxi]].

These battles were the Japanese '''Operation Kogo''' or [[Battle of Central Henan]], '''Operation Togo 1''' or the [[Battle of Changheng]], and '''Operation Togo 2''' and '''Togo 3''', or the [[Battle of Guilin-Liuzhou]], respectively. The two primary goals of Ichi-go were to open a land route to [[French Indochina]], and capture air bases in southeast China from which American bombers were attacking the Japanese homeland and shipping.&lt;ref&gt;''The U.S. Army Campaigns of World War II: China Defensive'', pg. 21&lt;/ref&gt;

In [[Japanese language|Japanese]] the operation was also called '''''Tairiku Datsū Sakusen''''' ({{lang|ja|大陸打通作戦}}), or "Continent Cross-Through Operation", while the Chinese refer to it as the '''Battle of Henan-Hunan-Guangxi''' ({{zh|t=豫湘桂會戰|s=豫湘桂会战|p=Yù Xīang Guì Huìzhàn}}).

==Prelude==
{{summarize section|date=May 2020}}
In 1944, China came off of several victories against Japan in Burma leading to overconfidence. Nationalist China also diverted soldiers to Xinjiang since 1942 to retake the province from the Soviet client [[Sheng Shicai]] whose puppet army was backed by the Soviet Red Army 8th Regiment in Hami, Xinjiang since the [[Soviet invasion of Xinjiang]] in 1934 when the Soviets occupied northern Xinjiang and [[Islamic rebellion in Xinjiang]] in 1937 when the Soviets occupied southern Xinjiang as well placing all of Xinjiang under Sheng Shicai and Soviet Communist control. The fighting then escalated in early 1944 with the [[Ili Rebellion]] with Soviet backed Uyghur Communist rebels, causing China to fight enemies on two fronts with 120,000 Chinese soldiers fighting against the Ili rebellion. The aim of the Japanese Operation Ichigo was to destroy American airfields in southern China that threatened the Japanese home islands with bombing and to link railways in Beijing, Hankou and Canton cities from northern China in Beijing to southern China's coast on Canton. Japan was alarmed by American air raids against Japanese forces in Taiwan's [[Hsinchu]] airfield by American bombers based in southern China, correctly deducing that southern China could become the base of a major American bombing campaign against the Japanese home islands so Japan resolved to destroy and capture all airbases where American bombers operated from in Operation Ichigo. [[Chiang Kai-shek]] and the Republic of China authorities deliberately ignored and dismissed a tip passed on to the Chinese government in Chongqing by the French military that the French picked up in colonial French Indochina on the impending Japanese offensive to link the three cities. The Chinese military believed it to be a fake tip planted by Japan to mislead them since only 30,000 Japanese soldiers started the first manoeuvre of Operation Ichigo in northern China crossing the Yellow river so the Chinese assumed it would be a local operation in northern China only. Another major factor was that the battlefront between China and Japan was static and stabilized since 1940 and continued for four years that way until Operation Ichigo in 1944 so Chiang assumed that Japan would continue the same posture and remain behind the lines in pre-1940 occupied territories of North China only bolstering the puppet Chinese government of Wang Jingwei and exploiting resources there. The Japanese had indeed acted this way for most of the 1940s from 1940-1944, with the Japanese only making a few failed weak attempts to capture China's provisional capital in Chongqing on the Yangtze river which they quickly abandoned and gave up on before 1944. Japan also exhibited no intention before of linking the transcontinental Beijing Hankow Canton railways. China also was confident by it's three victories in a row defending Changsha against Japan, [[Battle of Changsha (1939)]], [[Battle of Changsha (1941)]], and [[Battle of Changsha (1942)]]. China had also defeated Japan in the India-[[Burma campaign|Burma theater]] in Southeast Asia with [[X Force]] and [[Y Force]] and the Chinese  could not believe Japan had carelessly let information slip into French hands, believing Japan deliberately fed misinformation to the French to divert Chinese troops from India and Burma towards China. China believed the Burma theater to be far more important for Japan than southern China and that Japanese forces in southern China would continue to assume a defensive posture only. China believed the initial Japanese attack in Ichigo to be a localized feint and distraction in northern China so Chinese troops numbering 400,000 in North China deliberately withdrew without a fight when Japan attacked, assumimg it was just another localized Japamese operation where the Japanese would withdraw after attacking. This mistake led to the collapse of Chinese defensive lines as the Japanese soldiers which eventually numbered in the hundreds of thousands far more than the original 30,000 Japanese kept pressing the attack from northern China to central China to southern China's provinces as Chinese soldiers deliberately withdrew leading to confusion and collapse, except at the  [[Defense of Hengyang]] where 17,000 outnumbered Chinese soldiers held out against over 110,000 Japanese soldiers for months in the longest siege of the war inflicting 19,000-60,000 deaths on the Japanese. At Tushan im Guizhou province, the Nationalist government of China was forced to deploy 5 armies of the 8th war zone that they were using in th entire war up to Ichigo to contain the Communist Chinese to instead fight Japan. But at that point, dietary deficiencies of Japanese soldiers and increasing casualties suffered by Japan forced Japan to end Operation Ichigo in Guizhou causing the operation to cease. After Operation Ichigo, Chiang Kai-shek started a plan to withdrew Chinese troops from the Burma theatre against Japan in Southeast Asia for a counter offensive called "White Tower" and "Iceman" against Japanese soldiers in China in 1945.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=3Yt6TTRdUzwC&amp;dq=china%27s+bitter+victory&amp;q=Ichigo+30%2C000#v=onepage&amp;q=Ichigo&amp;f=false Hsiung, China's Bitter Victory pgs. 162-166]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Campaign==
[[File:Japanese mechanized forces marching towards Lo-yang.jpg|thumb|left|1944 Operation Ichigo]]
There were two phases to the operation. In the first phase, the Japanese secured the [[Beijing–Hankou Railway|Pinghan Railway]] between [[Beijing]] and Wuhan; in the second, they displaced the US air forces stationed in Hunan province and reached the city of [[Liuzhou]], near the border with Japanese-held [[Indochina]]. 17 divisions, including 500,000 men, 15,000 vehicles, 6,000 artillery pieces, 800 tanks and 100,000 horses participated in this operation.

The Japanese included [[Kwantung Army]] units and equipment from [[Manchukuo]], mechanized units, units from the North China theater and units from mainland Japan to participate in this campaign. It was the largest land campaign organized by the Japanese during the entire [[Second Sino-Japanese War]]. Many of the newest American-trained Chinese units and supplies were forcibly locked in the Burmese theater under [[Joseph Stilwell]] set by terms of the Lend-Lease Agreement.
[[File:1944 Operation Ichigo IJA invaded Henan.jpg|thumb|left|Operation Ichigo, IJA invading Henan, 1944]]
In [[Battle of Central Henan|Operation Kogo]], 390,000 Chinese soldiers, led by General [[Tang Enbo]] ({{lang|zh|湯恩伯}}), were deployed to defend the strategic position of [[Luoyang]]. &lt;!-- What does "strategic position" mean here? Please clarify.--&gt; The 3rd Tank Division of the IJA crossed the [[Yellow River]] around [[Zhengzhou]] in late April and defeated Chinese forces near [[Xuchang]], then swung around clockwise and besieged Luoyang. Luoyang was defended by three Chinese divisions. The 3rd Tank Division began to attack Luoyang on May 13 and took it on May 25.
[[File:Situation at the End of World War Two.PNG|thumb|left|Japanese occupation (red) of eastern China near the end of the war, and Communist guerrilla bases (striped)]]
The second phase of Ichigo began in May, following the success of the first phase. Japanese forces advanced southward and occupied [[Changsha]], [[Hengyang]], [[Guilin]] and [[Liuzhou]]. At the [[Defense of Hengyang]], the Japanese only won a [[Pyrrhic victory]] since 17,000 Chinese soldiers held out against over 110,000 Japanese soldiers from June 22–August 8, 1944,inflicting 19,000-60,000 dead on the Japanese. In December 1944, Japanese forces reached French Indochina and achieved the purpose of the operation. Nevertheless, there were few practical gains from this offensive. US air forces moved inland from the threatened bases near the coast. The operation also forced British Commandos working with the Chinese as part of [[Mission 204]] to leave China and return to Burma. The U.S. [[Fourteenth Air Force]] often disrupted the [[Hunan–Guangxi Railway]] between Hengyang and Liuzhou that had been established in Operation Ichigo. Japan continued to attack airfields where US air forces were stationed up to the spring of 1945.

The [[XX Bomber Command]] operating Strategic [[Boeing B-29 Superfortress|B-29 bombers]] of the [[Twentieth Air Force]], which were attacking Japan in [[Operation Matterhorn]], were forced to move as well, but although this affected their efficiency for a short time, in early 1945 the Twentieth Air Force moved to newly established bases in the [[Marianas]] under the command of the newly established [[XXI Bomber Command]]. This nullified the limited protection that the Japanese home islands had received from Operation Ichigo.

===Henan peasants attack Kuomintang forces===
General [[Jiang Dingwen]] of the First War Zone gave his account of the behavior of Henan civilians: "During the campaign, the unexpected phenomenon was that the people of the mountains in western Henan attacked our troops, taking guns, bullets, and explosives, and even high-powered mortars and radio equipment... They surrounded our troops and killed our officers. We heard this pretty often. The heads of the villages and baojia (village mutual-responsibility groups) just ran away. At the same time, they took away our stored grain, leaving their houses and fields empty, which meant that our officers and soldiers had no food for many days."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=China's War with Japan, 1937-1945: The Struggle for Survival|last=Mitter|first=Rana|publisher=Penguin Books|year=2014|isbn=978-0-141-03145-3 |location=|pages=323–324|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; This was revenge for the [[1938 Yellow River flood]] and the [[Chinese famine of 1942–43]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=China's War with Japan, 1937-1945: The Struggle for Survival|last=Mitter|first=Rana|publisher=Penguin Books|year=2014|isbn=978-0-141-03145-3 |location=|pages=271–272, 326|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; General Jiang's account also said: "Actually this is truly painful for me to say: in the end the damages we suffered from the attacks by the people were more serious than the losses from battles with the enemy."&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=China's War with Japan, 1937-1945: The Struggle for Survival|last=Mitter|first=Rana|publisher=Penguin Books|year=2014|isbn=978-0-141-03145-3 |location=|pages=324|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Henan peasants picked up the weapons Kuomintang troops had abandoned to defend themselves against the Japanese.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=China's War with Japan, 1937-1945: The Struggle for Survival|last=Mitter|first=Rana|publisher=Penguin Books|year=2014|isbn=978-0-141-03145-3 |location=|pages=325|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; When the Kuomintang army ordered the Henan locals to destroy the local highways to prevent the Japanese advance, they refused.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=China's War with Japan, 1937-1945: The Struggle for Survival|last=Mitter|first=Rana|publisher=Penguin Books|year=2014|isbn=978-0-141-03145-3 |location=|pages=326|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt; In fact they sometimes even went back at night and mended roads which the army had torn up by day.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=China's War with Japan, 1937-1945: The Struggle for Survival|last=Mitter|first=Rana|publisher=Penguin Books|year=2014|isbn=978-0-141-03145-3 |location=|pages=326|quote=|via=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
With the rapid deterioration of the Chinese front after Japanese launched Operation Ichi-Go in 1944, General [[Joseph Stilwell]] saw this as an opportunity to win his political struggle against [[Chiang Kai-shek]], China's leader, and gain full command of all Chinese armed forces. He was able to convince General [[George Marshall]] to have President [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] send an ultimatum to Chiang threatening to end all American aid unless Chiang "at once" placed Stilwell "in unrestricted command of all your forces."&lt;ref&gt;Romanus and Sunderland, Stilwell's Command Problem, p.446–447&lt;/ref&gt;

An exultant Stilwell immediately delivered this letter to Chiang despite pleas from [[Patrick Hurley]], Roosevelt's special envoy in China, to delay delivering the message and work on a deal that would achieve Stilwell's aim in a manner more acceptable to Chiang.&lt;ref&gt;Lohbeck, Hurley, p.292&lt;/ref&gt; Seeing this act as a move toward the complete subjugation of China, a defiant Chiang gave a formal reply in which he said that Stilwell must be replaced immediately and he would welcome any other qualified U.S. general to fill Stilwell's position.&lt;ref&gt;Lohbeck, Hurley, p.298&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Romanus and Sunderland, Stilwell's Command Problem, p.452&lt;/ref&gt;
As a result, Stilwell was replaced as Chief of Staff to Chiang Kai-shek and commander of the U.S. Forces, China Theater (USFCT) by Major General [[Albert Wedemeyer]]. Stilwell's other command responsibilities in the [[China Burma India Theater of World War II|China Burma India Theater]] were divided up and allocated to other officers.

Although Chiang was successful in removing Stilwell, the public relations damage suffered by his Chinese Nationalist Party ([[Kuomintang]]) regime was irreparable. Right before Stilwell's departure, [[The New York Times|''New York Times'']] drama critic-turned-war correspondent [[Brooks Atkinson]] interviewed him in [[Chungking]] and wrote:&lt;blockquote&gt;The decision to relieve General Stilwell represents the political triumph of a moribund, anti-democratic regime that is more concerned with maintaining its political supremacy than in driving the Japanese out of China.  The Chinese Communists... have good armies that they are claiming to be fighting guerrilla warfare against the Japanese in North China—actually they are covertly or even overtly building themselves up to fight Generalissimo's government forces... The Generalissimo [Chiang Kai-shek] naturally regards these armies as the chief threat to the country and his supremacy... has seen no need to make sincere attempt to arrange at least a truce with them for the duration of the war... No diplomatic genius could have overcome the Generalissimo's basic unwillingness to risk his armies in battle with the Japanese.&lt;ref name=CRISIS-TIME-MAGAZINE&gt;{{cite magazine
| title      = Crisis
| url        = http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,801570-4,00.html
| magazine  = [[Time (magazine)|Time]] magazine quoting ''[[The New York Times]]''
| date       = 1944-11-13
| accessdate = 2007-03-02}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

Atkinson, who had visited [[Mao Zedong]] in the communist capital of [[Yenan]], saw his Communist Chinese forces as a democratic movement (after Atkinson visited Mao, his article on his visit was titled ''Yenan: A Chinese Wonderland City''), and the Nationalists in turn as hopelessly reactionary and corrupt. This view was shared by many U.S. journalists in China at the time, but due to pro-Chiang Allied press censorship, it was not as well known to their readers until Stilwell's recall and the ensuing anti-Chiang coverage forced it into the open.&lt;ref&gt;
{{cite book
|author1=Knightley, Phillip
|title=The First Casualty: The War Correspondent as Hero and Myth-Maker from the Crimea to Iraq
|page=303
|date=2004
|edition=3rd
|publisher=[[Johns Hopkins University Press]]
|isbn=978-0-8018-8030-8
|author1-link=Phillip Knightley
}}
&lt;/ref&gt;

The Japanese successes in Operation Ichi-Go had a limited effect on the war. The U.S. could still bomb the Japanese homeland from [[Saipan]] and other Pacific bases. In the territories seized, Japanese forces controlled only the cities, not their surrounding countryside. The increased size of the occupied territory also thinned out the Japanese lines. A great majority of the Chinese forces were able to retreat out of the area, and later come back to attack Japanese positions. As a result, future Japanese attempts to fight into [[Sichuan]], such as in the [[Battle of West Hunan]], ended in failure. All in all, Japan was not any closer in defeating China after this operation, and the constant defeats the Japanese suffered in the Pacific meant that Japan never got the time and resources needed to achieve final victory over China. The Japanese suffered 11,742 KIAs by mid-November, and the number of soldiers that died of illness was more than twice this.&lt;ref&gt;http://d.hatena.ne.jp/Apeman/20070710/p1&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Until mid-November, IJA had a illness toll of 66,000，and a field hospital had taken in 6164 soldiers, 2,281 of which died due to malnutrition 餓死した英霊たち P116&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://mil.huanqiu.com/history/2013-06/4001059.html In 1944, twice as many Japanese soldiers died of illness as KIA]&lt;/ref&gt; The total death toll was about 100,000 by the end of 1944.&lt;ref name="中国慰霊"/&gt;

Operation Ichi-go created a great sense of social confusion in the areas of China that it affected. Chinese Communist guerrillas were able to exploit this confusion to gain influence and control of greater areas of the countryside in the aftermath of Ichi-go.&lt;ref&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=R7qNuIJJsNEC&amp;pg=PA162&amp;lpg ''China at War: An Encyclopedia'']. Ed. Li Xiaobing. United States of America: ABC-CLIO. 2012. {{ISBN|978-1-59884-415-3}}. Retrieved May 21, 2012. p.163.&lt;/ref&gt;

==In popular culture==
The 1958 novel ''The Mountain Road'', by [[Theodore H. White|Theodore White]], a ''[[Time (magazine)|Time]]'' magazine correspondent in China at the time of the offensive, was based on an interview with former [[Office of Strategic Services|OSS]] Major Frank Gleason, who led a demolition group of American soldiers during the offensive that were charged with blowing up anything left behind in the retreat that might be of use to Japan. His group ultimately destroyed over 150 bridges and 50,000 tons of munitions, helping slow the Japanese advance. In 1960, it was [[The Mountain Road|adapted into a film]] starring [[James Stewart]] and [[Lisa Lu]], noteworthy for being one of Stewart's only war films and the only one where he plays a soldier, as he was opposed to war films due to their inaccuracy. It is generally believed he made an exception for this film because it was anti-war.

==References==
{{reflist}}

===Bibliography===
* Mitter, Rana, ''China's War with Japan, 1937-1945: The Struggle for Survival'', Penguin Books (2014), {{ISBN|978-0-141-03145-3}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book| url = http://www.history.army.mil/brochures/72-38/72-38.HTM | series = The U.S. Army Campaigns of World War II| title=  China Defensive| publisher = [[United States Army Center of Military History]]| id = CMH Pub 72-38| first = Mark D. | last = Sherry}}

{{coord missing|China}}
{{World War II}}

[[Category:Battles of the Second Sino-Japanese War|Henan-Hunan-Guangxi 1944]]
[[Category:1944 in China]]
[[Category:1944 in Japan]]
[[Category:History of Henan]]
[[Category:History of Hunan]]
[[Category:History of Guangxi]]</text><sha1>6f5tig58ux5dlcy2nzfl40tlw1crw3w</sha1></revision></page>