<page><title>Japanese invasion of French Indochina</title><ns>0</ns><id>6696118</id><revision><id>963300524</id><parentid>963300482</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-19T01:20:04Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Tran Ai Quoc Vietnam</username><id>15037876</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="17584" xml:space="preserve">{{EngvarB|date=August 2015}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2015}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict   = Invasion of French Indochina
| partof     = the [[Second Sino-Japanese War]] and [[World War II]]
| image      = Japanese advance to Lang Son1940.jpg
| image_size = 300px
| caption    = Imperial Japanese Army soldiers advance to Lang Son, in September 1940 in French Indochina.
| date       = 22–26 September 1940
| place      = [[French Indochina]]
| casus      =
| territory  = Japanese occupation of Northern French Indochina
| result     = Japanese victory
| combatant1 = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
* {{flagicon|Empire of Japan|army}} [[Indochina Expeditionary Army]] 
| combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Vichy France}}
* {{flag|French Indochina}}
| commander1  = [[Aketo Nakamura]]&lt;br&gt;[[Takuma Nishimura]]
| commander2  = [[Maurice Martin (General)|Maurice Martin]]
| commander3  =
| strength1   =
| strength2   =
| casualties1 =
| casualties2 =
| campaignbox =
{{Campaignbox Pacific 1941}}
{{Campaignbox South-East Asia}}
{{Campaignbox Second Sino-Japanese War}}
{{Japanese colonial campaigns}}
}}
{{Campaignbox Vichy France Military in World War II}}
{{Campaignbox South-East Asian Theatre}}

The {{nihongo|'''Japanese invasion of French Indochina'''|仏印進駐|Futsu-in shinchū}} was a short undeclared military confrontation between [[Empire of Japan|Japan]] and [[Vichy France|France]] in northern [[French Indochina]]. Fighting lasted from 22 to 26 September 1940, simultaneous with the [[Battle of South Guangxi]] in the [[Second Sino-Japanese War|Sino-Japanese War]].

The main objective of the Japanese was to prevent [[Republic of China (1912-1949)|China]] from importing arms and fuel through French Indochina along the [[Kunming–Hai Phong Railway]], from the Indochinese port of [[Haiphong]], through the capital of [[Hanoi]] to the Chinese city of [[Kunming]] in [[Yunnan]].&lt;ref&gt;Jean-Philippe Liardet, [http://www.net4war.com/e-revue/dossiers/2gm/indochine-sgm/indochine-sgm-01.htm ''L'Indochine française pendant la Seconde Guerre mondiale''] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20120205122644/http://www.net4war.com/e-revue/dossiers/2gm/indochine-sgm/indochine-sgm-01.htm |date= 5 February 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

Although an agreement had been reached between the French and Japanese governments prior to the outbreak of fighting, authorities were unable to control events on the ground for several days before the troops stood down. Per the prior agreement, Japan was allowed to occupy [[Tonkin]] in northern Indochina and effectively blockade China.

==Background==
{{See also|Order of battle for the Japanese invasion of French Indochina}}
In early 1940, troops of the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] (IJA) moved to seize southern [[Guangxi]] and [[Longzhou County]], where the eastern branch of the Kunming–Hai Phong Railway reached the border at the [[Friendship Pass]] in [[Pingxiang, Guangxi|Pingxiang]]. They also tried to move west to cut the rail line to [[Kunming]]. The railway from Indochina was the Chinese government's last secure overland link to the outside world.

On 10 May 1940, [[Battle of France|Germany invaded France]]. On 22 June, France [[Armistice of 22 June 1940|signed an armistice]] with Germany (in effect from 25 June). On 10 July, the French parliament [[French Constitutional Law of 1940|voted full powers]] to Marshal [[Philippe Pétain]], effectively abrogating the [[Third French Republic|Third Republic]]. Although much of metropolitan France came under German occupation, the French colonies remained under the direction of Pétain's government at [[Vichy]]. Resistance to Pétain and the armistice began even before it was signed, with [[Charles de Gaulle]]'s [[appeal of 18 June]]. As a result, a ''de facto'' government-in-exile in opposition to Pétain, called [[Free France]], was formed in London.

==Franco-Japanese negotiations==
On 19 June, Japan took advantage of the defeat of France and the impending armistice to present the Governor-General of Indochina, [[Georges Catroux]], with a request, in fact an ultimatum, demanding the closure of all supply routes to China and the admission of a 40-man Japanese inspection team under General Issaku Nishihara. The Americans became aware of the true nature of the Japanese "request" through intelligence intercepts, since the Japanese had informed their German allies. Catroux initially responded by warning the Japanese that their unspecified "other measures" would be a breach of sovereignty. He was reluctant to acquiesce to the Japanese, but with his intelligence reporting that Japanese army and navy units were moving into threatening positions, the French government was not prepared for a protracted defense of the colony.&lt;ref name=Gunn&gt;Gunn (2014), pp. 38–40.&lt;/ref&gt; Therefore, Catroux complied with the Japanese ultimatum on 20 June.&lt;ref name=Boissarie&gt;Boissarie (2015), 233–34.&lt;/ref&gt; Before the end of June the last train carrying munitions crossed the border bound for Kunming.&lt;ref name=Gunn/&gt; Following this humiliation, Catroux was immediately replaced as governor-general by Admiral [[Jean Decoux]]. He did not return to France, however, but to London.&lt;ref name=Boissarie&gt;Boissarie (2015), 233–34.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Marr (1995), p. 14.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 22 June, while Catroux was still in his post, the Japanese issued a second demand: naval basing rights at [[Guangzhouwan]] and the total closure of the Chinese border by 7 July. Issaku Nishihara, who was to lead the "inspection team", the true purpose of which was unknown, even to the Japanese, arrived in [[Hanoi]] on 29 June. On 3 July, he issued a third demand: air bases and the right to transit combat troops through Indochina. These new demands were referred to the government in  France.&lt;ref name=Gunn/&gt;&lt;ref name=Marr15&gt;Marr (1995), p. 15.&lt;/ref&gt;

The incoming governor, Decoux, who arrived in Indochina in July, urged the government to reject the demands. Although he believed that Indochina could not defend itself against a Japanese invasion, Decoux believed it was strong enough to dissuade Japan from invading. At Vichy, General [[Jules-Antoine Bührer]], chief of the Colonial General Staff, counselled resistance. The still neutral United States had already been contracted to provide aircraft, and there were 4,000 ''[[Tirailleurs sénégalais]]'' in [[French Somaliland in World War II|Djibouti]] that could be shipped to Indochina in case of need.&lt;ref name=Marr15/&gt; In Indochina, Decoux had under his command 32,000 regulars, plus 17,000 auxiliaries, although they were all ill-equipped.&lt;ref name=Boissarie/&gt;

On 30 August 1940, the Japanese foreign minister, [[Yōsuke Matsuoka]], approved a draft proposal submitted by his French colleague, [[Paul Baudouin]],{{efn|Baudouin was a former general manager of the [[Bank of Indochina]].}} whereby Japanese forces could be stationed in and transit through Indochina only for the duration of the Sino-Japanese War. Both governments then "instructed their military representatives in Indochina to work out the details [although] they would have been better advised to stick to Tokyo–Vichy channels a bit longer". Negotiations between the supreme commander of Indochinese troops, [[Maurice Martin (general)|Maurice Martin]], and General Nishihara began at Hanoi on 3 September.&lt;ref name=Marr17&gt;Marr (1995), p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt;

During negotiations, the government in France asked the German government to intervene to moderate its ally's demands. The Germans did nothing. Decoux and Martin, acting on their own, looked for help from the American and British consuls in Hanoi, and even consulted with the Chinese government on joint defence against a Japanese attack on Indochina.&lt;ref name=Marr17/&gt;

On 6 September, an infantry battalion of the Japanese [[Twenty-Second Army (Japan)|Twenty-Second Army]] based in [[Nanning]] violated the Indochinese border near the French fort at [[Đồng Đăng]]. The Twenty-Second Army was a part of the [[Japanese Southern China Area Army]], whose officers, remembering the [[Mukden incident]] of 1931, were trying to force their superiors to adopt a more aggressive policy. Following the Đồng Đăng incident, Decoux cut off negotiations. On 18 September, Nishihara sent him an ultimatum, warning that Japanese troops would enter Indochina regardless of any French agreement at 22:00 (local time) on 22 September. This prompted Decoux to demand a reduction in the number of Japanese troops that would be stationed in Indochina. The Japanese [[Imperial Japanese Army General Staff Office|Army General Staff]], with the support of the Japanese Southern China Area Army, was demanding 25,000 troops in Indochina. Nishihara, with the support of the [[Imperial General Headquarters]], got that number reduced to 6,000 on 21 September&lt;!--, despite an angry visit from General [[Kyoji Tominaga]] of the Operations Division of the General Staff--&gt;.&lt;ref name=Marr18&gt;Marr (1995), p. 18.&lt;/ref&gt;

Seven and a half hours before the expiration of the Japanese ultimatum on 22 September, Martin and Nishihara signed an agreement authorizing the stationing of 6,000 Japanese troops in Tonkin north of the [[Red River (Asia)|Red River]], the use of four airfields in Tonkin, the right to move up to 25,000 troops through Tonkin to Yunnan and the right to move one division of the Twenty-Second Army through Tonkin via Haiphong for use elsewhere in China. Already on 5 September, the Japanese Southern Army had organized the amphibious [[Indochina Expeditionary Army]] under Major-General [[Takuma Nishimura]], it was supported by a flotilla of ships and aircraft, both carrier- and land-based. When the accord was signed, a convoy was waiting off [[Hainan Island]] to bring the expeditionary force to Tonkin.&lt;ref name=Marr19&gt;Marr (1995), p. 19.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Invasion==
The accord had been communicated to all relevant commands by 21:00, an hour before the ultimatum was set to expire. It was understood between Martin and Nishimura that the first troops would arrive by ship. The Twenty-Second Army, however, did not intend to wait to take advantage of the accord. Lieutenant-General [[Akihito Nakamura|Aketo Nakamura]], commander of the [[5th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|5th (Infantry) Division]], sent columns across the border near Đồng Đăng at precisely 22:00.&lt;ref name=Marr19/&gt;

At Đồng Đăng there was an exchange of fire that quickly spread to other border posts overnight. The French position at the railhead at [[Lạng Sơn]] was surrounded by Japanese armour and forced to surrender on 25 September. Before surrendering, the French commanders had ordered the [[breechblock]]s of the [[Canon de 155mm GPF|155mm cannons]] thrown into a river to prevent the Japanese from using them. During the [[Sino-French War]] of 1884–1885, the French had been forced into an embarrassing [[retreat from Lạng Sơn]] in which equipment had likewise been thrown into the same river to prevent capture. When the breechblocks of 1940 were eventually retrieved, several chests of money lost in 1885 were found also.&lt;ref name=Marr19/&gt; Among the units taken captive at Lạng Sơn was the 2nd Battalion of the [[5th Foreign Infantry Regiment]] that contained 179 German and Austrian volunteers, whom the Japanese in vain tried to induce to change sides.&lt;ref name=Porch&gt;Porch (2010), p. 511.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 23 September, the French Government protested the breach of the agreements by the IJA to the Japanese government.

On the morning of 24 September, Japanese aircraft from [[aircraft carrier]]s in the [[Gulf of Tonkin]] attacked French positions on the coast. A French Government envoy came to negotiate; in the meantime, shore defenses remained under orders to open fire on any attempted landing.

On 26 September, Japanese forces came ashore at [[Dong Tac Airport|Dong Tac]], south of [[Haiphong]], and moved on the port. A second landing put tanks ashore, and Japanese planes bombed [[Haiphong]], causing some casualties. By early afternoon the Japanese force of some 4,500 troops and a dozen tanks were outside Haiphong.

By the evening of 26 September, fighting had died down. Japan took possession of [[Gia Lam Airbase]] outside Hanoi, the rail marshaling yard on the Yunnan border at [[Lao Cai]], and [[Bac Giang|Phu Lang Thuong]] on the railway from Hanoi to Lạng Sơn, and stationed 900 troops in the port of Haiphong and 600 more in Hanoi.

==Aftermath==
{{See also|Franco-Thai War}}
The Japanese tendered an official apology for the incident at Lạng Sơn on 5 October 1940. The Japanese-occupied towns were returned to French control and all French prisoners were released.&lt;ref name=Porch/&gt;

The occupation of southern French Indochina did not happen immediately. The Vichy government had agreed that some 40,000 troops could be stationed there. However, Japanese planners did not immediately move troops there, worried that such a move would be inflammatory to relations between Japan, the United Kingdom, and the United States. Furthermore, within the Japanese high command there was a disagreement over what to do about the [[Soviet Union|Soviet]] threat to the north of their Manchurian territories. The tipping point came just after the [[Operation Barbarossa|Nazi invasion of the Soviet Union]] in late June 1941. With the Soviets tied down, the high command concluded that a "[[Nanshin-ron|strike south]]" would solve Japan's problems with the United States, most notably the increasing American concerns about Japan's moves in China, and the possibility of a crippling oil embargo on Japan. To prepare for an [[Dutch East Indies campaign|invasion of the Dutch East Indies]], some 140,000 Japanese troops invaded southern French Indochina on 28 July 1941.{{cn|date=July 2018}} French troops and the civil administration were allowed to remain, albeit under Japanese supervision. With the [[Invasion of Normandy|Allied invasion of France]] in 1944, Japan suspected that the French authorities in Indochina might assist any Allied operations in the region. Therefore, a [[Japanese coup d'état in French Indochina]] deposed the French authorities in the spring of 1945.

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
* Boissarie, Delphine. "Indochina during World War II: An Economy under Japanese Control", ''Economies under Occupation: The hegemony of Nazi Germany and Imperial Japan in World War II'', ed. Marcel Boldorf and Tetsuji Okazaki (Routledge, 2015), pp.&amp;nbsp;232–44.
* Dreifort, John E. "Japan's Advance into Indochina, 1940: The French Response", ''Journal of Southeast Asian Studies'', '''13''', 2 (1982), pp.&amp;nbsp;279–95.
* Ehrengardt, Christian-Jacques. "Ciel de feu en Indochine, 1939–1945", ''Aéro Journal'', '''29''', 1 (2003), pp.&amp;nbsp;4–26.
* Gunn, Geoffrey C. ''Rice Wars in Colonial Vietnam: The Great Famine and the Viet Minh Road to Power''. Rowman and Littlefield, 2014.
* [[Ikuhiko Hata|Hata, Ikuhiko]]. "The Army's Move into Northern Indochina", ''The Fateful Choice: Japan's Advance into Southeast Asia, 1939–1941'', ed. James W. Morley (New York: 1980), 155–63.
* Hsu Long-hsuen and Chang Ming-kai; trans. Wen Ha-hsiung. ''History of the Sino-Japanese War (1937–1945)'', 2nd ed. (Taipei:Chung Wu Publishing, 1971).
* Marr, David G. ''Vietnam, 1945: The Quest for Power'' (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1995).
* Michelin, Franck. "The Pacific War started in Indochina: the Occupation of French Indochina and the Route to Pearl Harbor", ''Vietnam-Indochina-Japan's relation during the Second World War Document and Interpretation'' (Waseda University Institute of Asia-Pacific Studies, 2017), pp.&amp;nbsp;54–59.
* Murakami, Sachiko. ''Japan's Thrust into French Indochina, 1940–1945''. Ph.D. diss., New York University, 1981.
* Murakami, Sachiko. "Indochina: Unplanned Incursion", in Hilary Conroy and Harry Wray (eds.), ''Pearl Harbor Re-examined: Prologue to the Pacific War'' (University of Hawaii Press, 1990), pp.&amp;nbsp;141–50.
* Porch, Douglas. ''The French Foreign Legion: A Complete History of the Legendary Fighting Force'' (Skyhorse, 2010).
* Tarling, Nicholas. "The British and the First Japanese Move into Indo-China", ''Journal of Southeast Asian Studies'', '''21''', 1 (1990), pp.&amp;nbsp;35–65.
* Yoshizawa, Minami. "The Nishihara Mission in Hanoi, July 1940", ''Indochina in the 1940s and 1950s'', ed. Shiraishi Takeshi and Furuta Motoo (Ithaca, N.Y.: 1992), pp.&amp;nbsp;9–54.
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://cgi2.nhk.or.jp/shogenarchives/jpnews/movie.cgi?das_id=D0001300403_00000&amp;seg_number=001 "Occupation of French Indochina"], ''Nippon News'', No. 18. in the official website of [[NHK]].
* [http://www.dailymotion.com/video/x2dkcx_conflit-en-indochine-15011941 ''Conflict in Indochina''], French newsreels archives (''Les Actualités Mondiales''), 15 January 1941

{{French Indochina}}
{{Vietnamese independence movement}}
{{World War II}}
{{Occupation of France}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Indochina}}
[[Category:World War II invasions]]
[[Category:Military history of Japan]]
[[Category:Battles of the Second Sino-Japanese War]]
[[Category:South-East Asian theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Military battles of Vichy France]]
[[Category:French Indochina]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1940]]
[[Category:Military history of Vietnam during World War II|Invasion]]
[[Category:1940 in Japan]]
[[Category:1940 in Vietnam]]
[[Category:Wars involving Vietnam]]
[[Category:France–Japan military relations]]
[[Category:1940 in French Indochina]]
[[Category:Invasions by Japan|French Indochina]]</text><sha1>65ivtv8jeap1df8vggdr056gffjp4zm</sha1></revision></page>