<page><title>Battle of Prachuap Khiri Khan</title><ns>0</ns><id>1076315</id><revision><id>963374225</id><parentid>963374170</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-19T13:22:46Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Snagemit</username><id>39030591</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="9017" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict    = Battle of Prachuap Khiri Khan
|image       = National Memorial, Thailand - Reproducution scene of the Battle of Ao Manao (3).jpg
|image_size  = 300px
|caption     = Reproduction scene of the Battle of Prachuap Khiri Khan, displayed at the National Memorial, Pathum Thani, Thailand. 
|partof      = the [[Japanese invasion of Thailand]]
|date        = 8 December 1941
|place       = [[Prachuap Khiri Khan]], [[Thailand]]
|result      = Ceasefire
|combatant1  = {{flagdeco|Thailand}} [[Kingdom of Thailand|Thailand]]
|combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
|commander1  = {{flagdeco|Thailand}} Prawat Chumsai
|commander2  = {{flagdeco|Empire of Japan}} Kisoyoshi Utsunomiya
|units1      = [[Royal Thai Armed Forces]]
* [[Royal Thai Air Force|RTAF Fifth Wing]]
* [[5th Infantry Division (Thailand)|5th Infantry Division]]
|units2      = [[55th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|55th Division]]
* [[55th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|143rd Infantry Regiment]]
** 2nd Battalion
|strength1   =
|strength2   =
|casualties1 = 42 killed &lt;br&gt; 27 wounded &lt;br&gt; 3 aircraft destroyed
|casualties2 = 217 killed &lt;br&gt; 300 wounded
}}
{{Campaignbox Japanese invasion of Thailand}}

The '''Battle of Prachuap Khri Khan''' was an early engagement of the [[Japanese invasion of Thailand]] in the [[Southeast Asian theatre of World War II]]. It was fought on 8–9 December 1941 at the airfield of [[Prachuap Khiri Khan]], on the coast of the [[Gulf of Thailand]] along the [[Kra Isthmus]].&lt;ref name="KSE-20180908"&gt;{{cite news |last1=Charuvastra |first1=Teeranai |title=33 Hours of Defiance: The Thai Airmen Who Resisted an Empire |url=http://www.khaosodenglish.com/featured/2018/09/08/33-hours-of-defiance-the-thai-airmen-who-resisted-an-empire/ |accessdate=17 September 2018 |work=Khaosod English |date=8 September 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Japan]]ese meant to use Thailand as a base to strike at [[United Kingdom|British]] possessions in [[Burma]] and [[British Malaya|Malaya]] and attacked Thailand without warning.

==Battle==
[[File:Manaw Panorama1.jpg|thumb|Fighting took place at [[Ao Manao]] Beach]]

About 03:00 on 8 December 1941, the 2nd Battalion, 143rd Infantry Regiment, [[55th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|55th Division]] of the [[Imperial Japanese Army]], under the command of [[Major]] Kisoyoshi Utsunomiya, began landing troops at Prachuab Khiri Khan. When informed of the invasion, Wing Commander [[Mom Luang]] Prawat Chumsai of ''Kong Bin Noi'' (Squadron) 5 immediately gave orders to resist.&lt;ref name="TBL"&gt;{{cite web|title=The battle of Ao Manao 1941|url=http://www.tour-bangkok-legacies.com/Bangkok_Travelbug-September10.html|website=Tour Bangkok Legacies|accessdate=8 December 2016|format=Blog|date=2010-08-30}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The units on the airfield were equipped with six heavy and two light machine guns, which they immediately turned against the Japanese troops trying to surround the airfield. The small garrison of pilots and ground crew was reinforced by members of the constabulary and the Yuwachon Thaharn (a quasi-military teenage auxiliary) who had managed to escape from the town of Prachuap Khiri Khan after the Japanese captured the [[telegraph]] office and the police station.

Despite the fact that the Japanese occupied part of the airfield, ''Kong Bin Noi'' 5's pilots attempted to take off at sunrise to bomb and strafe the advancing Japanese.

Chief [[Warrant Officer]] Prom Chuwong was first to take off in a [[Curtiss BF2C Goshawk|Hawk III]]. Japanese ground fire quickly shot him down, killing him. The Japanese shot down two more Hawks as they took off, killing both pilots, and wounded a third pilot as he brought his Hawk onto the runway. Only one other pilot managed to get airborne. [[Flying Officer]] Man Prasongdi took off in a Hawk III armed with four 50&amp;nbsp;kg bombs and attempted to attack Japanese transports in [[Ao Manao]] harbor, but he could not locate them due to heavy fog and rain.&lt;ref name="TBL"/&gt;

By 08:00, most of the northern hangars were in Japanese hands. The Thais smashed the instruments of the isolated airfield control tower and set fire to it, as the runways were abandoned. A new perimeter was set up and the withdrawing airmen were covered by a machine gun positioned in the clubhouse's [[tennis court]], manned by Airmen Singto Saensukh and Kasem Wongkangya. The machine gun kept firing throughout the morning and into the afternoon.

[[Pilot Officer]] Somsri Suchrittham and his men, whose strength was now around thirty, were forced to withdraw when their northern flank was threatened by the abandonment of the runways.

Having successfully secured the beachhead, the Japanese proceeded to occupy what was left of the hangars and runways, and reinforcements, including artillery and ten tanks, were landed from the transports.

The families of the airmen took refuge in guesthouses on Mount Laum Muak. The evacuation of the living quarters was supervised by Pilot Officer Phol Thongpricha.

Another position was set up by defenders, who divided themselves into three groups. One group was stationed by the guest houses on Prachuap Bay and fired on anything coming up the road from the guard house. A second group, under the immediate command of Wing Commander Prawat, placed itself in the area around the command and administrative buildings. The final group occupied houses facing Manao Bay. These two groups fired on the approaches from the hangars and the runways.

Fighting continued into late evening, but with lessening intensity. The machine gun at the tennis court held back the Japanese, while a light machine gun was held in reserve and moved to plug gaps in the perimeter.

Rumours that [[Royal Thai Navy]] sailors were fighting their way through to relieve the airmen kept up Thai hopes through the night. Ammunition was low, and at one point the airmen fired blank rounds at the Japanese.

The following morning, the exhausted Thais received a [[telegram]] from the Ministry of the Interior, brought in by a postman during a lull in the battle. The telegram ordered the defenders to cease fighting, as an armistice had been arranged by the government.&lt;ref name="TBL"/&gt; The Thai defenders suspected this was a trick by the Japanese and continued to resist. The infuriated invaders now mounted assaults with renewed vigor. The defenders were slowly pushed back. About this time, the lone machine gun in the tennis court was taken out, both gunners severely wounded.

By 10:00, with the Japanese closing in, Wing Commander Prawat ordered the command building to be burned, along with all military documents. As flames engulfed the building, Flying Officer Prayad Kanchonwiroj, the senior medical officer, ordered the hospital building evacuated and set on fire.

Wing Commander Prawat ordered all officers to save a bullet for themselves and said those who wanted to were free to try to break out on their own. The others, including the wounded, were to fall back on Mount Laum Muak.

At noon, a civilian car with a small white flag arrived. It contained a number of Thai government officials, including the provincial undersecretary, Jarunphan Isarangun na Ayutthaya. Jarunphan handed Wing Commander Prawat a direct order from the Prime Minister, Field Marshal [[Plaek Pibulsonggram|Phibunsongkhram]], telling him to cease resistance immediately. Fighting officially ended at 12:35 on 9 December 1941.&lt;ref name="TBL" /&gt;

==Casualties==
The Thais suffered 42 killed and 27 wounded, including airmen, police, and civilians.&lt;ref name="TBL" /&gt;&lt;ref name="BP-20140724" /&gt; Wing Commander Prawat's pregnant wife was among the dead, killed by a stray bullet. 

Japanese sources stated that the Japanese suffered 115 dead. However, Thai estimates of Japanese losses were put at 217 killed and more than 300 wounded.&lt;ref name="BP-20140724"&gt;{{cite news|last1=Karnjanatawe|first1=Karnjana|title=Bay watch|url=http://www.bangkokpost.com/print/422039/|accessdate=8 December 2016|work=Bangkok Post|date=2014-07-24}}&lt;/ref&gt; (The Japanese had cremated their dead and prevented the Thais from counting them.)&lt;ref name="TBL" /&gt;

==Memorials==
A monument to the Thai defenders stands on the Royal Thai Air Force base at Prachuap Khiri Khan. Each December a memorial is held to honour those who fought and died defending their country from invasion.{{Citation needed|date=December 2016}}

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*{{Wikivoyage-inline|Prachuap Khiri Khan}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20091027105023/http://geocities.com/thailandwwii/prachuap.html The Japanese Invasion of Prachuap Khiri Khan]

{{coord missing|Thailand}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Prachuab Khirikhan}}
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Southeast Asia Theatre]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:Battles involving Thailand]]
[[Category:Prachuap Khiri Khan Province]]
[[Category:Royal Thai Air Force]]
[[Category:Military history of Thailand during World War II]]
[[Category:1941 in Thailand]]</text><sha1>lodlcp5x4quuhrguzskiy0w9jkh3qlt</sha1></revision></page>