<page><title>Battle of Kampar</title><ns>0</ns><id>13401800</id><revision><id>919503325</id><parentid>913797414</parentid><timestamp>2019-10-04T02:30:14Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Molecule Extraction</username><id>27105730</id></contributor><comment>+images</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="16502" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Battle of the  Malayan Campaign in World War II}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Kampar
| partof      = the [[Battle of Malaya]], [[World War II]]
| image       = Sikh infantry during the Battle of Kampar, taken between 1941-1942.jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = [[Sikh]] infantry of the [[Indian Army during World War II|Indian Army]] served alongside the [[British Empire in World War II|British Empire]] troops where they were involved in a fierce battle against the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] (IJA) in Kampar, {{circa|1941–1942}}.
| date        = 30 December 1941&amp;nbsp;– 2 January 1942
| place       = [[Kampar, Perak|Kampar]], [[British Malaya|Malaya]]
| result      = Tactical Allied victory
| combatant1  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
* {{Flagdeco|Malayan Union}}{{Flagdeco|Straits Settlements}} [[British Malaya|Malaya]]
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Archibald Paris]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Japan}} [[Takuro Matsui]]
| strength1   = 1,300 infantry&lt;ref name="The Forgotten Heroes of the British Battalion"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.nmbva.co.uk/remembering_the_battle_of_kampar.htm|title=Remembering the Battle of Kampar|last=Ken|first=Orrill|accessdate=5 April 2009 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080628061645/http://www.nmbva.co.uk/remembering_the_battle_of_kampar.htm |archivedate=28 June 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| strength2   = 9,000 infantry&lt;br&gt;200 tanks&lt;br&gt;100 artillery pieces
| casualties1 = 150 killed&lt;br&gt;(Japanese estimate)
| casualties2 = 500 killed&lt;br&gt;(Japanese estimate)
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Malaya}}
}}
{{Campaignbox South-East Asian Theatre}}
The '''Battle of Kampar''' (30 December 1941&amp;nbsp;– 2 January 1942) was an engagement of the [[Malayan Campaign]] during [[World War II]], involving British and Indian troops from the [[11th Indian Infantry Division]] and the Japanese [[5th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|5th Division]].

On 27 December, in an effort to prevent the capture of [[RAF Kuala Lumpur]], the 11th Indian Infantry Division occupied [[Kampar, Perak|Kampar]], which offered a strong natural defensive position. In doing so they were also tasked with delaying the advancing Japanese troops long enough to allow the [[9th Indian Infantry Division]] to withdraw from the east coast. The Japanese intended to capture Kampar as a New Year’s gift to [[Emperor of Japan|Emperor]] [[Hirohito]] and on 30 December the Japanese began surrounding the British and Indian positions. The following day fighting commenced. The Allied forces were able to hold on for four days before withdrawing on 2 January 1942, having achieved their objective of slowing the Japanese advance.

==Background==
[[File:Divisions of Perak.png|thumb|right|The state of Perak. Kampar is situated in the [[Kinta District|Kinta]] district.]]
The site overlooking Kampar is set on what is now called [[Green Ridge (Malaysia)|Green Ridge]]. That ridge, together with the nearby Thompson, Kennedy and Cemetery Ridges overlook the main road to the south from [[Ipoh]], [[Perak]], and were of great strategic value. The ridges sit on top of the Gunung Bujang Melaka, a 4,070 foot limestone mountain. This jungle-covered mountain offered a clear view of the surrounding plains covered with open tin mining sites and swamps. The Gunung Bujang Melaka lies to the east of the town of Kampar, its steep slopes leading down to the Kampar Road. With this town and the mountain under control, the Japanese Army would have an excellent view of the [[Kinta Valley]] to the south. Allied forces knew that if the 5th Division of the Imperial Japanese Army captured Kampar, they would also be able to use it as a foothold into the Kinta Valley.&lt;ref name="Colin Smith"&gt;{{cite book|last=Smith|first=Colin|title=Singapore Burning|year=2006|pages=306–317|isbn=978-0-14-101036-6}}&lt;/ref&gt;

With the beginning of General [[Tomoyuki Yamashita]]'s 25th Army [[Japanese Invasion of Malaya|invasion of Malaya]] the III Indian Corps, defending the north of Malaya, was forced into a series of costly retreats southwards. The outcome of these retreats, ordered by [[Malaya Command]], was a badly mauled and decimated British infantry. The losses suffered by the 11th Indian Division in the battles at [[Battle of Jitra|Jitra]], [[Operation Krohcol|Kroh]], [[Alor Setar|Alor Star]] and [[Battle of Gurun|Gurun]] meant that the division's British and Indian [[battalion]]s had mostly been amalgamated. After the loss of [[Kedah]] province the [[12th Indian Infantry Brigade]] (Malaya Command reserve force and well trained in jungle warfare) replaced the 11th Division and commenced a very successful fighting withdrawal to the Kampar position, inflicting heavy casualties on the Japanese spearhead units.&lt;ref name="Colin Smith" /&gt; The 12th Brigade's job was to buy time for the re-organisation of the 11th Division and the preparation of defences at Kampar.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last=Thompson |first=Peter |title=The Battle for Singapore: The True Story of the Greatest Catastrophe of World War II| year=2005 |publisher=Portrait |location=London |isbn=0-7499-5085-4|page=185}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===British positions===
Of the three [[brigade]]s from the 11th Indian Division, two—the [[6th Indian Infantry Brigade|6th]] and [[15th Indian Infantry Brigade]]s—had been amalgamated to form the 15th/6th Brigade under Brigadier Henry Moorhead (commander of [[Operation Krohcol|Krohcol]]). The 15th/6th Brigade now consisted of the survivors from the 1st [[Leicestershire Regiment]] and 2nd [[East Surrey Regiment|East Surreys]] (which had been amalgamated to form the [[British Battalion (Malaya 1941)|British Battalion]]), and a composite Jat-Punjab Regiment (formed from survivors of the 1/[[8th Punjab Regiment]] and the 2/[[9th Jat Regiment]]). The remaining regiments of the brigade—1/[[14th Punjab Regiment|14th Punjab]], 5/14th Punjab and 2/[[16th Punjab Regiment]]s—covered the rear of the Kampar position. With all of those regiments in one formation the 15th/6th Brigade still only numbered about 1,600 men. The [[28th Gurkha Brigade]], under the command of Brigadier Ray Selby, though intact, was low in strength and morale; its three Gurkha [[battalion]]s had suffered heavy casualties in the fighting around [[Jitra]], [[Kroh]], [[Gurun, Kedah|Gurun]] and at [[Ipoh]].&lt;ref name="Colin Smith" /&gt;

Major General Archie Paris (temporary commander of the 11th Division) had to defend a line from the coast through[[Telok Anson | Telok Anson (now Telok Intan)]] up to the defensive positions at Kampar. The defensive perimeter at Kampar was an all round position, straddling Kampar Hill (Gunong Brijang Malaka) to the east of Kampar town, overlooking the Japanese advance and well concealed by thick jungle. Paris placed artillery spotters on the forward slopes protected by the 15th/6th Brigade on the western side of the position, and the 28th Gurkha Brigade covered the right flank on the eastern side.&lt;ref name="Colin Smith" /&gt; The two brigades were supported by the 88th Field Artillery Regiment, which was equipped with [[Ordnance QF 25 pounder|25 pounders]], and the [[QF 4.5 inch Howitzer|4.5 inch howitzers]] of the 155th Field Artillery Regiment. Once the 12th Brigade had passed through Kampar Paris sent them to cover the coast and his line of retreat at Telok Anson.&lt;ref name="Colin Smith" /&gt;

===Japanese positions===
The Japanese attacking force came from Lieutenant General Takuro Matsui's [[5th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|Japanese 5th Division]]. The intact and relatively fresh 41st Infantry Regiment (about 4,000 strong) from Major General Saburo Kawamura's 9th Brigade spearheaded the attack on Kampar Hill. Kawamura's brigade consisted of Colonel Watanabe's 11th Regiment and Colonel Kanichi Okabe's 41st Regiment.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson pg. 155 and 187&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===Kampar===
[[File:Japanese Type 97 Te-Ke tanks during the Battle of Kampar, 1941.jpg|thumb|left|Japanese [[Type 97 Te-Ke tankette|Type 97 Te-Ke]] tanks followed by their [[bicycle infantry]] advancing during the battle, December 1941.]]
On 30 December Kawamura's brigade arrived and began encircling and probing the British positions. On the 31 December Kawamura launched probing attacks on the 28th Gurkha Brigade's position on the right flank with a battalion from Watanabe's 11th Regiment. Once the well concealed Gurkhas' positions were found the Japanese formed up to attack and the howitzers of the 155th ([[Lanarkshire Yeomanry]]) Field Artillery opened up a concentrated fire on the Japanese troops.&lt;ref name="Colin Smith" /&gt; All through 31 December the 11th Regiment attacks were beaten off by the Gurkhas and the close support artillery fire. On midnight of New Year's Eve the commander of the 155th Field Regiment, Lieutenant Colonel Augustus Murdoch, "ordered a twelve gun salute to be fired at the Japanese".&lt;ref&gt;Smith pg. 304–305&lt;/ref&gt;

At seven in the morning, on 1 January 1942, Kawamura launched his main attack against the western side of the Kampar position.&lt;ref name="Colin Smith" /&gt; This attack was carried out by the 41st Regiment and the brunt of it was against the area held by Lieutenant Colonel Esmond Morrison's British Battalion. The 41st Regiment attacked straight into the British Battalion's positions, supported by heavy mortar fire.&lt;ref name="Colin Smith" /&gt; The fighting became fierce with Japanese and British positions taken and retaken at the point of a bayonet. Japanese casualties were heavy with a continuous stream of wounded passing Colonel Okabe's headquarters.&lt;ref name="Colin Smith" /&gt; Combined with the infantry assaults the Japanese poured continuous artillery fire and bombed and strafed the British positions with impunity (the Japanese had nearly complete air superiority by this stage in the campaign). Matsui brought in fresh soldiers to replace his mounting casualties. The well concealed and dug in 15th/6th Brigade, supported by the 88th (2nd West Lancashire) Field Artillery, held on to their positions throughout the two days of fierce fighting on the western slopes of Kampar Hill without relief.&lt;ref name="Colin Smith" /&gt;

The ferocity and confusion of the close-quarter fighting around the British Battalion was especially violent in the forward positions. Lieutenant Edgar Newland, commanding a [[platoon]] of 30 Leicesters, held the most forward position of the battalion. His platoon was surrounded and cut off for most of the battle but Newland and his men fought off all attacks and kept hold of their isolated position throughout the two days. For his actions Newland later received the [[Military Cross]].&lt;ref name="Colin Smith" /&gt;

During the two-day battle Japanese troops managed to capture trenches on the eastern sector of Thompson Ridge.&lt;ref name="Battle of Kampar by Loong" /&gt; After two counter-attacks by D Company of the British Battalion and a third by the Jat-Punjab Battalion failed, a reserve mixed [[Company (military unit)|company]] of 60 [[Sikhs]] and [[Gujars]] from the Jat-Punjab Battalion was brought in to attempt to retake the trenches. This half company under the command of Captain John Onslow Graham and Lieutenant Charles Douglas Lamb (both officers were from 1/8th Punjab) fixed bayonets and charged the Japanese position. The Japanese fire was so heavy that 33 men, including Lamb, were killed in the charge. Graham continued to lead the attack after being wounded and only stopped when a grenade mangled both his legs beneath the knees. Nevertheless, he continued to shout encouragement to his men and was seen throwing grenades at the Japanese trenches. Altogether 34 Indians died in the attack but they retook the position. Graham died of his wounds a day later and was subsequently [[Mentioned in Dispatches]] for his actions on Thompson Ridge.&lt;ref name="Battle of Kampar by Loong"&gt;{{cite web|url=http://khalsadiwan.org/projects-warriors.htm|title=Battle of Kampar|last=Loong|first=Chye Kooi|publisher=Khalsa Diwan Malayasia|accessdate=21 September 2009 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20080802223955/http://khalsadiwan.org/projects-warriors.htm |archivedate=2 August 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Telok Anson===
Matsui realised that the British position at Kampar was too strong for him to take, so General Yamashita ordered landings on the west coast south of Kampar near the 12th Brigade positions at [[Telok Anson]] in order to out flank and cut off the line of retreat of the 11th Division. The 11th Infantry Regiment were to land at [[Hutan Melintang]] and attack Telok Anson from the south and a force from the [[Imperial Guards Division]] headed overland, following the Perak River to attack Telok Anson from the north.&lt;ref&gt;Thompson pg. 187&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Owen |first=Frank |title=The Fall of Singapore |year=2001 |origyear=1960 |publisher=Penguin |location=London |isbn= |page=94}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The landings were successful and [[Telok Anson]] was taken after a brisk battle with the [[3rd Cavalry (India)|3rd Cavalry]] and 1st Independent Company on 2 January 1942. Once Telok Anson had fallen the 3rd Cavalry and 1st Independent Company fell back to the 12th Brigade which successfully delayed the Japanese from taking the main north–south road. Major-General Paris, with his line of retreat threatened, ordered the positions at Kampar to be abandoned. The 12th Brigade covered the retreat of 11th Division and the British pulled back to the next prepared defensive position at [[Battle of Slim River|Slim River]].&lt;ref name="Colin Smith" /&gt;

==Aftermath==
Over the four-day period, between 30 December 1941 and 2 January 1942, the 11th Division managed to fight off determined Japanese attacks and inflicted heavy casualties upon them. Such were the Japanese losses that the 41st Infantry Regiment was unable to participate in the later [[Battle of Singapore|invasion of Singapore]]. Japanese newspapers at the time claimed 500 Japanese casualties against an Allied loss of 150, but there was no official release of actual Japanese casualties.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Warren|first=Alan|title=Britain's Greatest Defeat: Singapore 1942|publisher=Continuum International Publishing Group|year=2006|edition=Illustrated|isbn=1-85285-597-5|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=zosKzAoocu8C}}&lt;/ref&gt; It was the first serious defeat the Japanese had experienced in the Malayan campaign. Even though the battle was a success for the Allies, the lack of reserves in Malaya Command to support the 11th Division forced the division's withdrawal towards the [[Battle of Slim River|Slim River]].&lt;ref&gt;Thompson pg. 187–188&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Owen pg. 94–95&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
*[[Malaya Command]]
*[[Japanese Order of Battle, Malayan Campaign]]

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References==
{{Refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Owen |first=Frank |title=The Fall of Singapore |year=2001 |origyear=1960 |publisher=Penguin |location=London |isbn=978-0-14-139133-5 }}
* {{cite book | title = Singapore Burning | author = Smith, Colin | publisher = Penguin Books | year = 2006 | location = England | isbn = 978-0-14-101036-6 }}
* {{cite book |last=Thompson |first=Peter |title=The Battle for Singapore: The True Story of the Greatest Catastrophe of World War II| year=2005 |publisher=Portrait |location=London |isbn=0-7499-5085-4}}
*{{cite book | title = Britain's Greatest Defeat&amp;nbsp;– Singapore 1942 | author = Warren, Alan | publisher = Continuum International Publishing Group | year = 2006 | isbn = 1-85285-597-5 }}
{{Refend}}

==Further reading==
{{Refbegin}}
*{{cite book | title = British Army in the Far East 1941–45 | author = Jeffreys, Alan |author2= Anderson,  Duncan | publisher = Osprey Publishing | year = 2005 | isbn = 1-84176-790-5}}
{{Refend}}

==External links==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20091021074421/http://geocities.com/alfix7/valour.htm The Battles of Kampar by Chye Kooi Loong]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20080628061645/http://www.nmbva.co.uk/remembering_the_battle_of_kampar.htm Remembering the Battle of Kampar : The Forgotten Heroes of The British Battalion.]

{{coord missing|Malaysia}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kampar, Battle of 1941}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1941]]
[[Category:1941 in British Malaya]]
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Southeast Asia Theatre]]
[[Category:Battles involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Battles involving Japan]]
[[Category:Military history of Malaya during World War II]]
[[Category:December 1941 events]]
[[Category:January 1942 events]]</text><sha1>rktdc1vfdl91v69mbbg08j14z4a5l4c</sha1></revision></page>