<page><title>Battle off Endau</title><ns>0</ns><id>25808083</id><revision><id>918445085</id><parentid>911448745</parentid><timestamp>2019-09-28T18:07:09Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Monkbot</username><id>20483999</id></contributor><minor /><comment>/* Background */[[User:Monkbot/task 16: remove replace deprecated dead-url params|Task 16]]: replaced (1×) / removed (0×) deprecated |dead-url= and |deadurl= with |url-status=;</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="20883" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Battle of the  Malayan Campaign in World War II}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2017}}
{{good article}}
{{infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle off Endau
| partof      = the [[Battle of Malaya]]
| image       = HMAS Vampire (AWM 012563).jpg
| image_size  = 300px
| caption     = {{HMAS|Vampire|D68|6}}, c. 1940, seen here before the application of wartime camouflage
| date        = 26–27 January 1942
| place       = off [[Endau]], [[British Malaya|Malaya]]
| result      = Japanese victory 
| status      = 
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
| combatant2  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|Australia}}
| commander1  = [[Shintarō Hashimoto]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Australia}} William Moran
| units1      = '''Naval:'''&lt;br&gt; [[1st Escort Unit]]&lt;br&gt;'''Air:'''&lt;br&gt; [[1st Air Squadron (Japan)|1st Air Squadron]]&lt;br/&gt;[[11th Air Squadron (Japan)|11th Air Squadron]]
| units2      = '''Naval:'''&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|UK|naval}} [[Royal Navy]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|UK|naval}} [[Royal Australian Navy]]&lt;br&gt;'''Air:'''&lt;br&gt;[[No. 36 Squadron RAF]]&lt;br&gt;[[No. 62 Squadron RAF]]&lt;br&gt;[[No. 100 Squadron RAF]]&lt;br&gt;[[No. 1 Squadron RAAF]]&lt;br&gt;[[No. 8 Squadron RAAF]]
| strength1   = 1 [[light cruiser]]&lt;br&gt;6 [[destroyer]]s&lt;br&gt;5 [[minesweeper]]s&lt;br/&gt;3 [[subchaser]]s&lt;br/&gt;4 converted [[patrol ship]]s&lt;br&gt;2 [[troopship]]s&lt;br/&gt;2 [[auxiliary ship]]s&lt;br&gt;32 fighters
| strength2   = 2 [[destroyer]]s&lt;br&gt;21 [[Fighter aircraft|fighters]]&lt;br&gt;15 [[light bomber]]s&lt;br&gt;22 [[torpedo bomber]]s
| casualties1 = 8 killed&lt;br&gt;18 wounded
| casualties2 = 1 destroyer sunk&lt;br&gt;39 killed&lt;br&gt;33 captured
| notes       = 
}}
{{Campaignbox Malaya}}
{{Campaignbox South-East Asian Theatre}}
The '''Battle off Endau''' was a [[Second World War]] battle that took place off [[Endau]] on 26–27 January 1942. Part of the [[Battle of Malaya]], it was the first notable naval engagement since the [[Sinking of Prince of Wales and Repulse|sinking of the battleship ''Prince of Wales'' and the battlecruiser ''Repulse'']] on 10 December 1941, and the last effort by the [[Royal Navy]] to intercept Japanese convoy shipping around the [[Malay Peninsula]].&lt;ref name="Paul S. Dull, page 40"&gt;Dull 2007, p. 40&lt;/ref&gt;

A Japanese convoy approaching Endau was detected by [[reconnaissance aircraft]] on 26 January and was ineffectually attacked multiple times by [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] aircraft as it was landing its troops. The Allies suffered heavy casualties, while the Japanese lost only a single aircraft. The Royal Navy committed two [[destroyer]]s later that day to break up the Japanese landings, despite the much larger Japanese escort force. Sailing under the cover of darkness, they were able to locate the convoy anchored there without being detected, but could not find the [[troopship]]s in the darkness. The ships attempted to disengage, but were fired upon by the convoy's escorts and one destroyer was sunk in the early morning hours of 27 January.

==Background==
The sinking of {{HMS|Prince of Wales|53|2}} and {{HMS|Repulse|1916|2}} in the opening stages of the [[Malayan Campaign]] left the task of intercepting Japanese convoys in the [[Gulf of Siam]] to the submarines of the [[Royal Netherlands Navy]] as the surface ships were occupied escorting Allied convoys to and from [[Ceylon]] and the [[Dutch East Indies]].&lt;ref name="Paul S. Dull, page 40"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Gill, p. 502&lt;/ref&gt; The Dutch recorded their first success when the [[troopship]] {{ship||Awazisan Maru|1939|2}} was sunk off [[Kota Bharu]] on 12 December 1941, probably by {{HNLMS|K XII}}.&lt;ref name="Dutch Submarines: The Submarine KXII"&gt;{{citation|title = Dutch Submarines: The Submarine K XII|url = http://www.dutchsubmarines.com/boats/boat_kxii.htm|publisher = Dutch Submarines|accessdate = 31 July 2015| archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101216185555/http://dutchsubmarines.com/boats/boat_kxii.htm| archivedate= 16 December 2010 | url-status= live}}&lt;/ref&gt; On 24 December, {{HNLMS|K XVI}} sank the [[Japanese destroyer Sagiri|destroyer ''Sagiri'']] off the coast of [[Kuching]], [[Borneo]].&lt;ref&gt;Rohwer 2005, p. 126&lt;/ref&gt; Several other vessels were also damaged or sunk during the early weeks, but losses were high for the Dutch submarines and they could do little to stem the Japanese advance.&lt;ref name="Dutch submarines in Australian waters"&gt;{{citation |title = Dutch Submarines in Australian Waters|url = http://www.awm.gov.au/exhibitions/alliesinadversity/australia/submarines.asp|publisher = Australian War Memorial|accessdate = 31 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Endau==
[[File:Location Sribuat.png|thumb|left|Seribuat, circled in red; Endau is at far left]]
An [[amphibious landing]] at [[Mersing]] was originally planned by the Japanese to sever the lines of communication between the British forces and [[Singapore]], but the [[Southern Expeditionary Army Group]] decided to land the rest of the [[18th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|18th Division]] at [[Singora]] instead,&lt;ref name="Defeat p188"/&gt; believing that the Allied defences at Mersing were too formidable. Although ground forces captured Endau on 21 January, they lacked the strength to break through the Australian defences at Sungei-Mersing.&lt;ref name="Paul S. Dull, page 40"/&gt;

On 20 January 1942, a convoy of eleven troopships departed [[Cam Ranh Bay]], [[French Indochina|Indochina]], to unload ground forces at Singora, of which two would proceed to Endau.&lt;ref&gt;Rohwer 2005, p. 137&lt;/ref&gt; The two transports, ''[[Kansai Maru]]'' and ''[[Canberra Maru]]'', were carrying troops of the 96th Airfield Battalion, assigned to bring the airfields of [[Kahang]] and [[Kluang]] into operation.&lt;ref name="Defeat p188"/&gt; They were escorted by the [[1st Escort Unit]], which was formed around [[Torpedo Squadron 3]], which consisted of the [[Japanese cruiser Sendai|light cruiser ''Sendai'']], [[flagship]] of [[Rear-Admiral]] [[Shintarō Hashimoto]], and six {{sclass-|Fubuki|destroyer|2}}s, {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Fubuki|1927|2}}, {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Hatsuyuki|1928|2}}, {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Shirayuki|1928|2}}, {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Asagiri|1929|2}}, {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Amagiri|1930|2}}, and {{ship|Japanese destroyer|Yūgiri|1930|2}}. The squadron was augmented with the five {{sclass-|W-1|minesweeper}}s of the 1st Minesweeper Division, three {{sclass-|CH-4|submarine chaser}}s of the 11th Submarine Chaser Division, and four converted [[patrol boat]]s.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon, pp. 62–64&lt;/ref&gt;

===Air attacks===
[[File:RAAF Hudson over Sydney Heads (AWM photo 128042).jpg|thumb|An Australian Hudson, c. 1940]]
[[Malaya Command]] anticipated that the Japanese force would soon be reinforced by a naval convoy, a suspicion confirmed on 26 January when two [[Royal Australian Air Force]] (RAAF) [[Lockheed Hudson]] aircraft sighted them {{convert|20|mi}} north of Endau.&lt;ref name="Paul S. Dull, page 40"/&gt; Although they spotted the Japanese convoy at 07:45, their radio transmissions were jammed, and news did not reach higher command until they landed in Singapore at 09:20. The RAF decided to attack the convoy with all available aircraft. The attack had to be delayed until that afternoon, however, to allow the crews of the [[Vickers Vildebeest]] and [[Fairey Albacore]] torpedo bombers of [[No. 36 Squadron RAF]] and [[No. 100 Squadron RAF]] to rest after their night missions.&lt;ref name="Bloody2 p19"&gt;Shores, Cull and Izawa 1993, pp. 18–19&lt;/ref&gt; The decision to use the elderly Vildebeest [[biplane]]s against the ships in daylight came as a shock to the pilots,&lt;ref name="Defeat p188"/&gt; who had been restricted to the relative safety of night [[sortie]]s following the first day of the invasion.&lt;ref name="Bloody1 p83-4"&gt;Shores, Cull and Izawa 1992, pp. 83–84&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Vildebeeste torpedo practice.jpg|thumb|Vickers Vildebeest of [[No. 100 Squadron RAF]] making a torpedo drop during target practice, c. 1936]]
The first air attack was carried out by the Vildebeests of Nos. 36 and 100 Squadrons and the Hudsons of [[No. 1 Squadron RAAF|Nos. 1]] and [[No. 8 Squadron RAAF|8 Squadron RAAF]]. Twelve Vildebeests and nine Hudson bombers took off from Singapore in the early afternoon of 26 January, with a fighter escort composed of twelve [[Brewster F2A Buffalo]]s and nine [[Hawker Hurricane]]s.&lt;ref name="Bloody2 p19-0"&gt;Shores, Cull and Izawa 1993, pp. 19–20&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese landings on Endau had been in progress for over four hours by the time the planes arrived at 15:00.&lt;ref name="Defeat p188"&gt;Warren 2007, p. 188&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese naval force had air cover consisting of 19 [[Nakajima Ki-27]]s from the [[1st Air Squadron (Japan)|1st]] and [[11th Air Squadron (Japan)|11th Squadrons]] and a single [[Nakajima Ki-44]] fighter.&lt;ref name="Bloody2 p20"&gt;Shores, Cull and Izawa 1993, p. 20&lt;/ref&gt; Despite heavy opposition, the two transports were bombed, and men and equipment on the beach were strafed.&lt;ref name="Dull p40-1"&gt;Dull 2007, pp. 40–41&lt;/ref&gt; Five Vildebeests were lost in the attack, including the commanding officer of No. 100 Squadron, while one Ki-27 was shot down.&lt;ref name="Bloody2 p22-9"&gt;Shores, Cull and Izawa 1993, pp. 22–29&lt;/ref&gt;

A second wave set off from Singapore at 16:15, consisting of seven Vildebeests and three Albacores of No. 36 Squadron and two Vildebeests of No. 100 Squadron. They arrived over Endau at 17:30, but their escort of seven Hurricanes and four Buffalos were late and the British biplanes were set upon by ten Ki-27s and two Ki-44s before their escorts could reach them. Five Vildebeests, two Albacores and one Hurricane were lost from this wave.&lt;ref name="Bloody2 p29-7"&gt;Shores, Cull and Izawa 1993, pp. 29–37&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 72 aircrew from Nos. 36 and 100 Squadrons who participated in the raids, 27 were killed, seven were wounded and two were captured. The returning pilots were congratulated by [[Air Vice-Marshal]] [[Paul Maltby]], who promised them that further daylight attacks were unnecessary.&lt;ref name="Defeat page 189"&gt;Warren 2007, p. 189&lt;/ref&gt;

A third raid, consisting of six unescorted Hudsons of [[No. 62 Squadron RAF]], flying from [[Palembang]], [[Sumatra]], attacked shortly afterwards, losing two of their number, with their entire crews, to six Ki-27s. A fourth raid, made up of five [[Bristol Blenheim]]s of [[No. 27 Squadron RAF]], set off from Palembang later in the day, but had only got as far as Singapore by sunset, so aborted the mission.&lt;ref&gt;Shores, Cull and Izawa 1993, pp. 37–38&lt;/ref&gt; Despite claims to have scored multiple hits on both transports and a cruiser, neither the transports, nor any of their escorts were damaged; the former were hit by splinters that killed 8 and wounded 18, but ''Sendai'' and the smaller ships were untouched.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon, p. 64&lt;/ref&gt;

===Naval battle===
[[File:Japanese minesweeper MSC4.jpg|thumb|The minesweeper ''W-4'' at anchor, July 1930]]
Rear-Admiral [[Ernest John Spooner|Ernest Spooner]], commander of naval forces at Singapore, ordered his only combat-ready warships, the elderly destroyers {{HMS|Thanet|H29|6}} and {{HMAS|Vampire|D68|6}}, to attack the shipping off Endau later that night. [[Commander]] William Moran was [[captain (nautical)|captain]] of ''Vampire'' while ''Thanet'' was under the command of [[Lieutenant Commander]] Bernard Davies. The destroyers departed [[Singapore Naval Base|Singapore]] at 16:30 with Moran in charge of the two ships and headed north. Initial intelligence reports assessed the Japanese strength defending the convoy as a dozen destroyers, but this was revised downward to a pair of destroyers at 22:55, based on inaccurate reporting by surviving RAF aircrew. The 1st Escort Unit was prepared for a surface attack based on an incorrect intelligence report that two British light cruisers were at sea and Hashimoto oriented his ships' patrol sectors to the north.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon, pp. 64–65, 69&lt;/ref&gt;

Moran led his ships between the [[Seribuat Archipelago]] and the coast of [[Johor]] in brilliant moonlight and then altered course northeast to search the area north of the archipelago. When dark clouds obscured the moon at 01:51, he turned southwestwards at a speed of {{convert|15|kn}} for Endau, keeping [[Tioman Island]] behind him to ensure that his ships were not silhouetted against the horizon. At 02:37, ''Vampire'' saw a Japanese destroyer (probably ''Amagiri''), but was not spotted in return and the Allied ships continued on their course. Three minutes later, they located another Japanese ship (the minesweeper ''W-4'') dead ahead at [[point-blank range]]. Moran decided to attack, as discovery was inevitable at such short range, and increased his speed to {{convert|25|kn}}, simultaneously firing two of his three torpedoes at a distance of {{convert|600|m|yd}}. One torpedo missed ahead by {{convert|15|-|20|yd|m}} and the other passed underneath the minesweeper. ''W-4'', in the middle patrol zone, was trying to identify the two destroyers when Moran attacked, but failed to alert any other Japanese ships to the Allied presence in their midst for 20 minutes before giving a location {{convert|6|nmi|spell=in}} away. ''W-4'' did not return fire and Moran resumed his search for the transports, reducing his speed again to 15 knots to reduce the visibility of his [[wake]]s. A half-hour later, with shallow water approaching, and no transports spotted, the Allied destroyers altered course to the north to clear the shallows and increased speed to 25 knots at 03:13 before turning southeast by east.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon, pp. 68–71&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Japanese destroyer Shirayuki in 1931.jpg|thumb|''Shirayuki'' at anchor, 1931]]
At 03:18, ''Vampire'' sighted the destroyer ''Shirayuki'' off the port bow and another ship astern. ''Vampire'' and ''Thanet'' made minor course adjustments to fire their torpedoes at ''Shirayuki'' at a range of {{convert|1500|yd}} – one from ''Vampire'' and all four of ''Thanet''{{'}}s – but all missed as ''Shirayuki'', having spotted the Allied ships at the same time, altered course to come behind the Allied destroyers and then signalled to confirm their identities. Not receiving a reply, the Japanese ship illuminated the Allied ships with her searchlight and finally opened fire at 03:31 despite the [[smoke screen]] being laid by both ships. Moran ordered both his ships to return fire with their four-inch guns while retiring southeast at maximum speed. ''Thanet'' only fired three [[Volley fire|volleys]] from her guns before she was hit in the engine room. The hit fractured both the main and auxiliary steam lines to the engines, causing the ship to go dead in the water and lose all electrical power. Constantly making small changes of course to throw off Japanese gun layers, neither ship hit any Japanese ships during the battle.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon, pp. 70–75, 78–79&lt;/ref&gt;

Allied and Japanese accounts of the gunnery action are difficult to reconcile, particularly as neither of the Allied destroyers recorded any times after firing their torpedoes at 03:18. ''Shirayuki'' fired 18 rounds at ''Vampire'' at a range of {{convert|4500|yd}} before the [[muzzle blast]] from her rear gun mounts tripped the [[circuit breaker]]s in her main [[electrical switchboard]], causing complete electrical failure throughout the ship. While electrical service was restored within two minutes, the ship had a series of smaller electrical failures that bedeviled her for the next 15 minutes. When she resumed firing, ''Vampire'' was no longer visible and ''Shirayuki'' targeted ''Thanet'' instead at a range of {{convert|3050|m}}, firing 82 rounds at her. ''Yugiri'' opened fire at 03:38 at ''Thanet'' {{convert|4500|yd}} away and both ships observed their target slowing down at 03:45. At that same time, ''Yugiri'' radioed Hashimoto that "The enemy is two destroyers" so she had spotted ''Vampire'' as she fled, although ''Yugiri'' lost sight of ''Vampire'' 10 minutes later. ''Sendai'', ''Fubuki'', ''Asagiri'', ''Amagiri'', ''Hatsuyuki'' and ''W-1'' all subsequently opened fire, mostly at ''Thanet'', although ''Vampire'' reported being under fire for a considerable time. All told, the Japanese ships fired 469 rounds at the Allied destroyers, failing to hit ''Vampire'' even once. ''Shirayuki'' reported that ''Thanet'' had sunk at 04:18 and rescued an officer and 30 [[other ranks (UK)|ratings]] from the water; another officer and 11 ratings died in the battle. The Japanese did not pursue&lt;ref&gt;Cannon, pp. 71–77&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Vampire'' reached Singapore at 10:00 that morning.&lt;ref name="Action off Endau"/&gt;

==Aftermath==
''Shirayuki'' handed over the rescued seamen to troops on Endau the following day. They were never seen again, but are believed to have been executed in retaliation for losses sustained by the Japanese in an ambush by the Australian [[2/18th Battalion (Australia)|2/18th Battalion]], which occurred south of Mersing about the same time as the naval action off Endau. Davies, four other officers, and 61 ratings from ''Thanet'' managed to reach shore and made their way to Singapore,&lt;ref name="Action off Endau"&gt;{{citation|title = Action off Endau|url = http://www.navyhistory.org.au/action-off-endau/|publisher = Naval Historical Society of Australia|date = March 2006|accessdate = 30 July 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; together with shot down aircrew.&lt;ref&gt;Shores, Cull and Izawa 1993, pp. 39–42&lt;/ref&gt;

The Japanese were able to finish landing their troops, which may have contributed to the impression of significant forces in front of the Australian defenders and their subsequent withdrawal. The heavy losses suffered by the Allied aircraft and aircrew virtually eliminated their ability to influence the subsequent ground battles.&lt;ref&gt;Wigmore, p. 266&lt;/ref&gt; Moran's report on Japanese incompetence at night fighting was the most important result of the battle. Since few details about the subsequent night combats off Java survived, Moran's assessment influenced Allied thinking about the IJN until the stunning victory during the nighttime [[Battle of Savo Island]] in August flipped the Allied beliefs about the Japanese ability at night fighting on their heads.&lt;ref&gt;Cannon, p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
*{{cite book|editor=Jordan, John|publisher=Conway|location=London|year=2014|title=Warship 2015|isbn=978-1-84486-276-4|first=Peter|last=Cannon|chapter=Night Action, Malaya 1942|pages=62–80}}
* {{cite book|last=Dull|first=Paul S|title=A Battle History of the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1941–1945|year=2007|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn=1-59114-219-9|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=SLfti-Dc1AcC&amp;pg=PR4&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;focus=viewport}}
* {{cite book |title=Australia in the War of 1939–1945: Series Two Navy: Volume I: The Royal Australian Navy, 1939–1942 |last=Gill |first=G. Hermon |year= 1957|publisher=Australian War Memorial |location=Canberra, Australia|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070207/|chapter=Chapter 14: South-West Pacific Area|chapterurl=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070349/|pages=484–512|oclc=848228}}
*{{cite book|last=Rohwer|first=Jürgen|title=Chronology of the War at Sea 1939–1945: The Naval History of World War Two|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|year=2005|edition=Third Revised|isbn=1-59114-119-2|authorlink=Jürgen Rohwer}}
* {{cite book|last1=Shores|first1=Christopher|last2=Cull|first2=Brian|last3=Izawa|first3=Yasuho |title=Bloody Shambles: Volume One: The Drift to War to the Fall of Singapore|year=1992|publisher=Grub Street|location=London|isbn=0-948817-50-X}}
* {{cite book|last1=Shores|first1=Christopher|last2=Cull|first2=Brian|last3=Izawa|first3=Yasuho |title=Bloody Shambles: Volume Two: The Defence of Sumatra to the Fall of Burma|year=1993|publisher=Grub Street|location=London| isbn=0-948817-67-4}}
* {{cite book|title = Britain's Greatest Defeat: Singapore 1942|url = https://books.google.com/books?id=zosKzAoocu8C&amp;printsec=frontcover|first= Alan|last= Warren|publisher=Hambleton Continuum|location=London|year=2007|isbn=1-85285-597-5}}
* {{cite book |title=Australia in the War of 1939–1945: Series One Army: Volume IV: The Japanese Thrust|last=Wigmore |first=Lionel Gage |year= 1957|publisher=Australian War Memorial |location=Canberra, Australia|url=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070203/|chapter=Chapter 13: To Singapore Island|chapterurl=https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070105/|pages=250–283}}

{{coord missing|Malaysia}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Endau, Battle of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1942]]
[[Category:1942 in British Malaya]]
[[Category:World War II naval operations and battles of the Southeast Asia Theatre|Battle off Endau]]
[[Category:Naval aviation operations and battles]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Australia]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:January 1942 events]]</text><sha1>lm7tv9z7ufll9gq3i5unh1p6aalch6w</sha1></revision></page>