<page><title>Battle of Bilin River</title><ns>0</ns><id>23666875</id><revision><id>881724833</id><parentid>881723831</parentid><timestamp>2019-02-04T12:08:48Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Adapad</username><id>31407554</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="5123" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Battle of Bilin River
|partof = The [[Burma Campaign]]
|image = 
|caption = 
|date = 14–18 February 1942
|place = [[Burma]]
|result = Tactical Japanese victory
|combatant1 = {{flagicon|UK}} [[British Empire]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|British Raj}} [[British India]]
|combatant2 = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}} 
|commander1 = {{flagicon|UK}} Brig. [[Sir John Smyth, 1st Baronet|Sir John Smyth]]
|commander2 = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan}} Lt Gen. [[Shōjirō Iida]]
|strength1 = 1 division
|strength2 = 2 divisions
|casualties1 = 
|casualties2 =  
}}
{{Campaignbox Burma}}
{{Campaignbox South-East Asia}}

The '''Battle of Bilin River''' was the first major battle of the [[Burma Campaign]] in [[World War II]]. Fought between 14 and 18 February 1942, the battle was a tactical victory for [[Empire of Japan|Japan]] over the [[Indian Army (1895–1947)|British Indian Army]], and it led to a decisive victory for Japan immediately afterwards at the [[Battle of Sittang Bridge]].

[[Sir John Smyth, 1st Baronet|Brigadier Sir John George Smyth, V.C.]]—who commanded [[17th Infantry Division (India)|17th Infantry Division]] of the British Indian Army at Bilin River—said the Bilin River "at that time of year was only a ditch, but a good co-ordinating line".&lt;ref name="LH p.213"&gt;Liddell Hart 1970, p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt; 17th Division was, at that time, a new formation that had yet to see its first battle.

The Japanese 112th Battalion of the Southern Army entered Burma (now [[Myanmar]]) on 15 January. They took Tavoy (now [[Dawei]]) on 19 January, cutting off the garrison at [[Mergui]] (which escaped by sea). In the process, they captured three small airfields, giving them close air support. They then advanced towards [[Kawkareik]].

Smyth wanted to withdraw immediately to better defensive terrain, but he was ordered to "stay put".&lt;ref name="LH p.213"/&gt;

==Prelude==
&lt;!-- Sidebar starts here --&gt;
&lt;div class="infobox" style="width:300px; background-color: #D1EEEE; margin: 2px; padding: 0.5em;"&gt;&lt;center&gt;'''Quotes'''&lt;/center&gt;

{{quote|''The 17th Division gave everything it had at Bilin and surrendered no ground to the Japanese; but, as the pressure increased, every single reserve had to be thrown into the battle—and even then we could not prevent strong parties of the enemy turning our flanks.''|Brigadier Sir John George Smyth, V.C.&lt;ref name="LH p.216"&gt;Liddell Hart 1970, p. 216.&lt;/ref&gt;}}&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!-- End of sidebar--&gt;
On 26 January, the Japanese 55th Division advanced on [[Mawlamyaing|Moulmein]]. Taking the town would give them another airfield, but it was hard for the Indians to defend. It was also a difficult place from which to retreat, because there was no bridge over the [[Gulf of Martaban]]; any retreat would need to be by ferry.

The British Indian Army held out for two days of fierce fighting, and then got away on a river steamer.&lt;ref name="LH p.213"/&gt; In the process, they lost about 600 soldiers and a significant amount of materiel.

Smyth sent [[David Tennant Cowan|Brigadier "Punch" Cowan]] to [[Yangon|Rangoon]] to speak with the Army Commander, General Hutton, and ask for permission to move to behind the Sittang River (now [[Sittaung River|Sittaung]]). In what Smyth called a "disastrous decision", and perhaps influenced by his own orders from higher up, Hutton refused.&lt;ref name="LH p.216"/&gt;

==The battle==
17th Division held at the Bilin River for two days of close-quarters jungle fighting. The Japanese tactics were to outflank, and eventually with encirclement imminent,&lt;ref&gt;Slim 1956, p. 17.&lt;/ref&gt; Hutton came up from Rangoon and gave Smyth permission to fall back. 17th Division disengaged under cover of darkness and began a {{convert|30|mi|km|adj=on}} retreat along the dusty track to the Sittang Bridge.

==Aftermath==
{{main|Battle of Sittang Bridge}}
17th Division slowly withdrew towards the bridge over the Sittang River. But it was outflanked by the Japanese who reached the area of the bridge and forced its demolition. The bulk of 17th Division was caught on the wrong side of the Sittang. While most of the men were able to eventually cross the river, almost all of their equipment had been lost.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
*[[Basil Liddell Hart|Liddell Hart, B.H.]], ''History of the Second World War.'' New York: G.P. Putnam, 1970. {{ISBN|0-306-80912-5}}.
*[[William Slim|Slim, William]] (1956), ''Defeat Into Victory''. Citations from the Four Square Books 1958 edition which lacks an ISBN, but also available from NY: Buccaneer Books {{ISBN|1-56849-077-1}}, Cooper Square Press {{ISBN|0-8154-1022-0}}; London: Cassell {{ISBN|0-304-29114-5}}, Pan {{ISBN|0-330-39066-X}}.

{{coord missing|Myanmar}}

[[Category:South-East Asian theatre of World War II|Bilin River]]
[[Category:Military history of Burma during World War II|Bilin River]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving India]]
[[Category:1942 in Burma]]
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Pacific theatre|Bilin River]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]
[[Category:February 1942 events]]</text><sha1>005j7fqcdgz1i2d1jgzphqb2bp6jpen</sha1></revision></page>