<page><title>Battle of Oktwin</title><ns>0</ns><id>12734078</id><revision><id>916461597</id><parentid>880139418</parentid><timestamp>2019-09-19T01:26:20Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Tom.Reding</username><id>9784415</id></contributor><minor /><comment>[[:Category:CS1 errors: deprecated parameters]]: migrate 1 |dead-url= to |url-status=; minor cleanup; [[WP:GenFixes]] on</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="4221" xml:space="preserve">{{Use mdy dates|date=February 2013}}
{{Campaignbox Burma}}

The '''Battle of Oktwin''' March 20–23, 1942, was the second battle in the [[Battle of Yunnan-Burma Road]] in the [[Burma Campaign]] of [[World War II]] and [[Second Sino-Japanese War]].

On March 20, the Japanese 143rd Regiment plus cavalry units of the [[55th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|55th Division]] attacked the positions of the Chinese 5th Army Cavalry Regiment north of the Kan River, driving the Chinese forces back with heavy losses. The bulk of the cavalry regiment was withdrawn to the north of Toungoo, leaving only a company of cavalry and infantry each to delay the advancing Japanese. Meanwhile, the commanding general of [[200th Division]], [[Dai Anlan]]’s fortifications at [[Oktwin]] and around [[Toungoo]] were now ready.  They were built using timber, which was in abundant supply, and all positions were carefully concealed.  On March 21, Japanese forces brushed aside the delaying forces and reached the 200th Division outposts at Oktwin.

The 122nd Regiment of the 55th Division attacked 200th Division positions at first light on March 22, but made little headway. Japanese forces attacking the Chinese positions consisted of a battalion of infantry with several guns; the defenders were the 1st Battalion, 600th Regiment. The Japanese sent cavalry forces around the left flank of the Chinese and the position was stabilized only when reserve forces of the 1st Battalion, 598th Regiment were committed immediately in counterattacks.

The Japanese were now more careful after the ambush, and used their artillery and machine guns to fire at suspected positions before sending their infantry forward. Light machine guns were positioned up among the trees and caused many Chinese casualties. Eventually the Chinese set up their heavy machine guns to fire at an angle to deal with this menace.

On March 23, the Japanese attacked again on the left flank with strong artillery and air support.  The battle continued until 4&amp;nbsp;pm without much success for the attackers, who then tried another flanking move with a company of infantry and scores of cavalry troops around the right side of the Chinese positions. The Chinese held their ground until nightfall and fell back to the main defensive line at Toungoo on March 24.

==See also==
* [[Battle of Toungoo]]

==References==
* {{cite book|author1= Hsu Long-hsuen |author2= Chang Ming-kai|title= History of The Sino-Japanese War (1937–1945)|edition= 2nd |date=1971|editor=  Translated by Wen Ha-hsiung |publisher= Chung Wu Publishing|location=33, 140th Lane, Tung-hwa Street Taipei, Taiwan Republic of China|pages= Pg. 376}}
* {{cite book|author= Guo Rugui|editor=Huang Yuzhang|publisher= Jiangsu People's Publishing House|date= 1 July 2005|ISBN= 7-214-03034-9|title= China's Anti-Japanese War Combat Operations (中国抗日战争正面战场作战记)|url= http://www.wehoo.net/book/wlwh/a30012/A0170.htm|language= zh|url-status= dead|archive-url= https://web.archive.org/web/20090116005113/http://www.wehoo.net/book/wlwh/a30012/A0170.htm|archive-date= January 16, 2009|df= mdy-all}}
*{{cite book|title=Yuan zheng Yin Mian kang zhan (Battles of the Expeditionary Force in India and Burma) |publisher=Zhongguo wen shi chu ban she |date=1 January 1998 |author=A collection of memoirs and first hand accounts by KMT officers}}
* {{cite book|title=Biography of Dai Anlan|author= Dai Chengdong|publisher= Anhui People’s Press|year= 1998}}

==External links==
* [http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/ams/burma/txu-oclc-6924198-ne47-5.jpg  Topographic Map NE 47–5 Toungoo]
* [http://forum.axishistory.com/viewtopic.php?t=124083&amp;start=6 Axis History Forum: Chinese 200th Division: descriptions of actions needed!] Discussion and map of the battle of Toungoo and the actions leading up to it.

{{coord|18.82897|96.405258|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Oktwin}}
[[Category:History of Myanmar]]
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Southeast Asia Theatre]]
[[Category:Battles of the Second Sino-Japanese War|Oktwin]]
[[Category:1942 in Japan]]
[[Category:1942 in Burma]]
[[Category:Military history of Burma during World War II]]
[[Category:March 1942 events]]</text><sha1>l9ktw47dllbgkvks0bqkeuv7dicwcyz</sha1></revision></page>