<page><title>Siege of Myitkyina</title><ns>0</ns><id>45289352</id><revision><id>967095447</id><parentid>950775001</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-11T03:35:22Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Toyopin</username><id>39321146</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="9311" xml:space="preserve">{{infobox military conflict
|conflict    = Siege of Myitkyina
|partof      = the [[Burma Campaign]] of the [[Pacific War]]
|image       = 75-mm pack howitzer.jpg
|image_size  = 300px
|caption     = An American M1A1 75-mm pack howitzer supports [[Merrill's Marauders|GALAHAD's]] operations at Myitkyina.
|date        = 17 May – 3 August 1944&lt;ref name="Jacques"&gt;Jaques, Tony (2007) Dictionary of Battles and Sieges: F-O [https://books.google.com/books?id=Dh6jydKXikoC&amp;pg=PA700&amp;lpg=PA700&amp;dq=Mizukami+Genzu&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=nJBawMu4I9&amp;sig=cNDSQCa9ocRqZImkA1fCXPL6ScQ&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=3xLPVPagOJD8sATY_ILYAw&amp;ved=0CCUQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=Mizukami%20Genzu&amp;f=false (p.700)]&lt;/ref&gt;
|place       = [[Myitkyina]], [[Burma]]
|coordinates =
|map_type    =
|map_relief  =
|latitude    =
|longitude   =
|map_size    =
|map_marksize =
|map_caption =
|map_label   =
|territory   = Myitkyina airfield and town captured by the Allies
|result      = Allied victory
|status      =
|combatant1  = {{flag|Republic of China (1912–1949)|name=China}}&lt;br&gt;{{flag|United States|1912}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[United Kingdom]]
|combatant2  = {{flag|Empire of Japan|name=Japan}}
|commander1  = {{flagicon|Republic of China (1912–49)|army}} [[Wei Li-huang]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|United States|1912}} [[Joseph Stilwell]]
|commander2  = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan|army}} Genzo Mizukami{{KIA}}&lt;ref name="Jacques"/&gt;
|strength1   = [[Chinese Expeditionary Force]]&lt;br&gt;[[Northern Combat Area Command]]
|strength2   = Garrison from [[56th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|56th division]] (3,000)
|casualties1 = '''Chinese'''&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/USA-CBI-Command/USA-CBI-Command-6.html China-Buma-India Command]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;br&gt;972 killed&lt;br&gt;3,184 wounded&lt;br&gt;188 invalid&lt;br&gt;'''U.S.'''&lt;br&gt;272 killed&lt;br&gt;955 wounded&lt;br&gt;980 invalid
|casualties2 = 2,400 killed,  wounded,  captured&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/USA-CBI-Command/USA-CBI-Command-6.html China-Buma-India Command], page 253; only about 600 men of the garrison escaped.&lt;/ref&gt;
|notes       =
|campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Burma}}
}}
[[File:Advance to Myitkyina 21 April - 3 August 1944.jpg|thumb|right|Advance to Myitkyina]]

The '''Siege of Myitkyina''' was an engagement during the [[Burma Campaign]] of [[World War II]].  The Allied victory was part of the larger [[Battle of Northern Burma and Western Yunnan|operation of North Burma &amp; Yunnan]] which succeeded in opening the [[Ledo Road]].

==Background==
[[Joseph Stilwell]] intended to make a rapid march against Myitkyina prophesying it to be a "feat which will live in military history", wanting the town for the nearby airstrip, strategically vital to the campaign as it would be an invaluable source of supplies and aerial support in the notoriously difficult jungle fighting in the China-Burma-India theater. Chinese Expeditionary Force commander Wei Lihuang also played a fundamental role in striking the Imperial Japanese Army. Sun li-Jen, as the second commander of the new Chinese 1st Army,  one of the best of the Chinese National Revolutionary Army. The 1st Army has since changed their equipment from old, unsuitable-for-combat caps into US-supplied M1 helmets, and had exchanged their bolt-action Type Zhongzheng rifles for newer American and British weaponry. In addition to that, the Chinese Expeditionary Force (CEF) had finally received artillery and air support from the US and British forces as well, giving them a distinct advantage against the now-malnourished, low-morale Japanese forces around Myitkyina. The US and British played a relatively minor role during the battle, although they also had combat units, such as the famed 'Merrill's Marauders', active in the fighting.

==Siege==
Stilwell gave the Chinese 22nd Division orders to advance against the bridges held by the Japanese on March 15. After two months of fighting, Myitkyina was now in reach. With the arrival of the rainy season, the incessant rain didn't stop until May 17. On that day, at 10:00&amp;nbsp;p.m., the Chinese Expeditionary Force launched an attack with the U.S. Army's 'Merrill's Marauders' unit against the Japanese airstrip at Myitkyina, supported by artillery. Eight Japanese planes were quickly destroyed as the battle escalated. The Japanese were caught by surprise, and, not knowing where their enemies were, poured gasoline onto the airfield in an attempt to disable it and retreated into Myitkyina proper, intending to fight the Chinese and Americans on more favorable terms there. The Chinese and the Americans quickly overran the field relatively intact, whereupon U.S. Army Air Forces  and Royal Air Force C-47 transport aircraft moved the Chinese 89th Regiment of the 30th Division to the battlefield to supplement the exhausted C.E.F. and Marauder units already at Myitkyina.

Afterward, some Chinese units attacked the town itself, but the attack was soon called off when two Chinese battalions, in the confusion and excitement of the battle, mistakenly engaged each other in a fierce firefight, and when two other battalions were moved in, they too repeated the mistake.

A stalemate ensued throughout June, but the [[Battle of Mogaung|capture of Mogaung]] by the British [[Chindits]] under [[Mike Calvert]] later that month was the beginning of the end for the Japanese garrison at Myitkyina. With supply lines cut, infighting grew between the two local Japanese commanders over their orders regarding the defence of the town. Stillwell had demanded that the Chindits join them but they were whittled down by disease and combat. Stillwell nevertheless was reinforced by the arrival of elements of [[Francis Festing]]'s [[36th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|36th Division]] from 15 July Myitkyina airfield. On hearing of the weakening Japanese garrison in Myitkyina, Stillwell sent that Division not to take Myitkyina but to advance on the 'Railway Corridor' from Mogaung towards [[Indaw]] on the right flank of [[Northern Combat Area Command|NCAC]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=Pitt |first1=Barrie |editor1-last=Hart |editor1-first=Basil Henry Liddell |title=History of the Second World War, Volume 6 History of the Second World War |date=1966 |publisher=Purnell |page=2584 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=VZhd6Wyp9jUC&amp;q=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On 26 Jul, the American 3rd Battalion of the Marauders made a significant gain by capturing the northern air field at Myitkyina and over the next week Japanese resistance was noticeably weaker.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book |last1=United States Department of State |title=Newsletter |date=1961 |publisher=Bureau of Administration |page=13 |url=https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=3ZyHm0bkYy4C&amp;dq=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On August 3, General Genzo Mizukami ordered the town abandoned and took his life in a literal compliance to "defend Myitkyina to the death" as the Chinese and US forces gradually cleared the city and the surrounding area of Japanese troops.&lt;ref&gt;[http://pwencycl.kgbudge.com/M/y/Myitkyina.htm Pacific War Online]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
The operations against Myitkyina was particularly hard on the Chinese Expeditionary Force, due to the hard fighting, lack of supplies, difficult terrain, and disease. Owing to excessive casualties, the unit effectively ceased to exist as a fighting force and was therefore disbanded. The long-awaited taking of Myitkyina and its airfield allowed for the opening of the [[Ledo Road]], connecting the old [[Burma Road]] with China. The Chinese forces' casualties were the highest among all the battles during the Chinese-intervention of Burma Campaign.{{citation needed|date=July 2017}}

===Order of Battle===
{| class="wikitable"
!American-Chinese order of battle&lt;ref&gt;[http://pwencycl.kgbudge.com/M/y/Myitkyina.htm Pacific War Online]&lt;/ref&gt;
!Japanese order of battle&lt;ref&gt;[http://pwencycl.kgbudge.com/M/y/Myitkyina.htm Pacific War Online]&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| valign = "top" style="width:50%"|
'''Chinese and American troops of the [[Northern Combat Area Command]]:''' General [[Joseph Stilwell]]
* New 1st Army: [[Zheng Dongguo]]
** 22nd Division: [[Liao Yaoxiang]]
** 30th Division: Tang Shouzhi
** 38th Division: [[Sun Li-Jen]]
** 14th Division: Long Tianwu
** 50th Division：Pan Yukun
* 1st Tank Division
* [[Merrill's Marauders|GALAHAD]]: BG [[Frank Merrill]]
** 5307th Provisional Regiment
'''[[Chinese Expeditionary Force]]:''' General  [[Wei Li-huang]]
* 11 Army Group: [[Song Xilian]]
** 2 Army: Wang Ling-yun
** 6 Army: [[Huang Chieh]]
** 71 Army: Chung Pin
* 20th Army Group: [[Huo Kuizhang]]
** 53 Army: Chou Fu-chen
** 54 Army: Chueh Han-chien
** 8 Army: Ho Shao-chou

| valign = "top" style="width:50%"|
'''33rd Japanese Army:''' General Hondo Masaki
* 2 Division: Okazaki
* 18 Division: Tanaka
* 53 Division: Takeda
* 56 Division: Matsuyama    
* 24 Independent Mixed Brigade: Hayashi
* Myitkyina: Genzo Mizukami
|}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/USA/USA-CBI-Command/USA-CBI-Command-6.html Stilwell's Command Problems]
* [https://books.google.com/books?id=e9JPQT6GPCoC&amp;pg=PA39&amp;lpg=PA39&amp;dq=siege+of+myitkyina+Marshall+Cavendish&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=N8LBd7NWla&amp;sig=Di_faHxr3_nFfWYF9LpatD4njQM&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ei=wgLPVK3lBci-ggTr24LgAg&amp;ved=0CCEQ6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q=siege%20of%20myitkyina%20Marshall%20Cavendish&amp;f=false Final Victories]

[[Category:Military history of Burma during World War II]]</text><sha1>qok9qqfae4yl4ipzpvimhv2om6dfsyn</sha1></revision></page>