<page><title>Battle of Sangshak</title><ns>0</ns><id>21192407</id><revision><id>963082848</id><parentid>959859347</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-17T18:37:14Z</timestamp><contributor><username>XavierGreen</username><id>3177032</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="13565" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Battle of the 1944 Burma campaign during World War II}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Sangshak
| partof      = the [[Battle of Imphal]]
| image       = 
| caption     = 
| date        = 20–26 March 1944
| place       = {{convert|8|mi|km}} south of [[Ukhrul]], [[Manipur]], [[India]]
| result      = Tactical Japanese victory, Strategic British victory
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|India|British}} [[British India]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagdeco|Nepal|old}} [[Kingdom of Nepal|Nepal]]&lt;ref name=Seaman75/&gt;
| combatant2  = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan}} [[Empire of Japan|Japan]]
| commander1  = [[Maxwell Hope-Thompson]]
| commander2  = [[:ja:宮崎繁三郎|Shigesaburo Miyazaki]]
| strength1   = approx. 1 understrength parachute brigade, elements of two infantry battalions, one mtn bty
| strength2   = approx. 1+ infantry regiment, elements of two regiments
| casualties1 = 652
| casualties2 = 400+
}}
{{Campaignbox Burma}}
{{Campaignbox South-East Asia}}

The '''Battle of Sangshak''' took place in [[Manipur]] in the forested and mountainous frontier area between [[India]] and [[Burma]], from 20 March to 26 March 1944. The Japanese drove a parachute brigade (fighting as infantry) of the [[British Indian Army]] from its positions with heavy casualties, but suffered heavy casualties themselves. The delay imposed on the Japanese by the battle allowed British and Indian reinforcements to reach the vital position at [[Kohima]] before the Japanese.

==Background==
In March 1944, the Japanese launched Operation [[U-GO]], a major invasion of India. Two divisions of the [[Fifteenth Army (Japan)|Japanese Fifteenth Army]] –  the [[15th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|15th]] and [[33rd Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|33rd]]  – attacked [[IV Corps (India)|IV Indian Corps]]  at Imphal, the [[IJA 31st Division|Japanese 31st Division]] advanced on Kohima, to cut the main road on which the troops at Imphal depended for supply from Dimapur.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, pp. 25 &amp; 49&lt;/ref&gt;

The Japanese division advanced over a wide front. It was divided into Left, Centre and Right Assault forces. The Left Assault Force consisted of two battalions of the Japanese 58th Regiment,&lt;ref name=Katoch37&gt;Katoch 2018, p. 37&lt;/ref&gt; with the regimental headquarters and detachments from the division's supporting arms. The regiment's commander was Colonel Utata Fukunaga,&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 56&lt;/ref&gt; but the force was accompanied by the division's Infantry Group commander, Major General [[Shigesaburo Miyazaki]], who was the senior officer. On 18 March, the force was approaching the village of [[Ukhrul]], about {{convert|25|mi|km}} north-east of Imphal and {{convert|8|mi|km}} north of Sangshak.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, pp. 50–53&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Allen 1984, pp. 213–215&lt;/ref&gt;

==British dispositions==
Early in 1944, the [[49th Indian Infantry Brigade]] of the [[23rd Indian Infantry Division]] had been stationed at Sangshak, tasked with defending against a Japanese advance from the [[Chindwin River]] towards Ukhurl.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 1984, p. 212&lt;/ref&gt; As the Japanese offensive began, the Japanese surrounded the [[17th Indian Infantry Division]] at [[Tiddim]], south of Imphal. Lieutenant General [[Geoffry Scoones]], the commander of IV Corps, was forced to send the 23rd Division (including the 49th Brigade) to help the 17th Division break out of encirclement.&lt;ref name=Rooney51&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 51&lt;/ref&gt; Subsequently, the [[50th Indian Parachute Brigade]] was ordered to move to the Sangshak area, to take over the position vacated by the departure of the 49th.&lt;ref name=Rooney51/&gt; 

At the time, two battalions of the 50th Indian Parachute Brigade had been conducting advanced jungle training in the Kohima area,&lt;ref&gt;Allen 1984, p.652&lt;/ref&gt; while the third battalion completed its parachute training in India.&lt;ref name=Rooney51/&gt; The brigade consisted of 152 (Indian) and 153 (Gurkha) Parachute Battalions, with a machine gun company, a mountain artillery battery and other supporting arms. Its commander was Brigadier Maxwell Hope-Thompson. Even before the Japanese attack opened, they had received preliminary orders to move to Sangshak. Because of shortage of transport, they required four days (from 14 March to 18 March) to complete the movement. They took under command the 4th Battalion, [[5th Mahratta Light Infantry]], which had been part of the 49th Brigade,&lt;ref&gt;Allen 1984, pp.212–213&lt;/ref&gt; and two companies of the [[Nepal]]ese Kalibahadur Regiment consisting of 200 men.&lt;ref name=Seaman75&gt;Seaman 1989, p. 75&lt;/ref&gt; 

Upon arrival, the brigade found that the area they had been assigned had not been prepared by the 49th, and there was no barbed wire to construct field obstacles. Repeated requests were made for defensive stores by the 50th Brigade, but the demands were not met before the battle began.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, pp. 51–52&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===Preliminaries===
The 50th Brigade initially deployed over a large area, with outposts {{convert|8|mi|km}} east of Sangshak and the machine-gun company in Ukhrul. On 19 March, the Japanese overran an isolated company (C Company of the 152 Parachute Battalion) deployed on a hill known as Point 7378.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, pp. 52–52&lt;/ref&gt; The company was reduced to 20 men. Urged by his second-in-command (Colonel Abbott) that the brigade risked defeat in detail if it remained strung out as isolated posts, Hope-Thompson ordered his forces to concentrate. Most of the force initially concentrated at Sheldon's Corner, {{convert|8|mi|km}} east of Sangshak on 21 March, but that afternoon, Hope-Thomson pulled them back, first to "Kidney Camp" {{convert|4|mi|km}} to the west, and then to Sangshak itself, where they took up a defensive position on a hill just east of the village, with an American missionary church at its north end. The position measured only {{convert|800|yd|m}} by {{convert|400|yd|m}}, and had no fresh water. Hard rock was found only {{convert|3|ft|m}} below the soil, so only shallow trenches could be dug.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 1984, pp. 213–214&lt;/ref&gt;

The II Battalion of the Japanese 58th Infantry Regiment had meanwhile captured Ukhrul from 50th Brigade's machine-gun company. Major General Miyazaki was present with the battalion. He was aware that there was a British brigade at Sangshak. Although Sangshak was in the sector assigned to 31st Division's neighbouring formation, the [[15th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|Japanese 15th Division]], Miyazaki knew that this formation was lagging behind his force. He therefore decided to clear the British from Sangshak to prevent them interfering with his advance.&lt;ref name=Allen215&gt;Allen 1984, p.215&lt;/ref&gt;

===Fighting at Sangshak===
The Japanese battalion attacked Sangshak from the north on the night of 22 March. Miyazaki was prepared to wait for his regimental guns and some attached mountain guns to arrive to support the attack, but the battalion commander (Captain Nagaya) attacked hastily without artillery support. The British had a total of 46 mountain guns and 3-inch mortars with which to provide indirect fire support, and despite initial gains, the assaulting Japanese force suffered heavily from British artillery and mortar fire.&lt;ref name=Allen215/&gt;

One of the Japanese officers killed in the 50th Parachute Brigade's positions was found to be carrying vital maps and documents, which contained all of 31st Division's plans. Brigadier Hope-Thompson sent two copies of the documents through the encircling Japanese to IV Corps HQ in Imphal. These were to be vital to IV Corps' and Fourteenth Army's response to the Japanese attack on Kohima.&lt;ref name=Allen220&gt;Allen 1984, p.220&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 55&lt;/ref&gt;

The next day (23 March), Allied aircraft tried to drop supplies to the 50th Parachute Brigade, but the brigade's position was so small that many of the supplies went to the Japanese. The Gurkhas of 152 Parachute Battalion attacked to recover them, supported by fighters which had escorted the transport aircraft. They were beaten back, but the Japanese also suffered heavy casualties.&lt;ref name=Allen216&gt;Allen 1984, p.216&lt;/ref&gt; Japanese artillery was moved into position using elephants, and began firing on Sangshak on 23 March.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 54&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Seaman 1989, p. 81&lt;/ref&gt;

On 24 March, the Japanese were reinforced by the III Battalion of the 58th Regiment, accompanied by the regimental commander and Miyazaki. They attacked immediately, but they too were repulsed.&lt;ref name=Allen216/&gt;

The III Battalion of the Japanese 60th Regiment, belonging to [[Masafumi Yamauchi]]'s 15th Division, also began attacking the defended position from the east on 25 March, supported by artillery fire from two mountain guns from the 21st Field Artillery Regiment. Their commander (Major Fukushima) insisted that his officers properly reconnoitre the objective and plan their approach&lt;ref&gt;Allen 1984, p.217&lt;/ref&gt; in contrast to the 58th Regiment's hasty tactics. However, his infantry became lost trying to approach the position at night. During the following day, their two attached mountain guns destroyed many of the defenders' shallow trenches. On 26 March, Fukushima's infantry of the 60th Regiment again became lost trying to attack at night and were caught in the open at dawn.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 1984, p.218&lt;/ref&gt;

The Japanese planned a last all-out assault on 27 March (although Miyazaki tried to insist that 58th Regiment alone should attack, so that they would have the sole honour of the victory), but ultimately this effort was unnecessary.&lt;ref name=Allen219&gt;Allen 1984, p.219&lt;/ref&gt; By that date, the defenders were exhausted and desperately short of water. There were 300 wounded in the position, and the smell of decomposing bodies (including those of the mules belonging to the attached mountain artillery, and supply column) was unbearable.&lt;ref name=Allen216/&gt; At 6:00 pm on 26 March, Hope-Thompson received orders to withdraw. His brigade moved out under cover of darkness at 10.30 pm, with the 45th/5th Mahrattas providing a rearguard.&lt;ref name=Allen219/&gt; About 100 wounded were left behind, although many others were carried out.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 56&lt;/ref&gt;  About 100 other men were captured by another battalion of the Japanese 60th Regiment (the "Uchibori battalion").&lt;ref&gt;Allen 1984, p. 221.&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese subsequently occupied the position after a patrol confirmed that it had been abandoned.&lt;ref name=Allen219/&gt;

==Aftermath and results==
The 50th Indian Parachute Brigade had suffered 652 casualties.&lt;ref&gt;Singh 2014, p. 221&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese reported capturing 100 prisoners, most of whom were wounded. The Japanese also captured plenty of air-dropped supplies which had missed the defenders at Sangshak, and other equipment including heavy weapons, vehicles and radios.&lt;ref name=Allen220/&gt; Many of the Indian troops that were taken prisoner were later released – albeit having been stripped of their equipment and clothes – by the Japanese after they were forced to withdraw and were no longer able to spare troops to guard them.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 57&lt;/ref&gt;

Japanese casualties were also heavy. The II Battalion, 58th Regiment was the hardest-hit unit, with more than 400 casualties.&lt;ref name=Allen216/&gt; However, the prolonged battle had also delayed Miyazaki's advance on Kohima by a week, and heavily depleted the 58th Regiment which would lead the attack.&lt;ref name=Allen220/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 58&lt;/ref&gt; It also delayed some of the 15th Division in their advance on Imphal.&lt;ref name=Katoch37/&gt; Miyazaki's Left Assault Force had the shortest and easiest route to Kohima. They arrived at the vital Kohima ridge only on April 3,&lt;ref&gt;Allen 1984, p. 230&lt;/ref&gt; by which time Allied reinforcements had also reached the area.&lt;ref name=Allen220/&gt; In the ensuing [[Battle of Kohima]], the Japanese failed to capture the entire ridge, and were eventually forced to retreat by British counter-attacks and shortage of food and ammunition.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 103&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Allen 1984, p. 289&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Sources==
* Allen, Louis, ''Burma: The Longest War 1941–45'', J.M. Dent &amp; Sons Ltd, 1984, {{ISBN|0-460-02474-4}}
* Katoch, Hemant Singh, ''Imphal 1944: The Japanese Invasion of India'', Bloomsbury, 2018, {{ISBN|978-1-47282-016-7}}
* Rooney, David, ''Burma Victory: Imphal and Kohima March 1944 to May 1945'', Cassell, 1992, {{ISBN|0-304-35457-0}}
* Seaman, Harry, ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=U9uXAwAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA75&amp;dq=kali+bahadur+regiment&amp;hl=en&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwitzqOg2tngAhUjnOAKHTX8CM4Q6AEIKDAA#v=onepage&amp;q=kali%20bahadur%20regiment&amp;f=false The Battle At Sangshak: Prelude to Kohima]'', Pen and Sword, 1989, {{ISBN|978-1-47381-214-7}}
* Singh, Suresh, ''The Endless Kabaw Valley: British Created Vicious Cycle of Manipur, Burma and India'', Quills Ink Publishing, 2014, {{ISBN|978-9-38431-800-0}}

==Further reading==
* [[William Slim|Slim, William]] (Field Marshal Sir), ''[[Defeat into Victory]]'', NY: Buccaneer Books {{ISBN|1-56849-077-1}}, Cooper Square Press {{ISBN|0-8154-1022-0}}; London: Cassell {{ISBN|0-304-29114-5}}, Pan {{ISBN|0-330-39066-X}}.

{{coord missing|Manipur}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sangshak, Battle of}}
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Southeast Asia Theatre]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving India]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Nepal]]
[[Category:1944 in India]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]
[[Category:Military history of Burma during World War II]]
[[Category:March 1944 events]]</text><sha1>kj81ej5llua9dge27qn87tquqapgg5c</sha1></revision></page>