<page><title>Battle of Kohima</title><ns>0</ns><id>1002718</id><revision><id>964873329</id><parentid>957278495</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-28T02:44:01Z</timestamp><contributor><username>InternetArchiveBot</username><id>27015025</id></contributor><comment>Rescuing 2 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0.1</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="46843" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|1944 battle around Kohima, Nagaland, India}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=July 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Kohima
| partof      = [[Operation U-Go]] during the [[Burma Campaign 1944|Burma Campaign]] in the [[South-East Asian theatre of World War II]]
| image       = IND 003698 Garrison Hill Kohima.jpg
| image_size  = 300
| caption     = View of the Garrison Hill battlefield, the key to the British defences at Kohima
| date        = 4 April – 22 June 1944
| place       = [[Kohima]], [[Nagaland]], [[British Raj|British India]]
| coordinates = {{Coord|25.66639|94.10035|display=inline}}
| result      = Allied victory
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[United Kingdom]]
* {{flagicon|British Raj}} [[British Raj|India]]
* {{flagicon|Nepal|old}} [[Kingdom of Nepal|Nepal]]
| combatant2  = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan}} [[Empire of Japan|Japan]]
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Montagu Stopford|Sir Montagu Stopford]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Empire of Japan|army}} [[Kotoku Sato]]
| strength1   = '''Start''':&lt;br&gt;1 infantry brigade &lt;small&gt;(1,500)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;'''End''':&lt;br&gt;2 infantry divisions&lt;br&gt;1 ''Chindit'' brigade&lt;br&gt;1 motor brigade
| strength2   = 1 infantry division &lt;small&gt;(12,000–15,000)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref name=Allen228&gt;Allen 2000, p. 228.&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties1 = 4,064&lt;ref name=Allen643&gt;Allen 2000, p. 643.&lt;/ref&gt;
| casualties2 = 5,764–7,000&lt;ref name=Allen643/&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(mainly from starvation and disease)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, pp. 103–104.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 313–314.&lt;/ref&gt;
| campaignbox={{Campaignbox Burma}}
{{Campaignbox South-East Asia}}
}}

The '''Battle of Kohima''' was the turning point of the [[Imperial Japan|Japanese]] [[Operation U-Go|U-Go offensive]] into [[British Raj|India]] in 1944 during the [[World War II|Second World War]]. The battle was fought in three stages from 4 April to 22 June 1944 around the town of [[Kohima]], the capital of [[Nagaland]] in northeast India. From 3 to 16 April, the Japanese attempted to capture Kohima ridge, a feature which dominated the road by which the besieged [[British Army|British]] and [[British Indian Army|Indian]] troops of [[IV Corps (United Kingdom)|IV Corps]] at [[Imphal]] were supplied. By mid-April, the small British and Indian force at Kohima was relieved.

From 18 April to 13 May, British and Indian reinforcements counter-attacked to drive the Japanese from the positions they had captured. The Japanese abandoned the ridge at this point but continued to block the Kohima–Imphal road. From 16 May to 22 June, the British and Indian troops pursued the retreating Japanese and reopened the road. The battle ended on 22 June when British and Indian troops from Kohima and Imphal met at Milestone 109, ending the [[Battle of Imphal|Siege of Imphal]].

The battle is often referred to as the "''[[Battle of Stalingrad|Stalingrad]] of the East''".&lt;ref&gt;Dougherty 2008, p. 159.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Ritter 2017, p. 123&lt;/ref&gt; In 2013, the British [[National Army Museum]] voted the Battle of Imphal and Kohima to be "Britain's Greatest Battle".&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.nam.ac.uk/exhibitions/online-exhibitions/britains-greatest-battles |title=Britain's Greatest Battles |publisher=National Army Museum |accessdate=15 December 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Background==
The Japanese plan to invade India, codenamed [[Operation U-Go|U-Go]], was originally intended as a spoiling attack against the [[IV Corps (United Kingdom)|British IV Corps]] at [[Imphal]] in [[Manipur]], to disrupt the [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] offensive plans for that year. The commander of the [[Japanese Fifteenth Army]], [[Lieutenant General]] [[Renya Mutaguchi]], enlarged the plan to invade India itself and perhaps even overthrow the [[British Raj]].&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 154–155.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|According to Julian Thompson, "To this day [in 2009] there is disagreement on whether or not Mutaguchi intended to stop at Imphal. He favoured pressing on into India, and with help from uprisings by Indian nationalist in India, throwing the British out. ... all very highly speculative ... A possible indicator of Mutaguchi's aspirations [was the inclusion of the INA]. The INA was ineffective in battle so Mutaguch's motive for saddling himself with seven thousand useless mouths could only have been to use them for propaganda on arrival in India".&lt;ref&gt;Thompson 2010, p. 208.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}

If the Japanese were able to gain a strong foothold in India they would demonstrate the weakness of the British Empire and provide encouragement to Indian nationalists in their decolonization efforts.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 154&lt;/ref&gt; Moreover, occupation of the area around Imphal would severely impact American efforts to supply [[Chiang Kai-shek]]'s army in China.&lt;ref&gt;Keane 2010, p. 5&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.historynet.com/burma-campaign-seizing-imphal-and-kohima-in-world-war-ii.htm |title=Burma Campaign: Seizing Imphal and Kohima In World War II |work=HistoryNet |date=6 December 2006 |accessdate=17 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The objections of the staffs of various headquarters were eventually overcome, and the offensive was approved by [[Imperial General Headquarters]] on 7 January 1944.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp.166–167&lt;/ref&gt;

Part of the plan involved sending the [[IJA 31st Division|Japanese 31st Division]] (which was composed of 58th Regiment, 124th Regiment, 138th Regiment and 31st Mountain Artillery Regiment) to capture Kohima and thus cut off Imphal. Mutaguchi wished to exploit the capture of Kohima by pushing the 31st Division on to [[Dimapur]], the vital railhead and logistic base in the [[Brahmaputra River]] valley.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 285.&lt;/ref&gt;

The 31st Division's commander, Lieutenant General [[Kotoku Sato]], was unhappy with his role. He had not been involved in the planning of the offensive, and had grave misgivings about its chances. He had already told his staff that they might all starve to death.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 232.&lt;/ref&gt; In common with many senior Japanese officers, Sato considered Mutaguchi a "blockhead". He and Mutaguchi had also been on opposite sides during the split between the ''[[Toseiha]]'' and ''[[Kodoha]]'' factions within the Japanese Army during the early 1930s, and Sato believed he had reason to distrust Mutaguchi's motives.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 284–285.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==
[[File:Kohima.jpg|thumb|Imphal and Kohima campaign]]
Starting on 15 March 1944, the Japanese 31st Division crossed the [[Chindwin River]]&lt;ref name=Allen189&gt;Allen 2000, p. 189.&lt;/ref&gt; near [[Homalin]] and moved north-west along jungle trails on a front almost {{convert|60|mi|km}} wide. Although the march was arduous, good progress was made. The left wing of the division, consisting of the bulk of the 58th Regiment and commanded by the division's Infantry Group commander, [[Major General]] [[Shigesaburo Miyazaki]], was ahead of the neighbouring formation (the [[15th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|Japanese 15th Infantry Division]]) when they clashed with Indian troops covering the northern approaches to Imphal on 20 March.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 213.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Indian troops were the [[50th Indian Parachute Brigade]] under Brigadier Maxwell Hope-Thompson, at Sangshak.&lt;ref name=Allen189/&gt; Although they were not Miyazaki's objective, he decided to clear them from his line of advance. The [[Battle of Sangshak]] continued for six days. The parachute brigade's troops were desperately short of drinking water,&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 216.&lt;/ref&gt; but Miyazaki was handicapped by lack of artillery until near the end of the battle. Eventually, as some of the Japanese 15th Division's troops joined the battle, Hope-Thompson withdrew. The 50th Parachute Brigade lost 600 men, while the Japanese had suffered over 400 casualties. Miyazaki had also captured some of the food and munitions that had been dropped by the [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF) to the defenders of Sangshak. However, his troops, who had the shortest and easiest route to Kohima, were delayed by a week.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 212–220.&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, the commander of the [[Fourteenth Army (United Kingdom)|British Fourteenth Army]], Lieutenant General [[William Slim, 1st Viscount Slim|William Slim]], belatedly realised (partly from Japanese documents that had been captured at Sangshak) that a whole Japanese division was moving towards Kohima.&lt;ref name=Allen220&gt;Allen 2000, p. 220.&lt;/ref&gt; He and his staff had originally believed that, because of the forbidding terrain in the area, the Japanese would only be able to send a regiment to take Kohima.&lt;ref name=Allen228/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Slim 1956, p. 299.&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|A Japanese regiment was approximately 2,600 men, while a division varied between 12,000 to 22,000 men.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 654.&lt;/ref&gt;|group=Note}}

Slim knew that there were few fighting troops, as opposed to soldiers in line-of-communication units and supporting services, in Kohima and none at all at the vital base of Dimapur {{convert|30|mi|km}} to the north. Dimapur contained an area of supply dumps {{convert|11|mi|km}} long and {{convert|1|mi|km}} wide.&lt;ref name=Allen229&gt;Allen 2000, p. 229.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Hantzis 2017, Chapter 13.&lt;/ref&gt; As the fall of Dimapur would have been disastrous for the Allies, Slim asked his superior, General [[George Giffard]] (commanding [[Eleventh Army Group (United Kingdom)|Eleventh Army Group]]),&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 206.&lt;/ref&gt; for more troops to protect Dimapur and to prepare to relieve Imphal.&lt;ref&gt;Swinson 2015, Chapter 2.&lt;/ref&gt;

The Allies were already hastily reinforcing the Imphal Front.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 144.&lt;/ref&gt; As part of this move, the infantry and artillery of the [[5th Indian Infantry Division]] were flown from the [[Rakhine State|Arakan]], where they had just participated in the defeat of a subsidiary Japanese offensive at the [[Battle of the Admin Box]]. While the main body of the division went to Imphal (where some units had been isolated and almost all of IV Corps' reserves had already been committed), the [[161st Indian Infantry Brigade]], commanded by Brigadier Dermot Warren and with 24th Mountain Artillery Regiment, [[Royal Indian Artillery|Indian Artillery]] attached, were flown to Dimapur.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 229–230.&lt;/ref&gt;

Early in March, the [[23rd British Infantry Brigade|23rd Long Range Penetration Brigade]] was removed from Major General [[Orde Wingate]]'s [[Chindit]] force, and was dispatched by rail from around Lalaghat to [[Jorhat]], {{convert|50|mi|km}} north of Dimapur, where they could threaten the flank of any Japanese attack on the base. Giffard and General [[Claude Auchinleck]], the Commander-in-Chief of the [[British Indian Army]], also prepared to send the [[2nd Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|British 2nd Division]] and [[XXXIII Corps (British India)|Indian XXXIII Corps]] HQ under Lieutenant General [[Montagu George North Stopford|Montagu Stopford]] from reserve in southern and central India to Dimapur, by road and rail.&lt;ref name=Slim300&gt;Slim 1956, pp. 300–301.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/4C2B25FC-2E6C-45F9-B785-8A75139E9A0A/0/ww2_kohima.pdf|title=The Battle of Kohima, North-East India, 4 April&amp;nbsp;– 22 June 1944|year=2004|publisher=Ministry of Defence (UK)|accessdate=1 August 2009|pages=2–3|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090806001743/http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/4C2B25FC-2E6C-45F9-B785-8A75139E9A0A/0/ww2_kohima.pdf|archivedate=6 August 2009|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Until XXXIII Corps headquarters could arrive at Dimapur, the HQ of 202 Line of Communication Area under Major General R.P.L. Ranking took command of the area.&lt;ref name=Allen229&gt;Allen 2000, p. 229.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Slim300/&gt;

==Battle==
===Geography===
[[File:Kohima ridge.jpg|thumb|upright=1.2|Kohima Ridge]]
Kohima's strategic importance in the wider 1944 Japanese Chindwin offensive lay in that it was the summit of a pass that offered the Japanese the best route from Burma into India.&lt;ref name=Allen228/&gt; Through it ran the road which was the [[Main Supply Route|main supply route]] between the base at Dimapur in the Brahmaputra River valley and Imphal,&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 232–234.&lt;/ref&gt; where the British and Indian troops of IV Corps (consisting of the [[17th Indian Infantry Division|17th]], [[20th Indian Infantry Division|20th]] and [[23rd Indian Infantry Division]]s) faced the main Japanese offensive.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 229 &amp; 657.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fowler 2009, Chapter 8.&lt;/ref&gt;

Kohima Ridge itself runs roughly north and south.&lt;ref&gt;See map in Allen 2000, p. 231.&lt;/ref&gt; The road from Dimapur to Imphal climbs to its northern end and runs along its eastern face. In 1944, Kohima was the administrative centre of [[Nagaland]]. The [[Deputy Commissioner]] was [[Charles Pawsey]]. His bungalow stood on the hillside at a bend in the road, with its gardens and tennis court, and a clubhouse, on terraces above.&lt;ref name=Allen228&gt;Allen 2000, p. 228.&lt;/ref&gt; Although some terraces around the village were cleared for cultivation, the steep slopes of the ridge were densely forested.&lt;ref name=Allen228/&gt;

North of the ridge lay the densely inhabited area of ''Naga Village'', crowned by ''Treasury Hill'',&lt;ref name=Allen228/&gt; and ''Church Knoll'' (Baptist and other Christian missionaries had been active in Nagaland over the preceding half century). South and west of Kohima Ridge were ''GPT Ridge'' and the jungle-covered ''Aradura Spur''. The various British and Indian service troop encampments in the area gave their names to the features which were to be important in the battle e.g. "Field Supply Depot" became ''FSD Hill'' or merely ''FSD''.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, Map p. 74.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Fowler 2009, Chapter 9.&lt;/ref&gt; The Japanese later assigned their own code-names to the features; for example, ''Garrison Hill'' was known as ''Inu'' (dog) and ''Kuki Piquet'' as ''Saru'' (monkey).&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 267.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Siege===
Before the 161st Indian Brigade arrived, the only fighting troops in the Kohima area were the newly raised 1st Battalion, the [[Assam Regiment]] and a few platoons from the 3rd (Naga Hills) Battalion of the paramilitary [[Assam Rifles]].&lt;ref name=Allen228/&gt; Late in March 161st Brigade deployed in Kohima, but Major-General Ranking ordered them back to Dimapur, as it was felt initially that Dimapur had more strategic importance. Kohima was regarded as a roadblock, while Dimapur was the railhead where the majority of Allied supplies were stored.&lt;ref name=Allen229/&gt; Slim also feared that the Japanese might leave only a detachment to contain the garrison of Kohima while the main body of the 31st Division moved by tracks to the east to attack Dimapur.&lt;ref name=Slim306&gt;Slim 1956, p. 306.&lt;/ref&gt;

To Slim's relief, Sato concentrated on capturing Kohima. (Early in the siege, on 8 April, Mutaguchi directly ordered Sato to send a detachment to advance on Dimapur. Sato unwillingly dispatched a battalion of the 138th Regiment but a few hours later Mutaguchi's superior, Lieutenant General [[Masakasu Kawabe]] commanding [[Burma Area Army]], vetoed the move.)&lt;ref&gt;Dennis &amp; Lyman 2010, p. 51.&lt;/ref&gt;

As the right wing and centre of the Japanese 31st Division approached [[Jessami]], {{convert|30|mi|km}} to the east of Kohima, elements of the Assam Regiment fought delaying actions against them commencing on 1 April. Nevertheless, the men in the forward positions were soon overrun and the Assam regiment was ordered to withdraw. By the night of 3 April, Miyazaki's troops reached the outskirts of the Naga village and began probing Kohima from the south.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 230.&lt;/ref&gt;

Stopford's Corps HQ took over responsibility for the front from Ranking on 3 April.&lt;ref name=Slim306/&gt; The next day, he ordered the 161st Indian Brigade to move forward to Kohima again, but only one battalion, 4th Battalion [[Queen's Own Royal West Kent Regiment]] commanded by Lieutenant Colonel John Laverty, and a company of the 4th Battalion, [[7th Rajput Regiment]] arrived in Kohima before the Japanese cut the road west of the ridge. Besides these troops from 161st Brigade, the garrison consisted of a raw battalion (the Shere Regiment) from the [[Nepal Army|Royal Nepalese Army]], some companies from the [[Burma Regiment]], some of the Assam Regiment which had retired to Kohima and various detachments of convalescents and line-of-communication troops. The garrison numbered about 2,500, of which about 1,000 were non-combatants&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 234.&lt;/ref&gt; and was commanded by Colonel [[Hugh Richards]], who had served formerly with the Chindits.&lt;ref name=Allen227&gt;Allen 2000, p. 227.&lt;/ref&gt;

The siege began on 6 April. The garrison was continually shelled and mortared, in many instances by Japanese using weapons and ammunition captured at Sangshak and from other depots, and was slowly driven into a small perimeter on ''Garrison Hill''. They had artillery support from the main body of 161st Brigade, who were themselves cut off {{convert|2|mi|km}} away at [[Jotsoma]], but, as at Sangshak, they were very short of drinking water. The water supply point was on ''GPT Ridge'', which was captured by the Japanese on the first day of the siege. Some of its defenders were unable to retreat to other positions on the ridge and instead withdrew towards Dimapur. Canvas water tanks on ''FSD'' and at the Indian General Hospital had neither been filled nor dug in to protect them from fire. While a small spring was discovered on the north side of ''Garrison Hill'', it could be reached only at night.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 235.&lt;/ref&gt; The medical dressing stations were exposed to Japanese fire, and wounded men were often hit again as they waited for treatment.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 236.&lt;/ref&gt;

Some of the heaviest fighting took place at the north end of Kohima Ridge, around the Deputy Commissioner's bungalow and tennis court, in what became known as the [[Battle of the Tennis Court]]. The tennis court became a [[no man's land]], with the Japanese and the defenders of Kohima dug in on opposite sides, so close to each other that grenades were thrown between the trenches. The American historians Alan Millet and Williamson Murray wrote about the fighting at Kohima between the Japanese vs. the Anglo-Indian troops: "Nowhere in World War II – even on the Eastern Front – did the combatants fight with more mindless savagery".&lt;ref&gt;Millet &amp; Murray 2000, p. 350.&lt;/ref&gt;

On the night of 17/18 April, the Japanese finally captured the DC's bungalow area. Other Japanese captured ''Kuki Picquet'', cutting the garrison in two.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 237.&lt;/ref&gt; The defenders' situation was desperate, but the Japanese did not follow up by attacking ''Garrison Hill'' as by now they were exhausted by hunger and by the fighting, and when daylight broke, troops of 161st Indian Brigade arrived to relieve the garrison.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 237–238.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Millet &amp; Murray 2000, p. 350.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Relief===
The British 2nd Division, commanded by Major General [[John Grover (British Army officer)|John M. L. Grover]], had begun to arrive at Dimapur in early April. By 11 April, the Fourteenth Army had about the same number of troops in the area as the Japanese. The [[5th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|British 5th Brigade]] of the 2nd Division broke through Japanese roadblocks to relieve 161st Brigade in Jotsoma on 15 April. The [[6th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|British 6th Brigade]] took over 161st Brigade's defensive position (the "Jotsoma Box"), allowing the 161st Brigade with air, artillery and armour support to launch an attack towards Kohima on 18 April. After a day's heavy fighting, the leading troops of the Brigade (1st Battalion, [[1st Punjab Regiment]]) broke through and started to relieve the Kohima garrison.&lt;ref&gt;Slim 1956, pp. 316–317.&lt;/ref&gt; By this point, Kohima resembled a battlefield from the [[World War I|First World War]], with smashed trees, ruined buildings and the ground covered in craters.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis &amp; Lyman 2010, p.58&lt;/ref&gt;

Under cover of darkness, the wounded (numbering 300) were brought out under fire. Although contact had been established, it took a further 24 hours to fully secure the road between Jotsoma and Kohima. During 19 April and into the early hours of 20 April, the British 6th Brigade replaced the original garrison and at 06:00 hours on 20 April, the garrison commander (Colonel Richards) handed over command of the area.&lt;ref&gt;Slim 1956, p. 317.&lt;/ref&gt; 6th Brigade observers were taken aback by the condition of the garrison; one battle hardened officer commentated: "They looked like aged, bloodstained scarecrows, dropping with fatigue; the only clean thing about them was their weapons, and they smelt of blood, sweat and death."&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, p. 110.&lt;/ref&gt;

Miyazaki continued to try to capture ''Garrison Hill'', and there was heavy fighting for this position for several more nights, with high casualties on both sides. The Japanese positions on ''Kuki Picquet'' were only {{convert|50|yd|m}} from ''Garrison Hill'', and fighting was often hand-to-hand.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 267–269.&lt;/ref&gt; On the other flank of ''Garrison Hill'', on the night of 26/27 April, a British attack recaptured the clubhouse above the Deputy Commissioner's bungalow, which overlooked most of the Japanese centre.&lt;ref&gt;Slim 1956, p. 314.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Counter-offensive===
[[File:IND 003483 tennis court at Kohima.jpg|thumb|300px|The mined tennis court and terraces of the District Commissioner's bungalow in Kohima]]
[[File:Kohima Imphal Road Now.jpeg|thumb|300px|Historic Kohima Imphal road in 2013]]
The Japanese reorganised their forces for defence. Their Left Force under Miyazaki held Kohima Ridge with four battalions.&lt;ref name=Allen270&gt;Allen 2000, p. 270.&lt;/ref&gt; The divisional HQ under Sato himself and the Centre Force under Colonel Shiraishi held ''Naga Village'' with another four battalions.&lt;ref name="Allen 2000, p. 289"&gt;Allen 2000, p. 289.&lt;/ref&gt; The much smaller Right Force held villages to the north and east.&lt;ref name=Allen270/&gt;

To support their attack against the Japanese position, the British had amassed thirty-eight [[QF 3.7-inch mountain howitzer|3.7 Inch Mountain Howitzers]], forty-eight [[Ordnance QF 25-pounder|25-pounder field guns]] and two [[BL 5.5-inch Medium Gun|5.5 inch medium guns]].&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 272.&lt;/ref&gt; The RAF (chiefly [[Hawker Hurricane|Hurricane]] fighter-bombers of [[No. 34 Squadron RAF|34 Squadron]] and [[Vultee A-31 Vengeance|Vultee Vengeance]] dive-bombers of [[No. 84 Squadron RAF|84 Squadron]])&lt;ref&gt;Luto 2013, p. 3.&lt;/ref&gt; also bombed and strafed the Japanese positions. The Japanese could oppose them with only seventeen light mountain guns, with very little ammunition.&lt;ref name=Allen286&gt;Allen 2000, p. 286.&lt;/ref&gt; Nevertheless, the progress of the British counter-attack was slow. Tanks could not easily be used, and the Japanese occupied bunkers which were very deeply dug in, well-concealed and mutually supporting.&lt;ref&gt;Dennis &amp; Lyman 2010, pp. 80–82&lt;/ref&gt;

While the British 6th Brigade defended ''Garrison Hill'', the other two brigades of 2nd Division tried to outflank both ends of the Japanese position, in ''Naga Village'' to the north and on ''GPT Ridge'' to the south. The [[monsoon]] had broken by this time and the steep slopes were covered in mud, making movement and supply very difficult. In places the [[4th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|British 4th Brigade]] had to cut steps up hillsides and build handrails in order to make progress.&lt;ref&gt;Wilson, p. 115.&lt;/ref&gt; On 4 May, the British 5th Brigade secured a foothold in the outskirts of ''Naga Village'' but was counter-attacked and driven back.&lt;ref&gt;Slim 1956, p. 315.&lt;/ref&gt; On the same day, the British 4th Brigade, having made a long flank march around Mount Pulebadze to approach Kohima Ridge from the south-west, attacked ''GPT Ridge'' in driving rain and captured part of the ridge by surprise but were unable to secure the entire ridge.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 273–274.&lt;/ref&gt; Two successive commanders of British 4th Brigade were killed in the subsequent close-range fighting on the ridge.&lt;ref name=Allen274&gt;Allen 2000, p. 274.&lt;/ref&gt;

Both outflanking moves having failed because of the terrain and the weather, the British 2nd Division concentrated on attacking the Japanese positions along Kohima Ridge from 4 May onwards. Fire from Japanese posts on the reverse slope of ''GPT Ridge'' repeatedly caught British troops attacking ''Jail Hill'' in the flank, inflicting heavy casualties and preventing them from capturing the hill for a week. However, the various positions were slowly taken. ''Jail Hill'', together with ''Kuki Picquet'', ''FSD'' and ''DIS'', was finally captured by [[33rd Indian Infantry Brigade]] on 11 May, after a barrage of smoke shells blinded the Japanese machine-gunners and allowed the troops to secure the hill and dig in.&lt;ref&gt;Slim 1956, p. 316.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Dennis &amp; Lyman 2010, p. 82.&lt;/ref&gt;

The last Japanese positions on the ridge to be captured were the tennis court and gardens above the Deputy Commissioner's bungalow. On 13 May, after several failed attempts to outflank or storm the position, the British finally bulldozed a track to the summit above the position, up which a tank could be dragged. A [[M3 Lee|Lee tank]] crashed down onto the tennis court and destroyed the Japanese trenches and bunkers there. The 2nd Bn, the [[Dorsetshire Regiment]], followed up and captured the hillside where the bungalow formerly stood, thus finally clearing Kohima Ridge.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 272–273.&lt;/ref&gt; The terrain had been reduced to a fly and rat-infested wilderness, with half-buried human remains everywhere. The conditions under which the Japanese troops had lived and fought have been described by several sources, including author Frank McLynn, as "unspeakable".&lt;ref&gt;McLynn 2011, p. 316.&lt;/ref&gt;

The situation worsened for the Japanese as yet more Allied reinforcements arrived.&lt;ref name=Allen275&gt;Allen 2000, p. 275.&lt;/ref&gt; The 7th Indian Infantry Division, commanded by Major General [[Frank Messervy]], was arriving piecemeal by road and rail from the Arakan. Its 33rd Indian Brigade had already been released from XXXIII Corps reserve to join the fighting on Kohima Ridge on 4 May.&lt;ref name=Allen274/&gt; The [[114th Indian Infantry Brigade]] and the Division HQ arrived on 12 May and (with 161st Brigade under command) the division concentrated on recapturing the ''Naga Village'' from the north. The independent [[268th Indian Infantry Brigade]] was used to relieve the brigades of British 2nd Division and allow them to rest, before they resumed their drive southwards along the Imphal Road.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 275.&lt;/ref&gt;

Nevertheless, when the Allies launched another attack on 16 May, the Japanese continued to defend ''Naga Village'' and ''Aradura Spur'' tenaciously.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 274–275.&lt;/ref&gt; An attack on ''Naga Hill'' on the night of 24/25 May gained no ground.&lt;ref name=Lyman85&gt;Dennis &amp; Lyman, p.85&lt;/ref&gt; Another attack, mounted against both ends of ''Aradura Spur'' on the night of 28/29 May was even more decisively repulsed. The repeated setbacks, with exhaustion and the effects of the climate began to affect the morale of the British 2nd Division especially.&lt;ref name=Lyman85/&gt;

===Japanese retreat===
The decisive factor was the Japanese lack of supplies. The Japanese 31st Division had begun the operation with only three weeks' supply of food.&lt;ref name=Allen286/&gt; Once these supplies were exhausted, the Japanese had to exist on meagre captured stocks and what they could forage in increasingly hostile local villages. (Shortly before the siege of Kohima began, the Japanese had captured a huge warehouse in ''Naga Village'' with enough rice to feed the division "for three years", but it was immediately bombed and the stock of rice was destroyed.)&lt;ref&gt;Keane 2010, p. 238.&lt;/ref&gt; The British 23rd LRP Brigade, which had been operating behind the Japanese division, cut the Japanese supply lines and prevented them foraging in the Naga Hills to the east of Kohima. The Japanese had mounted two resupply missions, using captured [[jeep]]s to carry supplies forward from the Chindwin to 31st Division, but they brought mainly artillery and anti-tank ammunition, rather than food.&lt;ref name=Allen286/&gt;

By the middle of May, Sato's troops were starving. He considered that Mutaguchi and the HQ of Japanese Fifteenth Army were taking little notice of his situation, as they had issued several confusing and contradictory orders to him during April.&lt;ref name=Allen287&gt;Allen 2000, p. 287.&lt;/ref&gt; Because the main attack on Imphal faltered around the middle of April, Mutaguchi wished 31st Division or parts of it to join in the attack on Imphal from the north, even while the division was struggling to capture and hold Kohima. Sato considered that Fifteenth Army headquarters were issuing unrealistic orders to his division without proper planning or consideration for the conditions. Nor did he believe that they were exerting themselves to move supplies to his division.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 287–293.&lt;/ref&gt; He began considering pulling his troops back to allow for resupply.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 103.&lt;/ref&gt;

On 25 May, Sato notified Fifteenth Army HQ that he would withdraw on 1 June, unless his division received supplies.&lt;ref name="Allen 2000, p. 288"&gt;Allen 2000, p. 288.&lt;/ref&gt; Finally on 31 May, he abandoned ''Naga Village'' and other positions north of the road, in spite of orders from Mutaguchi to hang on to his position.&lt;ref name="Allen 2000, p. 289"/&gt; (For a divisional commander to retreat without orders or permission from his superior was unheard-of in the Japanese Army.)&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 292 (fn), p. 308.&lt;/ref&gt; This allowed XXXIII Corps to outflank Miyazaki's position on ''Aradura Spur'' and begin pushing south.&lt;ref&gt;Lyman 2010, p. 68.&lt;/ref&gt;

Miyazaki's detachment continued to fight rearguard actions and demolish bridges along the road to Imphal, but was eventually driven off the road and forced to retreat eastwards. The remainder of the Japanese division retreated painfully south but found very little to eat, as most of what few supplies had been brought forward across the Chindwin had been consumed by other Japanese units, who were as desperately hungry as Sato's men.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 290.&lt;/ref&gt; Many of the 31st Division were too enfeebled to drag themselves further south than [[Ukhrul]] (near the Sangshak battlefield), where hospitals had been set up, but with no medicines, medical staff or food, or Humine {{convert|20|mi|km}} south of Ukhrul, where Sato vainly hoped to find supplies.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 290–292.&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:IND 003495 link up at Imphal-Kohima MS109.jpg|thumb|300px|The link-up at Milestone 109 between the two arms of the 14th Army which relieved the Japanese siege of Imphal.]]
Indian XXXIII Corps followed up the retreating Japanese. The British 2nd Division advanced down the main road, while the 7th Indian Division (using mules and jeeps for most of its transport), moved through the rough terrain east of the road. On 22 June, the leading troops of British 2nd Division met the main body of 5th Indian Infantry Division advancing north from Imphal at Milestone 109, {{convert|30|mi|km}} south of Kohima.&lt;ref name=Allen295&gt;Allen 2000, p. 295.&lt;/ref&gt; The siege of Imphal was over, and truck convoys quickly carried vital heavy supplies to the troops at Imphal.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, pp. 104–105.&lt;/ref&gt;

During the Battle of Kohima, the British and Indian forces had lost 4,064 men, dead, missing and wounded.&lt;ref name=Allen643/&gt; Against this the Japanese had lost 5,764 battle casualties in the Kohima area,&lt;ref name=Allen643/&gt; and many of the 31st Division subsequently died of disease or starvation, or took their own lives.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, pp. 103–104.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 313–314.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
After ignoring army orders for several weeks, Sato was removed from command of Japanese 31st Division early in July. The entire Japanese offensive was broken off at the same time. Slim had always derided Sato as the most unenterprising of his opponents, and even recounted dissuading the RAF from bombing Sato's HQ because he wanted him kept alive, as doing so would help the Allied cause.&lt;ref&gt;Slim 1956, p. 311.&lt;/ref&gt; Japanese sources, however, blame his superior, Mutaguchi, for both the weaknesses of the original plan, and the antipathy between himself and Sato which led Sato to concentrate on saving his division rather than driving on distant objectives.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 285–287.&lt;/ref&gt;

After Sato was removed from command, he refused an invitation to commit [[seppuku]] and demanded a [[court martial]] to clear his name and make his complaints about Fifteenth Army HQ public. At Kawabe's prompting, Sato was declared to have suffered a mental breakdown and was unfit to stand trial.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 308–309.&lt;/ref&gt; He was replaced as commander of the 31st Division by Lieutenant General Tsuchitaro Kawada.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, p. 314.&lt;/ref&gt; Major General Miyazaki was promoted and appointed to command the [[54th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|Japanese 54th Division]], serving in Arakan.&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 513–514.&lt;/ref&gt;

The huge losses the Japanese suffered in the Battles of Imphal and Kohima (mainly through starvation and disease) crippled their defence of Burma against Allied attacks during the following year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwtwo/ff6_imphal.shtml |title=Defence of Imphal and Kohima |author=Robinson, Bruce |publisher=BBC |accessdate=10 October 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

On the Allied side, Major General Grover was dismissed from command of the British 2nd Division on 5 July, for perceived slowness in conducting the offensive, and also after complaints about his handling of Indian formations (161st and 33rd Indian Brigades) attached to his division, and replaced by Major General [[Cameron Nicholson]]. He accepted his dismissal stoically and was appointed Director of Army Welfare Services at the [[War Office]].&lt;ref&gt;Keane 2010, pp. 385–386.&lt;/ref&gt; Seventy years after the Battle of Kohima a memorial to him was unveiled at Jotsoma, the site of his 2nd Division Headquarters.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://www.nagalandpost.com/channelnews/state/StateNews.aspx?news=TkVXUzEwMDA1ODI1Nw%3D%3D |title=Major General John M.L. Grover's monument unveiled |newspaper=Nagaland Post |date=17 April 2014 |accessdate=10 October 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20160304080115/http://www.nagalandpost.com/channelnews/state/StateNews.aspx?news=TkVXUzEwMDA1ODI1Nw%3D%3D |archive-date=4 March 2016 |url-status=dead }}&lt;/ref&gt; Brigadier Dermot Warren, who commanded the 161st Indian Brigade during the siege,&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 200.&lt;/ref&gt; was promoted to command the 5th Indian Division,&lt;ref&gt;Brett-James 1951, Chapter XXV.&lt;/ref&gt; but was killed in an air crash the following year.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news |url=http://eresources.nlb.gov.sg/newspapers/Digitised/Article/syonantimes19450501-1.2.7 |title=Indian Division Chief Killed |newspaper=The Syonan Shimbun |date=1 May 1945 |page=1 |accessdate=17 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Aerial resupply===
The aerial resupply of Kohima was part of an effort that, at its height, delivered around 500 tons of supplies per day to Allied forces in the theatre.&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 63.&lt;/ref&gt; At the sieges of both Kohima and Imphal, the Allies relied entirely on resupply from the air by British and American aircraft&lt;ref name=Allen244&gt;Allen 2000, p. 244.&lt;/ref&gt; flying from India until the road from the railhead at Dimapur was cleared. At Kohima, due to the narrow ridgelines, accuracy in the dropping of air delivered [[logistics]] proved to be a considerable problem and as the fighting intensified and the defended area decreased, the task became harder and more dangerous.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/4C2B25FC-2E6C-45F9-B785-8A75139E9A0A/0/ww2_kohima.pdf|title=The Battle of Kohima, North-East India, 4 April&amp;nbsp;– 22 June 1944|year=2004|publisher=Ministry of Defence (UK)|accessdate=1 August 2009|page=9|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090806001743/http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/4C2B25FC-2E6C-45F9-B785-8A75139E9A0A/0/ww2_kohima.pdf|archivedate=6 August 2009|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In order to improve the accuracy of the drops, the Dakota pilots were forced to fly "dangerously low".&lt;ref&gt;Rooney 1992, p. 64.&lt;/ref&gt;

The increasing dominance of Allied airpower by this stage of the Burma campaign was a major factor in helping the Allies turn the tide of the war in this theatre. Allied air supply enabled British and Indian troops to hold out in positions that they might otherwise have had to abandon due to shortages of ammunition, food and water, as reinforcements and supplies could be brought in even when garrisons were surrounded and cut off.&lt;ref&gt;Brayley 2002, p. 10.&lt;/ref&gt; Conversely, the Japanese found their own supply situation harder to resolve and in the end it was one of the deciding factors in the battle.&lt;ref name="Allen 2000, p. 288"/&gt;

===Victoria Cross===
Two [[Victoria Cross]]es were awarded for actions during the Battle of Kohima:
* [[Lance Corporal]] [[John Pennington Harman]],&lt;ref&gt;Allen 2000, pp. 235–236.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=36574 |supp=y|page=2961|date=20 June 1944}}&lt;/ref&gt; 4th Battalion, [[Queen's Own Royal West Kent Regiment]], [[161st Indian Infantry Brigade]], [[5th Infantry Division (India)|5th Indian Infantry Division]]. During heavy fighting around "Detail Hill" (FSD?) during the siege, he single-handedly took out two Japanese machine gun posts, the first on 7/8 April and a second on 8/9 April.&lt;ref&gt;Keane 2010, pp. 265–269.&lt;/ref&gt; He was killed withdrawing from the second attack and was later awarded a posthumous Victoria Cross for these actions.&lt;ref&gt;Keane 2010, p. 359.&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Captain (British Army and Royal Marines)|Captain]] [[John Niel Randle]],&lt;ref name=LG&gt;{{London Gazette|issue=36833 |supp=y|page=5673|date=8 December 1944}}&lt;/ref&gt; 2nd Battalion, [[Royal Norfolk Regiment]], [[4th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|4th Infantry Brigade]], [[2nd Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|2nd British Infantry Division]].&lt;ref&gt;Ashcroft 2007, pp. 319–320.&lt;/ref&gt;

===Memorial===
[[File:Kohima War Cemetery, Kohima, Nagaland (89).jpeg|thumb|300px|When You Go Home, Tell Them Of Us And Say, For Your Tomorrow, We Gave Our Today]]

The [[War Cemetery in Kohima]] of 1,420 Allied war dead is maintained by the [[Commonwealth War Graves Commission]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.cwgc.org/find-a-cemetery/cemetery/2058100 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20100305025859/https://www.cwgc.org/search/cemetery_details.aspx?cemetery=2058100&amp;mode=1 |archivedate=5 March 2010 |title=Kohima War Cemetery |publisher=Commonwealth War Graves Commission |accessdate=17 December 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt; The cemetery lies on the slopes of Garrison Hill, in what was once the Deputy Commissioner's tennis court.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/4C2B25FC-2E6C-45F9-B785-8A75139E9A0A/0/ww2_kohima.pdf|title=The Battle of Kohima, North-East India, 4 April&amp;nbsp;– 22 June 1944|year=2004|publisher=Ministry of Defence (UK)|accessdate=1 August 2009|page=17|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090806001743/http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/4C2B25FC-2E6C-45F9-B785-8A75139E9A0A/0/ww2_kohima.pdf|archivedate=6 August 2009|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}.&lt;/ref&gt; The [[epitaph]] carved on the memorial of the 2nd British Division in the cemetery has become world-famous as the Kohima Epitaph. It reads:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |url=http://www.worcestershireregiment.com/wr.php?main=inc/burma_Worc_Regt |title=Burma 1944&amp;nbsp;– 1945|publisher=Worcestershire Regiment website |accessdate=1 February 2012}} (Includes a photograph).&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=Burma-Star-epitaph&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.burmastar.org.uk/epitaph.htm|title=The Kohima 2nd Division Memorial|publisher=www.burmastar.org.uk|accessdate=1 August 2009|url-status=dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150510152752/http://www.burmastar.org.uk/epitaph.htm|archivedate=10 May 2015|df=dmy-all}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{cquote|When you go home, tell them of us and say,&lt;br&gt;For your tomorrow, we gave our today}}

The verse is attributed to [[John Maxwell Edmonds]] (1875–1958), and is thought to have been inspired by [[Battle of Thermopylae#Epitaph of Simonides|the epitaph]] written by [[Simonides of Ceos|Simonides]] to honour the Spartans who fell at the [[Battle of Thermopylae]] in 480 BC.&lt;ref name=Burma-Star-epitaph/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |author=[[Imperial War Museum]] |url=http://archive.iwm.org.uk/server/show/ConWebDoc.1261 |title=What is the Kohima Epitaph? |work=archive.iwm.org.uk |accessdate=4 April 2013 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20141230155628/http://archive.iwm.org.uk/server/show/ConWebDoc.1261 |archive-date=30 December 2014 |url-status=dead |df=dmy-all }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Bibliography==
* {{Cite book |last=Allen |first=Louis |year=2000 |origyear=1984 |title=Burma: The Longest War 1941–45 |publisher=Phoenix Press |location=London |isbn=1-84212-260-6}}
* {{cite book |last=Ashcroft |first=Michael |year=2007 |title=Victoria Cross Heroes |publisher=Headline Review |location=London |isbn=978-0-7553-1633-5}}
* {{Cite book |last=Brayley |first=Martin |year=2002 |title=The British Army 1939–45 (3): The Far East |publisher=Osprey Publishing |location=London |isbn=1-84176-238-5}}
* {{Cite book |last=Brett-James |first=Antony |year=1951 |url=http://ourstory.info/library/4-ww2/Ball/fireTC.html#TC |title=Ball of Fire: The Fifth Indian Division in the Second World War |publisher=[[Gale &amp; Polden]] |location=Aldershot |oclc=4275700 |access-date=10 October 2017 |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20200327021347/http://www.ourstory.info/library/4-ww2/Ball/fireTC.html#TC |archive-date=27 March 2020 |url-status=dead }}
* {{cite book |last1=Dennis |first1=Peter |last2=Lyman |first2=Robert |year=2010 |title=Kohima 1944: The Battle That Saved India|publisher=Osprey |isbn=978-1-84603-939-3 }}
* {{cite book |last=Dougherty |first=Martin J. |year=2008|title=Land Warfare |publisher=Thunder Bay Press |isbn= 978-1-59223-829-3}}
* {{cite book |last=Fowler |first=William |title=We Gave Our Today: Burma 1941–1945 |year=2009 |publisher=Hachette |isbn=978-0-29785-761-7}}
* {{cite book |last=Hantzis |first=Steven James |title=Rails of War: Supplying the Americans and Their Allies in China-Burma-India |year=2017 |publisher=University of Nebraska Press |location=Lincoln |isbn=978-1-61234-937-4 }}
* {{Cite book |last=Keane |first=Fergal |authorlink=Fergal Keane |year=2010 |title=Road of Bones: The Siege of Kohima 1944 |publisher=HarperPress |location=London |isbn=978-0-00-713240-9}}
* {{cite book| last=Luto| first=James| title=Fighting with the Fourteenth Army in Burma| publisher=Pen and Sword Military| year=2013| isbn=978-1-78303-031-6}}
* {{cite book |first=Frank |last=McLynn |year=2011 |title=The Burma Campaign: Disaster Into Triumph, 1942-45 |publisher=Yale University Press |location=New Haven |isbn= 978-0-30017-162-4}}
* {{cite book |last1=Murray |first1=Williamson  | last2=Millet |first2=Alan| year=2000 |title=A War To Be Won |url=https://archive.org/details/wartobewonfighti00murr_1 |url-access=registration |publisher=Harvard |location=Cambridge (US) |isbn=0-674-00163-X}}
* {{cite book |last=Ritter |first=Jonathan Templin |title=Stillwell and Mountbatten in Burma: Allies at War, 1943–1944 |year=2017 |publisher=University of North Texas |isbn=978-1-57441-674-9}}
* {{cite book |last=Rooney |first=David |title=Burma Victory: Imphal and Kohima, March 1944 to May 1945 |year=1992 |publisher=Cassell |location=London |isbn= 0-304-35457-0}}
* {{Cite book |last=Slim |first=William |authorlink=William Slim |year=1956 |title=[[Defeat into Victory]]  |publisher=Cassell |location=London |oclc=  891162827}}
* {{cite book |last=Swinson |first=Arthur |title=Kohima |origyear=1966 |year=2015 |publisher=Head of Zeus |isbn=978-1-78408-177-5}}
* {{Cite book |last=Thompson | first=Julian |year=2010 |title=Forgotten Voices of Burma: The Second World War's Forgotten Conflict |series=Forgotten Voices |edition=illustrated, reprint |publisher=Random House |isbn=0091932378 |url=https://books.google.com/books?id=7zSHCkljO7wC&amp;lpg=PP1&amp;pg=PA208#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false}}
* {{cite book |last=Wilson |first=David |title=The Sum of Things |year=2001 |publisher=Spellmount |location=Staplehurst |isbn= 1-86227-134-8}}

==Further reading==
* {{Cite book|last=Colvin|first=John|title=Not Ordinary Men: The Story of the Battle of Kohima |publisher = Leo Cooper|year=2012|isbn =9781848848719 |OCLC=793214121}}
* {{Cite book |last=Edwards |first=Leslie |year=2009 |title=Kohima: The Furthest Battle |publisher=[[The History Press]]|location=|isbn=978-1-86227-488-4}}
* {{Cite book |last=Graham |first=Gordon |year=2005 |title=The Trees Are All Young on Garrison Hill |publisher=The Kohima Educational Trust |location=Marlow, Buckinghamshire |isbn=0-9552687-0-2}}
* {{Cite book |last=Karnad |first=Raghu |authorlink=Karnad Raghu |year=2015 |title=Farthest Field: An Indian Story of the Second World War |publisher=W.W. Norton &amp; Company Ltd. |location=New York, N.Y |isbn=978-0-393-24809-8}}

==External links==
* [http://www.kohimamuseum.com The Kohima Museum]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20191031105647/http://ourstory.info/library/4-ww2/Ball/fire13.html Ball of Fire: 5th Indian Division in World War II, by Anthony Brett-James]
* [http://www.freewebs.com/masonictalks/myfathertomhope.htm Tom Hope (a Wearside man) recalls horrors of the brutal Battle of Kohima]
* [http://www.freewebs.com/masonictalks/myfathertomhope.htm&amp;nbsp;– With the Durham Light Infantry 25 years ago]
* {{Cite web|url=http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/4C2B25FC-2E6C-45F9-B785-8A75139E9A0A/0/ww2_kohima.pdf|title=The Battle of Kohima, North-East India, 4 April&amp;nbsp;– 22 June 1944|year=2004|publisher=Ministry of Defence (UK)|accessdate=1 August 2009|page=4|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20090806001743/http://www.mod.uk/NR/rdonlyres/4C2B25FC-2E6C-45F9-B785-8A75139E9A0A/0/ww2_kohima.pdf|archivedate=6 August 2009|url-status=dead|df=dmy-all}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kohima, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1944]]
[[Category:1944 in India]]
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Southeast Asia Theatre]]
[[Category:Military history of Burma during World War II]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving India]]
[[Category:Indian National Army]]
[[Category:Kohima]]
[[Category:History of Nagaland]]
[[Category:Land battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Japan]]
[[Category:India–Japan military relations]]
[[Category:April 1944 events]]
[[Category:May 1944 events]]
[[Category:June 1944 events]]</text><sha1>c9jd7x028qjgcs7dnr5agu2pkgvpouj</sha1></revision></page>