<page><title>Attack on Mers-el-Kébir</title><ns>0</ns><id>632450</id><revision><id>967384463</id><parentid>967363424</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-12T23:36:14Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Mathglot</username><id>2544398</id></contributor><comment>Undid [[WP:AGF|good faith]] revision 967363424 by [[Special:Contributions/2602:306:CFEA:170:103E:CE30:DDF9:60F1|2602:306:CFEA:170:103E:CE30:DDF9:60F1]] ([[User talk:2602:306:CFEA:170:103E:CE30:DDF9:60F1|talk]]) The change in positioning of the armistice link is arguably okay. "The French" is understood to mean the government, when talking about relations with "allies". But "grammar" has nothing to do with the name, which is overwhelmingly "[[French Third Republic]]" in English sources.</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="36593" xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=September 2019}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=October 2013}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Attack on Mers-el-Kébir
| image       = File:Croiseur de bataille Strasbourg 03-07-1940.jpg
| image_size  = 250px
| caption     = The battleship [[French battleship Strasbourg|''Strasbourg'']] under fire
| partof      = the [[Battle of the Mediterranean]] during the [[Second World War]]
| date        = 3 July 1940
| place       = Off [[Mers El Kébir]], [[French Algeria]], [[North Africa]]
| coordinates = {{Coord|35|43|10|N|0|41|20|W|type:landmark_scale:50000_region:DZ|display=inline}}
| result      = British victory&lt;!--See [[Template:Infobox military conflict]] for allowed terms here, "X victory" or "Inconclusive" only --&gt;
| combatant1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[United Kingdom]]
| combatant2  = {{flagicon|France|1830}} [[French Third Republic|France]]
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[James Somerville]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Dudley Pound]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|France|1830}} [[Marcel-Bruno Gensoul]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flagicon|France|1830}} [[François Darlan]]
| strength1   = 1 [[aircraft carrier]]&lt;br /&gt;2 [[battleship]]s&lt;br /&gt;1 [[battlecruiser]]&lt;br /&gt;2 [[light cruiser]]s&lt;br /&gt;11 [[destroyer]]s
| strength2   = 4 battleships&lt;br /&gt;5 destroyers&lt;br /&gt;1 seaplane tender
| casualties1 = 2 killed&lt;br /&gt;6 aircraft destroyed
| casualties2 = 1,297 killed&lt;br /&gt;350 wounded&lt;br /&gt;1 battleship sunk&lt;br /&gt;2 battleships damaged&lt;br /&gt;2 destroyers damaged&lt;br /&gt;1 seaplane tender damaged&lt;br /&gt;1 destroyer grounded&lt;br /&gt;1 tugboat destroyed{{sfn|Playfair|1959|p=137}}
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Mediterranean Campaign}}
{{Campaignbox Vichy France Military in World War II}}
}}
The '''Attack on Mers-el-Kébir''' (Battle of Mers-el-Kébir) on 3 July 1940, during the [[Second World War]] was, a British naval attack on [[French Navy]] ships at the naval base at [[Mers El Kébir]], at [[Oran]], on the coast of [[French rule in Algeria|French Algeria]]. The attack was part of Operation Catapult, a British plan to neutralise or destroy French ships to prevent them falling into German hands in the aftermath of the Allied defeat in the [[Battle of France]]. The British bombardment of the base killed 1,297 French servicemen, sank a [[battleship]] and damaged five other ships, for a British loss of five aircraft shot down and two crewmen killed.

The attack by air and sea was conducted by the [[Royal Navy]], after France had signed armistices with [[Nazi Germany|Germany]] and [[Kingdom of Italy|Italy]], coming into effect on 25 June. Of particular significance to the British were the five battleships of the {{Ship|French battleship|Bretagne||2}} and {{Ship|French battleship|Richelieu||2}} classes and the two [[fast battleship]]s of the {{Ship|French battleship|Dunkerque||2}} class, the second largest force of [[capital ships]] in Europe after the Royal Navy. The British [[Churchill war ministry|War Cabinet]] feared that the ships would fall into Axis hands. Admiral [[François Darlan]], commander of the French Navy, assured the British that the fleet would remain under French control but [[Winston Churchill]] and the War Cabinet judged that the risk was too great.

The French thought they were acting honourably towards their former ally in terms of their [[Armistice of 22 June 1940|armistices]] with Germany and Italy. The British attack was almost universally condemned in France and resentment festered for years over what was considered a betrayal by their former ally. Marshal [[Philippe Pétain]], who was appointed the prime minister of France on 16 June, [[Foreign relations of Vichy France|severed diplomatic relations]] with the [[United Kingdom]] on 8 July. The next day, deputies of the [[National Assembly (France)|National Assembly]] met at [[Vichy]] and voted to revise the constitution, bringing the [[French Third Republic]] to an end and Pétain was installed with full powers as leader of the new [[Vichy France|French State]]. 

French aircraft retaliated by [[Military history of Gibraltar during World War II#Vichy French attacks: 1940|bombing Gibraltar]] several times and French ships exchanged fire several times with British ships, before a [[wikt:tacit|tacit]] truce was observed in the western Mediterranean. On 27 November 1942, after the beginning of [[Operation Torch]], the Allied invasion of French North Africa, the French navy foiled [[Case Anton]], a German and Italian operation to capture the rest of the French fleet at Toulon by the [[scuttling of the French fleet in Toulon|scuttling]] of the ships. The British attack at Mers-el Kébir remains controversial but some historians have written that it demonstrated to the world that Britain would fight on.{{sfn|Thomas|1997|pp=643–670}}

==Background==

===French–German armistice===

{{main|Armistice of 22 June 1940}}

After the [[Fall of France]] in 1940 and the armistice between France and [[Nazi Germany]], the British War Cabinet was apprehensive about control over the French navy. The French and German navies combined could alter the balance of power at sea, threatening British imports over the Atlantic and communications with the rest of the [[British Empire]]. In Article 8, Paragraph 2 of the Armistice terms, the German government "solemnly and firmly declared that it had no intention of making demands regarding the French fleet during the peace negotiations" and there were similar terms in the armistice with Italy but they were considered by the British to be no guarantee of the neutralisation of the French fleet. On 24 June, Darlan assured [[Winston Churchill]] against such a possibility.{{sfn|Butler|1971|p=218}} Churchill ordered that a demand be made that the [[French Navy]] ({{lang|fr|Marine nationale}}) should either join with the [[Royal Navy]] or be neutralised in a manner guaranteed to prevent the ships falling into Axis hands.{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|2002|p=57}}

At Italian suggestion, the armistice terms were amended to permit the French fleet temporarily to stay in North African ports, where they might be seized by Italian troops from Libya. The British made a contingency plan, Operation Catapult, to eliminate the French fleet in mid-June, when it was clear that [[Philippe Pétain]] was forming a government with a view to ending the war and it seemed likely that the French fleet might be seized by the Germans.{{sfn|Lacouture|1991|pp=246–247}} In a speech to Parliament, Churchill repeated that the [[Armistice of 22 June 1940]] was a betrayal of the Allied agreement not to make a separate peace. Churchill said, "What is the value of that? Ask half a dozen countries; what is the value of such a solemn assurance?... Finally, the armistice could be voided at any time on any pretext of non-observance...".&lt;ref&gt;Hansard, [http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1940/jun/25/war-situation ''War Situation''], 25 June 1940, [http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1940/jun/25/war-situation#column_304 304–05]&lt;/ref&gt;

The French fleet had seen little fighting during the Battle of France and was mostly intact. By tonnage, about 40 per cent was in [[Toulon]], near [[Marseilles]], 40 per cent in [[French North Africa]] and 20 per cent in Britain, [[Alexandria]] and the [[French West Indies]]. Although Churchill feared the fleet would be used by the Axis, Hitler and Mussolini did not intend to employ a combined Franco–Italian–German force. The {{lang|de|Kriegsmarine}} and [[Benito Mussolini]] made overtures but [[Adolf Hitler]] feared that an attempted take-over would provoke the French fleet into defecting to the British. Churchill and Hitler viewed the fleet as a potential threat; the French leaders used the fleet (and the possibility of its rejoining the Allies) as a bargaining counter against the Germans to keep them out of unoccupied France ({{lang|fr|[[zone libre]]}}) and French North Africa. The armistice was contingent on the French right to man their vessels and the French Navy Minister, Admiral [[François Darlan]], had ordered the Atlantic fleet to Toulon to demobilise, with orders to [[scuttling|scuttle]] the ships if the Germans tried to take them.{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|2002|p=56}}

===British–French negotiations===
The British tried to persuade the French authorities in North Africa to continue the war or to hand over the fleet to British control. A British admiral visited Oran on 24 June, and [[Duff Cooper]], [[Minister of Information]], visited Casablanca on 27 June.{{sfn|Lacouture|1991|p=247}} The French Atlantic ports were in German hands and the British needed to keep the German surface fleet out of the Mediterranean, confine the Italian fleet to the Mediterranean and to blockade ports still under French control. The Admiralty was against an attack on the French fleet in case the ships were not sufficiently damaged, France declared war and the French colonies would be less likely to defect. The Royal Navy lacked the ships permanently to blockade the French naval bases in North Africa and keep the Atlantic approaches open, which made the risk of the Germans or the Italians seizing the French capital ships too great. Because the fleet in Toulon was well guarded by shore artillery, the Royal Navy decided to attack the base in North Africa.{{sfn|Bell|1997|pp=19–20}}

==Ultimatum==
[[File:French-ships-africa.png|thumb|upright=.75|{{centre|French ships based in Africa, June 1940}}]]
The most powerful group of French warships was at [[Mers-el-Kébir]] in [[French Algeria]], comprising the old battleships {{Ship|French battleship|Provence||2}} and {{Ship|French battleship|Bretagne||2}}, the newer ''[[Force de Raid]]'' battleships {{Ship|French battleship|Dunkerque||2}} and {{Ship|French battleship|Strasbourg||2}}, the [[seaplane tender]] {{Ship|French seaplane carrier|Commandant Teste||2}}, six destroyers and a gunboat, under the command of Admiral [[Marcel-Bruno Gensoul]]. Admiral [[James Somerville (admiral)|James Somerville]], commander of [[Force H]], based in [[Gibraltar]], was ordered to deliver an ultimatum to the French, the terms of which were contrary to the German-French armistice.{{sfn|Lacouture|1991|p=247}}{{efn|{{quote|It is impossible for us, your comrades up to now, to allow your fine ships to fall into the power of the German enemy. We are determined to fight on until the end, and if we win, as we think we shall, we shall never forget that France was our Ally, that our interests are the same as hers, and that our common enemy is Germany. Should we conquer we solemnly declare that we shall restore the greatness and territory of France. For this purpose we must make sure that the best ships of the French Navy are not used against us by the common foe. In these circumstances, His Majesty's Government have instructed me to demand that the French Fleet now at Mers el Kebir and [[Oran]] shall act in accordance with one of the following alternatives;

(a) Sail with us and continue the fight until victory against the Germans.

(b) Sail with reduced crews under our control to a British port. The reduced crews would be repatriated at the earliest moment.

If either of these courses is adopted by you we will restore your ships to France at the conclusion of the war or pay full compensation if they are damaged meanwhile.

(c) Alternatively, if you feel bound to stipulate that your ships should not be used against the Germans lest they break the [[Armistice with France (Second Compiègne)|Armistice]], then sail them with us with reduced crews to some French port in the [[West Indies]]—[[Martinique]] for instance—where they can be demilitarised to our satisfaction, or perhaps be entrusted to the United States and remain safe until the end of the war, the crews being repatriated.

If you refuse these fair offers, I must with profound regret, require you to sink your ships within 6 hours.
Finally, failing the above, I have orders from His Majesty's Government to use whatever force may be necessary to prevent your ships from falling into German or Italian hands.|Somerville{{sfn|Butler|1971|pp=223–224}}}}}} Somerville passed the duty of presenting the ultimatum to a French speaker, Captain [[Cedric Holland]], commander of the carrier {{HMS|Ark Royal|91|6}}. Gensoul was affronted that negotiations were not being conducted by a senior officer and sent his lieutenant, Bernard Dufay, which led to much delay and confusion. As negotiations dragged on, it became clear that neither side was likely to give way. Darlan was at home on 3 July and could not be contacted; Gensoul told the French government that the alternatives were internment or battle but omitted the option of sailing to the French West Indies.{{sfn|Lacouture|1991|p=247}} Removing the fleet to United States waters had formed part of the orders given by Darlan to Gensoul in the event that a foreign power should attempt to seize his ships.{{sfn|Butler|1971|pp=224–225}}

==Operation Catapult==

===Plymouth and Alexandria===

[[File:HMS Ark Royal planes.jpg|thumb|left|{{centre|[[Blackburn Skuas]] of [[800 Naval Air Squadron|No 800 Squadron Fleet Air Arm]] prepare to take off from HMS ''Ark Royal''}}]]
Along with French vessels in metropolitan ports, some had sailed to ports in Britain or to Alexandria in [[Kingdom of Egypt|Egypt]]. Operation Catapult was an attempt to take these ships under British control or destroy them and the French ships in [[Plymouth]] and [[Portsmouth]] were boarded without warning on the night of 3 July 1940.{{sfn|Butler|1971|p=222}}{{sfn|Roskill|1957|pp=240, 242}} The submarine {{Ship|French submarine|Surcouf||2}}, the largest in the world, had been berthed in Plymouth since June 1940.{{sfn|Smith|2010|p=48}} The crew resisted a boarding party and three Royal Navy personnel, including two officers, were killed along with a French sailor. Other ships captured included the old [[battleship]]s {{Ship|French battleship|Paris||2}} and {{Ship|French battleship|Courbet|1911|2}}, the [[destroyer]]s {{ship|French destroyer|Le Triomphant||2}} and {{ship|French destroyer|Léopard||2}}, eight [[torpedo boat]]s, five submarines and a number of lesser ships. The French squadron in Alexandria (Admiral [[René-Émile Godfroy]]) including the battleship ''Lorraine'', heavy cruiser ''Suffren'' and three modern light cruisers, was neutralised by local agreement.{{sfn|Smith|2010|pp=47–56, 93}}

===Attack on Mers-el-Kébir===

[[File:Attack on Mers-el-Kébir harbor-EN.svg|thumb|{{centre|Diagram of the British attack on Mers-el-Kébir}}]]
The British force comprised the [[battlecruiser]] {{HMS|Hood|51|6}}, the battleships {{HMS|Valiant|1914|6}} and {{HMS|Resolution|09|2}}, the aircraft carrier ''Ark Royal'' and an escort of cruisers and destroyers. The British had the advantage of being able to manoeuvre, while the French fleet was anchored in a narrow harbour and its crews did not expect an attack. The main armament of ''Dunkerque'' and ''Strasbourg'' was grouped on their bows and could not immediately be brought to bear. The British capital ships had {{convert|15|in|mm|0|abbr=on}} guns and fired a heavier [[broadside]] than the French battleships. On 3 July, before negotiations were formally terminated, British [[Fairey Swordfish]] planes escorted by [[Blackburn Skua]]s from ''Ark Royal'' dropped magnetic mines in the harbour exit. The force was intercepted by French [[Curtiss H-75]] fighters and a Skua was shot down into the sea with the loss of its two crew, the only British fatalities in the action.{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|2002|p=61}} French warships were ordered from [[Algiers]] and Toulon as reinforcements but did not reach Mers-El-Kebir in time.{{sfn|Lacouture|1991|p=247}} At {{nowrap|5:54 p.m.,}} Churchill ordered the British ships to open fire and the British commenced from {{cvt|17500|yd|mi+km}}.{{sfn|Brown|2004|p=198}} The third British salvo scored hits and a magazine aboard ''Bretagne'' exploded, the ship sinking with 977 of her crew at {{nowrap|6:09 p.m.}} After thirty salvoes, the French ships stopped firing; the British force altered course to avoid return fire from the French coastal forts but ''Provence'', ''Dunkerque,'' the destroyer {{Ship|French destroyer|Mogador||2}} and two other destroyers were damaged and run aground by their crews.{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|2002|pp=58–59}} 

[[File:Cuirassé Bretagne 03-07-1940.jpg|thumb|{{centre|Battleship [[French battleship Bretagne|''Bretagne'']] on fire, still under bombardment}}]]
''Strasbourg'', three destroyers and one gunboat managed to avoid the magnetic mines and escape to the open sea under attack from a flight of bomb-armed Swordfish from ''Ark Royal''. The French ships responded with anti-aircraft fire and shot down two Swordfish, the crews being rescued by the destroyer {{HMS|Wrestler|D35|6}}. As the bombing had little effect, at {{nowrap|6:43 p.m.}} Somerville ordered his forces to pursue and the light cruisers {{HMS|Arethusa|26|6}} and {{HMS|Enterprise|D52|2}} engaged a French gunboat. At {{nowrap|8:20 p.m.}} Somerville called off the pursuit, feeling that his ships were ill-deployed for a night engagement. After another ineffective Swordfish attack at {{nowrap|8:55 p.m.,}} ''Strasbourg'' reached Toulon on 4 July.{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|2002|pp=59–60}} The French {{lang|fr|[[aviso]]}} ([[gunboat]]) {{Ship|French aviso|Rigault de Genouilly||2}}, en route to Oran, met Force H at {{nowrap|7:33 p.m.}} and sailed towards ''Hood'', only to be fired on by ''Arethusa'' and ''Enterprise'' at {{cvt|12000|and|18000|yd|nmi+mi+km}} respectively, along with several {{cvt|15|in|mm}} shells from ''Hood'', against which the French ship fired nineteen {{cvt|5.45|in|mm}} shells before being hit by ''Enterprise''. On the next day, the British submarine {{HMS|Pandora|N42|6}} encountered the ship off the Algerian coast, mistook it for a cruiser and sank it.{{sfn|O'Hara|2009|p=24}} The [[French Air Force]] ({{lang|fr|Armée de l'Air}}) made reprisal raids on Gibraltar, including a half-hearted night attack on 5 July, when many bombs landed in the sea.{{sfn|Playfair|1959|p=142}}{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|2002|pp=94–95}} 

===Actions of 8 July===

The British believed that the damage inflicted on ''Dunkerque'' and ''Provence'' was not serious and raided Mers-el-Kébir again on the morning of 8 July, with Swordfish aircraft from ''Ark Royal''. A [[torpedo]] hit the patrol boat ''Terre-Neuve'', moored alongside ''Dunkerque'', full of [[depth charge]]s. ''Terre-Neuve'' quickly sank and the depth charges went off, causing serious damage to ''Dunkerque''.{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|2002|pp=60–61}} The last part of Operation Catapult was another attack on 8 July, by aircraft from the carrier {{HMS|Hermes|95|6}} against the battleship [[French battleship Richelieu#British attack on 8 July 1940|''Richelieu'']] at [[Dakar]]; the battleship was seriously damaged.{{sfn|Playfair|1959|p=142}}{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|2002|pp=94–95}}

==Aftermath==

===Analysis===

[[File:Mogador 03-07-1940.jpg|thumb|{{centre|The French destroyer [[French destroyer Mogador|''Mogador'']] running aground, after having been hit by a 15-inch shell.}}]]
Churchill wrote "This was the most hateful decision, the most unnatural and painful in which I have ever been concerned".{{sfn|Lacouture|1991|p=246}} Relations between Britain and France were severely strained for some time and the Germans enjoyed a [[propaganda]] coup. Somerville said that it was "...the biggest political blunder of modern times and will rouse the whole world against us...we all feel thoroughly ashamed...".{{sfn|Smith|2010|pp=86, 88}} The attack revived Anglophobia in France but demonstrated British resolve to continue the war and rallied the British Conservative Party around Churchill ([[Neville Chamberlain]], Churchill's predecessor as prime minister, was still party leader). The British action showed the world that defeat in France had not reduced the determination of the government to fight on and ambassadors in Mediterranean countries reported favourable reactions.{{sfn|Playfair|1959|p=142}}

The French ships in Alexandria under the command of Admiral [[René-Emile Godfroy]], including the old battleship {{Ship|French battleship|Lorraine||2}} and four [[cruiser]]s, were blockaded by the British on 3 July and offered the same terms as at Mers-el-Kébir. After delicate negotiations, conducted on the part of the British by Admiral [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Andrew Cunningham]], Godfroy agreed on 7 July to disarm his fleet and stay in port until the end of the war.{{sfn|Playfair|1959|pp=140–141}} Some sailors joined the Free French while others were repatriated to France; ''Surcouf'' and the ships at Alexandria went on to be used by the Free French after May 1943. The British attacks on French vessels in port increased tension between Churchill and [[Charles de Gaulle]], who was recognised by the British as the leader of the Free French Forces on 28 June 1940.{{sfn|Auphan|Mordal|1976|pp=124–126}}{{sfn|Butler|1971|p=230}}

According to his [[Principal Private Secretary to the Prime Minister|principal private secretary]] Eric Seal, "[Churchill] was convinced that the Americans were impressed by ruthlessness in dealing with a ruthless foe; and in his mind the American reaction to our attack on the French fleet in Oran was of the first importance". On 4 July, Roosevelt told the French ambassador that he would have done the same.{{sfn|Smith|2010|p=92}} De Gaulle's biographer [[Jean Lacouture]] blamed the tragedy mainly on miscommunication; had Darlan been in contact on the day or had Somerville possessed a more diplomatic character, a deal might have been done. Lacouture accepted that there was a danger that the French ships might have been captured by German or more likely Italian troops, as proven by the ease with which the British seized French ships in British ports or the German seizure of French ships in [[Bizerte]] in Tunisia in November 1942.{{sfn|Lacouture|1991|p=249}}{{sfn|Smith|2010|p=404}}

===Casualties===
[[File:Mers el Kebir Memorial at Toulon, France.jpg|thumb|{{centre|Memorial on the coast path at Toulon to the 1,297 French seamen killed at Mers El Kebir}}]]
{| align="centre" class="wikitable"
|+ Numbers killed at Mers-el-Kébir{{sfn|O'Hara|2009|p=19}}
!
! Officers !! Petty&lt;br /&gt;officers !! Sailors,&lt;br /&gt; marines !! Total
|-
! {{Ship|French battleship|Bretagne||2}}
| align="right" | 36
| align="right" | 151
| align="right" | 825
| align="right" | 1012
|-
! {{Ship|French battleship|Dunkerque||2}}
| align="right" | 9
| align="right" | 32
| align="right" | 169
| align="right" | 210
|-
! {{Ship|French battleship|Provence||2}}
| align="right" | 1
| align="right" | 2
| align="right" |—
| align="right" | 3
|-
! {{Ship|French battleship|Strasbourg||2}}
| align="right" |—
| align="right" | 2
| align="right" | 3
| align="right" | 5
|-
! {{Ship|French destroyer|Mogador||2}}
| align="right" |—
| align="right" | 3
| align="right" | 35
| align="right" | 38
|-
! {{Ship|French aviso|Rigault de Genouilly||2}}
| align="right" |—
| align="right" | 3
| align="right" | 9
| align="right" | 12
|-
! ''Terre Neuve''
| align="right" | 1
| align="right" | 1
| align="right" | 6
| align="right" | 8
|-
! ''Armen''
| align="right" |—
| align="right" | 3
| align="right" | 3
| align="right" | 6
|-
! ''Esterel''
| align="right" | 1
| align="right" | 5
| align="right" |—
| align="right" | 6
|-
! Total
| align="right" | '''48'''
| align="right" | '''202'''
| align="right" | '''1,050'''
| align="right" | '''1,300'''
|-
! Fleet Air Arm{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|2002|p=61}}
| align="right" | —
| align="right" | —
| align="right" | —
| align="right" | '''2'''
|}

===Subsequent events===

====British–Vichy hostilities====
Following the 3 July operation, Darlan ordered the French fleet to attack Royal Navy ships wherever possible; Pétain and his foreign minister [[Paul Baudouin]] over-ruled the order the next day. Military retaliation was conducted through ineffective [[Military history of Gibraltar during World War II#Vichy French attacks: 1940|air raids on Gibraltar]] but Baudouin noted that "the attack on our fleet is one thing, war is another". As sceptics had warned, there were also complications with the French empire; when French colonial forces defeated de Gaulle's Free French Forces at the [[Battle of Dakar]] in September 1940, Germany responded by permitting Vichy France to maintain its remaining ships armed, rather than demobilised.{{sfn|Playfair|1959|pp=142–143}}{{sfn|Smith|2010|p=99}} On 24 September Gibraltar was bombed by sixty Vichy French, aircraft which dropped {{cvt|45|LT|t}} of bombs and that night, 81 bombers dropped {{cvt|60|LT|t}} of bombs. The French 2nd Destroyer Division comprising {{Ship|French destroyer|Fougueux||2}}, {{Ship|French destroyer|Frondeur||2}}, {{Ship|French destroyer|Épée|1938|2}} and {{Ship|French destroyer|Fleuret|1938|2}} had sailed from Casablanca on 24 September and in the early hours of 25 September encountered the destroyer {{HMS|Hotspur|H01|6}} patrolling off Gibraltar. ''Épée'' opened fire but its {{cvt|5.1|in|mm}} guns broke down after firing fourteen shells, ''Fleuret'' did not open fire because it could not get on target and the other French destroyers fired six shots between them. ''Hotspur'' returned fire but this was not reported by the French ships.{{sfn|O'Hara|2009|p=56}}

On 27 September Force H stayed at sea after receiving "a charming message [that] the whole of the Toulon fleet was coming out to have a scrap with us" but the two navies adhered to a tacit understanding that the British did not attack more powerful French forces at sea or ships in port but intercepted other French ships, 

{{quote|Though British commanders had precise instructions regarding the interception of French shipping, discretion might prove the better part of valour if Vichy escorts were liable to inflict serious loss.{{sfn|O'Hara|2009|p=56}}}}

In the autumn, the French sent a convoy through the Straights of Gibraltar untroubled, a state of affairs which rarely changed during the Mediterranean Campaign.{{sfn|O'Hara|2009|p=56}}

====Gibraltarian civilians====

{{main|Military history of Gibraltar during World War II|Evacuation of the Gibraltarian civilian population during World War II}}

In early June 1940, about 13,500 civilians had been evacuated from Gibraltar to Casablanca in French Morocco.  Following the capitulation of the French to the Germans and the attack on Mers-el-Kébir, the Vichy government found their presence an embarrassment. Later in June, 15 British cargo vessels arrived in Casablanca under Commodore Crichton, repatriating 15,000 French servicemen who had been rescued from Dunkirk. Once the French troops had disembarked, the ships were interned until the Commodore agreed to take away the evacuees, who, reflecting tensions generated after the attack on Mers-el-Kébir, were escorted to the ships at bayonet point, minus many of their possessions.{{sfn|Bond|2003|p=98}}

====Case Anton====

{{main|Case Anton}}

On 19 November 1942, the Germans tried to capture the French fleet based at Toulon, against the armistice terms, as part of Case Anton, the military occupation of Vichy France by Germany. All ships of any military value were [[Scuttling of the French fleet at Toulon|scuttled]] by the French before the arrival of German troops, notably ''Dunkerque'', ''Strasbourg'' and seven (four heavy and three light) modern cruisers. For many in the French Navy this was a final proof that there had never been a question of their ships ending up in German hands and that the British action at Mers-el-Kébir had been unnecessary.{{sfn|Greene|Massignani|2002|p=61}} Darlan was true to his promise in 1940, that French ships would not be allowed to fall into German hands. Godfroy, still in command of the French ships neutralised at Alexandria, remained aloof for a while longer but on 17 May 1943 joined the Allies.{{sfn|Roskill|1962|pp=338, 444}}

==Orders of battle==
{{Div col|colwidth=20em}}
'''Royal Navy'''
* {{HMS|Hood|51|6}} – battlecruiser – Flagship
* {{HMS|Resolution|09|6}} – battleship
* {{HMS|Valiant|1914|6}} – battleship
* {{HMS|Ark Royal|91|6}} – aircraft carrier
* {{HMS|Arethusa|26|6}} – light cruiser
* {{HMS|Enterprise|D52|6}} – light cruiser
* {{HMS|Faulknor|H62|6}} – destroyer
* {{HMS|Foxhound|H69|6}} – destroyer
* {{HMS|Fearless|H67|6}} – destroyer
* {{HMS|Forester|H74|6}} – destroyer
* {{HMS|Foresight|H68|6}} – destroyer
* {{HMS|Escort|H66|6}} – destroyer
* {{HMS|Keppel|D84|6}} – destroyer
* {{HMS|Active|H14|6}} – destroyer
* {{HMS|Wrestler||6}} – destroyer
* {{HMS|Vidette|D48|6}} – destroyer
* {{HMS|Vortigern|D37|6}} – destroyer

'''French Navy (''Marine Nationale'')'''
* {{Ship|French battleship|Dunkerque||2}} – battleship – Flagship
* {{Ship|French battleship|Strasbourg||2}} – battleship
* {{Ship|French battleship|Bretagne||2}} – battleship
* {{Ship|French battleship|Provence||2}} – battleship
* {{Ship|French seaplane carrier|Commandant Teste||2}} – seaplane tender
* {{Ship|French destroyer|Mogador||2}} – destroyer
* {{Ship|French destroyer|Volta||2}} – destroyer
* {{Ship|French destroyer|Le Terrible||2}} – destroyer
* {{Ship|French destroyer|Kersaint|1931|2}} – destroyer
* {{Ship|French destroyer|Lynx||2}} – destroyer
* {{Ship|French destroyer|Tigre||2}} – destroyer
{{Div col end}}

==See also==
* [[Attack on Pearl Harbor]]
* [[Battle of Taranto]]
* [[Naval Battle of Casablanca]]

==Notes==
{{notelist|40em}}

==Footnotes==
{{Reflist|20em}}

==References==
===Books===
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Auphan|Mordal|1976}}
|last1=Auphan |first1=Gabriel |authorlink1=Gabriel Auphan |last2=Mordal |first2=Jacques |authorlink2=Jacques Mordal |title=The French Navy in World War II |year=1976 |publisher=Greenwood Press |location=London |isbn=978-0-8371-8660-3 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Bell|1997}}
|last=Bell |first=P. M. H. Bell |series=France and Britain |title=France and Britain, 1940–1994: The Long Separation |year=1997 |publisher=Longman |location=London |isbn=978-0-582-28920-8 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Bond|2003}}
|last=Bond |first=Peter |title=300 Years of British Gibraltar: 1704–2004 |year=2003 |publisher=Peter-Tan Ltd for Government of Gibraltar |location=Gibraltar |oclc=1005205264 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Brown|2004}}
|last=Brown |first=D. |series=Cass: Naval Policy and History No. 20 |title=The Road to Oran: Anglo-French Naval Relations, September 1939 – July 1940 |year=2004 |publisher=Taylor and Francis |location=London |isbn=978-0-7146-5461-4 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Butler|1971}}
|last=Butler |first=J. R. M. |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |series=[[History of the Second World War]] United Kingdom Military Series |title=Grand Strategy: September 1939 – June 1941 |volume=II |publisher=[[HMSO]] |year=1971 |orig-year=1957 |edition=2nd |isbn=978-0-11-630095-9 |url=https://archive.org/details/grandstrategy02butl }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Greene|Massignani|2002}}
|title=The Naval War in the Mediterranean 1940–1943 |last1=Greene |first1=J. |last2=Massignani |first2=A. |year=2002 |orig-year=1998 |publisher=Chatham |location=Rochester |edition=pbk. |isbn=978-1-86176-190-3 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Lacouture|1991}}
|last=Lacouture |first=Jean |title=De Gaulle: The Rebel 1890–1944 |year=1991 |orig-year=1984 |publisher=W. W. Norton |location=London |edition=English trans. |isbn=978-0-393-02699-3 |url=https://archive.org/details/degaullerebel18900laco }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|O'Hara|2009}}
|last=O'Hara |first=Vincent P. |year=2009 |title=Struggle for the Middle Sea: The Great Navies at War in the Mediterranean Theater, 1940–1945 |publisher=Naval Institute Press |location=Annapolis, MD |isbn=978-1-59114-648-3 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Playfair|1959}}
|first1=Major-General I. S. O. |last1=Playfair |author1-link=Ian Stanley Ord Playfair |first2=Commander G. M. S. |last2=with Stitt [[Royal Navy|RN]] |first3=Brigadier C. J. C. |last3=Molony |first4=Air Vice-Marshal S. E. |last4=Toomer |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=J. R. M. |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |series=History of the Second World War, United Kingdom Military Series |title=The Mediterranean and Middle East: The Early Successes Against Italy (to May 1941) |volume=I |publisher=[[HMSO]] |year=1959 |orig-year=1954 |edition=3rd impr. |oclc=494123451 |url = http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/UK-Med-I/index.html |access-date=24 November 2017 |display-authors=1 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Roskill|1957}}
|series=History of the Second World War United Kingdom Military Series |title=The War at Sea 1939–1945: The Defensive |volume=I |last=Roskill |first=S. W. |authorlink=Stephen Roskill |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=J. R. M. |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |year=1957 |orig-year=1954 |publisher=HMSO |location=London |edition=4th impr. |url = http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/UK-RN-I/index.html |accessdate=24 November 2017 |oclc=881709135 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Roskill|1962}}
|last=Roskill |first=S. W. |series=[[History of the Second World War]]: The War at Sea 1939–1945 |title=The Period of Balance |volume=II |publisher=[[HMSO]] |location=London |year=1962 |orig-year=1956 |edition=3rd impression |url = http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/UK-RN-II/index.html |accessdate=24 November 2017 |oclc=174453986 }}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Smith|2010}}
|last=Smith |first=C. |title=England's Last War Against France: Fighting Vichy 1940–1942 |year=2010 |orig-year=2009 |publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson |location=London |edition=Phoenix |isbn=978-0-7538-2705-5 }}

===Journals===
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|Thomas|1997}}
|last=Thomas |first=Martin |title=After Mers-el-Kébir: The Armed Neutrality of the Vichy French Navy, 1940–43 |year=1997 |journal=English Historical Review |volume=112 |issue=447 |issn=0013-8266}}

==Further reading==
* {{cite book |last=Collier |first=Paul |title=The Second World War: The Mediterranean 1940–1945 |volume=IV |year=2003 |publisher=Osprey |location=Oxford |isbn=978-1-84176-539-6}}
* {{cite book |last1=Ehrengardt |first1=Christian-Jacques Ehrengardt |last2=Shores |first2=Christopher J. |series=Grandes batailles de France |title=L'aviation de Vichy au combat: les campagnes oubliées 3 juillet 1940 – 27 novembre 1942 |trans-title=The Vichy Air Force in Combat: The Forgotten Campaigns |year=1985 |volume=I |publisher=C. Lavauzelle |location=Paris |isbn=978-2-7025-0092-7}}
* {{cite book |last=Jenkins |first=E. H. |title=A History of the French Navy: From its Beginnings to the Present Day |year=1979 |publisher=Macdonald and Jane's |location=London |isbn=978-0-356-04196-4}}
* {{cite journal |last=Lasterle |first=Philippe |s2cid=159759345 |title=Could Admiral Gensoul Have Averted the Tragedy of Mers el-Kebir? |year=2003 |journal=Journal of Military History |volume=67 |issue=3 |pages=835–844 |issn=0899-3718|doi=10.1353/jmh.2003.0234 }}
* {{cite book |first=R. O. |last=Paxton |title=Vichy France: Old Guard and New Order, 1940–1944 |year=1972 |publisher=Knopf |location=New York |isbn=978-0-394-47360-4}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Attack on Mers-el-Kébir}}
* [http://www.hmshood.org.uk/reference/official/adm234/adm234-317.htm A plan of the Mers-el-Kébir anchorage], hmshood.org.uk
* [https://www.imdb.com/title/tt0366769 ''Mers-El-Kebir''] (1979) a French made-for-TV movie
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20070927023403/http://www.digitalsurvivors.com/archives/churchillsinkingfrenchfleet.php Churchill's Sinking of the French Fleet (3 July 1940)], digitalsurvivors.com
* [http://video.pbs.org/video/1492157105/ Churchill's Deadly Decision], episode of ''Secrets of the Dead'' describing the attack and the events leading up to it
* Kappes, Irwin J. (2003) [http://www.militaryhistoryonline.com/wwii/articles/merselkebir.aspx ''Mers-el-Kebir: A Battle between Friends''], Military History Online

{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Mers-El-Kebir}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1940]]
[[Category:Battle of the Mediterranean]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|A]]
[[Category:Algeria in World War II]]
[[Category:1940 in France]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:Naval history of World War II]]
[[Category:France–United Kingdom military relations]]
[[Category:July 1940 events]]</text><sha1>76agy49xukduoj9veq9t1ocqw9hfcdz</sha1></revision></page>