<page><title>Battle of Ramree Island</title><ns>0</ns><id>3766316</id><revision><id>958344993</id><parentid>958344504</parentid><timestamp>2020-05-23T08:16:20Z</timestamp><contributor><username>AustralianRupert</username><id>8731061</id></contributor><minor /><comment>Reverted edits by [[Special:Contribs/102.182.166.103|102.182.166.103]] ([[User talk:102.182.166.103|talk]]) to last version by 147.147.249.123</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="16322" xml:space="preserve">{{Use British English|date=May 2019}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Ramree Island
| partof      = the [[Burma Campaign]]
| image       = File:SE 002256 landings on Ramree island.jpg
| image_size  = 250px
| caption     = British troops in landing craft make their way ashore on Ramree Island, 21 January 1945
| date        = 14 January – 22 February 1945
| place       = [[Ramree Island]] ([[Yangbye]] Kywan) off [[Burma]]
| coordinates = {{Coord|19|06|00|N|93|48|00|E|display=inline}}
| map_type    = Burma
| map_size    = 150
| map_caption = {{centre|Burma (Myanmar)}}
| map_label   = Ramree Island
| territory   =
| result      = Allied victory
| status      =
| combatant1  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
* {{flagcountry|British Raj}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Empire of Japan}}
| commander1  = [[Cyril Lomax]]
| commander2  = [[Kanichi Nagazawa]]
| strength1   = [[26th Indian Infantry Division]]&lt;br /&gt;1 squadron 146th Regiment RAC&lt;br /&gt;[[3 Commando Brigade]] (elements)
| strength2   = II Battalion (reinforced to 1,000 men), 121st Infantry Regiment&lt;br /&gt;[[54th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|54th Division]]
| casualties1 =
| casualties2 = 500 killed (possibly only 20 survivors)&lt;br /&gt;20 captured&lt;br /&gt;500 escaped to mainland
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Burma}}
}}
The '''Battle of Ramree Island''' (also '''Operation Matador''') was fought in January and February 1945, during the [[Second World War]], as part of the [[XV Corps (India)|XV Indian Corps]] offensive on the [[Burma Campaign#Southern Front 1944/45|Southern Front]] in the [[Burma Campaign]]. [[Ramree Island]] ([[Yangbye]] Kywan) lies off the [[Burma]] coast, {{convert|70|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on}} south of Akyab (now [[Sittwe]]). The island had been captured by the [[Imperial Japanese Army]] in early 1942, along with the rest of Southern Burma. In January 1945, the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] launched an attack to retake Ramree and its neighbour [[Cheduba|Cheduba Island]], to establish airbases on the islands for the supply of the mainland campaign. There have been reports of Japanese soldiers being eaten by [[saltwater crocodile]]s living in the inland [[mangrove swamps]]; the [[Guinness Book of World Records]] has listed it as "worst crocodile disaster in the world" and "most number of fatalities in a [[crocodile attack]]" but scientists and historians have dismissed this as implausible.{{sfn|Russell|1987|p=216}}{{sfn|Kynaston|1998|p=135}}

==Background==
The early capture of [[Sittwe|Akyab]] made the [[26th Indian Infantry Division]] (Major-General [[Henry Chambers (Indian Army officer)|Henry Chambers]]) available for an attack on Ramree Island, {{convert|70|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on}} to the south, the island being {{convert|50|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on}} long and {{convert|20|mi|km|order=flip|abbr=on}} wide, flat and an obvious site for airfields.{{sfn|Saunders|1975|p=350}} A plan was ready by 2 January, when it was clear that the advance of the [[Fourteenth Army (United Kingdom)|Fourteenth Army]] (Lieutenant-General [[William Slim, 1st Viscount Slim|William Slim]]) would soon pass beyond the range of its airbases at [[Imphal]] and [[Agartala]]; replacements at [[Chittagong]], Akyab and Ramree would be needed.{{sfn|McLynn|2011|p=433}} On 14 January, the 26th Indian Division was ordered to attack Ramree on 21 January, as a Royal Marine detachment from [[3 Commando Brigade]] occupied Cheduba Island.{{sfn|Woodburn Kirby|2004|pp=214–215}} The Japanese garrison of Ramree consisted of the II Battalion, 121st Infantry Regiment (Colonel Kanichi Nagazawa), part of the [[54th Division (Imperial Japanese Army)|54th Division]], with artillery and engineer detachments to act as an independent force.{{sfn|Woodburn Kirby|2004|p=215}}

==Prelude==

The battle started with [[Operation Matador (1945)|Operation Matador]], an amphibious assault to capture the strategic port of [[Kyaukpyu]] at the north end of Ramree Island and the airfield near the port, south of [[Akyab]] across Hunter's Bay. The invasion force was led by three Joint Assault Commanders, Captain Bush RN, Major-General [[Cyril Lomax]] and Wing Commander H. Smith. Reconnaissance carried out on 14 January 1945, found that Japanese forces were placing artillery in caves overlooking the landing beaches on Ramree and the [[Royal Navy]] assigned the [[battleship]] {{HMS|Queen Elizabeth|1913|6}}, the [[escort aircraft carrier|escort carrier]] {{HMS|Ameer|D01|6}}, [[light cruiser]] {{HMS|Phoebe|43|6}}, the destroyers ''Rapid'', ''Napier'', ''Norman'' and ''Pathfinder'', with the [[Black Swan-class sloop|sloops]] ''Flamingo'' and {{HMIS|Kistna|U46|6}}.{{sfn|Woodburn Kirby|2004|p=219}}

The large number of ships was intended to provide more firepower in support of the landing force. On 21 January, an hour before the [[71st Indian Infantry Brigade]] (Brigadier R. C. Cotterell-Hill) was to land, ''Queen Elizabeth'' opened fire with {{nowrap|69 rounds}} of {{convert|15|in|mm|adj=on}}-shell from the main battery, the fall of shot being watched by aircraft from ''Ameer''. ''Phoebe'' also joined the bombardment, along with Consolidated [[B-24 Liberator]]s, North American [[B-25 Mitchell]]s and Republic [[P-47 Thunderbolt]]s of [[No. 224 Group RAF|224 Group]] [[Royal Air Force]] (RAF), under the command of [[RAF Third Tactical Air Force|HQ RAF Bengal and Burma]], that strafed and bombed the beaches.{{sfn|Woodburn Kirby|2004|p=219}}

==Battle==
[[File:Indian Div beside temple on Ramree Island.jpg|thumb|{{centre|Men of the Wiltshire Regiment from the 26th Indian Infantry Division prepare a meal beside a temple on Ramree Island.}}]]
The assault troops were slightly delayed when a motor launch and a landing craft struck mines but landed unopposed on the beaches west of Kyaukpyu at {{nowrap|9:42 a.m.,}} securing the beachhead by the afternoon. The following day, the [[4th Indian Infantry Brigade]] (Brigadier J. F. R. Forman) landed, took over the beachhead and occupied Kyaukpyu and on 23 January, the 71st Infantry Brigade advanced southwards, down the west coast. Two days later Mayin was occupied and the troops reached the Yanbauk Chaung the next day. Resistance at the chaung from the troops of the II Battalion, 121st Regiment increased and on 31 January, the 71st Brigade was ordered to move inland, north-east towards Sane, then head south towards Ramree town. The 4th Brigade was to keep the defenders at Yanbauk Chaung under pressure and follow up vigorously should they retire.{{sfn|Woodburn Kirby|2004|p=219}}

(On 26 January in [[Operation Sankey]], a [[Royal Marines|Royal Marine]] force landed on [[Cheduba]] island, about {{convert|10|km|mi|order=flip|abbr=on}} from the south-west coast of Ramree Island and found it unoccupied.) On Ramree, the Japanese garrison put up tenacious resistance but on 1 February, the 71st Indian Infantry Brigade reached Sane and parts of the [[36th Indian Infantry Brigade]], from reserve, took Sagu Kuyun Island and relieved the marines on Cheduba Island.{{sfn|Woodburn Kirby|2004|p=219}} When the British outflanked a Japanese stronghold, the {{nowrap|900 defenders}} abandoned the base and marched to join a larger battalion of Japanese soldiers across the island. The route took the Japanese through {{convert|16|km|mi|abbr=on}} of [[mangrove]] swamp and as they struggled through it, the British encircled the area. Trapped in deep mud-filled land, tropical diseases soon started to afflict the soldiers, as did [[scorpion]]s, tropical [[mosquito]]es and [[saltwater crocodile]]s.{{sfn|Woodburn Kirby|2004|p=220}}

On 7 February, the 71st Indian Infantry Brigade and supporting tanks reached the town of Ramree and found determined Japanese resistance. The 4th Indian Infantry Brigade had advanced to Ledaung Chaung and was sent east to reinforce the attack; the town fell on 9 February. The navy and the 26th Indian Infantry Division then concentrated on blockading the ''chaungs'' (small streams) on the east coast to prevent the Japanese from escaping to the mainland. A Japanese air raid on 11 February seriously damaged a destroyer with a near miss and forty small craft were sent by the Japanese from the mainland to rescue the survivors of the garrison. Japanese resistance on the island ended on 17 February and the Allied blockade was maintained until 22 February, sinking many of the rescue craft and inflicting many casualties on the Japanese troops hiding in the mangrove swamps; about {{nowrap|500 troops}} managed to get away. Cheduba Island was not garrisoned and the 22nd East African Brigade was sent to hold Ramree Island.{{sfn|Woodburn Kirby|2004|pp=219–220}}

==Aftermath==

===Analysis===
In 1965, the British official historian [[Stanley Kirby|Stanley Woodburn Kirby]] wrote that the Japanese defence of the island and the escape of about {{nowrap|500 men}} against "fearful odds", had been courageous and determined.{{sfn|Woodburn Kirby|2004|p=220}} It took until 16 April for the airfield to be used for transport sorties, Akyab having come into use on 1 April. It had been vital to complete the occupation of Ramree Island quickly, as [[Operation Dracula]] against Rangoon needed to commence in the first week of May at the latest, to have a chance of finishing before the monsoon.{{sfn|Saunders|1975|p=350}} The experience in co-operation between the 26th Indian Division and the navy in the war of chaungs and small ports along the Arakan coast was intended to be exploited in the attack. An estimate put naval gunfire support from 4 January to 13 March for the land operations at Akyab, Ramree and Cheduba at {{nowrap|23,000 shells.}} The navy also carried {{nowrap|54,000 men,}} {{nowrap|1,000 vehicles,}} {{convert|14000|LT|t|abbr=on}} of stores and {{nowrap|800 animals.}}{{sfn|Allen|1984|p=468}}

===Crocodile attack===
[[File:SaltwaterCrocodile('Maximo').jpg|thumb|{{centre|A [[saltwater crocodile]]}}]]
Some British soldiers, including the naturalist [[Bruce Stanley Wright|Bruce Wright]], who participated in the battle, claimed that the large population of saltwater crocodiles native to the mangrove swamps on Ramree Island [[predation|preyed on]] the trapped Japanese force at night and ate many soldiers. Wright gave a description in ''Wildlife Sketches Near and Far'' (1962), quoted by [[Frank McLynn]],

{{quote|That night [of the 19 February 1945] was the most horrible that any member of the M. L. [motor launch] crews ever experienced. The scattered rifle shots in the pitch black swamp punctured by the screams of wounded men crushed in the jaws of huge reptiles, and the blurred worrying sound of spinning crocodiles made a cacophony of hell that has rarely been duplicated on earth. At dawn the vultures arrived to clean up what the crocodiles had left.... Of about one thousand Japanese soldiers that entered the swamps of Ramree, only about twenty were found alive.|Wright{{sfn|McLynn|2011|p=13}}}}

If Wright was correct, the Ramree Island [[crocodile attacks]] were the worst recorded in history. The British [[Burma Star Association]] seems to lend credence to the swamp attack stories but appears to draw a distinction between the {{nowrap|20 Japanese}} survivors of one attack and the {{nowrap|900 Japanese}} who were left to fend for themselves in the swamp. In his memoir, ''An Odyssey in War and Peace'', Lieutenant-General [[J.F.R. Jacob]] recounted his experiences during the battle,

{{quote|Over a 1000 soldiers of the Japanese garrison retreated into the crocodile-infested mangrove swamps. We went in with boats and interpreters using loud-hailers asking them to come out. Not a single one did. Salt-water crocodiles, some of them well over 20 ft in length frequented these waters. It is not difficult to imagine what happened to the Japanese who took refuge in the mangroves!{{sfn|Jacob|2012|loc=Ch 2}}}}

These figures have been disputed by other historians, who call the event an [[urban myth]].{{sfn|Platt|Ko|Khaing|Rainwater|2001|pp=15–18}} McLynn wrote

{{quote|Most of all, there is a single zoological problem. If 'thousands of crocodiles' were involved in the massacre, as in the urban (jungle) myth, how had these ravening monsters survived before and how were they to survive later? The ecosystem of a mangrove swamp, with an exiguous mammal life, simply would not have permitted the existence of so many saurians before the coming of the Japanese (animals are not exempt from the laws of overpopulation and starvation).{{sfn|McLynn|2011|p=14}}}}

The British official history (War against Japan volume IV, ''The Reconquest of Burma'', 1965 [2004]) referred only to "crocodile-infested mangrove swamps".{{sfn|Woodburn Kirby|2004|p=220}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|20em}}

== References ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Allen|1984}}
|last=Allen |first=Louis |title=Burma: The Longest War |publisher=Dent Paperbacks |location=London |year=1984 |isbn=978-0-460-02474-7}}
* {{cite book |last=Jacob |first=J. F. R.|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=99BbBAAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PT24&amp;dq=We+went+in+with+boats+with+interpreters+using+loud-hailers+asking+them+to+come+out.+Not+a+single+one+did.+salt-water+crocodiles&amp;hl=en&amp;newbks=1&amp;newbks_redir=0&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwil9JzpotLoAhVEmK0KHeqqC4YQ6AEwAHoECAYQAg#v=onepage&amp;q=We%20went%20in%20with%20boats%20with%20interpreters%20using%20loud-hailers%20asking%20them%20to%20come%20out.%20Not%20a%20single%20one%20did.%20salt-water%20crocodiles&amp;f=false|title=An Odyssey in War and Peace |year=2012 |publisher=Roli Books |isbn=978-81-7436-933-8 |ref=harv}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Kynaston|1998}}
|title=The Guinness 1999 Book of Records |editor1-first=Nick |editor1-last=Kynaston |publisher=Guinness Publishing |year=1998 |isbn=978-0-85112-070-6}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|McLynn|2011}}
|first=Frank |last=McLynn |title=The Burma Campaign: Disaster into Triumph, 1942–45 |publisher=Yale University Press |location= |year=2011 |isbn=978-0-300-17162-4}}
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|Platt|Ko|Khaing|Rainwater|2001}}
|last1=Platt |first1=S. G. |last2=Ko |first2=W. K. |last3=Khaing |first3=L. L. |last4=Rainwater |first4=T. R. |series=British Library Serials |title=Man Eating by Estuarine Crocodiles: The Ramree Island Massacre Revisited |year=2001 |journal=Herpetological Bulletin |issue=75 |others=BL shelfmark: 4300.326000 |id=209068329}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Russell|1987}}
|editor1-first=Alan |editor1-last=Russell |title=The Guinness Book of Records 1988 |publisher=Guinness Books |year=1987 |isbn=978-0-85112-873-3}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Saunders|1975}}
|last=St G. Saunders |first=H. |title=Royal Air Force 1939–45: The Fight is Won |volume=III |year=1975 |orig-year=1954 |publisher=HMSO |location=London |url=http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/UK-RAF-III/index.html |accessdate=13 December 2015 |edition=repr. |isbn=978-0-11-771594-3}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Woodburn Kirby|2004}}
|last1=Woodburn Kirby |first1=Major-General S. |editor-last=Butler |editor-first=Sir James |editor-link=James Ramsay Montagu Butler |series=[[History of the Second World War]], United Kingdom Military Series |title=The War Against Japan: The Reconquest of Burma |volume=IV |publisher=Naval &amp; Military Press |location=Uckfield |year=2004 |origyear=1st. pub. [[HMSO]]:1965 |isbn=978-1-84574-063-4}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |title=Wildlife Sketches: Near and Far |last=Wright |first=B. S. |authorlink= |year=1962 |publisher=Brunswick Press |location=Fredericton, NB |edition= |oclc=8099292}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
{{Commons category|Battle of Ramree Island}}
* [http://www.chebucto.ns.ca/environment/ASFWB/wright.html Bruce Stanley Wright, 17 September 1912 – 19 April 1975]

{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}

{{World War II}}
{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Ramree Island}}
[[Category:World War II operations and battles of the Southeast Asia Theatre|Ramree Island]]
[[Category:Military history of Burma during World War II|Ramree Island]]
[[Category:Deaths due to crocodile attacks]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1945|Ramree Island]]
[[Category:1945 in Burma]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]
[[Category:January 1945 events]]
[[Category:February 1945 events]]</text><sha1>huhr4dt0k7pscre257d1gz0xkg5qv0l</sha1></revision></page>