<page><title>Battle of Calabria</title><ns>0</ns><id>656035</id><revision><id>967622340</id><parentid>962648924</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-14T09:47:49Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Snagemit</username><id>39030591</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="30188" xml:space="preserve">{{redirect|Battle of Punta Stilo|the medieval battle between Byzantines and Aghlabids|Battle of Stelai}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2020}}
{{Infobox military conflict
 |conflict    = Battle of Calabria
 |image       = Cesare firing her guns.jpg
 |image_size  = 300px
 |caption     = Italian battleship ''Giulio Cesare'', circa July 9 1940
 |partof      = the [[Battle of the Mediterranean]] of [[World War II]]
 |date        = {{start date|1940|07|09|df=y}}
 |place       = Off [[Calabria]], [[Mediterranean Sea]]
 |result      = Indecisive
 |combatant1  = {{ubl|{{flagcountry|United Kingdom}}|{{flagcountry|Australia}}}}
 |combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
 |commander1  = {{flagdeco|UK|naval}} [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Andrew Cunningham]]
 |commander2  = {{flagdeco|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Inigo Campioni]]
 |strength1   = {{ubl|1 aircraft carrier|3 battleships|5 light cruisers|16 destroyers}}
 |strength2   = {{ubl|2 battleships|6 heavy cruisers|8 light cruisers|16 destroyers}}
 |casualties1 = {{ubl|1 light cruiser damaged|2 destroyers damaged}}
 |casualties2 = {{ubl|1 battleship damaged|1 heavy cruiser damaged|1 destroyer damaged}}
 |campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Mediterranean Campaign}}
}}

The '''Battle of Calabria''', (known to the Italian Navy as the '''Battle of Punta Stilo''') was a [[naval battle]] during the [[Battle of the Mediterranean]] in the [[World War II|Second World War]]. It was fought between the [[Kingdom of Italy|Italian]] [[Regia Marina|Royal Navy]] (''[[Regia Marina]]'') and the British [[Royal Navy]] and the [[Royal Australian Navy]]. The battle occurred 30 miles to the east of [[Punta Stilo]], [[Calabria]], on 9 July 1940. It was one of the few [[pitched battle]]s of the Mediterranean campaign during the Second World War involving large numbers of ships on both sides. Both sides claimed victory, but in fact the battle was a draw and everyone returned to their bases safely.

==Background==
When Italy entered the Second World War, its forces in [[Libya]] were ill-equipped for offensive operations, and the Italian fleet was forced to start large supply convoys in order to bring them up to fighting condition.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 65&lt;/ref&gt;

On 6 July a convoy of four merchant ships left [[Naples]] on their way to [[Benghazi]], while attempting to fool the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]] into thinking they were making for [[Tripoli]]. That evening two [[torpedo-boat]]s from [[Catania]] and another freighter met them off [[Messina]] and the next day their escort force joined the convoy from [[Taranto]] after being informed that the Allies had recently left port in [[Alexandria]]. The transports carried 2,190 troops, 72 [[Fiat M11/39|M11]] tanks, 232 vehicles, 10,445 tons of supplies and 5,720 tons of fuel. The convoy's escort, commanded by Admiral [[Inigo Campioni]], consisted of three groups. The first, comprising eight [[destroyer]]s and four torpedo boats, sailed directly protecting the cargo ships. A second group sailed {{convert|35|mi}} to the east consisting of six [[heavy cruiser]]s and another four destroyers. Finally, the main battle group consisted of two [[battleship]]s ({{ship|Italian battleship|Giulio Cesare||2}} and {{ship|Italian battleship|Conte di Cavour||2}}), eight [[light cruisers]] and another 16 destroyers.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 67&lt;/ref&gt; A substantial number of the Italian destroyers didn't take part in the battle due to mechanical problems and the need to refuel.&lt;ref name=Cunningham/&gt;

Meanwhile, the Allies were involved in a similar convoy action. The fleet sailed from Alexandria bound towards [[Malta]] where the destroyers would deliver supplies and a limited number of specialist reinforcements. Two convoys were arranged to take off fleet stores and civilians from Malta to Alexandria. Two groups of merchantmen sailed, a fast convoy at {{convert|13|kn|lk=in}} and slow one at {{convert|9|kn}}. Protecting them were three groups of ships: [[Force A]], with five cruisers and a destroyer; [[Force B]], with the battleship {{HMS|Warspite|03|2}} and five destroyers, and [[Force C]], the main battle group, with the battleships {{HMS|Royal Sovereign|05|2}} and {{HMS|Malaya||2}}, the [[aircraft carrier]] {{HMS|Eagle|1918|2}} and eleven destroyers.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 66&lt;/ref&gt; One of them, {{HMS|Imperial|D09|2}}, had to return to Alexandria with a burst steam pipe on the early hours of 8 July.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naval-history.net/xGM-Chrono-10DD-29I-Imperial.htm HMS Imperial ( D 0 9 )]&lt;/ref&gt; All were under the direction of Admiral [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Andrew Cunningham]].

At 14:40 on 8 July two Italian [[Cant Z.506]] seaplanes from [[Tobruk]] spotted the British fleet and shadowed it for nearly four hours. Admiral Campioni ordered his fleet to defend the convoy by turning eastward and preparing for action. The Italian Supreme Command, however, was reluctant to risk its warships in a night-time encounter, and they ordered the fleet to avoid contact.&lt;ref name=supremo&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 68&lt;/ref&gt; During the initial positioning the Italians suffered technical problems on three destroyers and two light cruisers, so these ships, with several additional destroyers, were detached to refuel in [[Sicily]]. In order to make up for these "losses", another destroyer group was summoned from Taranto. At this point, the Italian fleet had 16 destroyers.&lt;ref name=Cunningham/&gt;&lt;ref name=Campioni&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 70&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, the Allies were having problems as well. From 10:00 to 18.40, 72 land-based [[bomber]]s of the Italian {{lang|it|[[Regia Aeronautica]]}} (Royal Air Force) from the mainland attacked their fleet. Unlike the [[Dive bomber|dive-bombers]] favored by the Germans, Italian bombers operated in formations at high altitudes during the early stages of the war, about twelve thousand feet. While scores of bombs were dropped by the Italians, a single hit on {{HMS|Gloucester|C62|6}} represented the outcome of two major attacks.&lt;ref&gt;Miller, ''War at Sea'', pg. 113&lt;/ref&gt; This was a serious hit on the bridge, killing the captain, six officers and eleven ratings. In addition, three officers and six ratings were wounded. The forward fire control and the steering equipment was destroyed, and for the rest of the battle, she would be commanded from the emergency station.&lt;ref name="supremo"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naval-history.net/xGM-Chrono-06CL-Gloucester.htm HMS Gloucester  – Town-type Light Cruiser]&lt;/ref&gt;

At 15:10 on 8 July, Cunningham's fleet steamed toward Taranto, in order to cut the Italians' return route. At dusk, Cunningham changed course from 310° to 260° and slowed the fleet speed. During the first hours of 9 July, they took a 305° course, to avoid the Italian air reconnaissance while keeping their fleet between the Italian squadron and the [[Gulf of Taranto]].&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 68–69&lt;/ref&gt; By 12:30, the Italian Supreme Command was unaware of the situation of the British fleet. Campioni told his fleet to scramble by 14:00 about {{convert|60|mi}} south east of Cape Spartivento in search of the enemy. Campioni eventually received reports of the British position at 13:30, and six [[IMAM Ro.43|Ro.43]] floatplanes launched shortly after by the Italian cruisers spotted the British warships 30 miles closer than supposed.&lt;ref name=Campioni/&gt;

By late evening of 8 July, the Italian convoy had arrived in Bengazi unscathed.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=La battaglia dei convogli in Mediterraneo|last=Giorgerini|first=Giorgio|publisher=Mursia|year=1977|pages=110|language=Spanish}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==

===Cruiser engagement===
At noon on 9 July the two fleets were {{convert|90|mi}} apart. Vice Admiral Cunningham could not close the distance to engage with the significantly slower ''Royal Sovereign'' and ''Malaya'' ({{convert|18|kn|abbr=on}} vs {{convert|28|kn|abbr=on}}) and took ''Warspite'' in on its own. Meanwhile, at 13:15, ''Eagle'' launched several unsuccessful sorties by [[Fairey Swordfish]] against the Italian heavy cruisers, which they took for battleships.&lt;ref name=Campioni/&gt; At 13:10, the Italian Supreme Command had instructed Campioni to engage one of the two enemy forces facing him, but in fact they had planned to keep the action close to Italy and were deliberately moving north in order to draw the Allies closer to their airbases. By 14:00, however, Cunningham's plans to cut off the Italian fleet from Taranto had succeeded.&lt;ref name=Cunningham&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 72&lt;/ref&gt;

The Allied cruiser group was spread out in front of ''Warspite'' and at 15:15 they caught sight of the Italian main battle force and the two groups opened fire at {{convert|21500|m|yd}}. Italian rangefinding was better than the Allied, and within three minutes they had found the distance even though they were firing at extreme range. Although the Allies' rangefinding was not as good and they had trouble with their rounds falling short, the Allied gunlaying was better and they were able to place their rounds in much tighter groups. Generally the gunnery of the two forces was fairly well matched. After only a few minutes the range was down to {{convert|20000|m|yd}} and the Allied guns became useful. However, by 15:22, the Italian fire came dangerously close to the Allied cruisers and Vice Admiral [[John Tovey, 1st Baron Tovey|John Tovey]] decided to disengage.&lt;ref name=net&gt;[http://www.regiamarina.net/detail_text_with_list.asp?nid=35&amp;lid=1&amp;cid=3 Action off Calabria – Initial skirmish]&lt;/ref&gt; At this point splinters from a {{convert|6|in|mm|adj=on|0}} shell fired by the cruiser {{ship|Italian cruiser|Giuseppe Garibaldi|1936|2}}&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.regiamarina.net/detail_text_with_list.asp?nid=35&amp;lid=1&amp;cid=3 Action of Calabria] by Christian D'Adamo&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Jordan, John (2008). ''Warship 2008''. Conway maritime press, p. 32. {{ISBN|1-84486-062-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; hit {{HMS|Neptune|20|6}}, damaging her catapult and the [[Fairey Seafox|reconnaissance aircraft]] beyond repair.&lt;ref&gt;Smith, Peter Charles (1980). ''Action imminent: three studies of the naval war in the Mediterranean theatre during 1940''. Kimber, p. 66. {{ISBN|0-7183-0197-8}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lg /&gt; The cruisers continued to open the range and by 15:30 fire ceased.&lt;ref name=net/&gt;

===Battleship engagement===
One group of Italian [[light cruiser]]s, mistaken for the heavy cruisers of the {{sclass-|Zara|cruiser|4}}, was on the Allied side of the battle line and was soon within range of the charging ''Warspite''. Once again the Allied rounds fell short, and neither of her targets, {{ship|Italian cruiser|Alberico da Barbiano||2}} and {{ship|Italian cruiser|Alberto di Giussano||2}}, received any damage in the initial salvos. However, by this time ''Warspite'' was also out of position, and she circled in place in order to allow ''Malaya'' to catch up. Meanwhile, ''Royal Sovereign'' was still well to the rear.&lt;ref name="regiamarina"&gt;{{Cite web
| last       = D'Adamo
| first      = Cristiano
| title      = Action off Calabria – The battleships enter the fight
| publisher  = regiamarina.net
| url        = http://www.regiamarina.net/detail_text_with_list.asp?nid=35&amp;lid=1&amp;cid=4
| accessdate = 13 March 2011 }}&lt;/ref&gt;

The Italian commander decided to take on ''Warspite'', and started moving his two battleships into position. At 15:52 ''Giulio Cesare'' opened fire at a range of {{convert|26400|m|yd}}. ''Conte di Cavour'' held her fire, as Italian strategy was to have only one ship targeted at a time. It had been discovered during the [[Battle of Jutland]] that more than one ship firing at a single target made it very difficult for the rangefinding parties to tell which rounds were fired by their ship. ''Conte di Cavour'' had been assigned to ''Malaya'' and ''Royal Sovereign'', which did not enter the engagement.&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara, p. 40.&lt;/ref&gt;

''Warspite'', not aware of the Italian firing patterns, split her guns between the two ships. During the exchange one of ''Giulio Cesare''{{'}}s rounds fell long and caused splinter damage to ''Warspite''{{'}}s escorting destroyers {{HMS|Hereward|H93|2}} and {{HMS|Decoy|H75|2}}, which had formed up on the far side of the action.&lt;ref&gt;Jordan (2008), p. 34&lt;/ref&gt; At 15:54 ''Malaya'' started firing, well out of range, hoping to cause some confusion on the Italian ships. Meanwhile, the Italian heavy cruisers came into action and started firing on ''Warspite'' at 15:55 but had to break off as the Allied cruisers returned.&lt;ref name="regiamarina"/&gt;

At 15:59 two shells from ''Giulio Cesare'' fell very close to ''Warspite''. Almost immediately after one of ''Warspite''{{'}}s {{convert|15|in|mm|adj=on|0}} rounds hit the rear deck of ''Giulio Cesare'', exploding in the funnel, and setting off the stored ammunition for one of her {{convert|37|mm|in|abbr=on}} anti-aircraft guns. Two seamen were killed and several wounded.&lt;ref&gt;Marina Militare italiana, part 1 1940–45, p 39, Albertelli Edizioni, Parma, 2015&lt;/ref&gt; The fumes from the burning ammunition were sucked down into the engine room, which had to evacuate and shut down half of the boilers. ''Giulio Cesare''{{'}}s speed quickly fell off to 18 knots and ''Conte di Cavour'' took over. ''Giulio Cesare'' and ''Warspite'' were well over {{convert|24000|m|yd}} apart at the time of the hit, which was one of the longest-range naval artillery hits in history.{{#tag:ref|The German battleship {{ship|German battleship|Scharnhorst||2}} achieved a hit on the British aircraft carrier {{HMS|Glorious||6}} at approximately the same range the previous month.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| first=Tony| last=DiGiulian| url=http://www.navweaps.com/Weapons/WNGER_11-545_skc34.htm| work=Navweaps.com| title=German 28&amp;nbsp;cm/54.5 (11") SK C/34| accessdate=2010-12-23 | archiveurl= https://web.archive.org/web/20101219104929/http://navweaps.com/Weapons/WNGER_11-545_skc34.htm| archivedate= 19 December 2010 |url-status = live}}&lt;/ref&gt;| group=Note}}

It would appear that ''Warspite'' was in an excellent position to deal some serious blows to the slowing ''Giulio Cesare'', but she once again executed another tight turn to allow ''Malaya'' to catch up. With her guns suddenly silenced during the turn, rangefinders on ''Malaya'' discovered what the Italians had been intending to avoid, that her rounds were falling {{convert|2700|yd|m|order=flip}} short of ''Giulio Cesare'' and they had been watching ''Warspite''{{'}}s rounds, not their own.&lt;ref name="regiamarina"/&gt;

At 16:01 the Italian destroyers generated smoke and the battleships got under cover. There is some debate about this point today, the Allied position being that the battleships were leaving battle, the Italian that they were attempting to make a [[torpedo]] attack with their destroyers from within the smoke.&lt;ref name="regiamarina"/&gt;

===Final actions===
At 15:58 {{ship|Italian cruiser|Fiume||2}} re-opened fire on her counterpart in the Allied line, {{HMS|Liverpool|C11|2}}, and soon two groups of Italian cruisers ({{ship|Italian cruiser|Zara||2}}, {{ship|Italian cruiser|Bolzano||2}} and {{ship|Italian cruiser|Pola||2}}, closely followed by {{ship|Italian cruiser|Gorizia||2}} and {{ship|Italian cruiser|Trento||2}}) entered combat range with the main Allied cruiser battle group. Firing continued as both groups attempted to form up and at 16:07 ''Bolzano'' was hit three times by 6 in shells from HMS ''Neptune'', temporarily locking her rudder and causing two fatalities in the torpedo room. A near miss on the destroyer {{ship|Italian destroyer|Vittorio Alfieri||2}} caused minor damage.&lt;ref name=destr&gt;[http://www.regiamarina.net/detail_text_with_list.asp?nid=35&amp;lid=1&amp;cid=5 Action off Calabria – Cruisers and destroyers]&lt;/ref&gt;

Meanwhile, mechanics on ''Giulio Cesare'' were able to repair two of the four damaged boilers, allowing the battleship to reach {{convert|22|kn}}.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.militaryhistoryonline.com/wwii/articles/capitalshipsurfaceactions.asp ''Capital Ship Surface Actions World War 2'', by Terry A. Gardner, EMC(SW) USNR ret]{{Dead link|date=June 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}&lt;/ref&gt; Admiral Campioni, considering the possibility of his remaining battleship, ''Conte di Cavour'', having to face three enemy battleships and an aircraft carrier, decided to withdraw the battleships towards Messina.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 75&lt;/ref&gt; ''Giulio Cesare'' was out of action for 30 days.&lt;ref name=destr/&gt;

Over the next hour both fleets attempted to make long-range torpedo runs with their destroyer groups, without success.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 74–75&lt;/ref&gt; At 16:40, the Italian air force made an attack with 126 aircraft, reporting damage on ''Eagle'', ''Warspite'' and ''Malaya''; because of some misunderstanding, 50 of the Italian aircraft also attacked the Italian ships, without damage. The battle ended at 16:50 with both sides withdrawing.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 77&lt;/ref&gt;

One final victim was the destroyer {{ship|Italian destroyer|Leone Pancaldo||2}}, sent to Augusta in Sicily, which was hit by a torpedo launched from a Swordfish at 09:40 the next day and sank in shallow water.&lt;ref name=lg&gt;{{Cite web
| last       = Cunningham
| first      = Admiral Sir Andrew B.
| title      = REPORT OF AN ACTION WITH THE ITALIAN FLEET OFF CALABRIA, 9th JULY, 1940.
| work       = [[London Gazette]]
| publisher  = [[HMSO]]
| date       = 28 April 1948
| url        = http://ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/LondonGazette/38273.pdf
| format     = pdf
| accessdate = 30 July 2010 }}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=destr/&gt; (She was refloated and returned to service in December 1941.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book
| last       = Whitley
| first      = M J
| authorlink =M J Whitley
| title      = Destroyers of World War Two: An International Encyclopedia
| publisher  = [[Arms &amp; Armour Press]]
| year       = 2000
| location   = London
| page       = 164
| isbn         = 1-85409-521-8 }}&lt;/ref&gt;)

==Aftermath==
After the battle both fleets turned for home. This allowed the Italians to claim a victory of sorts, as their cargo ships were already past the action by this time and sailed safely for Libya.&lt;ref&gt;Sadkovich, James (1990).''Reevaluating major naval combatants of World War II''. Greenwood Press, p. 137. {{ISBN|0-313-26149-0}}&lt;/ref&gt; Meanwhile, the Allied ships also reached Alexandria along with their escort. Although the battle was indecisive, Allied sources claimed that the Royal Navy asserted an important "moral ascendancy" over their Italian counterpart.&lt;ref&gt;Hill, J. R. and Ranft, Bryan (2002). ''The Oxford illustrated history of the Royal Navy''. Oxford University Press, p. 358. {{ISBN|0-19-860527-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Other sources instead dispute those claims, pointing out that, in the immediate aftermath of the battle, the moods of the two commanders were quite different. Campioni wrote that, even having been able to employ only two old refurbished battleships, the battle gave to every man in the fleet, from the senior officers to the seamen, the impression of being able to cope with the British Fleet on equal terms. Cunningham, conversely, was dismayed by the performance of his two older units, whose lack of speed permitted the Italians to dictate the course of the action, and whose cannon were out-ranged not only by those of the two Italian battleships, but by those of the heavy cruisers as well. Cunningham dismissed the ''Royal Sovereign'' as a "constant source of anxiety", and asked the Admiralty for two or three more {{sclass-|Queen Elizabeth|battleship|1}}s, possibly equipped with radar, a new carrier with an armoured deck, the heavy cruisers {{HMS|York|90|2}} and {{HMS|Exeter|68|2}}, and enough smaller ships to cover the major units.&lt;ref&gt;Bernard Ireland, The War in the Mediterranean 1940–1943 (1993), p. 37. {{ISBN|9781844150472}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara, Vincent P. (2009). Struggle for the Middle Sea: The Great Navies at War in the Mediterranean Theater, 1940–1945. Annapolis, Maryland: Naval Institute Press. {{ISBN|978-1-59114-648-3}}.&lt;/ref&gt;

One question is why the Italians did not send their two operational battleships of {{sclass-|Vittorio Veneto|battleship|4}} at Taranto, both almost ready for action and only a few hours from the scene. Both capital ships were still undergoing trials, and {{ship|Italian battleship|Littorio||2}} had suffered an electrical mishap on one of her main turrets. ''Littorio'' and {{ship|Italian battleship|Vittorio Veneto||2}} would have tipped the balance of fire well onto the Italian side.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 69&lt;/ref&gt;

Even without these ships the fleets were fairly even. Despite Italian superiority in aircraft due to the nearby land-based aircraft of the {{lang|it|Regia Aeronautica}} the attacks proved ineffective, achieving little apart from the damage to ''Gloucester.''&lt;ref name=supremo/&gt; Despite this, the air arm's battle reports were inflated to the point of claiming damage to half of the Allied fleet.&lt;ref&gt;Knox, MacGregor (1986). ''Mussolini unleashed, 1939–1941: politics and strategy in fascist Italy's''. Cambridge University Press, p. 146. {{ISBN|0-521-33835-2}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Overall, Allied gunnery proved superior, while the Italian salvos were too widely dispersed due to technical reasons that were not to be overcome until the end of the conflict.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 79&lt;/ref&gt;

==Order of battle==
(F) denotes flagship

===Allies===
[[File:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|60px|border|RN Ensign]]

'''Force A''' – Commanded by Vice Admiral [[John Tovey, 1st Baron Tovey|John Tovey]]

''7th Cruiser squadron''
* 5 light cruisers: {{HMS|Orion|85|2}}, {{HMS|Neptune|20|2}} (''damaged''), {{HMAS|Sydney|1934|6}},&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.navy.gov.au/w/index.php/HMAS_Sydney_%28II%29 |title=HMAS Sydney (II) |accessdate=23 August 2008 |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |url-status = dead|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20081123092109/http://www.navy.gov.au/w/index.php/HMAS_Sydney_%28II%29 |archivedate=23 November 2008}}&lt;/ref&gt; {{HMS|Gloucester|C62|2}} (''damaged''), and {{HMS|Liverpool|1938|2}}.

''' [[Force B]]''' – Commanded by Vice Admiral [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Andrew Cunningham]] who was the Commander in Chief Mediterranean Fleet;

''1st Battle Squadron''
* 1 battleship: {{HMS|Warspite|03|2}} (F)
* 6 Destroyers: {{HMS|Nubian|F36|2}}, {{HMS|Mohawk|F31|2}}, {{HMS|Hero|H99|2}}, {{HMS|Hereward|H93|2}} (''damaged''), {{HMS|Decoy|H75|2}} (''damaged''), {{HMAS|Stuart|D00|6}},&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/w/index.php/HMAS_Stuart_%28I%29 |title=HMAS Stuart (I) |accessdate=23 August 2008 |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090508043248/http://www.navy.gov.au/w/index.php/HMAS_Stuart_%28I%29 |archive-date=8 May 2009 |url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

'''Force C''' – Commanded by Vice-Admiral Sir [[Henry Pridham-Wippell]].

''1st Battle Squadron''
* 2 battleships: {{HMS|Malaya||2}}, and {{HMS|Royal Sovereign|05|2}}.
* 1 aircraft carrier: {{HMS|Eagle|1918|2}}.
* 10 destroyers:   {{HMS|Hyperion|H97|2}}, {{HMS|Hostile|H55|2}}, {{HMS|Hasty|H24|2}}, {{HMS|Ilex|D61|2}}, {{HMS|Dainty|H53|2}}, {{HMS|Defender|H07|2}}, {{HMS|Juno|F46|2}}, {{HMS|Janus|F53|2}}, {{HMAS|Vampire|D68|6}},&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/w/index.php/HMAS_Vampire_%28I%29 |title=HMAS Vampire (I) |accessdate=23 August 2008 |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090508053541/http://www.navy.gov.au/w/index.php/HMAS_Vampire_%28I%29 |archive-date=8 May 2009 |url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt; and {{HMAS|Voyager|D31|6}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/w/index.php/HMAS_Voyager_%28I%29 |title=HMAS Voyager (I) |accessdate=23 August 2008 |publisher=Royal Australian Navy |archive-url=https://web.archive.org/web/20090508053423/http://www.navy.gov.au/w/index.php/HMAS_Voyager_%28I%29 |archive-date=8 May 2009 |url-status = dead}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The destroyer {{HMS|Escort|H66|6}} was sunk in the Western Mediterranean where Force H was providing a feint and demonstration against Sardinia to distract the Italian fleet from the sailing of the Allied convoys. She was torpedoed on 11 July by the Italian submarine [[Marconi-class submarine#Guglielmo Marconi|''Guglielmo Marconi'']] during Force H's return passage.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.awm.gov.au/collection/RCDIG1070207/ G. Hermon Gill "Royal Australian Navy, 1939–1942"] (1957)&lt;/ref&gt;

===Regia Marina===
[[File:Flag of Italy (1861-1946) crowned.svg|40px|border|Kingdom of Italy]]

Italian force commanded by Vice Admiral [[Inigo Campioni]].
{{ship|Italian cruiser|Pola||2}} (F)

'''Convoy Close Escort'''

'''2nd Light Cruiser Division'''
* [[Italian cruiser Giovanni delle Bande Nere|''Giovanni delle Bande Nere'']]
* [[Italian cruiser Bartolomeo Colleoni|''Bartolomeo Colleoni'']]

'''10th Destroyer Squadron'''
* [[Italian destroyer Maestrale|''Maestrale'']]
* [[Italian destroyer Libeccio|''Libeccio'']]
* [[Italian destroyer Grecale|''Grecale'']]
* [[Italian destroyer Scirocco|''Scirocco'']]

'''14th Destroyer Squadron'''
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Ugolino Vivaldi||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Antonio da Noli||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Leone Pancaldo||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Luca Tarigo||2}}

Torpedo Boats – {{ship|Italian destroyer|Rosolino Pilo||2}}, {{ship|Italian destroyer|Giuseppe Missori||2}}

'''1st Squadron'''

[[Angelo Iachino|Admiral Angelo Iachino]] – Commander

'''5th Battleship Division'''
* {{ship|Italian battleship|Giulio Cesare||2}}
* {{ship|Italian battleship|Conte di Cavour||2}} (F)

'''4th (Light) Cruiser Division'''
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Alberico da Barbiano||2}}
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Alberto di Giussano||2}}
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Luigi Cadorna||2}}
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Armando Diaz||2}}

'''8th (Light) Cruiser Division'''
Vice-Admiral [[Antonio Legnani]] – Division Commander
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Duca degli Abruzzi||2}}
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Giuseppe Garibaldi|1936|2}}
* 
'''7th Destroyer Squadron'''
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Freccia|1930|2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Saetta||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Dardo|1930|2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Strale|1931|2}}

'''8th Destroyer Squadron'''
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Folgore||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Fulmine|1931|2}} 
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Baleno||2}} 
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Lampo|1931|2}}

'''15th Destroyer Squadron'''
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Antonio Pigafetta||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Nicolò Zeno||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Alvise Da Mosto||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Giovanni da Verrazzano||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Lanzerotto Malocello||2}}

'''16th Destroyer Squadron'''
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Nicoloso da Recco||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Antoniotto Usodimare||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Luca Tarigo||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Emanuele Pessagno||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Sestri Ponente||2}}{{dubious|date=November 2017}}

'''2nd Squadron'''

(Admiral [[Riccardo Paladini]]) – Commander

'''1st (Heavy) Cruiser Division'''
Vice-Admiral Matteucci – Division Commander
* ''[[Italian cruiser Zara|Zara]]''
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Gorizia||2}} 
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Fiume||2}} (F)

'''3rd (Heavy) Cruiser Division'''
Vice-Admiral [[Carlo Cattaneo (admiral)|Carlo Cattaneo]] – Division Commander
* [[Italian cruiser Pola|''Pola'']]
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Trento||2}}
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Trieste||2}} (F)
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Bolzano||2}}

'''7th (Light) Cruiser Division'''
Vice-Admiral [[Luigi Sansonetti]] – Division Commander
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Emanuele Filiberto Duca d'Aosta||2}}
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Muzio Attendolo||2}}
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Raimondo Montecuccoli||2}}
* {{ship|Italian cruiser|Eugenio di Savoia||2}}

9th Destroyer Squadron
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Vittorio Alfieri||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Alfredo Oriani||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Giosuè Carducci||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Vincenzo Gioberti||2}}

11th Destroyer Squadron
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Artigliere|1937|2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Camicia Nera||2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Aviere|1937|2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Geniere|1938|2}}

'''12th Destroyer Squadron'''
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Lanciere|1938|2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Carabiniere|1938|2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Corazziere|1938|2}}
* {{ship|Italian destroyer|Ascari||2}}

==Notes==
{{Reflist|group=Note}}

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==Sources==
* Green, Jack &amp; Massignani, Alessandro (1998). ''The Naval War in the Mediterranean, 1940–1943'', Chatam Publishing, London. {{ISBN|1-885119-61-5}}
* Jordan, John (2008). ''Warship 2008''. Conway maritime press, p.&amp;nbsp;34. {{ISBN|1-84486-062-0}}
* Miller, Nathan: ''War at Sea:  A Naval History of World War II'', Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1995. {{ISBN|0-19-511038-2}} (Pbk.).
* {{Cite book
| last      = O'Hara
| first     = Vincent P.
| year      = 2009
| title     = Struggle for the Middle Sea:  The Great Navies at War in the Mediterranean Theater, 1940–1945
| publisher = Naval Institute Press
| location  = [[Annapolis, Maryland]]
| isbn      = 978-1-59114-648-3
}}

==External links==
* [http://www.naval-history.net Naval-History.Net]
* [http://digilander.libero.it/planciacomando/WW2/stilo1.htm Battaglia di Punta Stilo] – Plancia di Commando
* [http://www.ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/LondonGazette/38273.pdf Despatch by Admiral Sir Andrew B. Cunningham]
* [http://www.navweaps.com/.../OOB_WWII_Punto-Stilo_Calabria.htm Order of Battle – Battle off Punto Stilo/Calabria, 9 July 1940]{{Dead link|date=June 2019 |bot=InternetArchiveBot |fix-attempted=yes }}

{{Coord|37|40|N|17|20|E|type:event|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Calabria, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1940]]
[[Category:1940 in Italy]]
[[Category:Calabria]]
[[Category:Malta Convoys]]
[[Category:Battle of the Mediterranean]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Australia]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]
[[Category:Mediterranean convoys of World War II]]
[[Category:July 1940 events]]</text><sha1>hlpf7s5xhb5cu5osnkn4dlbd66vja33</sha1></revision></page>