<page><title>Battle of Cape Spartivento</title><ns>0</ns><id>840266</id><revision><id>962648946</id><parentid>960573280</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-15T07:58:55Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Lyndaship</username><id>26830857</id></contributor><minor /><comment>link, replaced: Lanciere|1937 → Lanciere|1938 (2)</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="14083" xml:space="preserve">{{short description|Naval battle during the Battle of the Mediterranean}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2017}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Cape Spartivento
| partof      = the [[Battle of the Mediterranean]] of the [[Second World War]]
|image=[[File:RNBolzano-Teulada.jpg|300px]]&lt;br&gt;[[File:HMS Ark Royal attack.jpg|300px]]
|caption=Top: Italian heavy cruiser ''Bolzano'' during the battle.&lt;br&gt;Bottom: British aircraft carrier ''Ark Royal'' straddled by enemy bombs
|date=27 November 1940
|place=[[Mediterranean Sea]], near [[Sardinia]], [[Italy]]
|coordinates={{coord|38|25|39|N|8|51|57|E|display=inline}}
|result= Inconclusive
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[James Somerville (admiral)|James Somerville]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Inigo Campioni]]
|strength1=1 carrier&lt;br /&gt;1 battleship&lt;br /&gt;1 battlecruiser&lt;br /&gt;1 heavy cruiser&lt;br /&gt;5 light cruisers&lt;br /&gt;1 anti-aircraft cruiser&lt;br /&gt;14 destroyers&lt;br /&gt;4 corvettes&lt;br /&gt;4 freighters
|strength2=2 battleships&lt;br /&gt;6 heavy cruisers&lt;br /&gt;14 destroyers
|casualties1=7 killed&lt;br /&gt;1 heavy cruiser damaged&lt;br /&gt;1 light cruiser slightly damaged
|casualties2=1 destroyer damaged&lt;br /&gt;1 heavy cruiser slightly damaged
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Mediterranean Campaign}}
}}

The '''Battle of Cape Spartivento''', known as the '''Battle of Cape Teulada''' in Italy, was a [[naval battle]] during the [[Battle of the Mediterranean]] in the [[World War II|Second World War]], fought between naval forces of the [[Royal Navy]] and the [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italian]] ''[[Regia Marina]]'' on 27 November 1940.

==Origins==
On the night of 11 November 1940, the British incapacitated or destroyed half of the Italian fleet's battleships in a daring aerial assault as they lay at rest at [[Taranto]]. Until then, the Italians had left their capital ships in harbour, hoping its mere presence as a [[fleet in being]] would deter British shipping through the area, though they would not decline battle if given the opportunity.&lt;ref name= int&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 116&lt;/ref&gt;

Six days later, on the night of 17 November, an Italian force consisting of two [[battleship]]s ({{Ship|Italian battleship|Vittorio Veneto||2}} and {{Ship|Italian battleship|Giulio Cesare||2}}) and a number of supporting units attempted to intercept two British [[aircraft carrier]]s, {{HMS|Ark Royal|91|6}} and {{HMS|Argus|I49|2}} and their cruiser escorts, who were ''en route'' to [[Malta]] in an attempt to provide planes to reinforce that island's defenses ([[Operation White]]). The British were warned of their approach and immediately turned about and returned to [[Gibraltar]], launching their aircraft (two [[Blackburn Skua]]s and 12 [[Hawker Hurricane]]s) prematurely. One Skua and eight Hurricanes were lost at sea, as they ran out of fuel well before arriving at their destination, with the loss of seven airmen.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 115&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Shores, et al. 1999 pp. 86-88&lt;/ref&gt;

The Italians' success in disrupting the reinforcement of Malta cast serious doubt upon British plans to send a further convoy to supply the island ([[Operation Collar (Convoy)|Operation Collar]]). However, the convoy was attempted, with increased support, including ships from Gibraltar-based [[Force H]] and Force D out of [[Alexandria]]. The convoy was spotted by the Italian intelligence service, and once again the Italian fleet sailed out to intercept it.&lt;ref name=int/&gt; The first Italian naval unit to make visual contact with the convoy was the torpedo boat {{ship|Italian torpedo boat|Sirio|1935|2}} on the night of 26 November. After launching two torpedoes from long range, which missed their target, ''Sirio'' reported seven enemy warships heading to the east.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 117&lt;/ref&gt;

==Battle==
The British, aware of the Italian fleet's movements, sent their forces north to intercept them before they could come anywhere near the cargo ships. At 09:45 on 27 November, an [[IMAM Ro.43]] reconnaissance [[floatplane]] from the heavy cruiser ''Bolzano'' discovered a British squadron steaming to the east, {{convert|17|nmi|lk=on|abbr=on}} north of [[Chetaïbi]].&lt;ref&gt;Shores, Cull and Malizia, p. 93&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Mattesini, Francesco (2000). ''La battaglia di Capo Teulada: 27-28 novembre 1940''. Ufficio storico della Marina Militare, p. 114. {{in lang|it}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Shortly after, at 9:56, Somerville received the report of his own aircraft from the carrier HMS ''Ark Royal'' about the presence of five cruisers and five destroyers, and assumed that these were Italian units closing for battle. Force D had not yet arrived from Alexandria and the British were outgunned, but 15&amp;nbsp;minutes later, Force D was spotted and the tables turned.&lt;ref name=admin&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 118&lt;/ref&gt; The two forces were fairly even; although the Italian ships possessed both longer-ranged and larger guns, the British had an aircraft carrier, which had shown several advantages over the battleship at Taranto. However, the Italian admiral [[Inigo Campioni]] had been given orders to avoid combat unless it was heavily in his favour, so a decisive battle was out of the question.&lt;ref name=int/&gt;&lt;ref name=contact&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 119&lt;/ref&gt;

Admiral Somerville deployed his forces into two main groups, with five [[cruiser]]s under Rear Admiral [[Lancelot Holland]] in front and two battleships and seven [[destroyer]]s in a second group following to the south. Meanwhile, and even further to the south, ''Ark Royal'' was preparing to launch its complement of [[Fairey Swordfish]]. The Italians had organized their fleet into three groups, two composed of the six heavy cruisers and seven of the destroyers and a third group of the two battleships and another seven escorting destroyers bringing up the rear. At 12:07, after a report received from the cruiser {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Gorizia||2}}{{'}}s floatplane, Campioni realized the closeness in strengths of the two forces and in accordance with his orders commanded the cruiser groups to re-form on the battleships and prepare to depart. However, by this point, the lead cruiser formation had already angled toward the British and was beginning to engage them in battle.&lt;ref name=contact/&gt;

At 12:22, the lead groups of both cruiser forces came into range and {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Fiume||2}} opened fire at {{convert|23500|m|yd|0}}. Rapid fire between the two forces continued as the distance between them closed, but as the range shortened Italian firepower began to put pressure on the outgunned British. The arrival of the battleship {{HMS|Ramillies|07|6}} on the British side helped to even the odds, but she was too slow to maintain formation and dropped out of battle after a few salvoes at 12:26. Four minutes later, Vice Admiral [[Angelo Iachino]], commander of the Italian cruiser group, received orders to disengage, although the battle had swung slightly in their favour. Iachino ordered an increase in speed to {{convert|30|kn|lk=on|abbr=on}}, laid smoke and started to withdraw.

At this time, the Italian destroyer {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Lanciere|1938|2}} was hit by a broadside from {{HMS|Manchester|15|6}} and seriously damaged, although she was towed to port after the battle. The heavy cruiser {{HMS|Berwick|65|6}} was hit at 12:22 by a single 203&amp;nbsp;mm (8&amp;nbsp;in) shell, which knocked out her "Y" turret, killed seven men, wounded nine others and ignited a fire that took an hour to subdue. A second hit at 12:35 destroyed the after breaker (electrical switchboard) room and cut power to the ship's aft section, including the remaining aft turret.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;O'Hara, 2009 pp. 70-71&lt;/ref&gt; Most sources believe that the first hit was scored by an Italian heavy cruiser from the 1º Cruiser Division, either from ''Fiume'' or {{ship|Italian cruiser|Pola||2}},&lt;ref&gt;Stern 2015, p. 60&lt;/ref&gt; while the second round came from the 3º Cruiser Division, either from {{ship|Italian cruiser|Trieste||2}} or {{ship|Italian cruiser|Trento||2}}, at the time the only Italian warships within range.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt;

For the next few minutes, the tables turned in favour of the British when the [[battlecruiser]] {{HMS|Renown|1916|6}} closed the distance on the Italian cruisers, and straddled ''Trieste'' with two salvoes. The Italian cruiser was hit by splinters.&lt;ref&gt;Stern, 2015, p. 62&lt;/ref&gt;  This advantage was soon negated, however, when at 13:00, ''Vittorio Veneto'' opened fire from {{convert|27000|m|yd|-3}}. ''Vittorio Veneto'' fired 19 rounds in seven salvoes from long range and that was enough for the now outgunned British cruisers, which turned back at the fourth salvo. In fact, as giant water-spouts erupted around ''Berwick'' and ''Manchester'', Holland ordered smoke, and his ships fled southeast to close with ''Renown''.&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara, 2009 p. 72&lt;/ref&gt; ''Manchester'' was holed by splinters from ''Vittorio Veneto''&lt;nowiki/&gt;'s rounds.&lt;ref&gt;Stern, 2015, p. 63&lt;/ref&gt; Both forces withdrew, the battle lasting a total of 54 minutes and causing little damage to either side.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 121-122&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.regiamarina.net/detail_text_with_list.asp?nid=37&amp;lid=1&amp;cid=4 Battle of Cape Teulada, by Cristiano D'Adamo]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Bragadin, Marc'Antonio (1957). ''The Italian Navy in WWII''. United States Naval Institute, p. 52. {{ISBN|0-405-13031-7}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
After the battle [[Winston Churchill]] wanted Somerville to be replaced, having questioned the admiral's offensive spirit ever since his objections to attacking the French at [[Mers-el-Kébir]]. However, a board of inquiry exonerated Somerville, who enjoyed the strong support of several fellow admirals. As for Campioni, although he had a mandate to be conservative, he had presided over the loss of Italy's best opportunity to deal the British a sharp setback in a fleet action. His days of command at sea were numbered. As Iachino remarked, "the use of these ships, which constituted at that moment nearly all of our fleet's effective units after the blow at Taranto, was decided by [[Supermarina]] mainly for reasons of morale, and to demonstrate that our combative spirit remained intact."&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara, 2009 p. 73&lt;/ref&gt;

==Popular culture==
The battle features in the 1941 Italian film ''[[The White Ship (1941 film)|The White Ship]]'' directed by [[Roberto Rossellini]].&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.archiviodelcinemaitaliano.it/index.php/scheda.html?codice=SV%5C%20413|title=Archivio del Cinema Italiano|last=|first=|date=|website=www.archiviodelcinemaitaliano.it|language=Italian|archive-url=|archive-date=|access-date=2019-05-24}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Order of battle==
{{unreferenced section|date=November 2017}}

===''Regia Marina''===
[[File:Flag of Italy (1861-1946) crowned.svg|50px|Kingdom of Italy]]
* Admiral [[Angelo Iachino]]
** 6 [[heavy cruiser]]s: {{ship|Italian cruiser|Bolzano||2}}, {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Fiume||2}}, {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Gorizia||2}}, {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Pola||2}}, {{ship|Italian cruiser|Trieste||2}} (''slightly damaged''), {{ship|Italian cruiser|Trento||2}}.
** 7 [[destroyer]]s: ''Ascari'', ''Carabiniere'', {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Lanciere|1938|2}} (''damaged''), ''Oriani'', ''Alfieri'', ''Carducci'', ''Gioberti''
* Admiral [[Inigo Campioni]]
** 2 [[battleship]]s: {{Ship|Italian battleship|Vittorio Veneto||2}}, {{Ship|Italian battleship|Giulio Cesare||2}}
** 7 destroyers: ''Alpino'', ''Bersagliere'', ''Fuciliere'', ''Granatiere'', {{ship|Italian destroyer|Dardo|1930|2}}, ''Freccia'', ''Saetta''

===Royal Navy===
[[File:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|border|60px|Royal Navy Ensign]]
* Admiral [[Lancelot Holland]] '''Force F'''
** 1 heavy cruiser: {{HMS|Berwick|65|2}} (''damaged'')
** 4 [[light cruiser]]s: {{HMS|Manchester|15|2}} (''slightly damaged''), {{HMS|Newcastle|C76|2}}, {{HMS|Sheffield|C24|2}}, {{HMS|Southampton|83|2}}
* Admiral Sir [[James Somerville]] [[Force B]]
** 1 battleship: {{HMS|Ramillies|07|2}}
** 1 [[battlecruiser]]: {{HMS|Renown|1916|2}}
** 9 destroyers: {{HMS|Encounter|H10|2}}, {{HMS|Faulknor|H62|2}}, {{HMS|Firedrake|H79|2}}, {{HMS|Forester|H74|2}}, {{HMS|Fury|H76|2}}, {{HMS|Gallant|H59|2}}, {{HMS|Greyhound|H05|2}}, {{HMS|Griffin|H31|2}}, {{HMS|Hereward|H93|2}}
* not entered in battle
** 1 [[aircraft carrier]]: {{HMS|Ark Royal|91|2}} (carrying 12 fighters, 12 dive bombers, 30 torpedo planes)
** 2 destroyers: {{HMS|Jaguar|F34|2}}, {{HMS|Kelvin|F37|2}}
* escort and convoy
** 1 anti-aircraft cruiser: {{HMS|Coventry|D43|2}}
** 1 light cruiser: {{HMS|Despatch|D30|2}}
** 3 destroyers: {{HMS|Duncan|D99|2}}, {{HMS|Hotspur|H01|2}}, {{HMS|Wishart|D67|2}}
** 4 corvettes: {{HMS|Gloxinia|K22|2}}, {{HMS|Hyacinth|K84|2}}, {{HMS|Peony|K40|2}}, {{HMS|Salvia|K97|2}}
** 4 freighters including {{SS|Clan Forbes|1938|2}}, {{SS|Clan Fraser|1938|2}}, {{SS|New Zealand Star||2}}

==See also==
{{Commons category-inline|Battle of Cape Spartivento}}

==Notes==
{{reflist|2}}

==References and external links==
* Green, Jack &amp; Massignani, Alessandro. ''The Naval War in the Mediterranean, 1940-1943'', Chatham Publishing, London 1998. {{ISBN|1-885119-61-5}}
* O'Hara, Vincent P.: ''Struggle for the Middle Sea'', Naval Institute Press, Annapolis, Maryland, 2009. {{ISBN|978-1-59114-648-3}}.
* Shores, Cull and Malizia. ''Malta: The Hurricane Years (1940–41).'' Grub Street, London, 1999. {{ISBN|0-948817-06-2}}
* Stern, Robert C. (2015). ''Big Gun Battles: Warship Duels of the Second World War''. Seaforth Publishing. {{ISBN|1473849691}}.
* [http://www.regiamarina.net/detail_text_with_list.asp?nid=37&amp;lid=1&amp;cid=1 The Battle of Cape Teulada]
* [http://digilander.libero.it/planciacomando/WW2/teulada1.htm Battaglia di Capo Teulada] - Plancia di Commando

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cape Spartivento, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Battle of the Mediterranean]]
[[Category:Malta Convoys]]
[[Category:1940 in Italy]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]
[[Category:November 1940 events]]</text><sha1>1i76mdp703608j8vhrnw05pcz3cp0dm</sha1></revision></page>