<page><title>Battle of Cape Matapan</title><ns>0</ns><id>203437</id><revision><id>965924072</id><parentid>965268081</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-04T07:23:53Z</timestamp><contributor><ip>178.16.13.196</ip></contributor><comment>/* Order of battle */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="29614" xml:space="preserve">{{For|the 18th-century battle|Battle of Matapan}}
{{EngvarB|date=March 2016}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2019}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Battle of Cape Matapan
| partof      = the [[Battle of the Mediterranean]] 
| image       = www2mR130BMatapan.GIF
| image_size  = 300
| caption     = Map of the battle
| date        = 27–29 March 1941
| place       = Off [[Cape Matapan]], [[Mediterranean Sea]]
| coordinates = {{coord|35|20|52.82|N|20|57|40.43|E|display=inline|region:GR_type:waterbody}}
| result      = Decisive Allied victory
| combatant1  = {{flagcountry|United Kingdom}} &lt;br&gt; {{flagcountry|Australia}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
| commander1  = {{flagdeco|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Andrew Cunningham]]
| commander2  = {{flagdeco|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Angelo Iachino]]
| strength1   = 1 aircraft carrier &lt;br&gt; 3 battleships &lt;br&gt; 7 light cruisers &lt;br&gt; 17 destroyers 
| strength2   = 1 battleship &lt;br&gt; 6 heavy cruisers &lt;br&gt; 2 light cruisers &lt;br&gt; 17 destroyers
| casualties1 = 3 killed &lt;br&gt; 4 light cruisers damaged &lt;br&gt; 1 aircraft destroyed
| casualties2 = 2,300 killed &lt;br&gt; 1,015 captured &lt;br&gt; 3 heavy cruisers sunk &lt;br&gt; 2 destroyers sunk &lt;br&gt; 1 battleship damaged &lt;br&gt; 1 destroyer damaged
| campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Mediterranean Campaign}}
}}

The '''Battle of Cape Matapan ''' ({{lang-el|Ναυμαχία του Ταινάρου}}) was a [[World War II|Second World War]] [[naval battle|naval engagement]] between [[British Empire|British Imperial]] and Axis forces, fought from 27–29 March 1941. The [[Cape Matapan|cape]] is on the south-west coast of the [[Peloponnesus|Peloponnesian]] peninsula of [[Greece]]. 

Following the interception of Italian signals by the [[Government Code and Cypher School]] (GC&amp;CS) at [[Bletchley Park]],&lt;ref name="Batey 2011 79–92"&gt;{{cite book |last=Batey |first=Mavis |editor-first=Michael |editor-last=Smith |title=The Bletchley Park Codebreakers |publisher=Biteback Publishing |year=2011 |pages=79–92 |chapter=Chapter 6: Breaking Italian Naval Enigma|isbn=978-1849540780 }}&lt;/ref&gt; ships of the [[Royal Navy]] and [[Royal Australian Navy]], under the command of the Royal Navy's Admiral [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Sir Andrew Cunningham]], intercepted and sank or severely damaged several ships of the Italian ''[[Regia Marina]]'' under [[Squadron vice-admiral|Squadron-Vice-Admiral]] [[Angelo Iachino]]. The opening actions of the battle are also known in Italy as the '''Battle of Gaudo'''.

==Background==
In late March 1941, as British ships of the Mediterranean Fleet covered troop movements to Greece, [[Mavis Batey]], a cryptographer at [[Ultra|Bletchley Park]], made a breakthrough, reading the [[Cryptanalysis of the Enigma#Italian naval Enigma|Italian naval Enigma]] for the first time. The first message, the cryptic "Today’s the day minus three,"&lt;ref name=mavis&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/military-obituaries/special-forces-obituaries/10447712/Mavis-Batey-obituary.html|title=Mavis Batey – obituary|work=Daily Telegraph|date=13 November 2013|accessdate=14 November 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt; was followed three days later by a second message reporting the sailing of an Italian battle fleet comprising one [[battleship]], six [[Heavy cruiser|heavy]] and two [[light cruiser]]s, plus [[destroyer]]s to attack the merchant convoys supplying British forces.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.bletchleypark.org.uk/news/docview.rhtm/666218 |title=Spanish Enigma Welcomed To Bletchley Park |publisher=Bletchley Park |date=5 July 2012 |accessdate=13 August 2012 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20121002234331/http://www.bletchleypark.org.uk/news/docview.rhtm/666218 |archivedate=2 October 2012 }}&lt;/ref&gt; As always with Enigma, the intelligence breakthrough was concealed from the Italians by ensuring there was a plausible reason for the Allies to have detected and intercepted their fleet. In this case, it was a carefully directed [[Reconnaissance aircraft|reconnaissance plane]].&lt;ref&gt;See the report in the official Admiralty publication of 1943, ''East of Malta, West of Suez:'' The Admiralty Account of the Naval War in the Mediterranean (London, His Majesty's Stationery Office, 1943), where the detection of the Italian force is credited to "one of ''Formidable's'' aircraft on reconnaissance." (p. 56)&lt;/ref&gt;

As a further deception, Admiral Cunningham made a surreptitious exit after dark from a golf club in Alexandria to avoid being seen boarding his [[flagship]], the battleship {{HMS|Warspite|03|6}}. He had made a point of arriving at the club the same afternoon with his suitcase as if for an overnight stay, and spent time on the golf course within sight of the Japanese consul.&lt;ref name="Batey 2011 79–92"/&gt; An evening party on his flagship was advertised for that night but was never meant to take place.

At the same time, there was a failure of intelligence on the [[Axis powers of World War II|Axis]] side. The Italians had been wrongly informed by the Germans that the [[Mediterranean Fleet (United Kingdom)|Mediterranean Fleet]] had only one operational battleship and no aircraft carriers.  In fact the Royal Navy had three battleships, while the damaged British [[aircraft carrier]] [[HMS Illustrious (87)|''Illustrious'']] had been replaced by [[HMS Formidable (67)|HMS ''Formidable'']].&lt;ref&gt;Admiralty: ''East of Malta, West of Suez'' (London, His Majesty's Stationery Office, 1943) p. 55&lt;/ref&gt;

==Prelude==
===Opposing forces===
The [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] force was the British [[Mediterranean]] fleet, consisting of the aircraft carrier HMS ''Formidable'' and the battleships {{HMS|Barham|04|6}}, {{HMS|Valiant|1914|2}}, and ''Warspite''. The main fleet was accompanied by the [[10th Destroyer Flotilla]] ({{HMS|Greyhound|H05|6}} and {{HMS|Griffin|H31|2}}, and {{HMAS|Stuart|D-00/100|6}}, commanded by Commander [[Hector Waller|"Hec" Waller]], RAN), and the [[14th Destroyer Flotilla]] ({{HMS|Jervis|F00|6}}, {{HMS|Janus|F53|2}}, {{HMS|Mohawk|F31|2}}, and {{HMS|Nubian|F36|2}}, commanded by [[Philip Mack]]); also present were {{HMS|Hotspur|H01|6}} and {{HMS|Havock|H43|2}}. [[Force B]], under Admiral Sir [[Henry Pridham-Wippell]], consisted of the British light cruisers {{HMS|Ajax|22|6}}, {{HMS|Gloucester|C62|2}}, and {{HMS|Orion|85|2}}, the Australian light cruiser {{HMAS|Perth|D29|6}}, and the British destroyers {{HMS|Hasty|H24|6}}, {{HMS|Hereward|H93|2}}, and {{HMS|Ilex|D61|2}}. The Australian {{HMAS|Vendetta|D69|6}} had returned to [[Alexandria]]. Allied warships attached to [[convoy]]s were available: {{HMS|Defender|H07|6}}, {{HMS|Jaguar|F34|2}}, and {{HMS|Juno|F46|2}} waited in the [[Cythera (island)|Kithira]] Channel and {{HMS|Decoy|H75|6}}, {{HMS|Carlisle|D67|2}}, {{HMS|Calcutta|D82|2}}, and {{HMS|Bonaventure|31|2}} and {{HMAS|Vampire|D68|6}} were nearby.

The Italian fleet was led by Iachino's flagship, the modern battleship {{Ship|Italian battleship|Vittorio Veneto||2}}, screened by destroyers ''Alpino'', ''Bersagliere'', ''Fuciliere'', and ''Granatiere'' of the 13th Flotilla. The fleet also included most of the Italian heavy cruiser force: {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Zara||2}}, {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Fiume||2}}, and {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Pola||2}}, accompanied by four destroyers (''[[Oriani class destroyer#Ships|Alfredo Oriani]]'', {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Giosuè Carducci||2}}, ''Vincenzo Gioberti'', and {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Vittorio Alfieri||2}}) of the 9th Flotilla; and ''[[Italian cruiser Trieste|Trieste]]'', ''[[Italian cruiser Trento|Trento]]'', and ''[[Italian cruiser Bolzano|Bolzano]]'', accompanied by three destroyers (''Ascari'', ''Corazziere'', and ''Carabiniere'') of the 12th Flotilla. Joining them were the light cruisers {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Duca degli Abruzzi||2}} and {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Giuseppe Garibaldi|1936|2}} (8th division) and two destroyers of the 16th Flotilla (''Emanuele Pessagno'' and ''Nicoloso de Recco'') from [[Brindisi]].&lt;ref&gt;Anthony M. Scalzo (2001) [http://www.historynet.com/battle-of-cape-matapan-world-war-ii-italian-naval-massacre.htm/2 – Battle of cape Matapan (2)] history.net "Originally published by World War II magazine"&lt;/ref&gt; Significantly, none of the Italian ships had radar, unlike several of the Allied ships.&lt;ref name=pola/&gt;

==Battle==
On 27 March, Vice-Admiral Pridham-Wippell—with the cruisers ''Ajax'', ''Gloucester'', ''Orion'' and ''Perth'' and a number of destroyers—sailed from Greek waters for a position south of Crete. Admiral Cunningham with ''Formidable'', ''Warspite'', ''Barham'' and ''Valiant'' left Alexandria on the same day to meet the cruisers.&lt;ref name=spotted/&gt;

The Italian Fleet was spotted by a [[Short Sunderland|Sunderland]] [[flying boat]] at 12:00, depriving Iachino of any advantage of surprise. The Italian admiral also learned that ''Formidable'' was at sea, thanks to the decryption team aboard ''Vittorio Veneto''. Nevertheless, after some discussion, the Italian headquarters decided to go ahead with the operation, to show the Germans their will to fight and confidence in the higher speed of their warships.&lt;ref name=spotted&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 148–150&lt;/ref&gt;

===Action off Gavdos===
[[Image:Veneto guns at Gaudos.jpg|thumb|The battleship ''Vittorio Veneto'' firing upon the Allied cruisers during the action off Gavdos]]

On 28 March, an [[IMAM Ro.43]] [[floatplane]] launched by ''Vittorio Veneto'' spotted the British cruiser squadron at 06:35. At 07:55, the ''Trento'' group encountered Admiral Pridham-Wippell's cruiser group south of the Greek island of [[Gavdos]]. The British squadron was heading to the south-east. Thinking they were attempting to run from their larger ships, the Italians gave chase, opening fire at 08:12 from {{convert|24000|yd|m|abbr=on}}. The three heavy cruisers fired repeatedly until 08:55, with ''Trieste'' firing 132 armour piercing rounds, ''Trento'' firing 204 armour-piercing and 10 explosive shells and ''Bolzano'' firing another 189 armour piercing shells, but the Italians experienced trouble with their [[rangefinder|rangefinding]] equipment and scored no significant hits.&lt;ref name=GV/&gt; HMS ''Gloucester'' fired three salvos in return. These fell short but did cause the Italians to make a course change.&lt;ref name=GV/&gt;&lt;ref name="Fraccaroli, Aldo 2001"&gt;Fraccaroli, Aldo: ''Lo combattimento navale di Gaudo'', Storia militare magazine jan 2001, Albertelli editions, Parma&lt;/ref&gt;

As they had not reduced the distance after an hour of pursuit, the Italian cruisers broke off the chase, turning to the north-west on a course to rejoin ''Vittorio Veneto''. The Allied ships changed course in turn, following the Italian cruisers at extreme range. Iachino let them come on in hopes of luring the British cruisers into the range of ''Vittorio Veneto''{{'}}s guns.&lt;ref name=GV/&gt;

An officer on ''Orion''{{'}}s bridge remarked to a companion, "What's that battleship over there? I thought ours were miles away." The Italians eavesdropped on ''Orion''{{'}}s signal that she had sighted an unknown unit and was going to investigate.&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara, 2009 p. 89&lt;/ref&gt; At 10:55, ''Vittorio Veneto'' joined the Italian cruisers and immediately opened fire on the shadowing Allied cruisers. She fired 94 rounds in 29 salvos from a distance of {{convert|25000|yd|m|abbr=on}}, all well aimed, but again with an excessive dispersal of her salvos. (Another 11 rounds got jammed in the barrels.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 151–152&lt;/ref&gt;) The Allied cruisers, until then unaware of the presence of a battleship, withdrew, suffering slight damage from {{convert|381|mm|in|abbr=on}} shell splinters.&lt;ref name=GV&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 150–151&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=spl&gt;''E fecero tutti il loro dovere:Cause ed effetti'', by Enrico Cernuschi. Rivista Maritima, November 2006 {{in lang|it}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=lif/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.perthone.com/pmat.html Battle of Matapan] from [http://www.perthone.com/pmat.html "A Brief History of the Australian Cruiser HMAS Perth"]&lt;/ref&gt; A series of photographs taken from HMS ''Gloucester'' showing Italian salvos falling amongst Allied warships was published by [[Life (magazine)|''Life'' magazine]] on 16 June 1941.&lt;ref name=lif&gt;[https://books.google.com/books?id=kkwEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA32 "Matapan: British fleet won sea victory over Italians"]&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--HMS ''Gloucester'' was capable of holding the speed of the formation, despite a fault in the shaft which had previously reduced her speed to only 24 knots; despite this, she was able to make 30–31 knots. Therefore, after 20 minutes of pursuit, ''Veneto'' was dropped back to 26,000 metres (3,000 more than the start) and as the visibility was worsened by smokescreen and bad weather, she ceased to fire at the British ships, it being impossible to observe the fall of shot and with the British being faster than the Italian battleship. Just a few moments later, the Italians saw several biplanes closing. Initially they thought that they were CR.42s but they were British [[torpedo-bomber]]s, escorted by some [[Fairey Fulmar]]s.--&gt;

===Air attacks===
[[Image:Veneto sailing out of the battle area.jpg|thumb|''Vittorio Veneto'' withdraws from the battle area after being torpedoed by RN aircraft.]]
Cunningham's force, which had been attempting to rendezvous with Pridham-Wippell, launched an attack by [[Fairey Albacore]] [[torpedo bomber]]s from HMS ''Formidable'' at 09:38. They attacked ''Vittorio Veneto'' without direct effect, but the required manoeuvring made it difficult for the Italian ships to maintain their pursuit. The Italian ships fired 152, 100 and 90&amp;nbsp;mm guns and also 37, 20 and 13.2&amp;nbsp;mm guns when at close range, repelling the attack, while one of the two [[Junkers Ju 88]]s escorting the Italian fleet was shot down by a [[Fairey Fulmar]].&lt;ref name="Fraccaroli, Aldo 2001"/&gt; Iachino broke off the pursuit at 12:20, retiring towards his own air cover at [[Taranto]].&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 152–153&lt;/ref&gt;

A second aerial attack at 15:09 surprised the Italians; Lieutenant-Commander John Dalyell-Stead ([[Distinguished Service Order|DSO]]) was able to fly his Albacore to within {{convert|1094|yd|m}} of ''Vittorio Veneto'' before releasing a torpedo which hit her outer port propeller and caused {{convert|4000|LT|t|lk=on}} of flooding. Dalyell-Stead and his crew were killed when their aircraft was shot down by anti-aircraft fire from the battleship. The ship stopped while the damage was repaired, but she was able to get under way again at 16:42, making {{convert|19|kn|lk=on}}. Cunningham heard of the damage to ''Vittorio Veneto'', and started a pursuit.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 153&lt;/ref&gt;
[[File:Bolzano under air torpedo attack.jpg|thumb|[[Italian cruiser Bolzano|''Bolzano'']] under torpedo attack by Fairey Swordfish]]

A third attack by six Albacores and two [[Fairey Swordfish]] of [[826 NAS|826]] and [[828 NAS|828]] Naval Air Squadrons from ''Formidable'' and two Swordfish of [[815 NAS|815]] squadron from Crete took place between 19:36 and 19:50. Admiral Iachino deployed his ships in three columns and used smoke, searchlights, and a heavy barrage to protect ''Vittorio Veneto''. The tactics prevented further damage to the battleship, but one torpedo hit ''Pola'', which had nearly stopped to avoid running into ''Fiume'' and could not take any evasive action. This blow knocked out five boilers and the main steam line, causing ''Pola'' to lose electric power and drift to a stop.&lt;ref&gt;O'Hara, 2009 p. 91&lt;/ref&gt; The torpedo was apparently dropped by Lieutenant [[Michael Torrens-Spence|F.M.A. Torrens-Spence]].

Unaware of Cunningham's pursuit, a squadron of cruisers and destroyers was ordered to return and help ''Pola''. This squadron included ''Pola''{{'}}s [[sister ship]]s, ''Zara'' and ''Fiume''. The squadron did not start to return towards ''Pola'' until about an hour after the order had been given by Iachino, officially due to communication problems, while ''Vittorio Veneto'' and the other ships continued to Taranto.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 152–156&lt;/ref&gt;

===Night action===
At 20:15, ''Orion''{{'}}s radar picked up a ship six miles to port, apparently dead in the water; she was the crippled ''Pola''. The bulk of the Allied forces detected the Italian squadron on radar shortly after 22:00, and were able to close without being detected. The Italian ships had no radar and could not detect British ships by means other than sight; Italian thinking did not envisage night actions and their main gun batteries were not prepared for action. At 22:20 they spotted the Allied squadron, but thought them to be Italian ships. The battleships ''Barham'', ''Valiant'', and ''Warspite'' were able to close to {{convert|3800|yd|m|-2}} – point blank range for battleship guns – at which point they opened fire. The Allied searchlights (including those aboard ''Valiant'', under the command of a young [[Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh|Prince Philip]]&lt;ref&gt;Philip: How I Sunk Italian Cruisers, by Tom Sykes, The Daily Beast, The Royalist, 24 April 2012&lt;/ref&gt;) illuminated their enemy. Some British gunners witnessed cruiser main turrets flying dozens of metres into the air. After just three minutes, ''Fiume'' and ''Zara'' had been destroyed. ''Fiume'' sank at 23:30, while ''Zara'' was finished off by a torpedo from the destroyer HMS ''Jervis'' at 02:40 of 29 March.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 156–157&lt;/ref&gt;

Two Italian destroyers, ''Vittorio Alfieri'' and ''Giosuè Carducci'', were sunk in the first five minutes. The other two, ''Gioberti'' and ''Oriani'', managed to escape in a [[smoke screen]], the former with heavy damage, after being chased and fired at by the British destroyers ''Griffin'' and ''Greyhound''.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://conlapelleappesaaunchiodo.blogspot.com/search|title=Vincenzo Gioberti|last=Colombo|first=Lorenzo|date=13 March 2017|website=Con la pelle appesa a un chiodo|access-date=2018-06-07}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Sea Battles in Close-Up: World War 2|last=Stephen|first=Martin|publisher=Naval Institute Press|year=1988|isbn=0-87021-556-6|location=Annapolis, MD|pages=[https://archive.org/details/seabattlesinclos00mart/page/65 65–67]|url-access=registration|url=https://archive.org/details/seabattlesinclos00mart/page/65}}&lt;/ref&gt; Towing ''Pola'' to Alexandria as a prize was considered, but daylight was approaching, and it was thought that the danger of enemy air attack was too high.&lt;ref name=pola&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 157–159&lt;/ref&gt; British boarding parties seized a number of much-needed [[Breda Model 35|Breda]] anti-aircraft machine guns.&lt;ref&gt;Pack, S. W. C. (1961). ''The Battle of Matapan''. British Battles Series. MacMillan, p. 151&lt;/ref&gt; ''Pola''{{'}}s crew was taken off and she was sunk by torpedoes from the destroyers ''Jervis'' and ''Nubian'' shortly after 04:00. The only known Italian reaction after the shocking surprise was a fruitless torpedo charge by ''Oriani'' and ''Gioberti'' and the aimless fire of one of ''Zara''{{'}}s 40&amp;nbsp;mm guns in the direction of the British warships.&lt;ref name=pola/&gt;

The Allied ships took on survivors but left the scene in the morning, fearing Axis air strikes. Admiral Cunningham ordered a signal to be made on the Merchant Marine emergency band. This signal was received by the Italian High Command. It informed them that, due to the risk of air strikes, the Allied ships had ceased their rescue operations and granted safe passage to a hospital ship for rescue purposes. The location of the remaining survivors was broadcast, and the Italian hospital ship ''Gradisca'' came to recover them.&lt;ref name=pola/&gt; Allied casualties during the battle were a single torpedo bomber shot down by ''Vittorio Veneto''{{'}}s 90&amp;nbsp;mm (3.5-inch) anti-aircraft batteries, with the loss of the three-man crew. Italian losses were up to 2,303 sailors, most of them from ''Zara'' and ''Fiume''. The Allies rescued 1,015 survivors, while the Italians saved another 160.&lt;ref name=pola/&gt;

==Aftermath==
===Balance of naval power===
Matapan was Italy's greatest defeat at sea, subtracting from its order of battle a cruiser division. The British in the Mediterranean lost the heavy cruiser {{HMS|York|90|2}} and the new light cruiser ''Bonaventure'' in the same period (26–31 March 1941), but while the Royal Navy lost four heavy cruisers during the war (''York'', ''Exeter'', ''Cornwall'' and ''Dorsetshire'', the latter two in a single engagement), at Matapan the Regia Marina lost three in a night. That the Italians had sortied so far to the east established a potential threat that forced the British to keep their battleships ready to face another sortie during the operations off Greece and Crete.&lt;ref name="O'Hara, 2009 p. 98"&gt;O'Hara, 2009 p. 98&lt;/ref&gt;

After the defeat at Cape Matapan, the Italian Admiral Iachino wrote that the battle had

{{Quote|... the consequence of limiting for some time our operational activities, not for the serious moral effect of the losses, as the British believed, but because the operation revealed our inferiority in effective aero-naval cooperation and the backwardness of our night battle technology.|Iachino&lt;ref name="O'Hara, 2009 p. 98"/&gt;}}

The Italian fleet did not venture into the Eastern Mediterranean again until the [[Battle of Crete|fall of Crete]] two months later and it did not come out in full force before being surrendered to Admiral Cunningham at Malta.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.historynet.com/battle-of-cape-matapan-world-war-ii-italian-naval-massacre.htm]&lt;/ref&gt; Despite his impressive victory, Admiral Cunningham was somewhat disappointed with the failure of the destroyers to make contact with ''Vittorio Veneto''. The escape of the Italian battleship was, in the words of the British admiral, "much to be regretted".&lt;ref&gt;Brown, David (2002). ''The Royal Navy and the Mediterranean: November 1940 – December 1941''. Routledge, p. 76. {{ISBN|0-7146-5205-9}}&lt;/ref&gt;

===Bletchley Park (GC&amp;CS)===
For reasons of secrecy, code breakers at the GC&amp;CS were rarely informed of the operational effects of their work, but their impact on the Battle of Cape Matapan was an exception. A few weeks after the end of the battle, Admiral Cunningham dropped into [[Bletchley Park]] to congratulate '[[Dilwyn Knox|Dilly]] and his girls, with a positive impact on morale:&lt;ref name="Batey 2011 79–92"/&gt; Mavis Batey, one of the code breakers remembers: "Our sense of elation knew no bounds when Cunningham came down in person to congratulate us".&lt;ref name="Batey 2011 79–92"/&gt; [[John Henry Godfrey|Admiral John Godfrey]], the [[Naval Intelligence Division (UK)|Director of Naval Intelligence]], stated: "Tell Dilly that we have won a great victory in the Mediterranean and it is entirely due to him and his girls".&lt;ref name="Batey 2011 79–92"/&gt;

===Post war===
There is still controversy in Italy regarding the orders given by the Italian Admiral Angelo Iachino to the ''Zara'' division to recover the ''Pola'', when it was clear that an enemy battleship force was steaming from the opposite direction.&lt;ref name=pola/&gt;

{{Rquote|right| When Cunningham won at Matapan

By the grace of God and Dilly

He was the brains behind them all

And should ne'er be forgotten. Will he?|[[Dilly Knox]]&lt;ref name="Batey 2011 79–92"/&gt;}}

For decades after the end of the [[Second World War]], the involvement of the GC&amp;CS, as well as the code breaking methods used, were kept secret. A number of controversial theories were published before more complete accounts emerged after records were declassified in 1978. Only later, after [[Dilly's rodding method]] was demonstrated by Mavis Batey to the Admiral in charge of naval history, were Italian official records corrected.&lt;ref name="Batey 2011 79–92"/&gt; In 1966, [[H. Montgomery Hyde]] published a story alleging that a spy ([[codename]] [[Amy Elizabeth Thorpe|Cynthia]]) seduced [[Alberto Lais|Admiral Alberto Lais]] (the Italian [[naval attaché]] in [[Washington, D.C.]]) and that she obtained a [[codebook]] used by the British to defeat the Italians at Matapan. Hyde was found guilty of libelling the dead, but evidence of GC&amp;CS involvement was not made public at that time.&lt;ref name="Batey 2011 79–92"/&gt; In 1980, the [[BBC]] series ''Spy!'' included similar allegations about a spy called 'Cynthia' who obtained a codebook.&lt;ref name="Batey 2011 79–92"/&gt; In 1974, [[Frederick Winterbotham]] in ''The Ultra Secret'' falsely credited the decryption of ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' [[Enigma machine|Enigma]] traffic.&lt;ref name="Batey 2011 79–92"/&gt;

==Order of battle==
===Italy===
[[Image:Flag of Italy (1861-1946) crowned.svg|border|50px]]
* ''Ammiraglio di squadra''&lt;ref&gt;[[Squadron vice-admiral|Squadron Vice Admiral]].(equivalent to [[Vice Admiral]] for RN)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Angelo Iachino]]
** One [[battleship]]: ''Vittorio Veneto'' (damaged)
** Four destroyers (''13a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere''): {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Alpino|1938|2}}, {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Bersagliere|1938|2}}, {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Fuciliere|1938|2}}, {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Granatiere|1938|2}}
* ''Ammiraglio di divisione''&lt;ref&gt;Vice Admiral.(equivalent to [[Rear Admiral]] for RN)&lt;/ref&gt; [[Antonio Legnani]]
** Two [[light cruiser]]s (''8a Divisione Incrociatori''): ''Duca degli Abruzzi'', ''Giuseppe Garibaldi''
** Two destroyers (''16a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere''): {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Emanuele Pessagno||2}}, {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Nicoloso da Recco||2}}
* ''Ammiraglio di divisione'' [[Luigi Sansonetti]]
** Three [[heavy cruiser]]s (''3a Divisione Incrociatori''): ''Bolzano'', ''Trento'', ''Trieste''
** Three destroyers (''12a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere''): {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Ascari||2}}, ''Carabiniere'', {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Corazziere|1938|2}}
* ''Ammiraglio di divisione'' [[Carlo Cattaneo (admiral)|Carlo Cattaneo]]
** Three heavy cruisers (''1a Divisione Incrociatori''): ''Fiume'' (sunk), ''Pola'' (sunk), ''Zara'' (sunk)
** Four destroyers (''9a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere''): {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Vittorio Alfieri||2}} (sunk), {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Giosuè Carducci||2}} (sunk), {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Vincenzo Gioberti||2}} (damaged), {{Ship|Italian destroyer|Alfredo Oriani||2}}

===Allies===
[[Image:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|border|50px]]
Included:&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |last1=DiGiulian |first1=Tony |title=Orders of Battle – Battle of Cape Matapan – Battles of the Mediterranean – World War II – NavWeaps |url=http://www.navweaps.com/index_oob/OOB_WWII_Mediterranean/OOB_WWII_Cape-Matapan.php |website=www.navweaps.com |accessdate=19 July 2018 |language=en}}&lt;/ref&gt;
Force A, 14th Destroyer Flotilla, 10th Destroyer Flotilla (of Force C), Force B, [[2nd Destroyer Flotilla]], Force D
* Admiral Sir Andrew Cunningham
** Three battleships: HMS ''Barham'', ''Valiant'', and ''Warspite''
** One aircraft carrier: HMS ''Formidable'' (1 aircraft lost, 3 dead)
** Nine destroyers: HMS ''Greyhound'', ''Griffin'', ''Jervis'', ''Janus'', ''Mohawk'', ''Nubian'', ''Hotspur'' and ''Havock'' and HMAS ''Stuart''
* Vice-Admiral Henry Pridham-Wippell
** Four light cruisers: HMS ''Ajax'', ''Gloucester'' and ''Orion'' and HMAS ''Perth''
** Three destroyers: HMS ''Hasty'', ''Hereward'' and ''Ilex''
* AG 9 convoy (from Alexandria to Greece)
** Two light cruisers: HMS ''Calcutta'' and ''Carlisle''
** Three destroyers: HMS ''Defender'' and ''Jaguar'' and HMAS ''Vampire''
* GA 8 convoy (from Greece to Alexandria)
** One anti-aircraft cruiser: HMS ''Bonaventure''
** Two destroyers: HMS ''Decoy'' and ''Juno''
** One merchant ship: ''Thermopylæ'' (Norwegian)

==Notes==
{{reflist|30em}}

==References==
* Greene, Jack &amp; Massignani, Alessandro (1998). ''The Naval War in the Mediterranean, 1940–1943'', Chatam Publishing, London. {{ISBN|1-86176-057-4}}.
* O'Hara, Vincent P.: ''Struggle for the Middle Sea'', Naval Institute Press, Annapolis, Maryland, 2009. {{ISBN|978-1-59114-648-3}}.
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110412171108/http://www.royalnavy.mod.uk/history/battles/cape-matapan/index.htm Royal Navy Website history section, Battle of Cape Matapan]
* [http://www.regiamarina.net/detail_text_with_list.asp?nid=38&amp;lid=1 Regiamarina.net Battle of Matapan]

== Further reading ==
* Sadkovich, James. J,  'Re-evaluating Who Won the Italo-British Naval Conflict 1940–2',  ''European History Quarterly, ''October 198818:455–471.

==External links==
* [http://www.thehistorynet.com/wwii/blitaliannavalmassacre/ "Battle of Cape Matapan: World War II Italian Naval Massacre"] by Anthony M. Scalzo at HistoryNet.com
* {{in lang|it}}&lt;!--Italian--&gt; [http://digilander.libero.it/planciacomando/WW2/gaudo1.htm ''Battaglia di Gaudo''] at Plancia di Comando
* {{in lang|it}}&lt;!--Italian--&gt; [http://digilander.libero.it/planciacomando/WW2/mata1.htm ''La notte di Matapan''] at Plancia di Comando
* [http://www.britishpathe.com/video/after-the-battle-of-cape-matapan/query/greece After The Battle Of Cape Matapan] a video from British Pathé

{{DEFAULTSORT:Cape Matapan}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1941]]
[[Category:1941 in Italy]]
[[Category:Allied naval victories in the battle of the Mediterranean|Cape Matapan]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of the European theatre of World War II]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Australia|Cape Matapan]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Italy|Cape Matapan]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Bletchley Park]]
[[Category:Night battles|Cape Matapan]]
[[Category:March 1941 events]]</text><sha1>0g4y3icot5g3l1l9lr173x6ab6szhkh</sha1></revision></page>