<page><title>Battle of the Tarigo Convoy</title><ns>0</ns><id>7168638</id><revision><id>964444087</id><parentid>964441953</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-25T14:51:00Z</timestamp><contributor><username>DagosNavy</username><id>1723027</id></contributor><comment>Add destroyed convoy</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="7366" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=April 2017}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict          = Battle of the Tarigo Convoy
| partof            = the [[Battle of the Mediterranean]] of [[World War II]]
| image             = Italian destroyer Lampo wreckage.jpg
| image_size        = 300px
| caption           = Wreckage of the destroyer ''Lampo'', beached during the battle and later salvaged by the Italian Navy
| date              = 16 April 1941
| place             = Off the [[Kerkennah Islands]], [[Mediterranean Sea]]
| result            = British victory
| combatant1        = {{flagcountry|United Kingdom}}
| combatant2        = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
| commander1        = {{flagdeco|United Kingdom|naval}} [[Philip Mack]]
| commander2        = {{flagdeco|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Pietro de Cristofaro]]{{KIA}}
| strength1         = 4 destroyers
| strength2         = 3 destroyers
| casualties1       = 43 killed &lt;br&gt; 1 destroyer sunk
| casualties2       = 350-1,800 killed &lt;br&gt; 2 destroyers sunk &lt;br&gt; 1 destroyer beached &lt;br&gt; 4 cargo ships sunk or destroyed
}}
{{Campaignbox Mediterranean Campaign}}

The '''Battle of the Tarigo Convoy''' (sometimes referred to as the '''Action off Sfax''') was a naval battle of [[World War II]], part of the [[Battle of the Mediterranean]]. It was fought on 16 April 1941, between four [[Royal Navy|British]] and three [[Regia Marina|Italian]] destroyers, near the [[Kerkennah Islands]] off [[Sfax]], in the [[Tunisia]]n coast. The battle was named after the Italian flagship, the destroyer [[Italian destroyer Luca Tarigo|''Luca Tarigo'']].

Control of the sea between Italy and [[Libya]] was heavily disputed as both sides sought to safeguard their own convoys while interdicting those of their opponent. Axis convoys to North Africa supplied the German and Italian armies there, and British attacks were based on [[Malta]], itself dependent upon convoys.

==The battle==

In mid-April, 1941, a five ship Axis convoy sailed from [[Naples]], en route to [[Tripoli]]. It consisted of four [[Nazi Germany|German]] [[troopship]]s (''Adana'', ''Arta'', ''Aegina'' and ''Iserlohn'') and an Italian [[ammunition ship]] (''Sabaudia''). The convoy was escorted by a {{sclass-|Navigatori|destroyer}} [[Italian destroyer Luca Tarigo|''Luca Tarigo'']] ([[flagship]]) and two {{sclass-|Folgore|destroyer|2}}&lt;nowiki/&gt;s, [[Italian destroyer Baleno|''Baleno'']] and [[Italian destroyer Lampo (1931)|''Lampo'']], all under orders from Commander [[Pietro de Cristofaro]]. The convoy was delayed by bad weather, sailing in the evening of 13 April.

The British had been alerted to the convoy's sailing by intercepted radio messages. On 15 April, a British [[Martin Maryland|Maryland]] reconnaissance plane sighted and shadowed the convoy. Two Italian [[Savoia-Marchetti SM.79|SM.79]]s that were ordered to provide air cover did not arrive, due to the continuing bad weather. During the night of 15–16 April, the convoy was intercepted by the British [[14th Destroyer Flotilla]] ({{HMS|Jervis}} (flagship), {{HMS|Janus|F53|6}}, [[HMS Nubian (F36)|HMS ''Nubian'']], and {{HMS|Mohawk|F31|6}}, commanded by Captain [[Philip Mack]]). At least three of these destroyers were equipped with [[radar]].&lt;ref&gt;D'Adamo, citing Derek Howse's ''Radar at Sea''&lt;/ref&gt; The encounter took place as the Italian convoy maneuvered around the shallow waters surrounding the Kerkennah Islands.

By the use of the radar, the British force ambushed the Axis convoy in the dark. As the convoy passed a buoy marking sandbanks, the British opened fire at {{convert|2000|yd|m}} and closed to as near as {{convert|50|yd|m}}.&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; Three of the Axis transports were sunk, and the other two [[Ship grounding|beached]] on the sandbar and became a total loss.{{citation needed|date=November 2017}} ''Lampo'' was run aground and later salvaged, while ''Baleno'' sank in shallow waters. The flotilla commander, Commander de Cristofaro, on board ''Tarigo'', had his leg shot off and later died of his wounds; he was posthumously awarded the ''[[Gold Medal of Military Valor|Medaglia d'Oro]]'' (the highest Italian [[military decoration]]). While listing to port and sinking, ''Tarigo'' (now under the command of the only surviving officer, Ensign Ettore Bisagno) launched two [[torpedo]]es that hit HMS ''Mohawk''; HMS ''Jervis'' subsequently [[Scuttling|scuttled]] ''Mohawk'', which sank to the sandy bottom at a depth of {{convert|12|m}}. The outcome of the battle marked the end of the relatively unopposed Axis transport to Libya, which they had enjoyed since June 1940.&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp. 163-164&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==
[[File:HMS Mohawk's wreckage.jpg|thumb|right|150px|The wreckage of HMS ''Mohawk'' as seen from an Italian reconnaissance aircraft (1941)]]
The Italian maritime command in Libya immediately organised a rescue operation which involved the destroyers ''Malocello'', ''Da Noli'', ''Vivaldi'', and {{ship|Italian destroyer|Dardo|1930|2}}, torpedo boats ''Centauro'', ''Clio'', ''Partenope'', ''Perseus'', and ''Sirtori'', seaplane carrier ''Orlando'', hospital ship ''Arno'', and merchant ships ''Antonietta Lauro'' and ''Capacitas''. A total of 1,271 survivors were recovered of about 3,000 men on board.

Italian naval forces also found the wreckage of HMS ''Mohawk'', settled on her port side in shallow water. During April, May, and June 1941, Italian divers, disguised as local fishermen, retrieved documents and other material from the wreck of ''Mohawk''. In 1998, researchers asserted that documents recovered were essential to the later, successful [[Raid on Alexandria (1941)|Italian attack on Alexandria]].&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p. 164&lt;/ref&gt;

The destroyer ''Lampo'' was salvaged from the shallow water after a four-month effort, and repaired by May 1942. She was sunk again on 30 April 1943.  ''Adana'' sank several hours after the engagement, while the wreck of ''Arta'' was destroyed with explosive charges by the crew of the submarine [[HMS Upholder (P37)|HMS ''Upholder'']] on the night of 26 April 1941.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title = Hero of the Upholder: The Story of Lieutenant Commander M.D. Wanklyn VC, DSO**|last = Allaway|first = Jim|publisher = Airlife|year = 1991|isbn = 978-1853102189|location = London|pages = 92–95}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Axis casualties are variously reported as 350, 700, or 1,800 men; British losses were 43.

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==

* Green, J; Massignani, A. (1998) ''The Naval War in the Mediterranean 1940-1943'' Chatham Publishing. {{ISBN|1-86176-057-4}}
*{{cite web
 |last=D'Adamo 
 |first=Cristiano 
 |title=Sinking of the Tarigo Convoy, April 16th, 1941 
 |url=http://www.regiamarina.net/engagements/tarigo/tarigo_us.htm 
 |accessdate=2006-12-19 
 |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20060910011054/http://regiamarina.net/engagements/tarigo/tarigo_us.htm 
 |archivedate=2006-09-10 
 |url-status=dead 
}}

{{coord|35|9|27.13|N|11|30|49.22|E |display=title|region:TN_type:waterbody}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Tarigo convoy}}
[[Category:Allied naval victories in the battle of the Mediterranean]]
[[Category:1941 in Italy]]
[[Category:Mediterranean convoys of World War II]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in April 1941]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|B]]
[[Category:April 1941 events]]</text><sha1>r3nd19byghy7ndzw9z21xqseh0tf6ru</sha1></revision></page>