<page><title>Operation Halberd</title><ns>0</ns><id>6398552</id><revision><id>953036251</id><parentid>949574712</parentid><timestamp>2020-04-25T10:48:21Z</timestamp><contributor><username>InternetArchiveBot</username><id>27015025</id></contributor><comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="17002" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2016}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict= Operation ''Halberd''
|partof= the [[Battle of the Mediterranean]] of [[World War II]]
|image= The Royal Navy during the Second World War A5634.jpg
|image_size= 300px
|caption= An Italian torpedo bomber on fire and crashing during Operation ''Halberd'', just beyond is {{HMS|Ark Royal|91|6}}
|date= 27 September 1941
|place=[[Mediterranean Sea]], southwest of [[Calabria]]
|result=British victory
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Netherlands}} [[Dutch government-in-exile|Netherlands]]&lt;br/&gt;{{flagicon|POL}} [[Polish Armed Forces in the West|Poland]]
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[James Somerville]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Angelo Iachino]]
|units1=[[Force H]]
|units2=[[Regia Marina]]&lt;br&gt;[[Regia Aeronautica]]
|strength1=1 aircraft carrier&lt;br&gt;12 bombers&lt;br&gt;54 fighters&lt;br&gt;3 battleships&lt;br&gt;5 cruisers&lt;br&gt;18 destroyers&lt;br&gt;8 submarines&lt;br&gt;9 transport ships
|strength2=62 bombers&lt;br&gt;68 fighters&lt;br&gt;2 battleships&lt;br&gt;5 cruisers&lt;br&gt;14 destroyers&lt;br&gt;11 submarines&lt;br&gt;8 torpedo boats
|casualties1=1 battleship damaged&lt;br&gt;1 merchant scuttled&lt;br&gt;4 aircraft
|casualties2=1 submarine&lt;br&gt;21 aircraft
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Mediterranean Campaign}}
}}

'''Operation Halberd''' was a British naval operation that took place on 27 September 1941, during the [[Second World War]]. The British were attempting to deliver a [[Malta Convoys|convoy]] from [[Gibraltar]] to [[Malta]]. The convoy was escorted by several battleships and an aircraft carrier, to deter interference from the Italian surface fleet, while a close escort of cruisers and destroyers provided an anti-aircraft screen.

The Italian fleet sortied after the convoy was detected, but turned back after learning the strength of the escorting force. Air attacks by Italian bombers and fighters damaged several ships, and forced one of the merchant vessels to be scuttled. The rest of the convoy arrived at Malta and discharged their cargo.

==The convoy==
Operation Halberd was at the time the largest Malta resupply effort of the war.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p.181&lt;/ref&gt; Nine merchant ships carrying 81,000 tons of military equipment and supplies sailed from [[Liverpool]] on 16 September and from the [[River Clyde|Clyde]] on 17 September as part of convoy WS ('''W'''inston '''S'''pecials) 11X, passing Gibraltar on 24 September 1941, with a close escort under the command of Rear-Admiral [[Harold Burrough]].&lt;ref&gt;Hague, p.195&lt;/ref&gt; The nine ships were:&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.naval-history.net/xAH-WSConvoys04-1941B.htm WS CONVOYS - July to December 1941 SAILINGS, including two DM Convoys, WS 10 to 14B]&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{MV|Breconshire}} ({{GRT|9776}}) 'Convoy Commodore' Auxiliary Supply Ship
*{{MV|Ajax|1931|2}} ({{GRT|7549}}) [[Blue Funnel Line]]
*{{SS|City of Calcutta|1940|2}} ({{GRT|8063}}) [[Ellerman Lines|Ellerman's City Line]]
*{{SS|City of Lincoln|1938|2}} ({{GRT|8039}}) [[Ellerman Lines|Ellerman &amp; Bucknall]]
*{{SS|Clan Ferguson||2}} ({{GRT|7347}}) [[Clan Line]]
*{{SS|Clan MacDonald||2}} ({{GRT|9653}}) Clan Line
*{{MV|Dunedin Star||2}} ({{GRT|12891}}) [[Blue Star Line]]
*{{MV|Imperial Star||2}} ({{GRT|12427}}) Blue Star Line
*{{MV|Rowallan Castle||2}} ({{GRT|7798}}) [[Union-Castle Line]]

==British forces==
[[Force H]], under the command of Admiral [[James Somerville]], accompanied the convoy as defence against Italian surface ships. Force H consisted of the [[battleship]]s {{HMS|Nelson|28|6}}, {{HMS|Rodney|29|2}} and {{HMS|Prince of Wales|53|2}} with the [[aircraft carrier]] {{HMS|Ark Royal|91|6}} operating 12 [[Fairey Swordfish]] and 27 [[Fairey Fulmar]]s of [[807 Naval Air Squadron|807]] and [[808 Naval Air Squadron]]s. Force H included [[cruiser]]s {{HMS|Kenya|14|6}}, {{HMS|Edinburgh|16|2}}, {{HMS|Sheffield|C24|2}}, {{HMS|Euryalus|42|2}} and {{HMS|Hermione|74|2}}, and was screened by [[destroyer]]s [[HNLMS Isaac Sweers (1940)|HNLMS ''Isaac Sweers'']], [[HMS Garland (H37)|ORP ''Garland'']] and {{ship|ORP|Piorun|G65|6}}, and {{HMS|Duncan|D99|6}}, {{HMS|Farndale|L70|2}}, {{HMS|Foresight|H68|2}}, {{HMS|Forester|H74|2}}, {{HMS|Fury|H76|2}}, {{HMS|Heythrop|L85|2}}, {{HMS|Laforey|G99|2}}, {{HMS|Lance|G87|2}}, {{HMS|Legion|G74|2}}, {{HMS|Lightning|G55|2}}, {{HMS|Lively|G40|2}}, {{HMS|Oribi|G66|2}}, {{HMS|Cossack|F03|2}}, {{HMS|Gurkha|G63|2}} and {{HMS|Zulu|F18|2}}. Submarines {{HMS|Ursula|N59|6}} and {{HMS|Unbeaten|N93|2}} patrolled south of the [[Strait of Messina]] while {{HMS|Upright|N89|6}} and {{HMS|Utmost|N19|2}} patrolled north of the Strait. The Polish submarine {{ship|ORP|Sokół|1940|6}} patrolled north of [[Sicily]] with {{HMS|Urge||6}} and {{HMS|Upholder|P37|2}} while the Dutch submarine {{ship|HNLMS|O 21}} patrolled south of [[Sardinia]]. Malta had recently received 27 long-range fighters (22 [[Bristol Beaufighter]]s and 5 [[Bristol Blenheim]]s), which had been bombing and strafing Italian airfields on Sicily and Sardinia, and would provide air cover for the convoy after Force H retired before reaching the Sicilian narrows.&lt;ref name=g&amp;m&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp.182-187&lt;/ref&gt;

==Italian forces==
Italian submarines deployed to ambush the British battleships thought to be planning a bombardment raid against the Italian coast. [[Marcello class submarine#Dandolo|''Dandolo'']], [[Italian submarine Adua|''Adua'']] and [[Italian submarine Turchese|''Turchese'']] patrolled south of [[Ibiza]] while [[Italian submarine Axum|''Axum'']], ''Serpente'', [[Italian submarine Aradam|''Aradam'']] and [[Italian submarine Diaspro|''Diaspro'']] patrolled east of the [[Balearic Islands]]. ''Squalo'', ''Bandiera'' and [[Italian submarine Delfino (1930)|''Delfino'']] patrolled Southwest of Sardinia and ''Narvalo'' was off the African shore of the Sicilian narrows. Light cruisers [[Italian cruiser Muzio Attendolo|''Muzio Attendolo'']] and [[Italian cruiser Duca degli Abruzzi|''Duca degli Abruzzi'']] of the 8th cruiser division sailed from [[Palermo]] with [[Maestrale-class destroyer]]s ''Maestrale'', ''Grecale'' and ''Scirocco'' of the 10th destroyer flotilla to take position off [[La Maddalena]]. Battleships [[Italian battleship Vittorio Veneto|''Vittorio Veneto'']] and [[Italian battleship Littorio|''Littorio'']] were prepared to sortie from [[Naples]] with [[Soldati-class destroyer|''Granatiere'']], [[Soldati-class destroyer|''Fuciliere'']], [[Soldati-class destroyer|''Bersagliere'']] and [[Oriani-class destroyer|''Gioberti'']] of the 13th flotilla, and [[Italian destroyer Nicoloso da Recco|''Nicoloso da Recco'']], [[Navigatori-class destroyer|''Pessagno'']] and [[Folgore-class destroyer|''Folgore'']] of the 16th flotilla while cruisers [[Italian cruiser Trieste|''Trieste'']], [[Italian cruiser Trento|''Trento'']] and [[Italian cruiser Gorizia|''Gorizia'']] from [[Taranto]] with [[Soldati-class destroyer|''Corazziere'']], [[Soldati-class destroyer|''Carabiniere'']], [[Soldati-class destroyer|''Ascari'']] and [[Soldati-class destroyer|''Lanciere'']] of the 12th flotilla prepared to join them. Sardinia deployed thirty [[Macchi C.200]], twenty [[Fiat CR.42]] and twenty-six [[Savoia-Marchetti SM.79]] and [[Savoia-Marchetti SM.84|SM.84]] torpedo bombers against the convoy while Sicily deployed fifteen C.200, three [[Reggiane Re.2000]], and nine [[Junkers Ju 87]] with twenty-four [[Fiat BR.20]], SM.79 and SM.84 as high-level bombers and plus three with torpedoes. More Italian aircraft were operational, but were assigned other missions including bombing Malta.&lt;ref name=g&amp;m/&gt;

==Prelude==
Ships of the [[Mediterranean Fleet]] operating from [[Alexandria]] began making heavy radio traffic in the hope of diverting ''Luftwaffe'' attention to possible preparations for a major operation in the eastern Mediterranean. On 24 September Admiral Somerville shifted his flag from ''Nelson'' to ''Rodney'' and ''Nelson'' sailed west into the [[Atlantic]] at 18:15 escorted by ''Garland'', ''Piorun'' and ''Isaac Sweers'' to give the impression the strength of Force H was being reduced. ''Nelson'' turned back after dusk to join the merchant ships from convoy WS 11X, now redesignated convoy GM 2 as the second convoy from '''G'''ibraltar to '''M'''alta. Force H separated from the merchant ships in the early hours of 25 September so [[Axis powers|Axis]] aerial reconnaissance might think only Force H was at sea. Fulmars from ''Ark Royal'' provided air cover over the convoy.&lt;ref name=g&amp;m/&gt;

Italian aircraft found Force H on the afternoon of 25 September, and assumed the battleships were on a bombardment raid against the Italian coast. A [[CANT Z.506]] seaplane observing Force H at 09:32 on 26 September reported a single battleship with an aircraft carrier incorrectly identified as {{HMS|Furious|47|6}}. Since ''Ark Royal'' had been seen leaving Gibraltar, the Italians assumed ''Furious'' might be flying off aircraft to reinforce Malta while ''Ark Royal'' attacked [[Genoa]]. The Italian fleet sailed from Naples to take a defensive position with the 8th cruiser division off northern Sardinia, but was ordered not to engage the British fleet unless the Italians held a decisive superiority of forces.&lt;ref name=g&amp;m/&gt;

==Battle of 27 September==
Force H rejoined the convoy at 07:10 27 September. Sixteen destroyers formed a bent line screen ahead of two columns of merchant ships. The port column was led by the cruiser ''Kenya'', followed by ''Ajax'', ''Clan MacDonald'', ''Imperial Star'', ''Rowallan Castle'' and ''City of Calcutta''. The starboard column was led by the cruiser ''Edinburgh'' followed by ''Clan Ferguson'', {{MV|Dunedin Star}}, HMS ''Breconshire'' and ''City of Lincoln''. ''Rodney'' took position behind the port wing of the screen followed by ''Prince of Wales''. ''Nelson'' took position behind the starboard wing of the screen followed by ''Ark Royal'' in formation with the [[Dido-class cruiser|anti-aircraft cruisers]] ''Euryalus'' and ''Hermione''. The cruiser ''Sheffield'' took position astern of the merchant ships, while the destroyers ''Piorun'' and ''Legion'' assumed [[plane guard]] positions astern of ''Ark Royal''.&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p.186&lt;/ref&gt;

Italian aircraft correctly identified ''Ark Royal'' at 08:10, and at 10:45 reported the convoy speed of {{convert|16|knot|kph}}, which indicated that merchant ships were with the convoy. The battleships from Naples rendezvoused with the cruisers from Taranto at 10:40, and were joined by the 8th cruiser division at 11:48. The Italian fleet was faster than the battleships of Force H, but was inferior to the British force in firepower. The ''[[Regia Aeronautica]]'' gave priority to fighter defence of bomber strikes, and the six fighters providing air cover over the Italian fleet could not travel more than {{convert|100|km|mi}} from their base. Since Italian aircraft had reported only a single British battleship, the Italian fleet received authorization at noon to engage the British formation. The ''Regia Aeronautica'' was requested to provide increased air cover for the Italian fleet by 14:00.&lt;ref name=g&amp;m2&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, pp.187-191&lt;/ref&gt;

The ''Regia Aeronautica'' launched a strike of 28 SM.79 and SM.84 torpedo planes with 20 Cr.42 fighters. The convoy came under air attack at 13:00. The strike was met by defending Fulmars and heavy anti-aircraft fire. Three bombers pressed through the barrage of starboard wing destroyers to launch torpedoes at ''Nelson''. ''Nelson'' turned to comb the torpedo tracks, and inadvertently steadied on the reciprocal course of a torpedo which struck the port side of the [[forecastle]].&lt;ref&gt;''The Royal Navy and the Mediterranean Convoys'', p.21. This account states that the torpedo attacks were carried out by [[SM-79]] and [[Fiat BR.20|BR-20]] torpedo bombers.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Nelson'' slowed to 15 knots, but maintained position in the convoy. The Italian plane had released the torpedo at a range of only {{convert|450|yd|m}} and endured concentrated anti-aircraft fire from ''Prince of Wales'' before being shot down by one of the Fulmars. Six more torpedo planes and 1 fighter failed to return from the strike. [[Friendly fire]] from ''Rodney'' and ''Prince of Wales'' shot down two Fulmars, and a patrolling Swordfish had been shot down by the Italian fighters before the strike ended at 13:30.&lt;ref name=g&amp;m2/&gt;

The Italian fleet was shadowed by British aircraft from Malta beginning at 13:07. At 14:30 the Italian fleet was about 40 miles from the convoy, but "...decided to return home around 14:30 on the 27th when..." it "... learned that the British had two battleships, a carrier and six cruisers at sea."&lt;ref&gt;''The Italian Navy in WW2'', Sadkovich, p.181: "He therefore decided to return home around 14:30 on the 27th when he learned that the British had two battleships, a carrier and six cruisers at sea."&lt;/ref&gt; Aircraft from ''Ark Royal'' shadowed the Italian fleet from 15:15 to 17:50. Cr.42 fighters arrived at 15:30 to provide air cover, but the squadron leader of the first flight was shot down by friendly fire from an Italian destroyer. Two more Italian pilots were lost when another flight of ten C.200s ran out of fuel and ditched at sea. At 14:46 ''Prince of Wales'', ''Rodney'', ''Sheffield'', ''Edinburgh'', and six destroyers steamed toward the Italian fleet; but were recalled at 17:00 before making contact, and rejoined the convoy at 18:30.&lt;ref&gt;''The Royal Navy and the Mediterranean Convoys'', p.28&lt;/ref&gt; ''Nelson'', ''Rodney'', ''Prince of Wales'' and ''Ark Royal'' turned west to return to Gibraltar escorted by ''Duncan'', ''Fury'', ''Gurkha'', ''Lance'', ''Legion'', ''Lively''. ''Garland'', ''Piorun'', and ''Isaac Sweers''. ''Euryalus'' fell in astern of the port column of merchant ships while ''Sheffield'' and ''Hermione'' joined the starboard column as the remaining destroyers closed into a night steaming formation. The night steaming formation was attacked by a few torpedo bombers, and ''Imperial Star'' was struck by a single torpedo. ''Oribi'' took the damaged freighter in tow. Italian [[MAS (boat)|''Motoscafo armato silurante'']] (MAS torpedo boats) deployed through the Strait of Messina, but failed to find the convoy.&lt;ref name=g&amp;m2/&gt;

==Aftermath==
''Hermione'' detached from the convoy to bombard [[Pantelleria]] so that airfield would be out of action when the convoy arrived in Malta. The damaged ''Imperial Star'' was scuttled without loss of life to maintain convoy speed of advance, and the convoy arrived in Malta on 28 September. Retiring Force H was attacked by three submarines; and ''Adua'' was sunk by ''Gurkha'' and ''Legion''. Another ''Ark Royal'' Fulmar fell to friendly fire from ''Prince of Wales'', raising British aircraft losses to three Fulmars from friendly fire and one Swordfish from enemy action.&lt;ref name=g&amp;m2/&gt; Italian aircraft losses were 21 including seven bombers and one fighter from enemy action, one fighter from friendly fire, and ten fighters from fuel exhaustion.&lt;ref&gt;''The Italian Navy in WW2'', Sadkovich, p.182&lt;/ref&gt;

Admiral Somerville was knighted in recognition of his successful command of Force H during Operation Halberd. It was the second time Somerville had received that honour, and it occasioned a memorable congratulatory message from [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Admiral Cunningham]]: "Fancy, twice a knight at your age."&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani, p.191&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Battle of the Mediterranean]]
* [[Malta Convoys]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* {{cite book |last=Hague |first=Arnold |authorlink = |title =The Allied Convoy System 1939–1945 |publisher =Naval Institute Press |volume = |edition = |date =2000 |location =Annapolis, Maryland |pages = |isbn =1-55750-019-3}}
* {{cite book |last1=Greene |first1=Jack |last2=Massignani |first2=Alessandro |authorlink = |title =The Naval War in the Mediterranean 1940–1943 |publisher =Chatham Publishing |volume = |edition = |date =1998 |location =London |pages = |isbn =1-885119-61-5}}
* [http://www.merlinsovermalta.com/ Merlins over Malta]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20060723104117/http://www.naval-history.net/WW2CampaignsMaltaConvoys.htm Malta Convoys]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20091215084028/http://freespace.virgin.net/e.gilroy/ The story of HMS Lightning - a WW2 destroyer ]
* [http://ibiblio.org/hyperwar/UN/UK/LondonGazette/38377.pdf MEDITERRANEAN CONVOY OPERATIONS] ([[London Gazette]])

==External links==
{{Commons category|Operation Halberd}}
*[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=it3pOYM0JkA Newsreel footage of Operation Halberd, as filmed from HMS ''Prince of Wales'']

{{coord|37.5167|N|10.7667|E|source:kolossus-fiwiki|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Halberd}}
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles of World War II]]
[[Category:Malta Convoys]]
[[Category:Allied naval victories in the battle of the Mediterranean]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:September 1941 events]]</text><sha1>aq9mpdxp122girm383t32kl7q5xlbno</sha1></revision></page>