<page><title>First Battle of Sirte</title><ns>0</ns><id>3019772</id><revision><id>960570616</id><parentid>960570546</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-03T17:51:35Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Parsecboy</username><id>1879095</id></contributor><comment>/* Minefield off Tripoli */</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="17896" xml:space="preserve">{{Other uses|Battle of Sirte (disambiguation){{!}}Battle of Sirte}}
{{EngvarB|date=August 2014}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=August 2014}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=First Battle of Sirte
|image=File:Andrea Doria 1940.jpg
|image_size = 300px
|caption=Italian battleship ''Andrea Doria''
| partof      = the [[Battle of the Mediterranean]] of [[World War II]]
|date=17 December 1941
|place=[[Gulf of Sidra]], [[Mediterranean Sea]]
|result=Inconclusive 
|combatant1={{flag|United Kingdom}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Australia}}&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|Netherlands}}
|combatant2={{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
|commander1={{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Andrew Cunningham, 1st Viscount Cunningham of Hyndhope|Sir Andrew Cunningham]]
|commander2={{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Angelo Iachino]]
|strength1=5 light cruisers&lt;br /&gt;14 destroyers
|strength2=4 battleships&lt;br /&gt;2 heavy cruisers&lt;br /&gt;3 light cruisers&lt;br /&gt;13 destroyers
|casualties1=2 destroyers lightly damaged
|casualties2=None
|}}
{{Campaignbox Mediterranean Campaign}}

The '''First Battle of Sirte''' was fought between the British [[Royal Navy]] and the ''[[Regia Marina]]'' (Italian Royal Navy) during the [[Battle of the Mediterranean|Mediterranean campaign]] of the [[Second World War]]. The engagement, largely uneventful, took place on 17 December 1941, south-east of [[Malta]], in the [[Gulf of Sidra|Gulf of Sirte]].

In the following days, two Royal Navy forces based at Malta ran into an Italian minefield off [[Tripoli]] and two British battleships were disabled by Italian [[Human torpedo|manned torpedoes]] at [[Alexandria]]. By the end of December, the balance of naval power in the Mediterranean had shifted in favour of the Italian Fleet.

==Background==
The British [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|Eighth Army]] and the [[Axis powers|Axis]] armies in North Africa were engaged in battles resulting from [[Operation Crusader]], which had been fought between 18 November and 4 December. Its aim was to defeat the ''[[Afrika Korps]]'' and relieve the siege of [[Tobruk]]. This had been achieved and Axis forces were conducting a fighting retreat; by 13 December, they were holding a defensive line at [[Gazala]], east of [[Benghazi]].&lt;ref name="m&amp;g"&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani pp.196–204&lt;/ref&gt; The Axis were desperate to supply their forces, intending to transport stores to [[Tripoli]], their main port in [[Libya]] and Benghazi, the port closest to the front line.&lt;ref name="m&amp;g"/&gt; The island garrison of Malta was under siege and the British wanted to supply their forces on the island.&lt;ref name="m&amp;g"/&gt;

==Prelude==

===Axis convoys M41 and M42===

The Italians were preparing to send M41, a convoy of eight ships, to Africa on 13 December 1941. That morning, their previous supply attempt, two fast cruisers carrying fuel to Tripoli, had failed when both ships were sunk at the [[Battle of Cape Bon (1941)|Battle of Cape Bon]] by a force of destroyers ''en route'' to [[Alexandria]].&lt;ref name="m&amp;g"/&gt;

Convoy M41 consisted of eight merchant ships in three groups, with a close escort of five destroyers and a distant cover force of the [[battleship]]s, {{Ship|Italian battleship|Littorio||2}} and {{Ship|Italian battleship|Vittorio Veneto||2}}, four [[destroyer]]s and two [[torpedo boat]]s.&lt;ref name="m&amp;g"/&gt;

Soon after sailing on 13 December, a group of M41 was attacked by the British [[submarine]] {{HMS|Upright|N89|6}} and two ships were sunk; later that day two ships collided and had to return to base, while the distant cover force was sighted by the submarine {{HMS|Urge|N17|6}} and ''Vittorio Veneto'' was torpedoed and forced to return to port.&lt;ref name="m&amp;g" /&gt;

''[[Supermarina]]'' the Italian navy high command, rattled by these losses and a report that a British force of two battleships was at sea, ordered the ships to return to await reinforcement but the "force of two battleships" was a decoy operation by the [[minelayer]] {{HMS|Abdiel|M39|6}}.&lt;ref name="grv"&gt;Grove pp.72–74&lt;/ref&gt;

On 16 December, the four-ship Italian convoy, renamed M42, left [[Taranto]], picking up escorts along the way. The close escort was provided by seven destroyers and a torpedo boat; by the time they reached [[Sicily]] they were also accompanied by a close cover force, comprising the battleship {{Ship|Italian battleship|Caio Duilio||2}}, three light cruisers and three destroyers.&lt;ref name="grv" /&gt; The distant covering force consisted of the battleships ''Littorio'', {{Ship|Italian battleship|Andrea Doria||2}} and {{Ship|Italian battleship|Giulio Cesare||2}}, two cruisers and 10 destroyers.&lt;ref name="grv" /&gt;

=== Allied convoy ===
The British planned to run supplies to Malta using the fast merchant ship ''Breconshire'', covered by a force of cruisers and destroyers, while the destroyers from the Cape Bon engagement, would proceed to Alexandria from Malta covered by [[Force K]] and [[Force B]] from Malta on 15 December.&lt;ref name="grv" /&gt;

The British force was depleted when the [[light cruiser]] {{HMS|Galatea|71|6}} was torpedoed and sunk by {{GS|U-557||2}}, just before midnight on 14 December.&lt;ref name="b54"&gt;Brown pp. 54–55&lt;/ref&gt; ''U-557'' was accidentally sunk less than 48 hours later, by the Italian torpedo boat ''Orione''.&lt;ref&gt;Blair pp. 400, 736&lt;/ref&gt;

On 15 December, ''Breconshire'' sailed from Alexandria escorted by three cruisers and eight destroyers under [[Rear admiral (Royal Navy)|Rear-Admiral]] [[Philip Vian]] in {{HMS|Naiad|93|6}}. On 16 December, the four destroyers of 4th Flotilla (Commander G. Stokes in {{HMS|Sikh|F82|6}}) left Malta, covered by Force K (Captain W. G. "Bill" Agnew in {{HMS|Aurora|12|6}}), two cruisers and two destroyers.&lt;ref name="m&amp;g"/&gt; Thirty Italian warships were escorting four cargo ships. The two British groups were also at sea and steaming toward each other; the opposing forces were likely to cross each other's tracks east of Malta on 18 December.

==Battle==
On 17 December, an Italian reconnaissance aircraft spotted the British west-bound formation near [[Sidi Barrani]], apparently proceeding from Alexandria to intercept the Italian convoy. The British convoy was shadowed by Axis aeroplanes and attacked during the afternoon but no hits were scored and Agnew and Stokes met the west-bound convoy. By late afternoon the Italian fleet was close by and spotter planes from the battleships had made contact with the British convoy, but the planes misidentified ''Breconshire'' as a battleship.&lt;ref&gt;Giorgio Giorgerini, ''La guerra italiana sul mare. La Marina tra vittoria e sconfitta 1940-1943'', p. 342.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="grv"/&gt; At 17:42, the fleets sighted each other; Admiral [[Angelo Iachino]]—commander of the Italian forces—moved to intercept to defend his convoy.&lt;ref name="grv"/&gt;

Vian also wished to avoid combat, so with the British giving ground and the Italians pursuing with caution, the British were easily able to avoid an engagement. Just after sunset, an air attack on the British ships caused them to return fire with their [[Anti-aircraft warfare|anti-aircraft guns]], allowing the Italian naval force to spot them. Iachino took in the distant covering force and opened fire at about {{convert|32000|m|yd|abbr=on}}, well out of range of the British guns. Vian immediately laid smoke and moved to the attack while ''Breconshire'' moved away, escorted by the destroyers {{HMS|Decoy|H75|6}} and {{HMS|Havock|H43|6}}.&lt;ref name="m&amp;g"/&gt;

Lacking [[radar]] and mindful of their defeat in the night action at the [[Battle of Cape Matapan]], the Italians wished to avoid night combat. The Italians fired for only 15 minutes before disengaging and returning westward to cover convoy M42. {{HMS|Kipling|F91|6}} suffered the loss of one seaman and some damage due to a near-miss either from an {{convert|8|in|mm|abbr=on}} shell, possibly fired by the Italian cruiser {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Gorizia||2}}&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=Mussolini s Navy: A Reference Guide to the Regia Marina 1930-1945|last=Brescia|first=Maurizio|publisher=Seaforth Publishing|year=2012|isbn=1848321155|location=|pages=77}}&lt;/ref&gt; or by {{convert|320|mm|in|order=flip|abbr=on}} shell splinters fired by ''Andrea Doria'' and ''Giulio Cesare'', knocking down wireless aerials and holing the hull, superstructure and ship's boats.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web |title=H. M. Ships Damaged or Sunk by Enemy Action in WWII |url=http://www.navy.gov.au/media-room/publications/hm-ships-damaged-or-sunk-enemy-action-wwii |website=Royal Australian Navy |accessdate=13 February 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; According to Italian sources, the [[Royal Australian Navy]] (RAN) destroyer {{HMAS|Nizam|G38|6}} was also damaged by near-misses from the Italian destroyer [[Maestrale class destroyer|''Maestrale'']].&lt;ref&gt;Bragadin, p. 149&lt;/ref&gt; British reports tell of other warships punctured by splinters.&lt;ref&gt;O´Hara (2009), p. 158&lt;/ref&gt;

==Aftermath==

===Minefield off Tripoli===

After dark, Vian to return with Stokes to Alexandria, leaving Agnew to bring ''Breconshire'' to Malta, joined by Force B, one cruiser (the other was under repair) and two destroyers. ''Breconshire'' and her escorts arrived in Malta at 15:00 on 18 December.&lt;ref name="grv"/&gt; At midday, the Italian force also split up and three ships headed for Tripoli, accompanied by the close cover force, while the German supply ship ''Ankara'', headed for Benghazi. The distant cover force remained on station in the Gulf of Sidra until evening, before heading back to base. The British had now realised that the Italians had a convoy in the area; Vian searched for it without success as he returned to Alexandria.

In the afternoon, the position of the Tripoli group was established; a cruiser and two destroyers of Force B and two cruisers and two destroyers of Force K (Captain O'Conor, on the cruiser {{HMS|Neptune|20|6}}) sortied at 18:00 to intercept. The force ran into a minefield {{convert|20|mi|nmi km|abbr=on}} off Tripoli, in the early hours of 19 December. The minefield took the British by surprise as the water-depth was {{convert|600|ft|m|abbr=on}}, which they had thought was too deep for mines. ''Neptune'' struck four mines and sank, the destroyer {{HMS|Kandahar|F28|6}} struck a mine and was scuttled the following day. The cruisers ''Aurora'' and {{HMS|Penelope|97|2}} were badly damaged but were able to return to Malta. About 830 Allied seamen, many of them New Zealanders from ''Neptune'', lost their lives in the disaster.&lt;ref name="b54"/&gt; The Malta Strike Force, which had been such an active threat to Axis shipping to Libya during most of 1941, was much reduced in its effectiveness and was later forced to withdraw to Gibraltar.&lt;ref&gt;Bartimeus p.195&lt;/ref&gt;

===Attack on Alexandria===
{{Main|Raid on Alexandria (1941)}}
While steaming back to Alexandria along with Vian's force, destroyer {{HMS|Jervis||6}} reported an apparently successful depth-charge attack on an unidentified submarine.&lt;ref&gt;Bartimeus p.190&lt;/ref&gt; The only axis submarine off Alexandria was the Italian {{Ship|Italian submarine|Sciré|1938|2}}, which was carrying a group of six Italian frogmen commandos, including [[Luigi Durand De La Penne]], equipped with [[manned torpedo]]es. Shortly after Vian's force arrived in Alexandria, on the night of 18 December, the Italians penetrated the harbour and attacked the fleet. ''Jervis'' was damaged, a large Norwegian tanker disabled and the battleships {{HMS|Valiant|1914|6}} and {{HMS|Queen Elizabeth|1913|2}} were severely damaged. This was a strategic change of fortune against the Allies whose effects were felt in the Mediterranean for several months.&lt;ref name="m&amp;g"/&gt;

==Results==

{{Unreferenced section|date=March 2016}}

Both sides achieved their strategic objectives; the British got supplies through to Malta and the Axis got their ships through to Tripoli and Benghazi, although Benghazi fell to the Eighth Army five days later, on 24 December.

==Order of battle==
Forces present 17 December 1941&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.navweaps.com/index_oob/OOB_WWII_Mediterranean/OOB_WWII_First-Sirte.htm Order of Battle -First Battle of Sirte by Dan Muir]&lt;/ref&gt;

===Italy===
[[File:Flag of Italy (1861-1946) crowned.svg|40px]]

Admiral Angelo Iachino (on ''Littorio'')
* Close covering force – Vice Admiral [[Raffaele de Courten]] (on ''Duca d'Aosta''):
** One [[battleship]]: {{ship|Italian battleship|Caio Duilio||2}};
** Three [[light cruiser]]s (''7a Divisione Incrociatori''): {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Emanuele Filiberto Duca d'Aosta||2}}, {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Muzio Attendolo||2}}, {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Raimondo Montecuccoli||2}};
** Three [[destroyer]]s: {{ship|Italian destroyer|Ascari||2}}, {{ship|Italian destroyer|Aviere|1937|2}}, and {{ship|Italian destroyer|Camicia Nera||2}}.
* Distant covering force – Vice Admiral [[Angelo Parona]] (on ''Gorizia''):
** Three battleships: {{ship|Italian battleship|Andrea Doria||2}}, {{ship|Italian battleship|Giulio Cesare||2}}, and {{ship|Italian battleship|Littorio||2}};
** Two [[heavy cruiser]]s:  {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Gorizia||2}}, and {{Ship|Italian cruiser|Trento||2}};
** 10 destroyers: ''[[Italian destroyer Vincenzo Gioberti|Vincenzo Gioberti]]'', [[Italian destroyer Alfredo Oriani|''Alfredo Oriani'']] (''9a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere'');
::{{ship|Italian destroyer|Maestrale||2}} (''10a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere'');
::{{ship|Italian destroyer|Carabiniere|1938|2}}, {{ship|Italian destroyer|Corazziere|1938|2}} (''12a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere'');
::{{ship|Italian destroyer|Alpino|1938|2}}, {{ship|Italian destroyer|Bersagliere|1938|2}}, {{ship|Italian destroyer|Fuciliere|1938|2}}, {{ship|Italian destroyer|Granatiere|1938|2}} (''13a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere'');
::{{ship|Italian destroyer|Antoniotto Usodimare||2}} (''16a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere'').
* Close escort:
** Six destroyers: {{ship|Italian destroyer|Saetta||2}} (''7a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere'');
::{{ship|Italian destroyer|Antonio da Noli||2}}, {{ship|Italian destroyer|Ugolino Vivaldi||2}} (''14a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere'');
::''[[Italian destroyer Lanzerotto Malocello|Lanzerotto Malocello]]'', {{ship|Italian destroyer|Nicolò Zeno||2}} (''15a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere'');
::{{ship|Italian destroyer|Emanuele Pessagno||2}} (''16a Squadriglia Cacciatorpediniere'');
* One [[torpedo boat]]: {{ship|Italian torpedo boat|Pegaso|1936|2}}.
* M42 convoy:
** Three [[motorship]]s: ''Monginevro'', ''Napoli'', ''Vettor Pisani'';
** One [[Cargo ship|freighter]]: ''Ankara'' (German).

===Allies===
[[File:Naval Ensign of the United Kingdom.svg|border|40px]] [[File:Flag of the Netherlands.svg|40px]] [[File:Flag of Australia.svg|40px]]  [[File:Flag of New Zealand.svg|40px]]
* Convoy Escort – Rear-Admiral Philip Vian (on ''Naiad'')
** Three light cruisers: {{HMS|Naiad|93|6}}, {{HMS|Euryalus|42|2}}, {{HMS|Carlisle|D67|2}};
** Eight destroyers : {{HMS|Jervis}}, {{HMS|Kimberley|F50|2}}, {{HMS|Kingston|F64|2}}, {{HMS|Kipling|F91|2}} (damaged), {{HMAS|Nizam|G38|6}} (damaged), {{HMS|Havock|H43|6}}, {{HMS|Hasty|H24|2}} and {{HMS|Decoy|H75|2}} (''14th Destroyer Flotilla'').
* Convoy
** One fast merchantman: [[MV Breconshire|''Breconshire'']]
* Force K
** Two light cruisers: {{HMS|Aurora|12|6}}, {{HMS|Penelope|97|2}}
** Two destroyers {{HMS|Lance|G87|6}}, {{HMS|Lively|G40|2}}
* [[Force B]]
** One cruiser: {{HMS|Neptune|20|6}}
** Two destroyers: {{HMS|Jaguar|F34|6}}, {{HMS|Kandahar|F28|2}}
* [[4th Destroyer Flotilla]]
** Four destroyers : {{HMS|Sikh|F82|6}}, {{HMS|Maori|F24|2}}, {{HMS|Legion|G74|2}}, [[HNLMS Isaac Sweers (1940)|HNLMS ''Isaac Sweers'']] (''4th Destroyer Flotilla'').

==See also==
* [[Second Battle of Sirte]]

==Notes==
{{reflist}}

==References==
* Bartimeus: ''East of Malta, West of Suez'', Little, Brown and Company, Boston, 1944.
* {{cite book|last=Blair|first=Clay|title=Hitler's U-Boat War:The Hunters 1939–1942|year=1996|publisher=Random House|location=New York|isbn=0-394-58839-8}}
* Bragadin, Marc'Antonio: ''The Italian Navy in World War II'', United States Naval Institute, Annapolis, 1957. {{ISBN|0-405-13031-7}}
* Brown, David: ''Warship Losses of World War Two'', Naval Institute Press, Annapolis, 1995. {{ISBN|1-55750-914-X}}
* G.G.Connell, ''Mediterranean Maelstrom: HMS Jervis and the 14th Flotilla'' (1987): ISBN
* {{cite book|last1=Greene|first1=Jack|last2=Massignani|first2=Alessandro|title=The Naval War in the Mediterranean 1940–1943|year=1998|publisher=Chatham Publishing|location=London|isbn= 1-885119-61-5}}
* Eric Groves : ''Sea Battles in Close-Up'' Vol II (1993): {{ISBN|0-7110-2118-X}}
* O'Hara, Vincent P. (2009). ''Struggle for the Middle Sea: the great navies at war in the Mediterranean theater, 1940-1945''. Naval Institute Press. {{ISBN|1-59114-648-8}}
* Stephen Roskill : ''The War at Sea 1939–1945 '' Vol I (1954): ISBN (none)
* {{cite book|last1=Rohwer|first1=Jürgen|last2=Hummelchen|first2=Gerhard|title=Chronology of the War at Sea 1939–1945|year=1992|publisher=Naval Institute Press|location=Annapolis, Maryland|isbn= 1-55750-105-X}}

==External links==
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20090912020612/http://www.regiamarinaitaliana.it/Sirte1.html La I Battaglia della Sirte] {{in lang|it}}
* [http://digilander.libero.it/planciacomando/WW2/primasirte1.htm Prima battaglia della Sirte] – Plancia di Commando {{in lang|it}}

{{coord|34|8|4|N|17|57|5|E|display=title}}

[[Category:Conflicts in 1941|Sirte]]
[[Category:1941 in Libya]]
[[Category:Battle of the Mediterranean|Sirte, First]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Australia|Sirte]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Italy|Sirte]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|F]]
[[Category:Libya in World War II|Sirte, First]]
[[Category:Gulf of Sidra]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in Libya]]
[[Category:Malta Convoys|Sirte, First Battle of]]
[[Category:Mediterranean convoys of World War II|Sirte]]
[[Category:Mine warfare|Sirte]]
[[Category:December 1941 events]]</text><sha1>ke5utrceutq2x7ahsxoa4a2pbzk0r47</sha1></revision></page>