<page><title>Operation Scylla</title><ns>0</ns><id>51035918</id><revision><id>963961352</id><parentid>962793457</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-22T19:56:52Z</timestamp><contributor><username>WikiCleanerBot</username><id>18872885</id></contributor><minor /><comment>v2.02b - [[User:WikiCleanerBot#T18|Bot T18]] - [[WP:WCW]] project (&lt;nowiki&gt; tags)</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="12069" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2016}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Operation Scylla
| partof      = the [[Battle of the Mediterranean]] of [[World War II]]
|image = RM-ScipioneAfricano.jpg
|image_size = 300px
|caption = Italian light cruiser ''Scipione Africano'' at Taranto
|date =17 July 1943
|place = [[Strait of Messina]]
|result = Italian victory
|combatant1 = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
|combatant2 = {{flagicon|Italy|1861}} [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italy]]
|commander1 = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} Dennis Jermain
|commander2 = {{flagicon|Italy|1861}} Ernesto Pellegrini
|strength1 = 4 motor torpedo boats
|strength2 = 1 light cruiser
|casualties1 = 1 motor torpedo boat sunk&lt;br/&gt;2 motor torpedo boats damaged&lt;br/&gt;12 killed
|casualties2 = 1 light cruiser damaged&lt;br/&gt;2 wounded
|campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Mediterranean Naval WW2}}
}}

'''Operation Scylla''' ([[Italian language|Italian]]: ''Operazione Scilla'') was a successful [[Italian Royal Navy|Italian Navy]] attempt to transfer the light cruiser ''[[Capitani Romani-class cruiser|Scipione Africano]]'' from its base in the [[Tyrrhenian Sea]] to [[Taranto]], in the [[Ionian Sea]], during the [[Allied invasion of Sicily]] in July 1943, in the course of [[World War II]]. The operation is notable for the night engagement between the Italian cruiser and four British [[motor torpedo boats]] during the passage of the [[strait of Messina]], in the early hours of 17 July 1943. The action also marked the only time that an Italian warship made an effective combat use of  surface radar in World War II.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal |last1=Preston |first1=Anthony |last2=Ando |first2=Elio |date=1978 |title=Capitani Romani |url= |journal=Warship |volume=5|issue= |pages=155 |quote="The only occasion when Italian radar was used effectively by the units was on the night of 17 July 1943, when Scipione Africano encountered four English motor torpedo boats."|doi= |access-date=}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==The mission==
After the Allied landings in Sicily, and in anticipation of an eventual blockade of the strait of Messina by American and British naval forces, the light cruiser ''Scipione Africano'' was ordered to Taranto to remedy the lack of fast cruisers in the Ionian Sea. The codename of the mission was "Operation Scylla".&lt;ref name=and&gt;Andò, Edoardo (1994) ''Incrociatori leggeri classe "Capitani Romani"''. Albertelli, pp. 80-81. {{ISBN|978-88-85909-45-8}} {{in lang|it}}&lt;/ref&gt; The Italian cruiser departed from [[La Spezia]] on 15 July 1943 bound for [[Naples]], which she reached the same evening, shadowed by a British seaplane. At Naples, ''Scipione Africano'' embarked an air liaison team and [[Metox]] equipment. She sailed again at 18:15 on 16 July and entered the Messina straits at 2:00 on 17 July,&lt;ref&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani (1998), p.290&lt;/ref&gt; with a full moon rising from the south.&lt;ref name=mem&gt;[http://ricerca.gelocal.it/iltirreno/archivio/iltirreno/2011/07/23/LXCPO_LXC01.html Ricordi di battaglia e di vita vissuta a bordo di Scipione] by Ludovica Monarca. ''Il Tirreno'', 23 July 2011 {{in lang|it}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Some days before, on the night of 12 July, British motor torpedo boat ''MTB 81'' had sunk the [[German submarine U-561|German submarine ''U-561'']] in the northern approaches of the straits.&lt;ref name=sub/&gt;

==Night action==
At the same time she reached the straits, ''Scipione Africano'', which had installed an [[Gufo radar|EC-3 ter Gufo]] [[search radar]],&lt;ref name=mem/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Baroni (2007), p. 187&lt;/ref&gt; spotted four small vessels lying 10,000 mt ahead, between [[Reggio di Calabria]] and [[Pellaro|Cape Pellaro]], initially misidentified by the Italian commander, Captain Ernesto Pellegrini, as friendly [[Marinefährprahm|motor barges]]. A closer look to the maneuvers of the leading vessel at 2:13 convinced Pellegrino that the craft were actually hostile motor torpedo boats, and the captain ordered to increase speed from 24 to 30 knots.&lt;ref name=and/&gt;&lt;ref name=pell&gt;{{cite journal|last=De Pellegrini Dai Coi|first=Maurizio|date=January-February 2012|title=Scipione: posto di combattimento|journal=Rivista Marittima|language=it|publisher=[[Italian Navy|Marina Militare]]|pages=28–40}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The motor boats were four British  [[PT boat#Elco|Elco]] [[motor torpedo boat]]s from the 10th MTB flotilla based on [[Augusta, Sicily|Augusta]]: ''MTB 260'', ''MTB 313'', ''MTB 315'' and ''MTB 316''. According to the flotilla's commander, Lieutenant Dennis Jermain, who was onboard ''MTB 315'': "I was caught completely napping. We were lying with engines stopped two miles south of Messina, in a flat calm with a full moon silhoutting us nicely. (...) We never dream that a cruiser wil be able to get down there unseen through our patrols." Jermain gave the alarm and ordered the other boats to start up and scatter.&lt;ref name=dude&gt;[[Dudley Pope|Pope, Dudley]]: ''Flag 4: The Battle of Coastal Forces in the Mediterranean 1939-1945''. Chatham Publishing, 1998, pp. 121-123. {{ISBN|1-86176-067-1}}&lt;/ref&gt; Jermain's mission was to intercept Axis landing
craft and [[E-boat]]s.
With no time to make signals, Jermain moved ''MTB 315'' to the east, leaving two boats for each side of ''Scipione Africano''. Jermain plans were to make a feint with ''MTB 315'' to attract the attention of the cruiser and leave the other boats in a better position for attack.&lt;ref name=dude/&gt;

Meanwhile, Captain Pellegrini had turned his ship to 200 degrees, heading to a point between the second and the third motor boats, namely ''MTB 313'' and ''MTB 316''.&lt;ref name=pell/&gt; ''Scipione Africano''&lt;nowiki/&gt;'s speed surprised the British,&lt;ref name="dude" /&gt; who were not fully prepared to fire their torpedoes until the Italian cruiser was just 1,500 yards away. The Italian warship started to fire all her armament in anger, with a precision that, in Pellegrini's own words, "left him amazed". The Italian report claims that the engagement lasted no more than three minutes, and that the first enemy craft to be hit by 135&amp;nbsp;mm rounds was the closest boat to starboard, which was left in a "sinking condition".&lt;ref name=pell/&gt;  The British unit was actually ''MTB 313'', only 300 yards away from the Italian warship. The small vessel was ready to launch their torpedoes, when incoming fire injured her commander officer Alec Forster in a leg and mortally wounded the spare officer of the flotilla, sub-lieutenant John McKim. One of the torpedoes passed just ahead of its intended target. After this action, the damaged boat limped away.&lt;ref name="MTB" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The other motor torpedo boat on the cruiser's starboard side was ''MTB 260'', which thought to have scored a torpedo hit on the cruiser.&lt;ref name="dude" /&gt; After being engaged by gunfire from ''Scipione Africano'',&lt;ref name="pell" /&gt; ''MTB 260'' got away with minor damage.&lt;ref name="MTB" /&gt; The Italian report says that she was set on fire.&lt;ref name="pell" /&gt;

The next boat to receive the Italian attention was ''MTB 316'', only 50 yards away from ''Scipione Africano''&lt;nowiki/&gt;'s port side. The motor torpedo vessel caught fire and blew up just a few seconds after the cruiser's salvos struck home. The craft, commanded by Lieutenant Richard Adams and with a crew of eleven, sank with all hands.&lt;ref name="pell" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":0"&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.naval-history.net/xDKCas1943-07JUL.htm|title=Royal Navy casualties, killed and died, July 1943|website=www.naval-history.net|access-date=2016-07-09}}&lt;/ref&gt; The explosion took place so close to the cruiser that pieces from ''MTB 316''&lt;nowiki/&gt;'s machinery and hull fell aboard ''Scipione Africano''. The analysis of these remains produced some controversy, when Italian sources claimed to have sunk ''MTB 305'', not at the Mediterranean theatre at the time, on the basis of an inscription from a recovered wooden panel.&lt;ref name="pell" /&gt;

''Scipione Africano'' was checked down the strait by ''MTB 315'' and ''MTB 260'' until she turned to port for Taranto.&lt;ref name="MTB" /&gt;&lt;ref name=":0" /&gt; The Italian commander reported that one of the craft on the port side sent two torpedoes which were successfully dodged by the Italian unit.&lt;ref name="pell" /&gt; The British motorboat was in fact ''MTB 315'',&lt;ref name="dude" /&gt; which became the target of the cruiser's heavy machine guns.&lt;ref name="pell" /&gt;  During the last phase of the action, the Italian cruiser endured the shelling of [[Friendly fire|friendly]] German and Italian coastal artillery, which resulted in splinter damage and two seamen injured.&lt;ref name="pell" /&gt; British sources recorded an air strike on ''Scipione Africano'' by Axis aircraft, not mentioned in Pellegrino's release.&lt;ref name="dude" /&gt;

==Aftermath==
After her eventful passage into the Ionian Sea, ''Scipione Africano'' reached Taranto the same day at 9:46.&lt;ref name=sub&gt;Greene &amp; Massignani (1998), p. 291&lt;/ref&gt; From 4 to 17 August, she laid four defensive minefields in the Gulfs of [[Gulf of Taranto|Taranto]] and [[Gulf of Squillace|Squillace]] along with the old light cruiser ''[[Italian cruiser Luigi Cadorna|Luigi Cadorna]]''.&lt;ref&gt;Cocchia, Aldo (1966). ''La Marina italiana nella seconda guerra mondiale: La guerra di mine''. Ufficio Storico della Marina Militare, p. 397 {{in lang|it}}&lt;/ref&gt; The day after the [[Cassibile armistice]] was made public, ''Scipione Africano'' escorted the corvette ''[[Italian corvette Baionetta (F578)|Baionetta]]'' in her task of transporting the [[Victor Emmanuel III of Italy|Italian Royal Family]] from [[Pescara]] to [[Brindisi]]. At Brindisi, she had to fight off a number of hostile aircraft. From there, ''Scipione Africano'' ferried the new head of government General [[Pietro Badoglio]] and his cabinet to [[Malta]].&lt;ref name=mem/&gt;

Barely an hour after ''Scipione Africano''&lt;nowiki/&gt;'s dash, the Italian submarine ''[[Italian submarine Ambra|Ambra]]'', escorted by the [[Spica-class torpedo boat|torpedo boat ''Partenope'']], reached Messina also from La Spezia. ''Ambra''&lt;nowiki/&gt;'s mission was to launch an attack on allied shipping at [[Syracuse, Sicily|Syracuse]] with [[MT explosive motorboat|MTRs]] on the night of 17 July, but the assault was cancelled after the submarine was damaged the next day not far from its target by depth charges dropped by a British [[Vickers Wellington]] bomber of the [[No. 221 Squadron RAF]]. The Italian submarine limped back to Messina without casualties.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite book|title=La Marina italiana nella seconda guerra mondiale, Volume 14 - I Messi D'Assalto|last=|first=|publisher=Ufficcio Storico della Marina Militare|year=1964|isbn=|location=|pages=249-250|language=Italian}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The morning after the action, the remains of sub-lieutenant McKim were buried at sea off Augusta. No traces of ''MTB 316'' and her crew were ever found by friendly forces.&lt;ref name=MTB&gt;Reynolds, L. C. and Cooper, h. F. (1999) ''MTBs at War''. Sutton Publishing, pp. 71-72. {{ISBN|9780750922746}}&lt;/ref&gt; The following night, another motor torpedo boat, ''MTB 75'', was hit and seriously damaged by shore batteries in the straits of Messina, while on the evening of 19 July, an unidentified U-boat was depth-charged by British small units and had a narrow escape off Reggio di Calabria.&lt;ref name=dude/&gt;

== See also ==
* [[Gufo radar]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==Bibliography==
* Baroni, Piero (2007). ''La guerra dei radar: il suicidio dell'Italia : 1935/1943''. Greco &amp; Greco, p.&amp;nbsp;193. {{ISBN|8879804316}} {{in lang|it}}
* {{cite book |last1=Greene |first1=Jack |last2=Massignani |first2=Alessandro |year=1998 |title=The Naval War in the Mediterranean, 1940–1943 |publisher=Chatham |location=London |isbn=1-885119-61-5}}
{{coord|38|3|20.20|N|15|35|28.35|E|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Scylla, Operation}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1943]]
[[Category:Naval battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Naval battles and operations of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Italian naval victories in the battle of the Mediterranean]]
[[Category:1943 in Italy]]
[[Category:Friendly fire incidents of World War II]]
[[Category:July 1943 events]]</text><sha1>d49fq4dxxma6wgqwcofik8ekckpc258</sha1></revision></page>