<page><title>Capture of Kufra</title><ns>0</ns><id>13757041</id><revision><id>967538096</id><parentid>948512293</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-13T20:46:50Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Mike Peel</username><id>214232</id></contributor><comment>Removing misplaced Commons category link</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="15475" xml:space="preserve">{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2020}}
{{More footnotes|date=September 2010}}
{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict = Battle of Kufra
|partof = [[Operation Compass]], during the [[Second World War]]
|image = File:Carte Koufra.jpg
|image_size = 250px
|caption = Map showing Kufra in south-east Libya
|date = 31 January – 1 March 1941
|place = [[Kufra]], [[Libya]]
|coordinates = {{coord|24|11|N|23|17|E|type:city|display=title}}
|result = Allied victory
|combatant1 = {{flagicon|Free French}} [[Free France]]&lt;br /&gt;{{flag|United Kingdom}}
|combatant2 = {{flagicon|Italy|1861}} [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italy]]
|commander1 ={{flagicon|Free French}} [[Philippe Leclerc de Hauteclocque|Col. Philippe Leclerc]]
|commander2 ={{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} Capt. Colonna
|strength1 =1 [[Free French Forces|FFF]] [[Battalion]] (350 men)&lt;br /&gt;1 [[LRDG]] (76 men)&lt;br /&gt;60 trucks
|strength2 =2 [[Askari|Italian Askari Company]] (310 men)&lt;br /&gt;1 [[Auto-Saharan Company]] (120 men)&lt;br /&gt;20 trucks&lt;br /&gt;4 aircraft
|casualties1 = 4 killed&lt;br /&gt;21 wounded
|casualties2 = 3 killed&lt;br /&gt;4 wounded&lt;br /&gt;282 captured&lt;br /&gt;3 aircraft destroyed
|campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Free French}}
{{Campaignbox Western Desert}}
}}
The '''Capture of Kufra ({{lang|fr|Prise de Koufra}}''', {{lang-it|Cufra}}) was part of the Allied [[Western Desert Campaign]] during the [[Second World War]]. Kufra is a [[Depression (geology)|basin]] and [[oasis]] group in the [[Kufra District]] of south-eastern [[Cyrenaica]] in the [[Libyan Desert]]. In 1940, it was part of the colony of [[Italian Libya]] {{lang|it|Libia Italiana}}, which was part of {{lang|it|Africa Settentrionale Italiana}} (ASI), which was established in 1934. With some early assistance from the British [[Long Range Desert Group]], [[Kufra]] was captured by [[Free France|Free French Forces]] when the Italian and Libyan garrison surrendered after a siege from 31 January to 1 March 1941.

==Background==
Kufra, in the [[Libyan Desert]] subregion of the [[Sahara]], was an important trade and travel centre for the nomadic desert peoples of the region, including [[Berbers]] and [[Senussi]]. The Senussi made the oasis their capital at one point against British, Italian and [[French Third Republic|French]] designs on the region. In 1931, the [[Kingdom of Italy]] captured Kufra and incorporated it into the [[Italian North Africa]] ({{lang|it|Africa [[Septentrional|Settentrionale]] Italiana}}) colonisation of the [[Maghreb]]. The Italian post at Kufra included the [[Kufra Airport|Buma airfield]] and radio station, used for air supply and communications with [[Italian East Africa]] and a fort at the nearby village of [[El Tag]].

==Prelude==
After the Allied defeat of 1940 in the [[Battle of France]], the colony of [[French Equatorial Africa]] (FEA) declared its allegiance to [[Free France]], the government-in-exile led by [[Charles de Gaulle]]. [[Chad]], the northern part of FEA, borders Libya. De Gaulle ordered the Free French in Chad to attack Italian positions in Libya. Kufra was the obvious target and the troops available to the Free French commander in [[French Chad|Chad]], [[Lieutenant Colonel]] Jean Colonna d'Ornano, were 5,000 {{lang|fr|[[tirailleur]]s}} (riflemen) of the [[Senegal]]ese Light Infantry Regiment of Chad ({{lang|fr|Régiment de Tirailleurs Sénégalais du Tchad}} (RTST) in twenty companies garrisoning various places and three detachments of {{lang|fr|[[méhariste]]}} ([[camel cavalry]]), in [[Borkou]], [[Tibesti]] and [[Ennedi]].

Attacking Kufra would be very difficult for this motley force. The Free French had very little motor transport and needed to cross {{convert|400|km|mi|0|abbr=on}} of desert, much of which was sand dune or the fine, powdery soil called {{lang|ar|[[fech fech]]}} which was thought impassable to motor vehicles. The French received assistance from the British [[Long Range Desert Group]] (LRDG), a reconnaissance and raiding unit formed to operate behind the Italian lines, who had become expert in desert navigation. [[Major]] [[Pat Clayton]] of the LRDG was keen to join with the Free French to test the Italians. Clayton commanded G Guard (Brigade of Guards) and T Patrol (New Zealand) of the LRDG, 76 men in 26 vehicles.

The LRDG and Free French first raided the Italian airfield at [[Murzuk]], in the {{lang|it|[[Territorio Sahara Libico]]}}–[[Fezzan]] region in south-western Libya. D'Ornano and ten Free French (three officers, two sergeants and five local soldiers) met Clayton's LRDG patrols on 6 January 1941 at Kayouge.{{efn|There is no inhabited place named Kayouge in southern Libya or northern Chad. The meeting point must have been the Kayouge Enneri Wadi, that is quite close to the town of Zouar in north-western Chad at 20°4'60" N and 16°45'0" E in DMS (Degrees Minutes Seconds) or 20.0833 and 16.75 (in decimal degrees).}} The combined force reached Murzuk on 11 January and in a daring daylight raid, surprised the sentries and devastated the base. Most of the force attacked the main fort; a troop from T Patrol under Lieutenant Ballantyne attacked the airfield, destroying three [[Caproni]] aircraft and capturing some prisoners; D'Ornano was killed in this raid along with one trooper of T Patrol.{{sfn|Mortimer|2010|p=44}} A French officer cauterised his leg wound with a cigarette, much to the admiration of the LRDG. A diversionary raid by French camel cavalry failed after it was betrayed by local guides. These troops were relegated to reconnaissance duties only.

==Battle==
{{see also|Operation Compass}}

[[File:Laffly S15T May1940.jpg|thumb|{{center|French Laffly S15T towing a 75 mm gun (photographed in May 1940}}]]
[[Colonel]] [[Philippe Leclerc de Hauteclocque|Philippe Leclerc]] assumed command in place of d'Ornano. After the success of the Murzuk raid, Leclerc marshalled his forces to take on Kufra. The attacking column included about 400 men in sixty trucks, two [[Laffly S15]] ({{lang|fr|théâtre d'opérations extérieures}} TOE) [[scout car]]s, four Laffly S15R cross country personnel carriers and two {{convert|75|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} [[mountain gun]]s. Kufra was protected by two defensive lines around the El Tag fort with barbed wire, trenches, machine-guns and light [[anti-aircraft artillery|anti-aircraft guns]]. The [[Royal Italian Army during World War II|Royal Italian Army]] ({{lang|it|Regio Esercito}}) garrison comprised the 59th and 60th Machine-gun companies, with 280 {{Lang|it|[[askari]]}} (local infantry) and an [[Auto-Saharan Company]], the {{lang|it|Compagnia Sahariana di Cufra}}. The Saharan companies were a mixed force of motorised infantry with well-armed cross-country vehicles (SPA [[AS37]]), which could also call on the {{lang|it|[[Regia Aeronautica]]}} (Italian Royal Air Force) for support. The {{lang|it|Compagnia Sahariana}} in Kufra was around 120-men strong (45 Italians and 75 Libyans).{{sfn|Molinari|2007|pp=27–29}}

Leclerc asked the LRDG to deal with the Saharan company, based in El Tag fort in the Kufra oasis. The LRDG was detected by a radio intercept unit at Kufra and the Italians organised a mobile column of forty men, one AS37 and four [[FIAT 634]] lorries to intercept them. G Patrol had been kept in reserve. On 31 January, Major Clayton was at Bishara ({{convert|130|km|mi|abbr=on}} south-south-west of Kufra) with T Patrol (30 men in 11 trucks). The patrol was spotted by an Italian aeroplane in the morning. T Patrol took cover in a small [[wadi]] at [[Gebel Sherif]], a few kilometres north. The plane directed the Saharan patrol to attack the LRDG force. Due to the fire-power of the Italian vehicles were armed with {{convert|20|mm|in|2|abbr=on}} cannon and constant air attack, T Patrol was driven off, losing four trucks and Major Clayton, who was captured with several others.{{sfn|Leclerc|1948|p=100}} Trooper [[Ronald Moore (Trooper)|Ronald Moore]] led other survivors to safety after a long foot march. The remaining LRDG force withdrew to Egypt for refitting, except for one vehicle of T Patrol, equipped for desert navigation. During the fight, 1st Lieutenant Caputo, in command of the {{lang|it|Compagnia Sahariana}}, was killed as were two Libyan soldiers.{{sfn|Molinari|2007|p=52}}

[[File:AS37 cassonato.jpg|thumb|{{centre|AS37 {{lang|it|Autocarro Sahariano}}}}]]
Leclerc pressed on with his attack, even though the Italians had captured a copy of his plans from Major Clayton. After conducting further reconnaissance, Leclerc reorganised his forces on 16 February. He abandoned his two armoured cars and took with him the remaining serviceable artillery piece. Only about 350 men reached Kufra, due to breakdowns of trucks on the march. Aware of the French approach, the Italians organised another strong mobile column from the Saharan company (seventy men, ten AS37 and five trucks).{{sfn|Molinari|2007|p=57}} On 17 February, Leclerc's forces met the {{lang|it|Compagnia Sahariana}} north of Kufra. Despite losing many trucks to the 20&amp;nbsp;mm guns of the Italian AS37 cars, the French drove off the {{lang|it|Compagnia Sahariana}} as the Kufra garrison failed to intervene. The French surrounded El Tag and laid siege to the fort, despite another attack by the {{lang|it|Compagnia Sahariana}} and harassment from the air. The 75&amp;nbsp;mm gun was placed {{convert|3000|m|km+mi|0|abbr=on}} from the fort, beyond range of the defenders and fired twenty shells per day at regular intervals from different places to give the appearance of more guns.{{sfn|Leclerc|1948|p=111}} Some [[81mm mortar|{{convert|81|mm|in|1|abbr=on}} mortar]]s were placed {{convert|1500|m|yd|0|abbr=on}} from the fort and bombed the Italian positions to increase the pressure on the defenders.{{sfn|Martel|1994|p=108}}

===Italian surrender===
The fort was commanded by an inexperienced reserve captain, who lacked the will and the determination to fight.{{sfn|Molinari|2007|p=57}} Surrender negotiations began on 28 February and on 1 March 1941, the Italian garrison of 11 officers, 18 NCOs and 273 Libyan soldiers (12, 47 and 273, according to French sources) surrendered El Tag and the Kufra oasis to the Free French. During the siege, the Italian garrison had suffered one Italian officer killed, two Libyan soldiers killed and four wounded; the French suffered four fatal casualties and 21 wounded. The Italian garrison was permitted to withdraw to the north-west and the French forces took over eight [[SPA AS.37]] {{lang|it|Autocarro Sahariano}} light trucks, six lorries, four 20&amp;nbsp;mm cannon and 53 machine-guns.{{sfn|Martel|1994|p=108}}

==Orders of battle==

'''French'''
* HQ: 1 [[Matford]] truck, 2 [[Chevrolet]] light trucks, 2 [[Bedford Vehicles|Bedford]] 1.5 ton trucks, 1 ER26bis radio
* 1 reduced infantry company (Captain Rennepont): 23 Bedford 1.5 ton trucks
* 2 platoons, GN Ennedi (Captain Barboten): 120 men, 1 [[Dodge]] truck, 16 Matford V8 3 ton trucks
* 1 platoon, 7th Company, RTST (Captain Florentin): 60 men, 1 Dodge truck, 2 Matford V8 3 ton trucks
* Artillery platoon (Lieutenant Ceccaldi): 2 75&amp;nbsp;mm Mle1928 Schneider mountain guns, 4 Laffly S15 carriers, 1 Dodge truck, 2 Matford V8 3 ton trucks
* Armoured car detachment (Adjudant Detouche): 2 Laffly S15TOE, 1 Matford V8 3 ton truck, 1 ER26bis/39 radio

----

'''Italian'''
* HQ forces ''Settore Cufra'' (Kufra sector)
* 59th {{lang|it|Compagnia mitraglieri}}: 3 officers, 1 NCO, 3 Italian enlisted, 110 colonial troops enlisted, 13 MG (8&amp;nbsp;mm [[Schwarzlose 07/12]] or 6.5&amp;nbsp;mm FIAT mod. 14)
* 60th {{lang|it|Compagnia mitraglieri}}: 3 officers, 1 NCO, 3 Italian enlisted, 110 colonial troops enlisted, 13 MG (8&amp;nbsp;mm Schwarzlose 07/12 or 6.5&amp;nbsp;mm FIAT mod. 14)
* {{lang|it|Compagnia Sahariana di Cufra}} (LT Caputo – KIA): 4 officers, 7 NCO, 32 Italian enlisted, 77 colonial troops enlisted, 16 AS 37 off-road vehicles, 4 FIAT 634 trucks
* {{lang|it|Sezione aeroplani}}: 4 officers, 4 NCO, 32 Italian enlisted, four aircraft

{{anchor|Oath}}

==Oath of Kufra==
[[File:Serment de Koufra 2 mars 1941.JPG|thumb|Oath of Kufra, 2 March 1941]]
After the fall of Kufra, Leclerc and his troops swore an oath to fight until "our flag flies over the Cathedral of [[Strasbourg]]"

{{quote|Swear not to lay down arms until our colours, our beautiful colours, fly over [[Strasbourg Cathedral]].|Leclerc{{sfn|Jennings|2015|p=120}}}}

The oath was fulfilled on 23 November 1944, when Leclerc and the French [[2nd Armored Division (France)|2nd Armoured Division]] liberated Strasbourg.{{sfn|herodote|2011|nopp=y}}

==See also==
{{Portal|World War II}}
* [[North African Campaign timeline]]
* [[List of World War II Battles]]
* [[Sudan Defence Force]]
* [[Kufra District]]

==Notes==
{{notelist}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|20em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite web |ref={{harvid|herodote|2011}}
|title=2 mars 1941: Le "serment de Koufra" et le triomphe de la France Libre |trans-title=The Testament of Koufra and the Glory of the Free French |url=http://www.herodote.net/2_mars_1941-evenement-19410302.php |work=herodote.net |accessdate=27 December 2015}}&lt;!--link recovered--&gt;
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Jennings|2015}}
|title=Free French Africa in World War II: The African Resistance |last=Jennings |first=E. T. |year=2015 |publisher=Cambridge University Press |location=London |edition=1st Engl. |isbn=978-1-10704-848-5}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Leclerc|1948}}
|last=Le Clerc de Hauteclocque |first=Philippe |authorlink=Philippe Leclerc de Hauteclocque |title=Le Général Leclerc vu par ses compagnons de combat |trans-title=General Leclerc Seen by his Fellow Soldiers |language=French |publisher=Éditions Alsatia |year=1948 |location=Paris |oclc=3459863}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Martel|1994}}
|last=Martel |first=Andre |title=Histoire militaire de la France |trans-title=Military History of France |language=French |publisher=Presses Universitaires de France |year=1994 |location=Paris |isbn=2-13-046074-7}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Molinari|2007}}
|last=Molinari |first=Andrea |title=Desert Raiders: Axis and Allied Special Forces 1940–43 |publisher=Osprey |year=2007 |location=Oxford |isbn=978-1-84603-006-2}}
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|Mortimer|2010}}
|last=Mortimer |first=D. |journal=World War II |date=July–August 2010 |title=Pirates of the Sand Seas: Britain's Legendary Long Range Desert Group |publisher=Historynet.com World History Group |location=Leesburg, VA |oclc=46829545}}
{{refend}}

==Further reading==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |last=Kelly |first=Saul |title=The Hunt for Zerzura, the Lost Oasis and the Desert War |publisher=John Murray |year=2002 |location=London |isbn= 0-7195-6162-0}}
* {{cite book |last=Morgan |first=M. |title=Sting of the Scorpion |publisher=Sutton |year=2000 |location=Stroud |isbn=0-7509-2481-0}}
{{refend}}

==External links==
* [http://warart.archives.govt.nz/node/343 Peter McIntyre, Salt Lake at Kufra Oasis, 1941–1943 (Painting)]
*  [https://www.google.com/maps/place/Kayouge,+Tchad/@19.8638803,22.2691313,1679754m/data=!3m1!1e3!4m2!3m1!1s0x115e0eb6acf1fc7d:0xbb70cfcdfb71d5f8 Real location of Kayouge rendezvous]

{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kufra, Capture of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1941]]
[[Category:1941 in Libya]]
[[Category:Western Desert Campaign]]
[[Category:Libya in World War II]]
[[Category:Kufra District]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving France]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom|C]]</text><sha1>rl0two9noqblw24j7r66ujrbo349zoe</sha1></revision></page>