<page><title>Battle of Elaia–Kalamas</title><ns>0</ns><id>25973759</id><revision><id>886778037</id><parentid>867935443</parentid><timestamp>2019-03-08T13:46:46Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Adapad</username><id>31407554</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="10519" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
|conflict=Battle of Elaia–Kalamas
|partof=the [[Greco-Italian War]]
|image=Kalamas1939.JPG
|image_size=240px
|caption=Trench construction in Elaia–Kalamas line by Greek military personnel, March 1939
|date=2–8 November 1940
|place=[[Epirus (region)|Epirus]]
|coordinates = {{Coord|39|35|12|N|20|08|32|E|display=INLINE,title}}
|result=Greek victory
|combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
|combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Greece}}
|commander1  = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} Ezio Rossi&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;([[XXV Army Corps (Italy)|XXV Army Corps]])&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} Gen. Giannini&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(23rd Division)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} Gen. Maglie&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(131st Division)&lt;/small&gt;
|commander2  = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece}} [[Charalambos Katsimitros]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(8th Infantry Division)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece}} [[Nikolaos Lioumbas]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Thesprotia Sector)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece}} [[Dimitrios Giatzis]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Kalamas Sector)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece}} [[Georgios Dres]]&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(Negrades Sector){{sfn|AHD|1960|p=49}}&lt;/small&gt;
|units1      = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[23rd Infantry Division Ferrara|23rd Infantry Division]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[51st Infantry Division Siena|51st Infantry Division]]&lt;br&gt;{{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[131st Armoured Division Centauro|131st Armoured Division]]
|units2      = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Greece}} [[8th Infantry Division (Greece)|8th Infantry Division]]
|strength1   = 42,000&lt;br&gt;170 light tanks&lt;br&gt;76 guns&lt;br&gt;400 aircraft
|strength2   = 15 battalions&lt;br&gt;56 guns&lt;br&gt;&lt;small&gt;(14 batteries){{sfn|AHD|1960|p=49}}&lt;/small&gt;
|casualties1 = '''28 October–5 November''':&lt;br&gt;160 killed&lt;br&gt;41 missing&lt;br&gt;561 wounded
|casualties2 = '''1–5 November''':&lt;br&gt;59 killed&lt;br&gt;208 wounded{{sfn|AHD|1960|p=114}}
|campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Greco-Italian War}}
|map_type=Greece
|map_relief=y
}}
The '''Battle of Elaia–Kalamas''' ({{lang-el|Μάχη Ελαίας-Καλαμά}}, ''Machi Elaias-Kalama'') took place in [[Epirus (region)|Epirus]] from 2–8 November 1940. The battle was fought between the [[Kingdom of Greece|Greeks]] and the [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italians]] during the initial stage of the [[Greco-Italian War]]. The [[Royal Italian Army (1940–1946)|Italian Army]], deployed on the Greek-Albanian border, launched an offensive against Greece on 28 October 1940. The main thrust of the Italian invasion occurred in the Epirus sector, with a further flanking move through the [[Pindus mountains]]. In Epirus, the Greeks held the [[Kalpaki|Elaia]]–[[Kalamas river]] line, and even though the Greek army was outnumbered, the local Greek forces under Major General [[Charalambos Katsimitros]] managed to stop the Italian advance.{{sfn|Koliopoulos|Veremis|2009|p=107}} Along with the Italian failure in the [[Battle of Pindus]], these Greek successes signified the complete failure of the Italian invasion, leading to the dismissal of the Italian commander in Albania, [[Sebastiano Visconti Prasca]], on 9 November. In the next few weeks the Greek forces managed to initiate a counter-offensive, which forced the Italians to retreat deep into Albania.

==Background==
After the [[Italian invasion of Albania]] in April 1939, the Greek General Staff became alerted to a potential Italian attack from Albanian territory. Faced with the strong likelihood of a concerted Italian-Bulgarian attack against both Epirus and [[Macedonia (Greece)|Macedonia]]-[[Western Thrace|Thrace]], the main Greek contingency plan, codenamed "IB" (for "Italy-Bulgaria"), essentially prescribed a defensive stance in Epirus. Two versions of the plan existed: the first suggested forward defence on the border line, while the second dictated initial defense in an intermediate position prior to a gradual retreat to the [[Arachthos River]]–[[Metsovo]]–[[Aliakmon River]]–[[Vermio Mountains|Mt. Vermio]] line, leaving most of Epirus in Italian hands. It was left to the judgment of the local commander of the [[8th Infantry Division (Greece)|8th Infantry Division]], based in [[Ioannina]], Charalambos Katsimitros, to choose which plan to follow.{{sfn|Koliopoulos|Veremis|2009|p=107}} A significant factor in Greek favor was that they had managed to obtain intelligence about the approximate date of the attack, and had just completed a limited [[mobilization]] in the areas facing the expected Italian plans.{{sfn|Sakellariou|1997|p=389}}

==Battle==
[[File:Greek soldier Kalpaki 1940.jpg|thumb|Greek soldier sitting on a captured Italian [[L3/35]] tankette.]]
The Greek High Command in the first days of the conflict was pessimistic about the ability of the [[Hellenic Army|Greek Army]] to repulse an Italian attack, against a position which was difficult to defend. The defensive line near the Greek-Albanian border could only be thinly manned, before the general mobilization and concentration could be completed and thus was expected to fight the enemy forces only in order to delay their advance.{{sfn|Koliopoulos|Veremis|2009|p=107}}

The commander of the only Greek division ([[8th Infantry Division (Greece)|8th Infantry Division]]) covering that part of the border, Major General [[Charalambos Katsimitros]], realised the strategic value of the area, in which the Italian superiority in men and armour had limited value because of the mountainous and marshy terrain. Contrary to the directives from the High Command under Lieutenant General [[Alexander Papagos]], he concentrated the main forces of his division there, with the intention to give an all-out battle in that position. Papagos had reluctantly approved Katsimitros's plan, after sending Colonel Drakos as a new chief of staff in the division, who after careful study of the area, also agreed with the plan.{{sfn|Katsimētros|2007|p=}}

The Italian forces initiated their offensive on the morning of 28 October. The Italian ''Ciamuria'' Corps, spearheaded by the [[51st Infantry Division Siena|51st Infantry Division ''Siena'']] and [[23rd Infantry Division Ferrara|23rd Infantry Division ''Ferrara'']] (''Ferrara'' Division) and the [[131st Armoured Division Centauro|131st Armoured Division ''Centauro'']], attacked toward [[Kalpaki]] (Elaia), while on its right it was supported by a small brigade-sized ''Littoral Group'' of ca. 5,000 men.

According to the plans the Greek screening units started a slow retreat toward the main defensive line of Elaia-Kalamas, about {{convert|30|km|mi|0|abbr=on}} southward of the Greek-Albanian border, north of Ioannina. On the 2 November, the Greek forces were positioned according to the defensive plan in the line: Kalamas–Elaia–Grabala–Kleftis hill. On this day, after repeated air and artillery strikes, the Italian infantry of the ''Ferrara'' Division attacked unsuccessfully in order to advance the bulk of their forces closer to Elaia sector.{{sfn|Gedeon|1997|p=}}

The Italians faced difficulties because of the harshness of the terrain. The next day, their light [[L3/35]] [[tankette]]s and medium [[Fiat M13/40|M13/40]] tanks were unable to cope with the hilly terrain and the muddy ground. The Greek defensive line could not be breached. On its right, the Littoral Group managed a slow advance along the coast and was able to secure a bridgehead over the Kalamas River on the 5 November. The winter weather, poor leadership and minefields, caused the Italians many casualties.{{sfn|Willingham|2005|p=28}} On the 8 November, the fruitless Italian offensive was suspended.{{sfn|Gedeon|1997|p=}} Because of the complete failure of the Italian operations, commander [[Sebastiano Visconti Prasca]] was relieved of his command after only two weeks and replaced with General [[Ubaldo Soddu]].{{sfn|Mitcham|2007|p=114}}

==Aftermath==
After the successful Greek defense in Elea-Kalamas and in the mountains of [[Battle of Pindus|Pindus]], the Greek forces were able to push back the Italians, advancing into southern Albania. Before the [[Battle of Greece|German intervention]] in April 1941, the Greeks penetrated {{convert|30|–|80|km|mi}} into Albanian territory.{{sfn|Gedeon|1997|p=}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Gedeon|1997}}
|last=Gedeon |first=Dimitrios |title=An abridged history of the Greek-Italian and Greek-German war, 1940–1941: (land operations) |year=1997 |publisher=Hellenic Army General Staff, Army History Directorate |location=Athens |isbn=978-960-7897-01-5}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Katsimētros|2007}}
|series=Bibliothēkē Ēpeirōtikēs Hetaireias Athēnōn |number=61 |title=Ē Ēpeiros promachusa : ē drasē tēs VIII merarchias kata ton polemo 1940–41 |language=Greek |last=Katsimētros |first=Charalampus |authorlink= |year=2007 |publisher=Ēpeirōtikē Etaireia |location=Athens |edition= |isbn=960-89690-0-X}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Koliopoulos|Veremis|2009}}
|first1=Giannēs |last1=Koliopoulos |last2=Veremis |first2=Thanos M. |title=Modern Greece: A History Since 1821 |publisher=Wiley-Blackwell |location= |year=2009 |isbn=978-1-4051-8681-0}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Mitcham|2007}}
|last=Mitcham |first=Samuel W. |title=Eagles of the Third Reich: Men of the Luftwaffe in World War II |year=2007 |publisher=Stackpole Books |location=Mechanicsburg, PA |isbn=978-0-8117-3405-9}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Sakellariou|1997}}
|last=Sakellariou |first=M. V. |title=Epirus, 4,000 years of Greek History and Civilization |publisher=Ekdotikē Athēnōn |location=Athens |year=1997 |isbn=978-960-213-371-2}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|AHD|1960}}
|author=&lt;!--Staff writer(s); no by-line.--&gt; |title=Η Ιταλική Εισβολή |trans-title=The Italian Invasion |year=1960 |publisher=Army History Directorate |location=Athens |oclc=}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Willingham|2005}}
|last=Willingham |first=Matthew |title=Perilous Commitments: the Battle for Greece and Crete: 1940–1941 |year=2005 |publisher=Spellmount |location=Staplehurst UK|isbn=978-1-86227-236-1}}
{{refend}}

{{Greece during World War II|state=collapsed}}
{{World War II}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Elaia-Kalamas, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Conflicts in 1940]]
[[Category:1940 in Greece]]
[[Category:Battles of the Greco-Italian War|Elaia]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Greece]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Epirus in World War II]]
[[Category:November 1940 events]]</text><sha1>l28anc0b2f4zpk3aqw4u4r5lr1aw6dg</sha1></revision></page>