<page><title>Battle of Himara</title><ns>0</ns><id>34605165</id><revision><id>961856597</id><parentid>928616400</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-10T19:35:12Z</timestamp><contributor><username>NedFausa</username><id>38063585</id></contributor><minor /><comment>copy edit</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="7293" xml:space="preserve">{{Infobox military conflict
 |conflict    = Battle of [[Himara]]
 |partof      = the [[Greco-Italian War]]
 |image       = Greek Offensive 1940 41 in Northern Epirus.svg
 |image_size  = 300
 |caption     = Greek counter-offensive
 |date        = {{start and end date|1940|12|13|1940|12|22|df=y}}
 |place       = [[Himara]], Albania
 |result      = Greek victory; capture of Himara
 |combatant1  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
 |combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Greece}}
 |commander1  = 
 |commander2  = {{ubl|[[Georgios Bakos]]|[[Thrasyvoulos Tsakalotos]]}}
 |units1      = {{ubl|[[51 Infantry Division Siena]]}}
 |units2      = {{ubl|[[3rd Infantry Division (Greece)|3rd Infantry Division]]|[[3/40 Evzone Regiment]]}}
 |campaignbox = {{Campaignbox Greco-Italian War}}
}}

The '''Battle of Himara''' ({{lang-el|Η Μάχη της Χειμάρρας}}) was a military conflict that took place in the [[Greco-Italian War]] in December 1940, during the counteroffensive of the [[Kingdom of Greece|Greek]] Army that followed the failed [[Kingdom of Italy (1861–1946)|Italian]] invasion of Greece. After the Greek victory in Himara, the Italian dictator [[Benito Mussolini]], admitted that one of the causes of the Italian defeat was the high morale of the Greek troops.

==Background==
The [[Royal Italian Army during World War II|Italian Army]], initially deployed on the Greek–[[Albania]]n border, launched a major offensive against Greece on 28 October 1940. After a two-week conflict, Greece managed to repel the invading Italians in the battles of [[Battle of Pindus|Pindus]] and [[Battle of Elaia–Kalamas|Elaia–Kalamas]]. Beginning on 9 November, the Greek forces launched a counteroffensive and penetrated deep into Italian-held Albanian territory all over the front. As a result, the Greek forces entered the cities and towns of the region one after another: [[Korçë]], on 22 November, [[Pogradec]], on 30 November, [[Sarandë]], on 6 December and [[Gjirokastër]], on 8 December.{{sfn|Willmott|2008|p=}}

==Battle==
[[File:PROKOPIOU-AIXMALOTI.jpg|thumb|Italian POW, December 1940]]

On 13 December, Porto Palermo, a coastal village south of Himara came under the control of the Greek forces.{{sfn|Storrs|Graves|1940|p=112}} Two days later, the Greek [[3rd Infantry Division (Greece)|3rd Infantry Division]] continued the offensive toward Himara. However, the advance was slowed due to heavy enemy counter-action, supported by air force raids, as well as extremely harsh weather conditions. On 19 December, the Greek forces after a hard fight captured the Giami height.{{sfn|Gedeon|1997|p=117}} Meanwhile, at the dawn of same day, the [[3/40 Evzone Regiment]] (Colonel [[Thrasyvoulos Tsakalotos]]) launched, without artillery preparation, a surprise attack against the Italian troops at Mount Mali i Xhorët (or Mount Pilur), a strategic spot east of Himara. The [[Evzones]] of the regiment, after being informed about the topography of the region by locals, performed a charge with fixed bayonets from various positions against the Italian garrison.{{sfn|Terzakis|1990|pp=149–150}}

The snow was {{convert|3|m|ft}} high, which helped the advancing Greek troops to cross barbed wire and capture an Italian mountain battery.{{sfn|Storrs|Graves|1940|p=112}} After three days of fierce fighting, the men of the 3rd Division took control of the height, as well as the [[Kuç,Vlorë|Kuç]] saddle. The capture of Kuç saddle gave access to the valley of [[Shushicë (river)|Shushicë]]. Furthermore, the Italian troops lost six artillery guns, a mortar company and a multitude of war supplies. The Greek losses did not exceed 100 killed in action and wounded, while the Italians had approximately 400 casualties and more than 900 were taken prisoner.{{sfn|Gedeon|1997|p=117}} On 21 December, the Greek forces captured the height of Tsipista north-west of Himara. To avoid encirclement, the Italians abandoned Himara. Finally, the Greek troops entered the town in the morning on 22 December, where they were welcomed by the locals with enthusiastic celebrations.{{sfn|Gedeon|1997|p=117}}

==Aftermath==
The capture of Himara was celebrated as a major success in Greece and proved that the Greek army was in condition to continue the advance pushing the Italians further north.{{sfn|Cervi|1972|p=188}}{{sfn|Willingham|2005|p=36}} On the other hand, the Italian headquarters was alarmed by the Greek success, and on 24 December [[Benito Mussolini]] addressed his concerns to the Italian military commander, [[Ugo Cavallero]].{{sfn|Gedeon|1997|p=117}} In his letter, Mussolini does not doubt that one of the causes of the Italian defeat was the high morale of the Greek forces, which led to their capture of Himara.{{sfn|Tsirpanlis|1992|pp=111–190}}

==Footnotes==
{{reflist|colwidth=30em}}

==References==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Cervi|1972}}
|last=Cervi |first=Mario |authorlink=Mario Cervi |others=transl. from the Italian by [[Eric Mosbacher]] |title=The Hollow Legions: Mussolini's Blunder in Greece, 1940–1941 |year=1972 |publisher=Chatto &amp; Windus |location=London |isbn=978-0-7011-1351-3}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Gedeon|1997}}
|last=Gedeon |first=Dimitrios |title=An Abridged History of the Greek-Italian and Greek-German War, 1940–1941: (land operations) |year=1997 |publisher=Hellenic Army General Staff, Army History Directorate |location=Athens |isbn=978-960-7897-01-5}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Storrs|Graves|1940}}
|last1=Storrs |first1=Sir Ronald |authorlink=Ronald Storrs |last2=Graves |first2=Philip Perceval |authorlink2=Philip Graves |title=A Record of the War |year=1940 |publisher=Hutchinson |location=London |oclc=1523010}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Terzakis|1990}}
|last=Terzakis |first=Angelos |script-title=el:Ελληνική Εποποιϊα 1940–1941 |trans-title=The Greek Epic 1940–1941 |year=1990 |publisher=Hellenic Army General Staff |location=Athens |language=Greek |oclc=26524374}}
* {{cite journal |ref={{harvid|Tsirpanlis|1992}}
|last=Tsirpanlis |first=Zacharias N. |title=The Morale of the Greek and the Italian Soldier in the 1940–41 War |journal=Balkan Studies |year=1992 |volume=33 |publisher=[[Institute for Balkan Studies (Greece)|Institute for Balkan Studies]] |location=New York |issn=0005-4313}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Willingham|2005}}
|last=Willingham |first=Matthew |title=Perilous Commitments: The Battle for Greece and Crete: 1940–1941 |year=2005 |publisher=Spellmount |location=Staplehurst |isbn=978-1-86227-236-1}}
* {{cite book |ref={{harvid|Willmott|2008}}
|last=Willmott |first=H. P. |title=The Great Crusade: A New Complete History of the Second World War |year=2008 |publisher=Potomac Books |location=Washington, D.C. |edition=revised |isbn=978-1-59797-191-1}}
{{refend}}

{{Greece during World War II|state=collapsed}}
{{World War II}}

{{coord missing|Albania}}

{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2017}}
{{Authority control}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Himara}}
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Greece|Himara]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Italy|Himara]]
[[Category:Conflicts in 1940]]
[[Category:1940 in Albania]]
[[Category:1940 in Greece]]
[[Category:Battles of the Greco-Italian War|Himara]]
[[Category:Himara]]
[[Category:December 1940 events]]</text><sha1>fpzskccrukktehjvb64eeaw7y6is4ic</sha1></revision></page>