<page><title>Battle of Rethymno</title><ns>0</ns><id>27047356</id><revision><id>964887506</id><parentid>957566102</parentid><timestamp>2020-06-28T04:56:08Z</timestamp><contributor><username>InternetArchiveBot</username><id>27015025</id></contributor><comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead.) #IABot (v2.0.1</comment><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="10565" xml:space="preserve">{{More citations needed|date=April 2010}}
{{Infobox military conflict|conflict   = Battle of &lt;br/&gt; Rethymnon/Retimo
|partof     = [[World War II]], [[Battle of Crete]]
|image      =
|caption    =
|date       = 20 May 1941
|place      = [[Rethymnon]], [[Crete]]
|result     = [[Allies of World War II|Allied]]&amp;nbsp;tactical&amp;nbsp;victory;&amp;nbsp;[[Nazi Germany|German]]&amp;nbsp;strategic&amp;nbsp;victory.
|combatant1 = {{flagicon|Greece|royal}}&amp;nbsp;[[Kingdom of Greece|Greece]] &lt;br&gt; {{flag|Australia}}
|combatant2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}} [[Nazi Germany|Germany]]
|commander1 = {{flagicon|Australia}}&amp;nbsp;Lieutenant-Colonel [[Ian Ross Campbell|Ian&amp;nbsp;Campbell]] 
|commander2 = {{flagicon|Nazi Germany}}&amp;nbsp;''Oberst'' [[Alfred Sturm|Alfred&amp;nbsp;Sturm]]&amp;nbsp;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;nowiki&gt;[&lt;/nowiki&gt;[[prisoner of war|POW]]&lt;nowiki&gt;]&lt;/nowiki&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
|strength1  = ~ 4,600 &lt;small&gt;(1,200 Australian regular infantry; 3,400 Greek reservists &amp; [[gendarmerie]])&lt;/small&gt;
|strength2  = ~ 3,500 &lt;small&gt;(one parachute infantry regiment &amp; support personnel)&lt;/small&gt;
|casualties1= Unknown
|casualties2= Unknown
}}
{{Campaignbox Mediterranean Campaign}}
{{Campaignbox Balkans Campaign}}

The '''Battle of Rethymno''', also commonly known as the '''Battle of Retimo''', was a battle fought during [[World War II]] for control of [[Pigi, Rethymno|Pigi]] airfield, near [[Rethymno]] ([[Greek script]] Ρέθυμνο) on the [[Greece|Greek]] island of [[Crete]]. It began on the morning of 20 May 1941, when [[Nazi Germany]] launched an [[Airborne forces|airborne invasion]] of Crete under the codename '''Unternehmen Merkur''' ("Operation Mercury"). [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] forces, consisting mainly of Greek [[reserve army|reservists]] and [[gendarmerie]], along with [[Australia]]n [[Second AIF|regular infantry]], defended the airfield.

While the Allies succeeded in controlling the airfield, inflicting heavy casualties on the Germans, and taking many prisoners (including the commander of the German assault on Retimo, ''Oberst'' (Colonel) [[Alfred Sturm]]), the victory was quickly nullified by the defeat of Allied forces on Crete as a whole.

==Background==
{{Further|Crete order of battle}}
[[Rethymnon]], a town on the north coast of Crete, was important to the military defense of Crete by the British and Commonwealth force because an airport had been completed about {{convert|8|km|mi}} east of the town and near [[Pigi, Rethymno|Pigi]] village shortly before the battle.

[[United Kingdom|British]] and other [[Commonwealth]] forces had been [[Battle of Greece|forced out]] of mainland [[Greece]] by the Germans and had retreated to Crete. While there were between 27,000–28,000 troops in Crete to defend it, most were only lightly armed because the heavier equipment had been left in Greece.&lt;ref&gt;Bassett, James A. "Past Airborne Employment", Military Affairs, Vol. 12, No. 4 (Winter, 1948), p 214 URL: https://www.jstor.org/stable/1983420&lt;/ref&gt; Although the Germans were able to dominate the skies, the British [[Royal Navy]] had control of the sea. The German plan was to use [[paratrooper]]s and [[glider aircraft|glider]]s to send forces down by air.

==Prelude==
The Australian [[2/1st Battalion (Australia)|2/1st]] and [[2/11th Battalion (Australia)|2/11th Battalion]]s, supported by elements from Australian artillery, medical, engineer and signals units, as well as the Greek 4th and 5th Regiments, took up positions in the hills south of the airfield. This was in anticipation of an airborne German attack. Australian [[Lieutenant Colonel]] Ian Campbell, commanding the 2/1st Battalion, was overall commander of the Rethymnon units and had been charged to defend the area.&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20101021022019/http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-battles/retimo.htm Battle of Retimo]&lt;/ref&gt; The defence was based around two hills that overlooked the airstrip.&lt;ref&gt;Bell, ATJ, "The Battle for Crete - The Tragic Truth", Australian Defence Force Journal 1991 no.88, May–June p.15-18&lt;/ref&gt;

The day before the battle, a lone German plane flow over Rethymnon on a reconnaissance mission. Against orders, a Bren gun position shot it down. Campbell obtained a code book and photos of the area from the crashed aircraft. From the photos, Campbell could see that part of the defences were hidden by trees and would not be known by the Germans. The code was used by the commander of the 2/11th Battalion, Lieutenant Colonel [[Raymond Sandover|Ray Sandover]], to order supplies.

==The offensive==
German paratroopers, ''[[Fallschirmjäger]]'', landed in three areas on 20 May: [[Maleme]], Rethymnon and [[Iraklion]]. The German operation was a three-pronged strike. The central assault, codenamed ''Aris'', focused on Rethymnon.&lt;ref&gt;Stouros, I Brigadier. "Allied forces in Greece and Crete. 1941" Australian Defence Force Journal 1991 no.88, May–June pp 31 - 42&lt;/ref&gt; The [[Battle of Maleme]], on the west of the island, was over relatively quickly,&lt;ref&gt;Bassett, James A. "Past Airborne Employment", Military Affairs, Vol. 12, No. 4 (Winter, 1948), p 214 URL: https://www.jstor.org/stable/1983420&lt;/ref&gt; and the [[Battle of Heraklion]] continued for some days.

The German 2nd Parachute Rifle Regiment, numbering two [[battalion]]s and with detachments from divisional support troops, were to land and attack [[Rethymnon]]. The paratroopers had expected to take the airfield easily, but were surprised when they found it heavily defended.

Preceded by heavy aerial bombing, the initial German landing was disorganised, with seven transport [[Junkers Ju 52]]s  shot down and the paratroopers receiving heavy casualties. However, the paratroopers did manage to capture the hill that 2/1st Battalion was positioned on. German forces were also able to block the roads east and west of Rethymnon. On 22 May, after two failed counterattacks, a third counterattack organised in four columns by the Australians drove the Germans off the hill, who took up positions in an old olive oil factory at Stavromenos. While the German paratroopers had no heavy equipment or armour, the Australian troops had the use of two Matilda tanks as well as artillery. However, the two tanks were not used effectively, as both tank crews were originally captured after the tanks were trapped in ditches. Control of one was later regained, and it was used to support the infantry with a further attack by the Australians, which drove the Germans out of the factory on 26 May, who later retreated to [[Heraklion]].&lt;ref&gt;Handel, Paul. Matilda Tanks at Rethymnon on the Island of Crete Part 1  http://www.docstoc.com/docs/28108326/Matilda-Tanks-at-Retimo-on-the-Island-of-Crete-1/&lt;/ref&gt;

Another group of German paratroopers made a landing to the west of the airfield. However, their landings were scattered, and some landed on top of the 2/11th Battalion with others dropping in the nearby plain. Those that were not intercepted or captured moved towards the town of Rethymnon itself. Finding Rethymnon defended by Cretan police, the Germans took up defensive positions in a ridge that ran from the mountains to the sea.

From 22–28 May, Australian and Greek troops moved together against the German paratroopers in this ridge. Coordination between the Australians and the Greeks proved difficult, and at one point, the lesser-trained Greek soldiers opened fire early and warned the Germans of the incoming Australian attack. There was no [[communication]] with other Allied units on Crete, so Campbell was unaware as to what had been happening with the overall Allied effort. An attack was made against Pervolia on 27 May, with the use of the two Matilda tanks (both of which had now been recovered from their immobilised positions). When one tank was knocked out by anti-tank guns and the other was hit by a mine, the attack stalled. The assault on Pervolia again proceeded on 28 May, and this time the town was taken. By this time, the Australians were running low on supplies and were forced to withdraw after holding Pervolia for only a short while.&lt;ref&gt;Handel, Paul. Matilda Tanks at Rethymnon on the Island of Crete Part 1  http://www.docstoc.com/docs/28108326/Matilda-Tanks-at-Retimo-on-the-Island-of-Crete-1/&lt;/ref&gt;

On 29 May, the Greeks abandoned their positions and the Australians were forced to reduce the size of their perimeter. While the battles for Rethymnon and the [[Battle of Heraklion]] had been more successful for the allies, the German were quickly successful at the [[Battle of Maleme]] where New Zealand troops had mistakenly retreated, giving up control of the airport. The German control of the airstrip there, coupled with their total air superiority, meant that the [[Luftwaffe]] could now land infantry and equipment by plane.

At this time, reinforcements from Maleme arrived to assist the original [[Fallschirmjäger]], including German [[panzers]], and the Australians soon found themselves outgunned and surrounded.

==Aftermath==
With the Greek troops gone, a lack of food, dwindling supplies, no contact with the rest of the Allied troops on [[Crete]] (who were in fact surrendering or retreating), and the appearance of additional German troops, Campbell chose to order the Rethymnon group to surrender to the Germans. However, Lieutenant Colonel Sandover, in charge of the 2/11th Battalion, instructed his men that they could either surrender or evade capture. Many chose the latter by hiding in the hills, some protected by local Cretans who were under threat of being executed by the Germans.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-battles/retimo.htm |title=Battle for Retimo (Crete) |accessdate=2010-10-21 |url-status=dead |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20101021022019/http://www.diggerhistory.info/pages-battles/retimo.htm |archivedate=21 October 2010 |df=dmy }} Battle of Retimo&lt;/ref&gt; Of the 2/11th Battalion, 13 officers and 39 other ranks escaped to [[Egypt]].&lt;ref&gt;Bell, ATJ, The Battle for Crete - The Tragic Truth, Australian Defence Force Journal 1991 no.88, May–June p.17&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

== External links ==
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20110720150849/http://www.my-crete-site.co.uk/group1.htm Group Centre would operate towards Rethymnon]

{{Greece during World War II}}

{{coord missing|Greece}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=May 2011}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Rethymno, Battle Of}}
[[Category:Battle of Crete]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Germany]]
[[Category:Battles involving Greece]]
[[Category:Battles of World War II involving Australia]]
[[Category:Rethymno]]
[[Category:May 1941 events]]</text><sha1>5oweocustdxkfqvpi881e6irr6vfgew</sha1></revision></page>