<page><title>Operation Ladbroke</title><ns>0</ns><id>254009</id><revision><id>966885403</id><parentid>924790497</parentid><timestamp>2020-07-09T19:50:41Z</timestamp><contributor><username>Ninevehorion</username><id>39619296</id></contributor><model>wikitext</model><format>text/x-wiki</format><text bytes="31378" xml:space="preserve">{{good article}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=December 2016}}
{{Infobox military conflict
| conflict    = Operation Ladbroke
| partof      = the [[Allied invasion of Sicily]]
| image       = Sicily in Italy.svg
| image_size  = 200px
| caption     = Sicily (pictured in red).
| coordinates = {{coord|37|03|16|N|15|15|54|E|type:event_scale:10000_region:IT|}}
| date        = 9–10 July 1943
| place       = [[Syracuse, Sicily]]
| result      = British victory{{#tag:ref|Although the [[1st Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Airlanding Brigade]] could not hold onto the bridge after it had been captured. Their removal of the demolition charges prevented its destruction when the first units from the [[5th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|British 5th Infantry Division]] arrived.|group =nb}}
| combatant1  = {{flag|United Kingdom}}
| combatant2  = {{flagcountry|Kingdom of Italy}}
| commander1  = {{flagicon|United Kingdom}} [[Philip Hugh Whitby Hicks|Philip Hicks]]
| commander2  = {{flagicon|Kingdom of Italy}} [[Priamo Leonardi]]
| units1      = [[1st Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Airlanding Brigade]]
| units2      = 385th Coastal Battalion&lt;br&gt;[[54th Infantry Division Napoli|1st Battalion, 75th (Napoli) Infantry Regiment]]
| strength1   = 2,075
| strength2   = unknown
| casualties1 = 313 killed and 174 missing or wounded
| casualties2 = unknown
| notes       =
|campaignbox={{Campaignbox Invasion of Sicily}}
{{Campaignbox Italy}}
{{Campaignbox British airborne forces operations}}
}}

'''Operation Ladbroke''' was a [[Military glider|glider]] landing by [[British Army|British]] [[airborne forces|airborne troops]] during the [[World War II|Second World War]] near [[Syracuse, Italy|Syracuse]], [[Sicily]], that began on 9&amp;nbsp;July&amp;nbsp;1943 as part of [[Allied invasion of Sicily|Operation Husky]], the [[Allied invasion of Sicily]]. The first [[Allies of World War II|Allied]] mission using large numbers of the aircraft, the operation was carried out from [[Tunisia]] by [[glider infantry]] of the [[1st Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|British 1st Airlanding Brigade]], commanded by [[Brigadier (United Kingdom)|Brigadier]] [[Philip Hugh Whitby Hicks|Philip Hicks]], with a force of 136 [[Waco CG-4|Waco Hadrians]] and eight [[Airspeed Horsa]]s. The objective was to establish a large invasion force on the ground near the town of Syracuse, secure the Ponte Grande Bridge and ultimately take control of the city itself with its strategically vital docks, as a prelude to the full-scale invasion of Sicily.

En route to Sicily, sixty-five gliders released too early by the American and British towing aircraft crashed into the sea, drowning approximately 252 men. Of the remainder, only eighty-seven men arrived at the Pont Grande Bridge, although they successfully captured the bridge and held it beyond the time they were to be relieved. Finally, with their ammunition expended and only fifteen soldiers remaining unwounded, the Allied troops surrendered to Italian forces. The Italians, having gained control of the bridge, sought to destroy the structure, but were frustrated by troopers of the 1st Airlanding Brigade who had removed the previously attached explosive charges. Other troops from the brigade, who had landed elsewhere in Sicily, aided further by destroying communications links and capturing gun batteries.

==Background==
By December 1942, with [[Allies of World War II|Allied forces]] [[Tunisian Campaign|advancing through Tunisia]] after landing there the month before in [[Operation Torch]], the [[North African Campaign]] was coming to a close; with victory there imminent, discussions began among the Allies regarding the nature of their next objective.&lt;ref name=war21&gt;Warren, p. 21&lt;/ref&gt; Many Americans argued for an immediate invasion of Northern France, while the British, as well as then-[[Lieutenant general (United States)|Lieutenant General]] [[Dwight D. Eisenhower]],&lt;ref&gt;Eisenhower, p. 159&lt;/ref&gt; argued that the island of [[Sardinia]] was the best subsequent target of the Allied forces.&lt;ref name=war21/&gt; In January 1943 the [[Prime Minister of the United Kingdom|British Prime Minister]] [[Winston Churchill]] and [[President of the United States|U.S. President]] [[Franklin D. Roosevelt]] settled at the [[Casablanca Conference]] on the island of [[Sicily]],&lt;ref name=war21/&gt; whose invasion and occupation could potentially provide the Allies with Mediterranean shipping routes and airfields nearer to mainland Italy and Germany.&lt;ref&gt;Eisenhower, p. 60&lt;/ref&gt; The codename [[Allied invasion of Sicily|Operation Husky]] was decided upon for the [[Allied invasion of Sicily]], and planning for ''Husky'' began in February. Initially the [[Eighth Army (United Kingdom)|British Eighth Army]], under the command of [[General (United Kingdom)|General]] [[Bernard Montgomery|Sir Bernard Montgomery]], were to land on the south-eastern corner of the island and advance north to the port of [[Syracuse, Sicily|Syracuse]]. Two days later the [[Seventh United States Army|U.S. Seventh Army]], commanded by Lieutenant General [[George S. Patton]], would land on the western corner of the island and move towards the port of [[Palermo]].&lt;ref name=war21 /&gt;

In March it was decided that the [[82nd Airborne Division|U.S. 82nd Airborne Division]], under [[Major general (United States)|Major General]] [[Matthew Ridgway]], and the [[1st Airborne Division (United Kingdom)|British 1st Airborne Division]], under [[Major-general (United Kingdom)|Major-General]] [[George F. Hopkinson]], would be dropped by [[Paratrooper|parachute]] and [[Military glider|glider]] just prior to the [[Amphibious warfare|amphibious landings]]; they would land a few miles behind the beaches and neutralize their defenders, thereby aiding the landing of the Allied ground forces.&lt;ref name = war21 /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Huston, p. 155&lt;/ref&gt; However, in early May these directives were radically changed at the insistence of the Eighth Army commander, General Montgomery; he argued that with Allied forces landing separately at either end of the island, the defending Axis forces would have the opportunity to defeat each Allied army in turn before both could unite.&lt;ref name = war21 /&gt; Instead, the plans were altered to land both the Eighth and Seventh Armies simultaneously along a {{convert|100|mi}} stretch of coastline on Sicily's south-eastern corner.&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p. 275&lt;/ref&gt; At the same time, the plans for the two airborne divisions, the British 1st and U.S. 82nd, were also adjusted; Montgomery believed that the airborne troops should be landed near Syracuse, so that they could seize the valuable port. The commander of the [[82nd Airborne Division Artillery]], [[Brigadier general (United States)|Brigadier General]] [[Maxwell D. Taylor]], further asserted that dropping behind the island's beaches and overcoming its defences was not a suitable mission for the airborne troops, as they were only lightly armed and vulnerable to the '[[friendly fire]]' of the planned Allied naval bombardment.&lt;ref name=war22&gt;Warren, p. 22&lt;/ref&gt; In the revised blueprint for the airborne divisions, a reinforced [[regimental combat team]] (the [[505th Infantry Regiment (United States)|505th Parachute Infantry]], under [[Colonel (United States)|Colonel]] [[James M. Gavin]], with the 3rd Battalion of the [[504th Infantry Regiment (United States)|504th PIR]] and numerous other units attached) from Major General Ridgway's U.S. 82nd Airborne Division would be dropped by parachute north-east of the port of [[Gela]] to block the movement of Axis reserves towards the Allied [[beachhead]]s.&lt;ref name= war22/&gt; Major General Hopkinson's British 1st Airborne Division was now to conduct three brigade-size airborne operations: the Ponte Grande road bridge south of Syracuse was to be captured by the [[1st Airlanding Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Airlanding Brigade]], under [[Brigadier (United Kingdom)|Brigadier]] [[Philip Hugh Whitby Hicks|Philip Hicks]], the port of [[Augusta, Sicily|Augusta]] was to be seized by Brigadier [[Ernest Down]]'s [[2nd Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|2nd Parachute Brigade]], and finally the Primasole Bridge over the River Simeto was to be [[Operation Fustian|taken and secured]] by Brigadier [[Gerald Lathbury]]'s [[1st Parachute Brigade (United Kingdom)|1st Parachute Brigade]].&lt;ref&gt;Harclerode, p. 256&lt;/ref&gt;

==Planning==
[[File:Map operation husky landing.jpg|left|thumb|alt=Topographical map of Sicily, with details of landing areas and Axis positions|Map showing the landing areas during the invasion of Sicily, July 1943.]]
As there were insufficient transport aircraft for all three brigades to conduct their operations simultaneously, it was decided that the first operation would be ''Ladbroke'', whose objective was the capture of the Ponte Grande Bridge.&lt;ref name=tho97/&gt; The mission, under the command of [[Brigadier (United Kingdom)|Brigadier]] [[Philip Hugh Whitby Hicks|Philip Hicks]], was conducted just prior to the amphibious landings, on the night of 9&amp;nbsp;July, while the remaining two operations took place on successive two nights.&lt;ref name=tho97&gt;Thompson, p. 97&lt;/ref&gt; The 1st Airlanding Brigade was also given the additional tasks of capturing Syracuse harbour and the urban area that adjoined it, and either destroying or confiscating a coastal artillery battery that was in range of the amphibious landings.&lt;ref&gt;Otway, p. 119&lt;/ref&gt; When training began for the operation, difficulties immediately arose. The original plan for the airborne operations had called for all three to employ parachutists, but in May Montgomery altered the plan; after determining that airborne troops would be at a considerable distance from Allied ground forces, he believed that the force sent to capture Syracuse would be served best by gliders in order to provide them with the maximum possible amount of firepower.&lt;ref name=war23&gt;Warren, p. 23&lt;/ref&gt; His airborne advisor, Group Captain Cooper of the [[Royal Air Force]], argued that a glider landing conducted at night with inexperienced aircrews was not practical, but the decision was left unchanged.&lt;ref name=war23/&gt;

Montgomery's orders raised several issues, the first with the transport aircraft of the Troop Carrier Wings assigned to the airborne operations. When they had arrived in North Africa, it had been decided that the [[52nd Troop Carrier Wing (World War II)|52nd Troop Carrier Wing]] would operate with 1st Airborne Division and its counterpart, the [[51st Troop Carrier Wing (World War II)|51st]], with 82nd Airborne Division.&lt;ref name=war23/&gt; A few weeks later this arrangement was switched, with the 52nd now operating with 82nd Airborne Division and the 51st with 1st Airborne Division; this seemed a logical decision, as each Wing had operational experience with the division it had been paired with. However, the decision to turn the Syracuse assault into a glider-based one was problematic; the 51st had practically no glider experience, whilst the 52nd had much more but was already training for a parachute-based mission. To switch both was impractical and would have led to a number of problems, which left 1st Airborne Division, and thus 1st Airlanding Brigade, with an inexperienced Troop Carrier Wing.&lt;ref name=war26&gt;Warren, p. 26&lt;/ref&gt;

[[File:Jeep being loaded into waco glider.jpg|thumb|alt=Waco glider with the front cockpit raised and four men pushing a jeep inside|One of the 1st Airlanding Brigade's [[Willys MB|jeeps]] being loaded aboard a [[Waco CG-4|Waco Hadrian glider]]]]

===Glider problems===
Further problems were encountered with the gliders to be used in the operation, and the glider pilots themselves. Until a few months prior to the operation, there was a notable shortage of serviceable gliders in North Africa. In late March a small number of Wacos arrived at [[Accra]] on the [[Gold Coast (British colony)|Gold Coast]], but pilots sent to ferry them to North Africa found that they were in poor condition. Due to neglect and the deleterious effects of tropical weather, the pilots were able to assemble only a small number of Wacos and fly them back on 22 April.&lt;ref name=war27&gt;Warren, p. 27&lt;/ref&gt; On 23&amp;nbsp;April, a larger number of the American gliders began to arrive in North African ports, but were not immediately available for use as the crates holding them were unloaded haphazardly, instructions were often found to be missing, and those men assigned to assemble the gliders were often inexperienced.&lt;ref name=war27/&gt; However, when the decision was made to conduct a glider-borne assault with 1st Airlanding Brigade, assembly was improved, and by 12 June 346 gliders had been put together and delivered to the Troop Carrier Wings.&lt;ref name=war27/&gt; A small number of [[Airspeed Horsa|Horsa]] gliders were transported to North Africa for use by the brigade. Thirty took off from England and undertook a trip of approximately {{Convert|1,500|mi|km}} in [[Operation Turkey Buzzard]].&lt;ref&gt;Lloyd, p. 40&lt;/ref&gt; After attacks from ''[[Luftwaffe]]'' fighter patrols and experiencing often turbulent weather, a total of 27 Horsas were delivered to North Africa in time for the operation.&lt;ref&gt;Lloyd, pp. 43–44&lt;/ref&gt;

When sufficient gliders had arrived in North Africa, however, they were not all usable even in training; on 16&amp;nbsp;June, most of the gliders were grounded for repairs, and on 30&amp;nbsp;June, large numbers of them had developed weaknesses in their tail-wiring, necessitating another grounding period of three days.&lt;ref name=war27/&gt; Given these problems and delays, 51st Troop Carrier Wing was not able to conduct a large-scale glider exercise until mid-June. On 14&amp;nbsp;June, fifty-four Wacos were flown over {{Convert|70|mi|km}} and then released to land at an airfield, and a larger exercise was conducted on 20&amp;nbsp;June; but even these limited exercises were unrealistic, as they were conducted in broad daylight.&lt;ref name=war27/&gt; The British glider pilots themselves also caused difficulties; although there were a sufficient number of them to conduct the operation, they were highly inexperienced.&lt;ref name=war26/&gt; Detached from the [[Glider Pilot Regiment]] for the operation, they had no experience with the Waco gliders and night operations involving them, as British doctrine had deemed such operations impossible.&lt;ref name=war26/&gt; On average, the pilots had eight hours of flight experience in gliders. Few were rated as being 'operationally ready' and none had combat experience. Colonel George Chatterton, the commander of the Glider Pilot Regiment, had protested their participation as he believed they were entirely unfit for any operation.&lt;ref&gt;Lloyd, p. 35&lt;/ref&gt; When the training period for the brigade ended with a total of two exercises completed, the glider pilots had an average of 4.5 hours training in flying the unfamiliar Waco, which included an average of 1.2 hours night flying.&lt;ref&gt;Warren, pp. 27–28&lt;/ref&gt;

===1st Airlanding Brigade===
The units of the 1st Airlanding Brigade were: the 1st Battalion, [[Border Regiment]]; 2nd Battalion, [[South Staffordshire Regiment]]; [[181st (Airlanding) Field Ambulance]] and 9th Field Company, [[Royal Engineers]]. The Staffords were tasked with securing the bridge and the area to the south, while the Borders were to capture Syracuse.&lt;ref name=cole36&gt;Cole, p. 36&lt;/ref&gt; For the mission the 1st Airlanding Brigade were allocated 136 Waco and eight Horsa gliders.&lt;ref name=tug159/&gt; With the shortage of space in the gliders—Wacos could only accommodate fifteen troops, half that of the Horsa, thus the whole brigade could not be deployed.{{#tag:ref|For example, only six of the brigade's sixteen anti-tank guns were taken, with a similar reduction in mortars and no [[Vickers machine gun]]s. The 181st Field Ambulance needed thirty-two Wacos but were only allocated six, and five of them failed to reach Sicily.&lt;ref name=cole36/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Cole, p.  40&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}} Six of the Horsas carrying 'A' and 'C' companies from the Staffords were scheduled to land at the bridge at 23:15 on 9&amp;nbsp;July in a [[coup-de-main]] operation.&lt;ref name=tug159&gt;Tugwell, p. 159&lt;/ref&gt; The remainder of the brigade would arrive at 01:15 on 10&amp;nbsp;July using a number of landing-zones between {{convert|1.5|and|3|mi}} away, then converge on the bridge to reinforce the defence.&lt;ref name=mitch73/&gt;

===Italian forces===
The Ponte Grande Bridge was immediately outside the area defended by the Italian [[206 Coastal Division]], which would oppose the British seaborne landing. The fortress commander was [[Rear Admiral]] [[Priamo Leonardi]], with [[Colonel]] Mario Damiani in command of the army contingent.&lt;ref name=mitch334/&gt; The Augusta-Syracuse Naval Fortress Area, which included the Coastal Division, was protected by six medium and six heavy coastal artillery batteries, with eleven additional dual-purpose coastal and anti-aircraft batteries, with six batteries only of anti-aircraft guns. Finally the Fortress contained an armoured train with four 120&amp;nbsp;mm guns.&lt;ref name=mitch334&gt;Mitcham, p. 334&lt;/ref&gt; The army contingent was the 121st Coastal Defence Regiment, which included four battalions. There were also naval and air force battalions available,&lt;ref name=mitch334/&gt; while the [[54 Infantry Division Napoli]] was in a position to send reinforcements if required.&lt;ref name=mitch75/&gt;
[[File:1st Border reg.jpg|thumb|alt=Seven British soldiers only one facing the camera, wearing hot climate uniform in a desert terrain|Men from the 1st Battalion, [[Border Regiment]] 9 July 1943, just prior to take off. Note the [[Folding bicycle|folding airborne bicycle]].]]

==Mission==
On 9 July, a contingent of 2,075 British troops, along with seven [[Willys MB|jeeps]], six anti-tank guns and ten mortars, boarded their gliders in Tunisia and took off at 18:00, bound for Sicily.&lt;ref name=mitch73/&gt; In the hours that preceded the landing, twelve Boeing B-17 and six Vickers Wellington equipped with radar jamming devices flew back and forth along the coast in the Siracusa-Licata sector; between 21:00 and 21:30, 55 Wellingtons of 205th Group carried out a diversionary bombing of the port and airport of Syracuse, causing a number of civilian and military casualties, including the commander of the Italian naval base, Commander Giuseppe Giannotti.&lt;ref name=pedriali&gt;Ferdinando Pedriali, ''L'invasione dal cielo'', on ''Storia Militare'' no. 210 (May 2011), p. 6.&lt;/ref&gt; 280 puppets dressed in paratrooper uniforms were launched north of the landing area, in order to deceive the Italian defense.&lt;ref name=pedriali/&gt;
En route, the gliders encountered strong winds, poor visibility and at times were subjected to anti-aircraft fire.&lt;ref name=mitch73/&gt; To avoid gunfire and searchlights, pilots of the towing aircraft climbed higher or took evasive action. In the confusion surrounding these manoeuvres, some gliders were released too early and sixty-five of them crashed into the sea, drowning around 252 men.&lt;ref name=mitch73/&gt; Of the remainder, only twelve landed in the right place. Another fifty-nine landed up to {{convert|25|mi}} away while the remainder were either shot down or failed to release and returned to Tunisia.&lt;ref name=mitch73&gt;Mitcham, pp. 73–74&lt;/ref&gt; About 200 American paratroopers, having been mistakenly parachuted in the area assigned to the Eighth Army, were captured by the Italian 146th Coastal Regiment (206th Coastal Division) in the early hours of 10 July.&lt;ref name=pedriali/&gt;

Only one Horsa with a platoon of infantry from the Staffords landed near the bridge. Its commander, Lieutenant Withers, divided his men into two groups, one of which swam across the river and took up position on the opposite bank. Thereafter the bridge was captured following a simultaneous assault from both sides. The Italian defenders from the 120th Coastal Infantry Regiment abandoned their [[bunker|pillboxes]] on the north bank.&lt;ref name=mitch74&gt;Mitcham, p. 74&lt;/ref&gt;{{#tag:ref|Coastal units were second line formations, usually made up from men in their forties and fifties, and were intended to perform labouring or other second line duties. Recruited from the local population, their officers were mostly men who had retired and had been called up again. Their morale was low, not least because of the second rate equipment and weapons they had been issued. It had been intended to improve their armaments with equipment seized from the recently disbanded [[Vichy French]] army, but when the arms arrived in Sicily, they had often been made unusable and had the wrong type or no ammunition at all.&lt;ref&gt;Jowett, p. 6&lt;/ref&gt;|group=nb}}

The British platoon then dismantled some demolition charges that had been fitted to the bridge and dug-in to wait for reinforcement or relief.&lt;ref name=mitch74/&gt; Another Horsa landed roughly {{convert|200|yd}} from the bridge but exploded on landing, killing all on board. Three of the other Horsas carrying the ''coup-de-main'' party landed within {{convert|2|mi}} of the bridge—their occupants eventually finding their way to the site.&lt;ref&gt;Tugwell (1971), p.&amp;nbsp;160&lt;/ref&gt; Reinforcements began to arrive at the bridge, but by 06:30 they numbered only eighty-seven men.&lt;ref name=mitch75&gt;Mitcham, p. 75&lt;/ref&gt;

Elsewhere, about 150 men landed at [[Cape Murro di Porco]] and captured a radio station. Based on a warning of imminent glider landings transmitted by the station's previous occupants, the local Italian commander ordered a counter-attack but his troops failed to receive his message. The scattered nature of the landings now worked in the Allies' favour as they were able to cut all telephone wires in the immediate area.&lt;ref name=mitch74/&gt; The glider carrying the brigade deputy commander, Colonel O. L. Jones, landed beside an Italian coastal artillery battery; at daylight the staff officers and radio operators attacked and destroyed the battery's five guns and their ammunition dump.&lt;ref&gt;Mrazek, p. 79&lt;/ref&gt; Other isolated groups of Allied soldiers tried to aid their comrades, assaulting Italian defences and targeting reinforcements.&lt;ref&gt;Mrazek, pp. 79–80&lt;/ref&gt; Another attack by a group of paratroopers on three 149/35&amp;nbsp;mm Italian coastal batteries failed, and the batteries were able to open fire on Allied landing craft and troops at 6:15 on 10 July.&lt;ref name=pedriali/&gt; At 9:15, the 1st Battalion of the Italian 75th Infantry Regiment ("Napoli" Division) captured another 160 American paratroopers on the [[Palazzolo Acreide]]–Syracuse road. Another group of paratroopers attacked an Italian patrol led by Major Paoli, commander of the 126th Artillery Group; Paoli was killed and his unit fell in disarray, and was thus unable to intervene in the later fight against British tanks near the bridge.&lt;ref name=pedriali/&gt;
[[File:Batteria Lamba Doria 02.JPG|thumb|left|250px|Remains of the ''Lamba Doria'' coastal battery, captured by 250 British commandos after about two hours of fighting, in the night of 10 July 1943.]]

The first counterattack on the bridge was by two companies of Italian sailors, who were repulsed by the British. As the Italians responded to the Allied landings, they gathered more troops and brought up artillery and mortars to bombard the Allied-controlled Pont Grande Bridge.&lt;ref name=mitch75/&gt; The British defenders came under attack from the Italians while the expected [[5th Infantry Division (United Kingdom)|British 5th Infantry Division]] relief did not appear at 10:00 as planned.&lt;ref name=tug161/&gt; At 11:30 the Italian 385th Coastal Battalion arrived at the bridge, followed soon afterward by the 1st Battalion, 75th (Napoli) Infantry Regiment. The Italians were positioned to attack the bridge from three sides. By 14:45 there were only fifteen British troops defending the bridge that had not been killed or wounded (four officers and eleven soldiers). At 15:30, with their ammunition consumed, the British stopped fighting. Some men on the south side of the bridge escaped into the countryside, but the rest became [[prisoner of war|prisoners of war]].&lt;ref name=mitch75/&gt; With the bridge back in Italian hands, the first unit from 5th Infantry Division, the 2nd Battalion, [[Royal Scots Fusiliers]], of [[17th Infantry Brigade (United Kingdom)|17th Infantry Brigade]], arrived at the bridge at 16:15 and mounted a successful counter-attack,&lt;ref name=tug161/&gt; which had been made possible by the prior removal of demolition charges from the bridge, preventing its destruction by the Italians.&lt;ref name=tug161&gt;Tugwell, p. 161&lt;/ref&gt; The 1st Battalion of the 75th Infantry Regiment, having no artillery, was unable to oppose the British tanks and had to retreat after suffering heavy losses.&lt;ref name=pedriali/&gt; The survivors from the 1st Airlanding Brigade took no further part in the fighting and were withdrawn back to North Africa on 13 July.&lt;ref name=mitch78&gt;Mitcham, p. 78&lt;/ref&gt; During the landings, the losses by 1st Airlanding Brigade were the most severe of all British units involved.&lt;ref&gt;Tugwell, p. 162&lt;/ref&gt; The casualties amounted to 313 killed and 174 missing or wounded.&lt;ref name=mitch78/&gt; Fourteen accompanying glider pilots were killed, and eighty-seven were missing or wounded.&lt;ref name=mitch78/&gt;

==Aftermath==
After an enquiry into the problems with the airborne missions in Sicily, the British Army and Royal Air Force submitted recommendations in the aftermath of Operation Ladbroke.&lt;ref name=tug167&gt;Tugwell, p. 167&lt;/ref&gt; Aircrew were to be trained in parachute and glider operations, and pathfinders were to be landed before the main force, to set out their beacons.&lt;ref name=tug167/&gt; The landing plan was simplified with complete brigades landing on a drop zone, instead of the smaller battalion landing areas used on Sicily.&lt;ref name=tug167/&gt; Gliders were no longer released at night while still over water, and their landing zones would be large enough to accommodate the aircraft with room to spare.&lt;ref&gt;Mrazek, p. 85&lt;/ref&gt; Following a friendly fire incident over an Allied convoy, more training was given to ship's crews in aircraft recognition; Allied aircraft were also painted with three large [[Invasion stripes|white stripes]].&lt;ref&gt;Nigl, p. 68&lt;/ref&gt; Training for pilots of the Glider Pilot Regiment was increased, and improvements to the gliders were implemented, including better inter-aircraft communication.&lt;ref&gt;Nigl, p. 69&lt;/ref&gt; To provide another method of delivering jeeps and artillery by air, the Royal Air Force started experimenting with how to use parachutes to drop them into combat, the jeeps and guns being carried in aircraft's bomb bays.&lt;ref name=lake81&gt;Lake, p. 81&lt;/ref&gt; A second Royal Air Force transport group, [[No. 46 Group RAF|No. 46]], was formed and equipped solely with [[Douglas C-47 Skytrain|Douglas Dakotas]], instead of the mixture of aircraft in [[No. 38 Group RAF|No. 38 Group]].&lt;ref name=tug202&gt;Tugwell, p. 202&lt;/ref&gt; Together, the Royal Air Force groups were capable of supplying eighty-eight [[Armstrong Whitworth Albemarle|Albermarles]], eighty-eight [[Short Stirling|Stirlings]], thirty-six [[Handley Page Halifax|Halifaxes]] and 150 Dakotas, a total of 362 planes which did not include aircraft held as reserves.&lt;ref name=tug202/&gt;{{#tag:ref|While an improvement of what went before the total of 362 is only a fraction of the 1,166 C-47s in the American transport fleet.&lt;ref name=tug202/&gt; The lack of transport aircraft hampered every British airborne operation of the war. Nonetheless, since 1941 following an [[Air Ministry]] order, many Royal Air Force bombers had equipment fitted to tow gliders; as a result, Albemarle, Halifax and Stirling bombers were able to conduct parachute operations. Even so, it was the Commander-in-Chief of [[RAF Bomber Command]] [[Sir Arthur Harris, 1st Baronet|Arthur Harris]], who refused to divert [[Avro Lancaster]]s from the strategic bombing campaign, for the transportation of  troops.&lt;ref&gt;Tugwell, pp. 136–37&lt;/ref&gt;| group =nb}}

==Notes==
===Footnotes===
{{reflist |group=nb}}

===Citations===
{{reflist |colwidth=15em}}

==Bibliography==
{{refbegin}}
* {{cite book|last=Cole|first=Howard N|title=On wings of healing: the story of the Airborne Medical Services 1940–1960|publisher=William Blackwood|location= Edinburgh | year = 1963|oclc= 29847628}}
* {{cite book|last=Eisenhower|first=Dwight D.|title=Crusade in Europe|url=https://archive.org/details/crusadeineurope00eise|url-access=registration|publisher=Doubleday|location=New York|year=1948|isbn= 0-385-41619-9}}
* {{cite book|last=Harclerode|first=Peter|title=Wings of War&amp;nbsp;– Airborne Warfare 1918–1945| publisher=Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson|year=2005|location=London|isbn = 0-304-36730-3}}
* {{cite book|last = Huston|first=James A.|title = Out of The Blue&amp;nbsp;– US Army Airborne Operations In World War II|publisher=Purdue University Press|location= West Lafayette, IN|year=1998|isbn = 1-55753-148-X}}
* {{cite book|last=Jowett|first=Philip S.|title=The Italian Army 1940–45 | volume = Vol. 3: Italy 1943–45|series=Men at arms | publisher = Osprey Publishing|location=Oxford, UK|year=2001|isbn= 1-85532-866-6}}
* {{cite book|last=Lake|first= Jon|title= Halifax Squadrons of World War 2|volume= 14 | series = Combat Aircraft|publisher= Osprey Publishing|year= 1999|location= Oxford, UK | isbn = 1-85532-892-5}}
* {{cite book|last=Lloyd|first=Alan|title=The Gliders: The story of Britain's fighting gliders and the men who flew them|publisher=Corgi|location=Ealing, UK|year= 1982 | isbn = 0-552-12167-3}}
* {{cite book|last1=Mitcham|first1=Samuel W|last2=Von Stauffenberg|first2= Friedrich|title= The Battle of Sicily: How the Allies Lost Their Chance for Total Victory | series = Stackpole Military History Series|publisher=Stackpole Books|location=Mechanicsburg,  [[Pennsylvania|PA]] |year=2007|isbn=0-8117-3403-X}}
* {{cite book|last=Mrazek|first=James|title=Airborne Combat: Axis and Allied Glider Operations in World War II|series=Military History Series|publisher=Stackpole Books | year =2011|location=Mechanicsburg,  [[Pennsylvania|PA]] |isbn= 0-8117-0808-X}}
* {{cite book|last=Nigl|first=Alfred J|title=Silent Wings Savage Death|publisher=Graphic Publishers|year=2007|location=Santa Anna,  [[California|CA]] |isbn = 1-882824-31-8}}
* {{cite book|last=Otway|first=Lieutenant-Colonel T.B.H|title=The Second World War 1939–1945 Army&amp;nbsp;– Airborne Forces|publisher=Imperial War Museum|location=London | year = 1990|isbn= 0-901627-57-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Thompson|first=Major-General Julian|title=Ready for Anything: The Parachute Regiment at War|publisher=Fontana|location=Fontana, CA|year=1990|isbn = 0-00-637505-7}}
* {{cite book|last=Tugwell|first=Maurice|title=Airborne to Battle: A History of Airborne Warfare, 1918–1971|publisher=Kimber|location=London|year=1971| isbn = 0-7183-0262-1}}
* {{cite book|last=Warren|first=Dr John C.|title= Airborne Missions in the Mediterranean 1942–1945|publisher=US Air Force Historical Research Agency|location= Air University, Maxwell AFB|year=1955|isbn= 0-89126-023-4}}
{{refend}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ladbroke, Operation}}
[[Category:Airborne operations of World War II]]
[[Category:Allied invasion of Sicily]]
[[Category:Battles and operations of World War II involving Italy]]
[[Category:Land battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Aerial operations and battles of World War II involving the United Kingdom]]
[[Category:Glider Pilot Regiment operations]]
[[Category:July 1943 events]]</text><sha1>r5i1vx85y8490hlmu8xgpfz9k5axmyv</sha1></revision></page>